<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader xml:lang="eng">
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title xml:lang="lat">
     De sensu et sensibilibus
    </title>
    <author>
     Aristotle
    </author>
    <editor>
     Immanuel Bekker
    </editor>
    <funder>
     Andrew W. Mellon Foundation
    </funder>
    <respStmt>
     <resp>
      Published original versions of the electronic texts
     </resp>
     <orgName ref="http://www.graeco-arabic-studies.org/">
      A Digital Corpus for Graeco-Arabic Studies, funded by the Andrew W. Mellon Foundation
     </orgName>
     <persName>
      Mark Schiefsky, Harvard University
     </persName>
     <persName>
      Gregory R. Crane, Universität Leipzig
     </persName>
     <persName>
      Uwe Vagelpohl, University of Warwick
     </persName>
    </respStmt>
    <respStmt>
     <resp>
      Keyboarding
     </resp>
     <orgName xml:id="DDD">
      Digital Divide Data
     </orgName>
    </respStmt>
    <respStmt>
     <resp>
      Editor-in-Chief, Perseus Digital Library
     </resp>
     <persName>
      Gregory R. Crane
     </persName>
    </respStmt>
    <respStmt>
     <resp>
      Project Manager (University of Leipzig), 2016 - present
     </resp>
     <persName>
      Matt Munson
     </persName>
    </respStmt>
    <respStmt>
     <resp>
      Project Assistant (University of Leipzig), 2015 - present
     </resp>
     <persName>
      Annette Geßner
     </persName>
    </respStmt>
    <respStmt>
     <resp>
      Lead Developer (University of Leipzig)
     </resp>
     <persName>
      Thibault Clérice
     </persName>
    </respStmt>
    <respStmt>
     <resp>
      Technical Advisor
     </resp>
     <persName>
      Bruce Robertson
     </persName>
    </respStmt>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <authority>
     A Digital Corpus for Graeco-Arabic Studies, funded by the Andrew W. Mellon Foundation
    </authority>
    <publisher>
     University of Leipzig
    </publisher>
    <pubPlace>
     Germany
    </pubPlace>
    <idno type="filename">
     tlg0086.tlg041.1st1K-grc1.xml
    </idno>
    <availability>
     <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">
      Available under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 International License
     </licence>
    </availability>
    <date>
     2016
    </date>
   </publicationStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <biblStruct>
     <monogr>
      <title xml:lang="lat">
       Aristotelis Opera
      </title>
      <author>
       Aristotle
      </author>
      <editor>
       Immanuel Bekker
      </editor>
      <imprint>
       <publisher>
        Oxford University Press
       </publisher>
       <pubPlace>
        Oxford
       </pubPlace>
       <biblScope unit="vol">
        3
       </biblScope>
       <biblScope from="243" to="276" unit="pp">
        243-276
       </biblScope>
       <date>
        1837
       </date>
      </imprint>
     </monogr>
     <ref target="https://archive.org/stream/aristotelisoper03arisuoft">
      Internet Archive
     </ref>
    </biblStruct>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <p>
    The following text is encoded in accordance with EpiDoc standards and with the CTS/CITE Architecture.
   </p>
   <p lang="it">
    Il testo seguente è codificato in conformità con gli standard EpiDoc e con l'architettura CTS/CITE.
   </p>
   <p lang="en">
    The following text is encoded in accordance with EpiDoc standards and with the CTS/CITE Architecture.
   </p>
   <refsDecl n="CTS">
    <cRefPattern matchPattern="(\w+).(\w+)" n="section" replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div/tei:div[@n='$1']/tei:div[@n='$2'])"/>
    <cRefPattern matchPattern="(\w+)" n="chapter" replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div/tei:div[@n='$1'])"/>
   </refsDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <langUsage>
    <language ident="lat">
     Latin
    </language>
    <language ident="grc">
     Greek
    </language>
   </langUsage>
  </profileDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <body>
   <div n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg041.1st1K-grc1" type="edition" xml:lang="grc">
    <pb n="243"/>
    <div n="1" subtype="chapter" type="textpart">
     <head>
      ΠΕΡΙ ΑΙΣΘΗΣΕΩΣ ΚΑΙ ΑΙΣΘΗΤΩΝ.
     </head>
     <div n="1" subtype="section" type="textpart">
      <p>
       ἘΠΕΙ δὲ περὶ ψυχῆς καθ’ αὑτὴν διώρισται καὶ περὶ
τῶν δυνάμεων ἑκάστης κατὰ μόριον αὐτῆς, ἐχόμενον ἐστι
ποιήσασθαι τὴν ἐπίσκεψιν περὶ τῶν ζῴων καὶ τῶν ζωὴν
ἐχόντων ἁπάντων, τίνες εἰσὶν ἴδιαι καὶ τίνες κοιναὶ πράξεις
αὐτῶν. Τὰ μὲν οὖν εἰρημένα περὶ ψυχῆς ὑποκείσθω, περὶ
δὲ τῶν λοιπῶν λέγωμεν, καὶ πρῶτον περὶ τῶν πρώτων.
      </p>
      <p lang="it">
       E lì l'anima in sé è divisa e in giro
delle forze di ciascuna delle sue molecole, l'essere
hai fatto la visita sugli animali e sulle vite
avendo risposto, le vostre sono le stesse e le vostre azioni congiunte
di loro. Mi sottometto a ciò che si dice dell'anima, ca
ma degli altri parliamo, e anzitutto del primo.
      </p>
      <p lang="en">
       And there about the soul in itself it is divided and about
of the forces of each of its molecules, being
you made the visit about the animals and the lives
having answered, yours are the same and your joint actions
of them. I submit to what is said about the soul, approx
but of the others we speak, and first of all about the former.
      </p>
     </div>
     <div n="2" subtype="section" type="textpart">
      <p rend="cont">
       Φαίνεται δὲ τὰ μέγιστα, καὶ τὰ κοινὰ καὶ τὰ ἴδια τῶν
ζῴων, κοινὰ τῆς ψυχῆς ὄντα καὶ τοῦ σώματος, οἷον αἴσθησις
καὶ μνήμη καὶ θυμὸς καὶ ἐπιθυμία καὶ ὅλως ὄρεξις, καὶ
πρὸς τούτοις ἡδονή τε καὶ λύπη· καὶ γὰρ ταῦτα σχεδὸν
ὑπάρχει πᾶσι τοῖς ζῴοις.
      </p>
      <p lang="it">
       Ma le massime, il comune e lo stesso, si vedono
degli animali, esseri comuni dell'anima e del corpo, che è il senso
e la memoria, l'ira, il desiderio e ogni appetito, e
per questo c'è piacere e dolore;
esiste in tutti gli esseri viventi.
      </p>
      <p lang="en">
       But the maxims, and the common and the same, are seen
of animals, common beings of the soul and of the body, which is sense
and memory and anger and desire and all appetite, and
for this there is pleasure and sorrow;
exists in all living things.
      </p>
     </div>
     <div n="3" subtype="section" type="textpart">
      <p rend="cont">
       Πρὸς δὲ τούτοις τὰ μὲν πάντων
ἐστὶ τῶν μετεχόντων ζωῆς κοινά, τὰ δὲ τῶν ζῴων ἐνίοις.
Τυγχάνουσι δὲ τούτων τὰ μέγιστα τέτταρες οὖσαι συζυγίαι
τὸν ἀριθμόν, οἷον ἐγρήγορσις καὶ ὕπνος, καὶ νεότης
καὶ γῆρας, καὶ ἀναπνοὴ καὶ ἐκπνοή, καὶ ζωὴ καὶ θάνατος·
περὶ ὧν θεωρητέον, τί τε ἕκαστον αὐτῶν, καὶ διὰ τίνας αἰτίας
       <pb n="244"/>
       συμβαίνει.
      </p>
      <p lang="it">
       Ma a questi, tutto
Non è comune a coloro che partecipano alla vita, ma a coloro che vivono eternamente.
Ma di questi al massimo quattro sono sposati
il numero, che è vigilanza, sonno e giovinezza
e la vecchiaia, il respiro e l'espirazione, la vita e la morte;
su cosa è considerato, cos'è ciascuno di essi e per quale motivo



succede.
      </p>
      <p lang="en">
       But to these, everything
It is common to those who partake of life, but to those who live eternally.
But the maximum four of these are married
the number, which is alertness and sleep and youth
and old age, and breathing and exhaling, and life and death;
about what is considered, what is each of them, and for what reason



it happens.
      </p>
     </div>
     <div n="4" subtype="section" type="textpart">
      <p rend="cont">
       Φυσικοῦ δὲ καὶ περὶ ὑγιείας καὶ νόσου τὰς
πρώτας ἰδεῖν ἀρχάς· οὔτε γὰρ ὑγίειαν οὔτε νόσον οἷόν τε
γίνεσθαι τοῖς ἐστερημένοις ζωῆς. Διὸ σχεδὸν τῶν τε περὶ
φύσεως οἱ πλεῖστοι καὶ τῶν ἰατρῶν οἱ φιλοσοφωτέρως τὴν
τέχνην μετιόντες, οἱ μὲν τελευτῶσιν εἰς τὰ περὶ ἰατρικῆς,
οἱ δ’ ἐκ τῶν περὶ φύσεως ἄρχονται περὶ τῆς ἰατρικῆς.
      </p>
      <p lang="it">
       E, naturalmente, sulla salute e sulla malattia
prima vedi prima; né per la salute né per la malattia
diventare coloro che sono privati ​​della vita. A causa del design del
per natura la maggioranza e il più filosofico dei medici
detrattori dell’arte, quelli che finiscono in questioni mediche,
il quarto di quelli sulla natura comincia con la medicina.
      </p>
      <p lang="en">
       And of course, about health and disease
first see first; for neither health nor disease
become those deprived of life. Because of the design of the
by nature the majority and the most philosophical of the doctors
art detractors, those who end up in medical matters,
the fourth of those about nature begin about medicine.
      </p>
     </div>
     <div n="5" subtype="section" type="textpart">
      <p rend="cont">
       Ὅτι δὲ τὰ λεχθέντα κοινὰ τῆς τε ψυχῆς ἐστὶ καὶ τοῦ
σώματος, οὐκ ἄδηλον. Πάντα γὰρ τὰ μὲν μετ’ αἰσθήσεως
συμβαίνει, τὰ δὲ δι’ αἰσθήσεως· ἔνια δὲ τὰ μὲν πάθη ταύτης
ὄντα τυγχάνει, τὰ δ’ ἕξεις, τὰ δὲ φυλακαὶ καὶ σωτηρίαι,
τὰ δὲ φθοραὶ καὶ στερήσεις. Ἡ δ’ αἴσθησις ὅτι διὰ σώματος
γίνεται τῇ ψυχῇ, δῆλον καὶ διὰ τοῦ λόγου καὶ τοῦ
λόγου χωρίς.
      </p>
      <p lang="it">
       Ma quanto detto è comune all'anima e a lei
corpo, non ovvio. Dopotutto, sempre con sentimento
succede, ma per sentimento; ma per passione
quando ciò accade, le quattro azioni, e le prigioni e le salvezze,
ma le perdite e le privazioni. Il senso che attraverso il corpo
si fa all'anima, ingannando sia attraverso la parola che con il
senza motivo.
      </p>
      <p lang="en">
       But what has been said is common to the soul and to him
body, not obvious. After all, always with feeling
it happens, but by feeling; but one by passion
when it happens, the four actions, and the prisons and salvations,
but the losses and deprivations. The sense that through the body
it is done to the soul, deceiving both through the word and the
without reason.
      </p>
     </div>
     <div n="6" subtype="section" type="textpart">
      <p rend="cont">
       Ἀλλὰ περὶ μὲν αἰσθήσεως καὶ τοῦ αἰσθάνεσθαι,
τί ἐστι καὶ διὰ τί συμβαίνει τοῖς ζῴοις τοῦτο τὸ
πάθος, εἴρηται πρότερον ἐν τοῖς περὶ ψυχῆς. Τοῖς δὲ
ζῴοις, ᾗ μὲν ζῷον ἕκαστον, ἀνάγκη ὑπάρχειν αἴσθησιν· τούτῳ
γὰρ τὸ ζῷον εἶναι καὶ μὴ ζῷον διορίζομεν.
      </p>
      <p lang="it">
       Ma riguardo al sentimento e al sentimento,
cos'è e perché succede agli animali?
passione, menzionata prima in quelle sull'anima. Ma a loro
esseri viventi, dove ognuno vive, c'è bisogno di sentire questo;
poiché la vita è e non siamo noi a decidere la vita.
      </p>
      <p lang="en">
       But about feeling and feeling,
what is this and why does this happen to animals
passion, mentioned earlier in those about the soul. But to them
living beings, where every one lives, there is a need for feeling; this
for life is and we do not appoint life.
      </p>
     </div>
     <div n="7" subtype="section" type="textpart">
      <p rend="cont">
       Ἰδίᾳ δ’
ἤδη καθ’ ἕκαστον ἡ μὲν ἁφὴ καὶ γεῦσις ἀκολουθεῖ πᾶσιν ἐξ
ἀνάγκης, ἡ μὲν ἁφὴ διὰ τὴν εἰρημένην αἰτίαν ἐν τοῖς περὶ
ψυχῆς, ἡ δὲ γεῦσις διὰ τὴν τροφήν· τὸ γὰρ ἡδὺ διακρίνει
καὶ τὸ λυπηρὸν αὕτη περὶ τὴν τροφήν, ὥστε τὸ μὲν
φεύγειν τὸ δὲ διώκειν, καὶ ὅλως ὁ χυμός ἐστι τοῦ θρεπτικοῦ
μορίου πάθος.
      </p>
      <p lang="it">
       Parte IV
già in ognuno consegue tutto il senso del tatto e del gusto
necessariamente il perdono per la detta causa in coloro che si avvicinano
dell'anima, ma il gusto del cibo, perché qui si distingue
e la sua tristezza per il cibo, come la mia
Se ne vanno, ma perseguitano e tutto il succo è nutriente
molecola della passione.
      </p>
      <p lang="en">
       Part IV
already in each one the sense of touch and taste follows all from
of necessity, the pardon for the said cause in those about
of the soul, but the taste for the food, for here it distinguishes
and her sadness about food, like mine
They leave, but they persecute, and all the juice is nourishing
passion molecule.
      </p>
     </div>
     <div n="8" subtype="section" type="textpart">
      <p rend="cont">
       Αἱ δὲ διὰ τῶν ἔξωθεν αἰσθήσεις
τοῖς πορευτικοῖς αὐτῶν, οἷον ὄσφρησις καὶ ἀκοὴ καὶ ὄψις,
πᾶσι μὲν τοῖς ἔχουσι σωτηρίας ἕνεκεν ὑπάρχουσιν, ὅπως
διώκωσί τε προαισθανόμενα τὴν τροφὴν καὶ τὰ φαῦλα καὶ
τὰ φθαρτικὰ φεύγωσι, τοῖς δὲ καὶ φρονήσεως τυγχάνουσι
       <pb n="245"/>
       τοῦ εὖ ἕνεκα· πολλὰς γὰρ εἰσαγγέλλουσι διαφοράς, ἐξ ὧν ἥ
τε τῶν νοητῶν ἐγγίνεται φρόνησις καὶ ἡ τῶν πρακτῶν.
      </p>
      <p lang="it">
       E quelli attraverso i sensi esterni
ai loro marciatori, che senti, senti e vedi,
tutti tranne quelli che hanno la salvezza sono presenti, come
Inseguire con presentimento cibo e vizi e
i corruttibili fuggono, ma colpiscono anche quelli che preoccupano



di eὖ eneka; per molti araldi di differenza, da cui ἥ
Dagli intellettuali viene la saggezza e quella delle azioni.
      </p>
      <p lang="en">
       And those through the external senses
to their marchers, whom you smell and hear and see,
all but those who have salvation are present, as
Forebodingly chase food and vices and
the corruptibles flee away, but those of concern also befall them



of eὖ eneka; for many heralds of difference, from which ἥ
Of the intellectuals comes wisdom and that of actions.
      </p>
     </div>
     <div n="9" subtype="section" type="textpart">
      <p rend="cont">
       Αὐτῶν δὲ τούτων πρὸς μὲν τὰ ἀναγκαῖα κρείττων ἡ ὄψις
καὶ καθ’ αὑτήν, πρὸς δὲ νοῦν καὶ κατὰ συμβεβηκὸς ἡ ἀκοή.
      </p>
      <p lang="it">
       Ma nei miei confronti era necessario lo sguardo di queste persone
E a lei, e alla mente, e per convenzione, all'udito.
      </p>
      <p lang="en">
       But the view of these people was necessary towards me
And to her, and to the mind, and by convention, the hearing.
      </p>
     </div>
     <div n="10" subtype="section" type="textpart">
      <p rend="cont">
       Διαφορὰς μὲν γὰρ πολλὰς εἰσαγγέλλει καὶ παντοδαπὰς
ἡ τῆς ὄψεως δύναμις διὰ τὸ πάντα τὰ σώματα μετέχειν
χρώματος, ὥστε καὶ τὰ κοινὰ διὰ ταύτης αἰσθάνεσθαι μάλιστα
(λέγω δὲ κοινὰ σχῆμα, μέγεθος, κίνησιν, ἀριθμόν)·
ἡ δ’ ἁκοὴ τὰ τοῦ ψόφου διαφορὰς μόνον, ὀλίγοις δὲ καὶ
τὰς τῆς φωνῆς.
      </p>
      <p lang="it">
       A differenza di me, predica molto e ovunque
il potere dell'occhio per tutto ciò che i corpi condividono
colore, in modo che anche la gente comune ne senta la sensazione
(dico forma, dimensione, movimento, numero comuni);
solo la seconda udienza del vecchio è diversa, e solo poche
la voce.
      </p>
      <p lang="en">
       Unlike me, he preaches a lot and everywhere
the power of the eye for everything the bodies share
color, so that even the common people feel for it
(I say common shape, size, movement, number);
the second hearing of the old man is different only, and only a few
the voice.
      </p>
     </div>
     <div n="11" subtype="section" type="textpart">
      <p rend="cont">
       Κατὰ συμβεβηκὸς δὲ πρὸς φρόνησιν ἡ
ἀκοὴ πλεῖστον συμβάλλεται μέρος. Ὁ γὰρ λόγος αἴτιός
ἐστι τῆς μαθήσεως ἀκουστὸς ὤν, οὐ καθ’ αὑτὸν ἀλλὰ κατὰ
συμβεβηκός· ἐξ ὀνομάτων γὰρ σύγκειται, τῶν δ’ ὀνομάτων
ἕκαστον σύμβολόν ἐστιν.
      </p>
      <p lang="it">
       È un dato di fatto, il
L'udito è la parte più coinvolta. Perché il motivo è la causa
È l'ascoltatore dell'apprendimento, non per se stesso ma contro
contingente; poiché deriva da nomi, di quattro nomi
ognuno è un simbolo.
      </p>
      <p lang="en">
       As a matter of fact, the
Hearing is the most involved part. Because the reason is the cause
He is the listener of learning, not for himself but against
contingent; for it is derived from names, of four names
each is a symbol.
      </p>
     </div>
     <div n="12" subtype="section" type="textpart">
      <p rend="cont">
       Διόπερ φρονιμώτεροι τῶν ἐκ γενετῆς
ἐστερημένων εἰσὶν ἑκατέρας τῆς αἰσθήσεως οἱ τυφλοὶ
τῶν ἐνεῶν καὶ κωφῶν. Περὶ μὲν οὖν τῆς δυνάμεως ἣν ἔχει
τῶν αἰσθήσεων ἑκάστη, πρότερον εἴρηται.
      </p>
      <p lang="it">
       Più prudente di quelli nati
i ciechi sono privi di senno
dei sordi e dei sordi. Su di me per il potere che ha
dei sensi di ciascuno, precedentemente menzionato.
      </p>
      <p lang="en">
       More prudent than those born
the blind are destitute of sense
of the deaf and the deaf. About me because of the power he has
of the senses of each one, previously mentioned.
      </p>
     </div>
    </div>
    <div n="2" subtype="chapter" type="textpart">
     <div n="1" subtype="section" type="textpart">
      <p>
       Τοῦ δὲ σώματος ἐν οἷς ἐγγίγνεσθαι πέφυκεν αἰσθητηρίοις,
ἔνιοι μὲν ζητοῦσι κατὰ τὰ στοιχεῖα τῶν σωμάτων·
οὐκ εὐποροῦντες δὲ πρὸς τέτταρα πέντ’ οὔσας συνάγειν,
γλίχονται περὶ τῆς πέμπτης.
      </p>
      <p lang="it">
       E del corpo dove viene toccato mancano i sensi,
anni senza chiedere secondo gli elementi dei corpi;
Ma chi non è ricco non ti porta alle quattro alle cinque,
scivolano verso le cinque.
      </p>
      <p lang="en">
       And of the body where it is touched, the senses are gone,
years without asking according to the elements of the bodies;
But those who are not wealthy do not bring you to four to five,
they slip around five o'clock.
      </p>
     </div>
     <div n="2" subtype="section" type="textpart">
      <p rend="cont">
       Ποιοῦσι δὲ πάντες τὴν
ὄψιν πυρὸς διὰ τὸ πάθους τινὸς ἀγνοεῖν τὴν αἰτίαν· θλιβομένου
γὰρ καὶ κινουμένου τοῦ ὀφθαλμοῦ φαίνεται πῦρ
ἐκλάμπειν· τοῦτο δ’ ἐν τῷ σκότει πέφυκε συμβαίνειν, ἢ
τῶν βλεφάρων ἐπικεκαλυμμένων· γίνεται γὰρ καὶ τότε
σκότος. Ἔχει δ’ ἀπορίαν τοῦτο καὶ ἑτέραν.
      </p>
      <p lang="it">
       Chi sono tutti?
guarda il fuoco della passione di chi ignora la causa dolorosa;
perché anche quando l'occhio si muove sembra fuoco
lampeggiava; è successo quando è caduto nell'oscurità, o
delle palpebre coperte perché succede anche allora
buio. Ha domande su questo e quello.
      </p>
      <p lang="en">
       Who is everyone?
look at the fire of the passion of one who ignores the cause; sorrowful
because even when the eye is moving it looks like fire
flashed; did this happen when it fell in the dark, or
of the eyelids covered; because it happens even then
darkness. He has questions about this and that.
      </p>
     </div>
     <div n="3" subtype="section" type="textpart">
      <p rend="cont">
       Εἰ γὰρ μὴ
ἔστι λανθάνειν αἰσθανόμενον καὶ ὁρῶντα ὁρώμενόν τι,
       <pb n="246"/>
       ἀνάγκη ἄρ’ αὐτὸν ἑαυτὸν ὁρᾶν τὸν ὀφθαλμόν. Διὰ τί
οὖν ἠρεμοῦντι τοῦτ’ οὐ συμβαίνει;
      </p>
      <p lang="it">
       Perché no?
essere latente sentire e vedere vedere cosa,



bisogno dell’occhio che vede sé stesso. Per quello
quindi non succede?
      </p>
      <p lang="en">
       Why not?
be latent feeling and seeing seeing what,



need for the self-seeing eye. For what
so it's not happening?
      </p>
     </div>
     <div n="4" subtype="section" type="textpart">
      <p rend="cont">
       Τὰ δ’ αἴτια τούτου,
καὶ τῆς ἀπορίας καὶ τοῦ δοκεῖν πῦρ εἶναι τὴν ὄψιν, ἐντεῦθεν
ληπτέον. Τὰ γὰρ λεῖα πέφυκεν ἐν τῷ σκότει λάμπειν, οὐ
μέντοι φῶς γε ποιεῖ, τοῦ δ’ ὀφθαλμοῦ τὸ καλούμενον
μέλαν καὶ μέσον λεῖον φαίνεται. Φαίνεται δὲ τοῦτο κινουμένου
τοῦ ὄμματος διὰ τὸ συμβαίνειν ὥσπερ δύο γίνεσθαι
τὸ ἕν. Τοῦτο δ’ ἡ ταχυτὴς ποιεῖ τῆς κινήσεως, ὥστε δοκεῖν
ἕτερον εἶναι τὸ ὁρῶν καὶ τὸ ὁρώμενον.
      </p>
      <p lang="it">
       Le ragioni di ciò,
e della questione e del fuoco di prova è la vista, da qui
destinatario Perché le parole cadevano nel buio, brillavano, no
menta luce ge poeti, del quarto occhio il chiamato
sembra nero e mediamente liscio. Ma questo sembra muoversi
dell'omma perché avviene come se ce ne fossero due
l'unico Questa è la velocità del movimento, in modo che abbiano un sapore
un altro è il vedere e il vedere.
      </p>
      <p lang="en">
       The reasons for this,
and of the question and of the trial fire is the sight, from here
recipient For the words fell in the dark, they shone, no
mint light ge poeti, of the fourth eye the called
it looks black and medium smooth. But this seems to be moving
of the omma because it happens as if there are two
the one This is the speed of the movement, so that they taste
another is the seeing and the seeing.
      </p>
     </div>
     <div n="5" subtype="section" type="textpart">
      <p rend="cont">
       Διὸ καὶ οὐ γίνεται,
ἂν μὴ ταχέως καὶ ἐν σκότει τοῦτο συμβῇ· τὸ γὰρ λεῖον ἐν
τῷ σκότει πέφυκε λάμπειν, οἷον κεφαλαὶ ἰχθύων τινῶν
καὶ ὁ τῆς σηπίας θολός· καὶ βραδέως μεταβάλλοντος τοῦ
ὄμματος οὐ συμβαίνει ὥστε δοκεῖν ἅμα ἓν καὶ δύο εἶναι τό
θ’ ὁρῶν καὶ τὸ ὁρώμενον.
      </p>
      <p lang="it">
       Perché non è possibile,
se ciò non avviene rapidamente e al buio;
Nell'oscurità cadde una lampada, che era la testa di alcuni pesci
e quello del seppia torbido e lentamente cangiante
Naturalmente non succede come si suol dire, se uno e due sono la stessa cosa
Vedrò e ciò che è visto.
      </p>
      <p lang="en">
       Because it's not possible,
if this does not happen quickly and in the dark;
In the darkness fell a lamp, which was the head of some fishes
and that of the sepia cloudy; and slowly changing
Of course, it doesn't happen as they say, if one and two are the same
I will see and what is seen.
      </p>
     </div>
     <div n="6" subtype="section" type="textpart">
      <p rend="cont">
       Ἐκείνως δ’ αὐτὸς αὑτὸν ὁρᾷ
ὁ ὀφθαλμός, ὥσπερ καὶ ἐν τῇ ἀνακλάσει, ἐπεὶ εἴ γε πῦρ
ἦν, καθάπερ Ἐμπεδοκλῆς φησὶ καὶ ἐν τῷ Τιμαίῳ γέγραπται,
καὶ συνέβαινε τὸ ὁρᾶν ἐξιόντος ὥσπερ ἐκ λαμπτῆρος
τοῦ φωτός, διὰ τί οὐ καὶ ἐν τῷ σκότει ἑώρα ἂν ἡ ὄψις;
      </p>
      <p lang="it">
       Poi lo vide
l'occhio, come nel riflesso, in fiamme
Era, secondo Empedocle, ed è scritto nel Timeo,
e avvenne la vista del sole come da una lampada
di luce, perché non anche nell'ora buia se la vista?
      </p>
      <p lang="en">
       Then he saw him
the eye, as in the reflection, on fire
It was, according to Empedocles, and it is written in the Timaeus,
and the sight of the sun as from a lamp happened
of light, why not even in the dark hour if the sight?
      </p>
     </div>
     <div n="7" subtype="section" type="textpart">
      <p rend="cont">
       Τὸ
δ’ ἀποσβέννυσθαι φάναι ἐν τῷ σκότει ἐξιοῦσαν, ὥσπερ ὁ
Τίμαιος λέγει, κενόν ἐστι παντελῶς· τίς γὰρ ἀπόσβεσις
φωτός ἐστιν; Σβέννυται γὰρ ἢ ὑγρῷ ἢ ψυχρῷ τὸ θερμὸν
καὶ ξηρόν, οἷον δοκεῖ τό τ’ ἐν τοῖς ἀνθρακώδεσιν εἶναι πῦρ
καὶ ἡ φλόξ, ὧν τῷ φωτὶ οὐδέτερον φαίνεται ὑπάρχον.
      </p>
      <p lang="it">
       IL
non svanirono nell'oscurità che sentivano, come il
Timeo dice che sei sempre vuoto, perché li consumi
c'è luce? Perché il calore si spegne con l'umidità o con il freddo
e secco, chi prova la t nei carboni è fuoco
e il flox, che sembra esistere senza la luce.
      </p>
      <p lang="en">
       The
they did not fade away in the darkness they felt, as the
Timaeus says, you are always empty, because you wear them out
is there light? Because heat is extinguished by wet or cold
and dry, whoever tries the t in the coals is fire
and the phlox, which seems to exist without the light.
      </p>
     </div>
     <div n="8" subtype="section" type="textpart">
      <p rend="cont">
       Εἰ
δ’ ἄρα ὑπάρχει μὲν ἀλλὰ διὰ τὸ ἠρέμα λανθάνει ἡμᾶς, ἔδει
μεθ’ ἡμέραν τε καὶ ἐν τῷ ὕδατι ἀποσβέννυσθαι τὸ φῶς,
καὶ ἐν τοῖς πάγοις μᾶλλον γίνεσθαι σκότον· ἡ γοῦν φλὸξ
καὶ τὰ πεπυρωμένα σώματα πάσχει τοῦτο· νῦν δ’ οὐδὲν
       <pb n="247"/>
       συμβαίνει τοιοῦτον.
      </p>
      <p lang="it">
       E
vedi, ci sono io, ma a causa del vento siamo bloccati, vedi
di giorno e nell'acqua la luce si affievolisce,
e nel ghiaccio probabilmente diverrà tenebra la pelle è fiamma;
e i corpi bruciati ne soffrono; ora non c'è più nulla



gli succede.
      </p>
      <p lang="en">
       E
see, there is me, but because of the wind, we are stranded, see
by day and in the water the light fades,
and in the ice it will probably become darkness; the skin is a flame
and burnt bodies are afflicted by this; now there is nothing



it happens to him.
      </p>
     </div>
     <div n="9" subtype="section" type="textpart">
      <p rend="cont">
       Ἐμπεδοκλῆς δ’ ἔοικε νομίζοντι ὁτὲ
μὲν ἐξιόντος τοῦ φωτός, ὥσπερ εἴρηται πρότερον, βλέπειν·
λέγει γοῦν οὕτως.
      </p>
      <p lang="it">
       Empedocle 4a Casa la pensa così
mediante l'emissione di luce, come detto prima, vedono;
lo dice lui.
      </p>
      <p lang="en">
       Empedocles 4th house thinking that
by the emission of light, as stated before, they see;
he says so.
      </p>
      <lg>
       <l>
        Ὡς δ’ ὅτε τις πρόοδον νοέων ὡπλίσσατο λύχνον,
       </l>
       <l lang="it">
        Come il progresso della semplice lampada,
       </l>
       <l lang="en">
        As the progress of the mere lamp,
       </l>
       <l>
        χειμερίην διὰ νύκτα πυρὸς σέλας αἰθομένοιο,
       </l>
       <l lang="it">
        inverno attraverso le notti dell'aurora boreale,
       </l>
       <l lang="en">
        winter through the nights of the aurora borealis,
       </l>
       <l>
        ἅψας παντοίων ἀνέμων λαμπτῆρας ἀμουργούς,
       </l>
       <l lang="it">
        Assenza di venti eterni, lampada di sabbia,
       </l>
       <l lang="en">
        Absence of eternal winds, a lamp of sand,
       </l>
       <l>
        οἵτ’ ἀνέμων μὲν πνεῦμα διασκιδνᾶσιν ἀέντων,
       </l>
       <l lang="it">
        che vento e spirito lacerano i respiri,
       </l>
       <l lang="en">
        that wind and spirit tear apart breaths,
       </l>
       <l>
        φῶς δ’ ἔξω διαθρῶσκον, ὅσον ταναώτερον ἦεν,
       </l>
       <l lang="it">
        la luce del giorno, quando era più giovane,
       </l>
       <l lang="en">
        light of day, when he was younger,
       </l>
       <l>
        λάμπεσκεν κατὰ βηλὸν ἀτειρέσιν ἀκτίνεσσιν·
       </l>
       <l lang="it">
        brillare come una freccia
       </l>
       <l lang="en">
        shine like an arrow
       </l>
       <l>
        ὢς δὲ τότ’ ἐν μήνιγξιν ἐεργμένον ὠγύγιον πῦρ
       </l>
       <l lang="it">
        ὢs ὢs ὢs tot' in meningxin ermenon ygygion pyr
       </l>
       <l lang="en">
        ὢs ὢs ὢs tot' in meningxin ermenon ygygion pyr
       </l>
       <l>
        λεπτῇσιν ὀθόνῃσι λοχάζετο κύκλοπα κούρην·
       </l>
       <l lang="it">
        λεπτῇσιν ὀθονῃσι lohazeto kkloppa kourin;
       </l>
       <l lang="en">
        λεπτῇσιν ὀθονῃσι lohazeto kkloppa kourin;
       </l>
       <l>
        αἱ δ’ ὕδατος μὲν βένθος ἀπέστεγον ἀμφινάοντος,
       </l>
       <l lang="it">
        le quarte acque gocciolavano di dolore,
       </l>
       <l lang="en">
        the fourth waters dripped with sorrow,
       </l>
       <l>
        πῦρ δ’ ἔξω διαθρῶσκον, ὅσον ταναώτερον ἦεν.
       </l>
       <l lang="it">
        pir d'exo diathroskon, purché fosse più giovane.
       </l>
       <l lang="en">
        pir d'exo diathroskon, as long as he was younger.
       </l>
      </lg>
     </div>
     <div n="10" subtype="section" type="textpart">
      <p>
       Ὁτε μὲν οὖν οὕτως ὁρᾶν φησίν, ὁτὲ δὲ ταῖς ἀπορροίαις
ταῖς ἀπὸ τῶν ὁρωμένων. Δημόκριτος δ’ ὅτι μὲν ὕδωρ
εἶναί φησι, λέγει καλῶς, ὅτι δ’ οἴεται τὸ ὁρᾶν εἶναι τὴν
ἔμφασιν, οὐ καλῶς· τοῦτο μὲν γὰρ συμβαίνει ὅτι τὸ ὄμμα
λεῖον, καὶ ἔστιν οὐκ ἐν ἐκείνῳ ἀλλ’ ἐν τῷ ὁρῶντι· ἀνάκλασις
γὰρ τὸ πάθος.
      </p>
      <p lang="it">
       Se è così, lasciamoli vedere, ma quali sono le conseguenze
quelli degli eletti. Democrito IV perché senz'acqua
è finzione, dice bene, perché non vede la vista, è il
sottolineo, non bene, perché questo non avviene a causa della nazione
leon, e non è in quello ma nel vedere;
perché la passione
      </p>
      <p lang="en">
       If so, let them see, but what are the consequences
those of the chosen ones. Democritus IV because without water
it's fiction, he says well, because he doesn't see the sight, it's the
emphasin, not well, because this does not happen because the nation
leon, and it is not in that but in the seeing; reflection
because the passion
      </p>
     </div>
     <div n="11" subtype="section" type="textpart">
      <p rend="cont">
       Ἀλλὰ καθόλου περὶ τῶν ἐμφαινομένων καὶ
ἀνακλάσεως οὐδέν πω δῆλον ἦν, ὡς ἔοικεν. Ἄτοπον
δὲ καὶ τὸ μὴ ἐπελθεῖν αὐτῷ ἀπορῆσαι διὰ τί ὁ ὀφθαλμὸς
       <pb n="248"/>
       ὁρᾷ μόνον, τῶν δ’ ἄλλων οὐδὲν ἐν οἷς ἐμφαίνεται τὰ εἴδωλα.
Τὸ μὲν οὖν τὴν ὄψιν εἶναι ὕδατος ἀληθὲς μέν, οὐ μέντοι
συμβαίνει τὸ ὁρᾶν ᾗ ὕδωρ ἀλλ’ ᾗ διαφανές· ὃ καὶ ἐπὶ τοῦ
ἀέρος κοινόν ἐστιν.
      </p>
      <p lang="it">
       Ma nemmeno per niente riguardo alle apparenze
di riflessione, non direi che sia stata un'illusione, così com'è stata. Atopon
ma anche se non lo raggiunge, ti chiedi perché l'occhio



Degli altri quattro dice soltanto nessuno in cui appaiono gli idoli.
Quello che vedo nei miei occhi è acqua, davvero, non mento
succede che la vista sia acqua ma trasparente cosa e su di essa
l'aria è comune.
      </p>
      <p lang="en">
       But not at all about appearances either
of reflection, I would not say it was a delusion, as it was. Atopon
but even if it does not reach him, you wonder why the eye



He only says, of the other four, none in which the idols appear.
What I see in my eyes is water, really, I don't lie
it happens that the sight is water but transparent; what and on it
air is common.
      </p>
     </div>
     <div n="12" subtype="section" type="textpart">
      <p rend="cont">
       Ἀλλ’ εὐφυλακτότερον καὶ εὐπιλητότερον
τὸ ὕδωρ τοῦ ἀέρος· διόπερ ἡ κόρη καὶ τὸ ὄμμα
ὕδατός ἐστιν. Τοῦτο δὲ καὶ ἐπ’ αὐτῶν τῶν ἔργων δῆλον·
φαίνεται γὰρ ὕδωρ τὸ ἐκρέον διαφθειρομένων, καὶ ἔν
γε τοῖς πάμπαν ἐμβρύοις τῇ ψυχρότητι ὑπερβάλλον
καὶ τῇ λαμπρότητι.
      </p>
      <p lang="it">
       Ma più cauto e amichevole
l'acqua dell'aria; dioper la figlia e la umma
è acqua. E questo anche su queste opere che fanno;
poiché l'acqua corrente dei corrotti sembra essere acqua, e
ge agli embrioni sempre presenti della freddezza esagerata
e la brillantezza.
      </p>
      <p lang="en">
       But more cautious and friendly
the water of the air; dioper the daughter and the umma
it is water. And this also upon these works they do;
for the flowing water of the corrupt seems to be water, and
ge to the ever-present embryos of the coldness exaggeration
and the brilliance.
      </p>
     </div>
     <div n="13" subtype="section" type="textpart">
      <p rend="cont">
       Καὶ τὸ λευκὸν τοῦ ὄμματος ἐν
τοῖς ἔχουσιν αἷμα πῖον καὶ λιπαρόν· ὅπερ διὰ τοῦτ’ ἐστί,
πρὸς τὸ διαμένειν τὸ ὑγρὸν ἄπηκτον. Καὶ διὰ τοῦτο τοῦ
σώματος ἀρριγότατον ὁ ὀφθαλμός ἐστιν· οὐδεὶς γάρ πω
τὸ ἐντὸς τῶν βλεφάρων ἐρρίγωσεν. Τῶν δ’ ἀναίμων
σκληρόδερμοι οἱ ὀφθαλμοί εἰσι, καὶ τοῦτο ποιεῖ τὴν σκέπην.
      </p>
      <p lang="it">
       E il bianco del sigillo dentro
per loro hanno sangue più ubriaco e più grasso;
verso il liquido persistente. E per questo motivo
L'occhio è la parte più importante del corpo; niente da dire
l'interno delle palpebre si riversò. Di quattro anime
gli occhi hanno la pelle dura, e questo ha senso.
      </p>
      <p lang="en">
       And the white of the seal in
to them they have blood that is drunker and fatter; for therefore it is,
towards the abiding liquid. And because of this
The eye is the most important part of the body; nothing to say
the inside of the eyelids poured. Of four souls
the eyes are hard-skinned, and this makes sense.
      </p>
     </div>
     <div n="14" subtype="section" type="textpart">
      <p rend="cont">
       Ἄλογον δὲ ὅλως τὸ ἐξιόντι τινὶ τὴν ὄψιν ὁρᾶν, καὶ
ἀποτείνεσθαι μέχρι τῶν ἄστρων, ἢ μέχρι τινὸς ἐξιοῦσαν
συμφύεσθαι, καθάπερ λέγουσί τινες. Τούτου μὲν γὰρ βέλτιον
τὸ ἐν ἀρχῇ συμφύεσθαι τοῦ ὄμματος. Ἀλλὰ καὶ
τοῦτο εὔηθες· τό τε γὰρ συμφύεσθαι τί ἐστι φωτὶ πρὸς
φῶς; Ἣ πῶς οἷόν θ’ ὑπάρχειν; Οὐ γὰρ τῷ τυχόντι
συμφύεται τὸ τυχόν.
      </p>
      <p lang="it">
       Ma dopo un cavallo, vedono uscire tutto, e
arrivare fino alle stelle, o finché vissero
stringiti, parliamo di te. Niente di meglio di questo
la compressione iniziale della umma. Ma anche
Questo è quello che hai detto;
leggero; Come può qualcuno esistere? Affatto
è allegato, se presente.
      </p>
      <p lang="en">
       But after a horse, they see the whole thing coming out, and
reach up to the stars, or until they lived
squeeze in, let's talk about you. Nothing better than this
the initial compression of the umma. But also
This is what you said;
light; How can anyone exist? Not at all
is attached if any.
      </p>
     </div>
     <div n="15" subtype="section" type="textpart">
      <p rend="cont">
       Τό τ’ ἐντὸς τῷ ἐκτὸς πῶς; Ἡ
γὰρ μῆνιγξ μεταξύ ἐστιν. Περὶ μὲν οὖν τοῦ ἄνευ φωτὸς
μὴ ὁρᾶν εἴρηται ἐν ἄλλοις· ἀλλ’ εἴτε φῶς εἴτ’ ἀήρ ἐστι τὸ
μεταξὺ τοῦ ὁρωμένου καὶ τοῦ ὄμματος, ἡ διὰ τούτου κίνησίς
ἐστιν ἡ ποιοῦσα τὸ ὁρᾶν. Καὶ εὐλόγως τὸ ἐντός ἐστιν
       <pb n="249"/>
       ὕδατος· διαφανὲς γὰρ τὸ ὕδωρ.
      </p>
      <p lang="it">
       L'interno come? IL
perché c'è poco in mezzo. Su di me, quindi, senza luce
non lo vedo negli altri; ma se sia la luce o l'aria
tra l'uno e l'altro, il movimento dovuto a questo
è lei che lo vede. E fortunatamente è dentro



d'acqua; perché l'acqua è trasparente.
      </p>
      <p lang="en">
       The inside out how? The
for there is little between. About me, therefore, without light
do not see it in others; but whether light or air is the
between the one and the other, the movement due to this
she is the one who sees it. And blessedly it is within



of water; for water is transparent.
      </p>
     </div>
     <div n="16" subtype="section" type="textpart">
      <p rend="cont">
       Ὁρᾶται δὲ ὥσπερ καὶ ἔξω
οὐκ ἄνευ φωτός, οὕτω καὶ ἐντός· διαφανὲς ἄρα δεῖ εἶναι.
Καὶ ἀνάγκη ὕδωρ εἶναι, ἐπειδὴ οὐκ ἀήρ. Οὐ γὰρ ἐπὶ
τοῦ ἐσχάτου ὄμματος ἡ ψυχὴ ἢ τῆς ψυχῆς τὸ αἰσθητήριόν
ἐστιν, ἀλλὰ δῆλον ὅτι ἐντός· διόπερ ἀνάγκη διαφανὲς
εἶναι καὶ δεκτικὸν φωτὸς τὸ ἐντὸς τοῦ ὄμματος.
      </p>
      <p lang="it">
       Può essere visto anche dall'esterno
non senza luce, quindi anche trasparente, quindi eccola qui;
E l'acqua è necessaria, perché non c'è aria. Non perché su
dell'ultima omma l'anima o dell'anima il senso
lo è, ma sembra che sia trasparente per necessità
anche l'interno della umma è ricettivo alla luce.
      </p>
      <p lang="en">
       It can be seen from outside as well
not without light, so also inside; transparent, so here it is.
And water is needed, because there is no air. Not because on
of the ultimate omma the soul or of the soul the sense
it is, but it seems that it is inside; transparent because of necessity
the inside of the umma is also receptive to light.
      </p>
     </div>
     <div n="17" subtype="section" type="textpart">
      <p rend="cont">
       Καὶ τοῦτο
καὶ ἐπὶ τῶν συμβαινόντων δῆλον· ἤδη γάρ τισι πληγεῖσιν
ἐν πολέμῳ παρὰ τὸν κρόταφον οὕτως ὥστ’ ἐκτμηθῆναι
τοὺς πόρους τοῦ ὄμματος, ἔδοξε γενέσθαι σκότος ὥσπερ
λύχνου ἀποσβεσθέντος, διὰ τὸ οἷον λαμπτῆρά τινα ἀποτμηθῆναι
τὸ διαφανές, τὴν καλουμένην κόρην.
      </p>
      <p lang="it">
       E questo
e per le cose che stanno accadendo, saranno già feriti per questo
in guerra per il tempio tanto che venne reciso
i pori delle persone, lascia che ci sia l'oscurità come
una lampada spenta, per la quale le lampade sono apprezzate
la trasparente, la figlia chiamata.
      </p>
      <p lang="en">
       And this
and on the things that are happening, they will be hurt already because of this
in war over the temple so that it is severed
the pores of the people, let there be darkness as
a lamp extinguished, for whose lamps are valued
the transparent, the called daughter.
      </p>
     </div>
     <div n="18" subtype="section" type="textpart">
      <p rend="cont">
       Ὤστ’ εἴπερ τούτων
τι συμβαίνει, καθάπερ λέγομεν, φανερὸν ὡς δεῖ τοῦτον
τὸν τρόπον ἀποδιδόναι καὶ προσάπτειν ἕκαστον τῶν αἰσθητηρίων
ἑνὶ τῶν στοιχείων. Τοῦ μὲν ὄμματος τὸ ὁρατικὸν
ὕδατος ὑποληπτέον, ἀέρος δὲ τὸ τῶν ψόφων αἰσθητικόν,
πυρὸς δὲ τὴν ὄσφρησιν.
      </p>
      <p lang="it">
       Inoltre
ciò che sta accadendo, come diciamo, chiaramente come lo vede
il modo in cui sprigiona e offende ciascuno dei sensi
uno degli elementi. L'occhio visibile
l'acqua è gradevole e l'aria è sensuale,
ma spara l'odore.
      </p>
      <p lang="en">
       On top of that
what is happening, as we say, clearly as he sees it
the way it gives off and offends each of the senses
one of the elements. The visible eye
water is palatable, and air is sensuous,
but fire the smell.
      </p>
     </div>
     <div n="19" subtype="section" type="textpart">
      <p rend="cont">
       Ὃ γὰρ ἐνεργείᾳ ἡ ὄσφρησις,
τοῦτο δυνάμει τὸ ὀσφραντικόν· τὸ γὰρ αἰσθητὸν ἐνεργεῖν
ποιεῖ τὴν αἴσθησιν, ὥσθ’ ὑπάρχειν ἀνάγκη αὐτὴν δυνάμει
πρότερον. Ἡ δ’ ὀσμὴ καπνώδης τίς ἐστιν ἀναθυμίασις, ἡ
δ’ ἀναθυμίασις ἡ καπνώδης ἐκ πυρός.
      </p>
      <p lang="it">
       Poiché l'olfatto è attivo,
questo in virtù dell'olfatto, perché attiva il senso
crea la sensazione, come se ci fosse bisogno di questo potere
prima. Il secondo odore di fumo è l'anatimiasi, il
Non vaporizzare quello fumoso dal fuoco.
      </p>
      <p lang="en">
       Because smell is active,
this by virtue of the smell, because it activates the sense
it creates the feeling, as if there is a need for this power
earlier. The second smoky smell of them is anathimiasis, the
Don't vaporize the smoky one from the fire.
      </p>
     </div>
     <div n="20" subtype="section" type="textpart">
      <p rend="cont">
       Διὸ καὶ τῷ περὶ
τὸν ἐγκέφαλον τόπῳ τὸ τῆς ὀσφρήσεως αἰσθητήριόν ἐστιν
ἴδιον· δυνάμει γὰρ θερμὴ ἡ τοῦ ψυχροῦ ὕλη ἐστίν. Καὶ
ἡ τοῦ ὄμματος γένεσις τὸν αὐτὸν ἔχει τρόπον· ἀπὸ τοῦ
ἐγκεφάλου γὰρ συνέστηκεν· οὗτος γὰρ ὑγρότατος καὶ ψυχρότατος
τῶν ἐν τῷ σώματι μορίων ἐστίν.
      </p>
      <p lang="it">
       Per e riguardo
il cervello è il luogo in cui si trova l'olfatto
anche, perché la materia fredda è calda per forza. E
La nascita della nazione ha una via da lui;
poiché era composto da un cervello; perché questo è umido e freddo
delle molecole del corpo.
      </p>
      <p lang="en">
       For and about
the brain is the place where the sense of smell is
even, because cold matter is hot by force. And
The birth of the nation has a way; from him
for he was composed of a brain; for this one is moist and cold
of the molecules in the body.
      </p>
     </div>
     <div n="21" subtype="section" type="textpart">
      <p rend="cont">
       Τὸ δ’ ἁπτικὸν
γῆς. Τὸ δὲ γευστικὸν εἶδός τι ἁφῆς ἐστίν. Καὶ διὰ
τοῦτο πρὸς τῇ καρδίᾳ τὸ αἰσθητήριον αὐτῶν, τῆς τε γεύσεως
       <pb n="250"/>
       καὶ τῆς ἁφῆς· ἀντίκειται γὰρ τῷ ἐγκεφάλῳ αὕτη, καὶ
ἔστι θερμότατον τῶν μορίων. Καὶ περὶ μὲν τῶν αἰσθητικῶν
τοῦ σώματος μορίων ἔστω τοῦτον τὸν τρόπον
διωρισμένα.
      </p>
      <p lang="it">
       Il quarto tocco
terra Per quanto riguarda il gusto, vedrai di cosa si tratta. E da
questo al cuore della loro sensibilità, del loro gusto



e di pace: poiché è contrario a questo capo, e
È la più calda delle molecole. E sull'estetica
del corpo delle molecole essere in questo modo
separato.
      </p>
      <p lang="en">
       The fourth touch
land As for the taste, you will see what it is. And by
this to the heart of their sensibility, of their taste



and of peace: for it is opposed to this head, and
It is the hottest of molecules. And about the aesthetics
of the body of molecules be this way
separated.
      </p>
     </div>
    </div>
    <div n="3" subtype="chapter" type="textpart">
     <div n="1" subtype="section" type="textpart">
      <p>
       Περὶ δὲ τῶν αἰσθητῶν τῶν καθ’ ἕκαστον αἰσθητήριον,
οἷον λέγω χρώματος καὶ ψόφου καὶ ὀσμῆς καὶ χυμοῦ καὶ
ἁφῆς, καθόλου μὲν εἴρηται ἐν τοῖς περὶ ψυχῆς, τί τὸ ἔργον
αὐτῶν καὶ τί τὸ ἐνεργεῖν καθ’ ἕκαστον τῶν αἰσθητηρίων·
τί δέ ποτε δεῖ λέγειν ὁτιοῦν αὐτῶν, οἷον τί χρῶμα ἢ τί
ψόφον ἢ τί ὀσμὴν ἢ χυμόν, ὁμοίως δὲ καὶ περὶ ἁφῆς, ἐπισκεπτέον,
καὶ πρῶτον περὶ χρώματος.
      </p>
      <p lang="it">
       Per quanto riguarda i sensi di ciascun senso,
che io chiamo colore, gusto, odore, succo e
Naturalmente tra coloro che parlano dell'anima non si dice affatto cosa sia il lavoro
di loro e cosa attivano in ciascuno dei sensi;
cosa dicono quando dicono chi sono, chi di che colore o cosa
respiro o qualsiasi odore o succo, e allo stesso modo riguardo al tatto, alla visita,
e prima sul colore.
      </p>
      <p lang="en">
       As for the senses of each sense,
who I call color and taste and smell and juice and
Of course, it is not at all said among those about the soul, what the work is
of them and what they activate in each of the senses;
what do they say when they say who they are, who what color or what
breath or any smell or juice, and likewise about touch, visiting,
and first about color.
      </p>
     </div>
     <div n="2" subtype="section" type="textpart">
      <p rend="cont">
       Ἔστι μὲν οὖν ἕκαστον
διχῶς λεγόμενον, τὸ μὲν ἐνεργείᾳ τὸ δὲ δυνάμει. Τὸ
μὲν οὖν ἐνεργείᾳ χρῶμα καὶ ὁ ψόφος πῶς ἐστὶ τὸ αὐτὸ ἢ
ἕτερον ταῖς κατ’ ἐνέργειαν αἰσθήσεσιν, οἷον ὁράσει καὶ ἀκούσει,
εἴρηται ἐν τοῖς περὶ ψυχῆς· τί δὲ ἕκαστον αὐτῶν ὂν
ποιήσει τὴν αἴσθησιν καὶ τὴν ἐνέργειαν, νῦν λέγωμεν.
      </p>
      <p lang="it">
       Lui è con me allora una volta
senza dirlo, l'uno per l'energia e l'altro per la potenza. IL
ma poi colora l'energia e la mente com'è oppure
altri con i loro sensi energetici, che vedono e sentono,
si dice tra quelli dell'anima; ma cos'è ciascuno di essi?
fai il sentimento e l'energia, ora diciamo.
      </p>
      <p lang="en">
       He is with me then once
without saying, the one by energy and the other by power. The
but then color energy and the mind how is it or
others by their energetic senses, who see and hear,
it is said among those about the soul; but what is each of them
do the feeling and the energy, now we say.
      </p>
     </div>
     <div n="3" subtype="section" type="textpart">
      <p rend="cont">
       Ὥσπερ οὖν εἴρηται περὶ φωτὸς ἐν ἐκείνοις, ὅτι ἐστὶ χρῶμα
τοῦ διαφανοῦς κατὰ συμβεβηκός· ὅταν γὰρ ἐνῇ τι πυρῶδες
ἐν διαφανεῖ, ἡ μὲν παρουσία φῶς, ἡ δὲ στέρησίς ἐστι
σκότος.
      </p>
      <p lang="it">
       Perciò si dice della luce tra loro, perché è colore
trasparente per lui come una cosa ovvia;
nella trasparenza, la presenza della luce, ma l'assenza di essa
buio.
      </p>
      <p lang="en">
       Therefore it is said of light among them, because it is color
transparent to him as a matter of course;
in transparency, the presence of light, but the absence of it
darkness.
      </p>
     </div>
     <div n="4" subtype="section" type="textpart">
      <p rend="cont">
       Ὃ δὲ λέγομεν διαφανές, οὐκ ἔστιν ἴδιον ἀέρος ἢ
ὕδατος οὐδ’ ἄλλου τῶν οὕτω λεγομένων σωμάτων, ἀλλά
τίς ἐστι κοινὴ φύσις καὶ δύναμις, ἣ χωριστὴ μὲν οὐκ
ἔστιν, ἐν τούτοις δ’ ἐστί, καὶ τοῖς ἄλλοις σώμασιν ἐνυπάρχει,
τοῖς μὲν μᾶλλον τοῖς δ’ ἧττον. Ὥσπερ οὖν καὶ τῶν
σωμάτων ἀνάγκη τι εἶναι ἔσχατον, καὶ ταύτης.
      </p>
      <p lang="it">
       Ma quando diciamo trasparente non è la stessa aria, vero?
acqua di nessun altro dei cosiddetti corpi, ma
qual è la natura e il potere comune, ἣ separati dal n
è, anche se non è, ed esiste in altri corpi,
a quelli che sono con me piuttosto a quelli che sono morti. Ὥsper oὖn e tạn
i corpi hanno bisogno dell'ultimo, e di questo.
      </p>
      <p lang="en">
       But when we say transparent, it is not the same air, is it?
water of none other of the so-called bodies, but
what is the common nature and power, ἣ separated by no
it is, although it is not, and it exists in other bodies,
to those with me rather to those who died. Ὥsper oὖn and tạn
bodies need what is the last, and this one.
      </p>
     </div>
     <div n="5" subtype="section" type="textpart">
      <p rend="cont">
       Ἡ μὲν οὖν
τοῦ φωτὸς φύσις ἐν ἀορίστῳ τῷ διαφανεῖ ἐστίν· τοῦ δ’ ἐν
τοῖς σώμασι διαφανοῦς τὸ ἔσχατον, ὅτι μὲν εἴη ἄν τι,
       <pb n="251"/>
       δῆλον, ὅτι δὲ τοῦτ’ ἐστὶ τὸ χρῶμα, ἐκ τῶν συμβαινόντων
φανερόν. Τὸ γὰρ χρῶμα ἢ ἐν τῷ πέρατί ἐστιν ἢ πέρας·
διὸ καὶ οἱ Πυθαγόρειοι τὴν ἐπιφάνειαν χροιὰν ἐκάλουν.
      </p>
      <p lang="it">
       Il me stesso
la natura della luce nell'aoristo è trasparente alla quarta
ai corpi trasparenti gli ultimi, perché se fosse cosa,



Delon, perché questo è il colore, degli avvenimenti
ovvio. Perché il colore o è nel passato o è oltre;
così i Pitagorici chiamano la superficie abbronzatura.
      </p>
      <p lang="en">
       The me oὖn
the nature of light in the aorist is transparent to the fourth
to the bodies transparent the last, because if it was what,



Delon, because this is the color, from the happenings
obvious. Because color is either in the past or beyond;
so the Pythagoreans call the surface tan.
      </p>
     </div>
     <div n="6" subtype="section" type="textpart">
      <p rend="cont">
       Ἔστι μὲν γὰρ ἐν τῷ τοῦ σώματος πέρατι, ἀλλ’ οὔ
τι τὸ τοῦ σώματος πέρας, ἀλλὰ τὴν αὐτὴν φύσιν δεῖ νομίζειν,
ἥπερ καὶ ἔξω χρωματίζεται, ταύτην καὶ ἐντός. Φαίνεται
δὲ καὶ ἀὴρ καὶ ὕδωρ χρωματιζόμενα· καὶ γὰρ ἡ
αὐγὴ τοιοῦτόν ἐστιν.
      </p>
      <p lang="it">
       Perché sono nell'aldilà del corpo, ma non è così
ciò che passa il corpo, ma questa natura vedono,
È colorato sia all'esterno che all'interno. Sembra
e l'aria e l'acqua si colorano;
è la sua gloria.
      </p>
      <p lang="en">
       For I am in the body beyond, but not
what the body passes, but this nature they see,
It is colored both outside and inside. It looks
and air and water being colored;
it is his glory.
      </p>
     </div>
     <div n="7" subtype="section" type="textpart">
      <p rend="cont">
       Ἀλλ’ ἐκεῖ μὲν διὰ τὸ ἐν ἀορίστῳ οὐ
τὴν αὐτὴν ἐγγύθεν καὶ προσιοῦσι καὶ πόρρωθεν ἔχει χροιὰν
οὔθ’ ὁ ἀὴρ οὔθ’ ἡ θάλαττα· ἐν δὲ τοῖς σώμασιν ἐὰν μὴ τὸ
περιέχον ποιῇ τὸ μεταβάλλειν, ὥρισται καὶ ἡ φαντασία
τῆς χρόας. Δῆλον ἄρα ὅτι τὸ αὐτὸ κἀκεῖ κἀνθάδε δεκτικὸν
τῆς χρόας ἐστίν.
      </p>
      <p lang="it">
       Ma non c'è a causa dell'aoristo
Ha la stessa carnagione da vicino e da lontano
né l'aria né il mare ma nei corpi se non il
contenendo chi lo cambia, si determina anche l'immaginazione
del tempo. Sto dicendo che questo è un male per tutti
del tempo che è.
      </p>
      <p lang="en">
       But there is no because of the aorist
He has the same complexion from near and far
neither the air nor the sea; but in the bodies if not the
containing who changes it, the imagination is also determined
of the time. I am saying that this is bad for everyone
of the time it is.
      </p>
     </div>
     <div n="8" subtype="section" type="textpart">
      <p rend="cont">
       Τὸ ἄρα διαφανὲς καθ’ ὅσον ὑπάρχει
ἐν τοῖς σώμασιν (ὑπάρχει δὲ μᾶλλον καὶ ἧττον ἐν πᾶσι)
χρώματος ποιεῖ μετέχειν. Ἐπεὶ δ’ ἐν πέρατι ἡ χρόα, τούτου
ἂν ἐν πέρατι εἴη. Ὥστε χρῶμα ἂν εἴη τὸ τοῦ διαφανοῦς
ἐν σώματι ὡρισμένῳ πέρας.
      </p>
      <p lang="it">
       Così trasparente per quanto esiste
nei corpi (ma probabilmente c'è anche l'ottavo in tutto)
di colore che partecipa. Allora il tempo è finito
se oltre. È un colore se è trasparente
in un certo corpo.
      </p>
      <p lang="en">
       So transparent as far as it exists
in the bodies (but there is probably also the eighth in all)
of color who participates. Then the time of this is over
if beyond that. It is a color if it is transparent
in a certain body.
      </p>
     </div>
     <div n="9" subtype="section" type="textpart">
      <p rend="cont">
       Καὶ αὐτῶν δὲ τῶν
διαφανῶν, οἷον ὕδατος καὶ εἴ τι ἄλλο τοιοῦτον, καὶ ὅσοις
φαίνεται χρῶμα ἴδιον ὑπάρχειν κατὰ τὸ ἔσχατον, ὁμοίως
πᾶσιν ὑπάρχει. Ἔστι μὲν οὖν ἐνεῖναι ἐν τῷ διαφανεῖ τοῦθ’
ὅπερ καὶ ἐν τῷ ἀέρι ποιεῖ φῶς, ἔστι δὲ μή, ἀλλ’ ἐστερῆσθαι.
Ὥσπερ οὖν ἐκεῖ τὸ μὲν φῶς τὸ δὲ σκότος. οὕτως ἐν τοῖς
σώμασιν ἐγγίνεται τὸ λευκὸν καὶ τὸ μέλαν.
      </p>
      <p lang="it">
       E questi
trasparente, sia acqua o qualsiasi altra cosa del genere, e quelli
sembra essere lo stesso colore alla fine, allo stesso modo
esiste sempre. Che cosa è dunque nella trasparenza di questo?
Perché c'è luce nell'aria, ma non c'è luce, ma mancherà.
Poi c'è la luce e l'oscurità. quindi tra i
il tocco bianco e nero.
      </p>
      <p lang="en">
       And these ones
transparent, whether water or anything else like that, and those
it seems to be the same color in the end, likewise
it always exists. What, then, is he in the transparency of this?
For there is light in the air, but there is no light, but it will be lacking.
Then there is light and darkness. thus among the
the white and the black touch.
      </p>
     </div>
     <div n="10" subtype="section" type="textpart">
      <p rend="cont">
       Περὶ δὲ τῶν
ἄλλων χρωμάτων ἤδη διελομένους ποσαχῶς ἐνδέχεται γίγνεσθαι
λεκτέον. Ἐνδέχεται μὲν γὰρ παρ’ ἄλληλα τιθέμενα
τὸ λευκὸν καὶ τὸ μέλαν, ὥσθ’ ἑκάτερον μὲν εἶναι ἀόρατον
       <pb n="252"/>
       διὰ σμικρότητα, τὸ δ’ ἐξ ἀμφοῖν ὁρατὸν οὕτω γίνεσθαι.
      </p>
      <p lang="it">
       Ma riguardo a
è possibile realizzare altri colori già modificati
Lezione. Dopotutto è possibile
il bianco e il nero, poiché entrambi sono invisibili



per piccolezza la quarta è ben visibile così.
      </p>
      <p lang="en">
       But about the
of other colors that have already been changed can be made
lecteon. It is possible, after all
the white and the black, as both are invisible



due to smallness, the fourth is clearly visible like this.
      </p>
     </div>
     <div n="11" subtype="section" type="textpart">
      <p rend="cont">
       Τοῦτο γὰρ οὔτε λευκὸν οἷόν τε φαίνεσθαι οὔτε μέλαν·
ἐπεὶ δ’ ἀνάγκη μέν τι ἔχειν χρῶμα, τούτων δ’ οὐδέτερον
δυνατόν, ἀνάγκη μικτόν τι εἶναι καὶ εἶδός τι χρόας ἕτερον.
      </p>
      <p lang="it">
       Perché questo non è né bianco né nero;
su d' bisogno di ciò che ha colore, di questi d' neutri
possibile, è necessario mescolare ciò che è e che tipo di tempo è diverso.
      </p>
      <p lang="en">
       For this is neither white nor black;
on d' need of what has color, of these d' neutral
possible, need to mix what it is and what kind of time it is different.
      </p>
     </div>
     <div n="12" subtype="section" type="textpart">
      <p rend="cont">
       Ἔστι μὲν οὖν οὕτως ὑπολαβεῖν πλείους εἶναι χρόας παρὰ τὸ
λευκὸν καὶ τὸ μέλαν, πολλὰς δὲ τῷ λόγῳ· τρία γὰρ πρὸς
δύο, καὶ τρία πρὸς τέτταρα, καὶ κατ’ ἄλλους ἀριθμοὺς ἔστι
παρ’ ἄλληλα κεῖσθαι, τὰ δ’ ὅλως κατὰ μὲν λόγον μηδένα,
καθ’ ὑπεροχὴν δέ τινα καὶ ἔλλειψιν ἀσύμμετρον, καὶ τὸν
αὐτὸν δὴ τρόπον ἔχειν ταῦτα ταῖς συμφωνίαις· τὰ μὲν
γὰρ ἐν ἀριθμοῖς εὐλογίστοις χρώματα, καθάπερ ἐκεῖ τὰς
συμφωνίας, τὰ ἥδιστα τῶν χρωμάτων εἶναι δοκοῦντα, οἷον
τὸ ἁλουργὸν καὶ φοινικοῦν καὶ ὀλίγ’ ἄττα τοιαῦτα, δι’
ἥνπερ αἰτίαν καὶ αἱ συμφωνίαι ὀλίγαι, τὰ δὲ μὴ ἐν ἀριθμοῖς
τἆλλα χρώματα, ἢ καὶ πάσας τὰς χρόας ἐν ἀριθμοῖς εἶναι,
τὰς μὲν τεταγμένας τὰς δὲ ἀτάκτους, καὶ αὐτὰς ταύτας,
ὅταν μὴ καθαραὶ ὦσι, διὰ τὸ μὴ ἐν ἀριθμοῖς εἶναι τοιαύτας
γίνεσθαι.
      </p>
      <p lang="it">
       Se, quindi, ne assumono di più, è tempo di
bianco e nero, ma tanti per il motivo, per tre parole
due, da tre a quattro e ad altri numeri
d'altro canto tutti e quattro sono, in una parola, zero,
In un modo meraviglioso, non vuoi essere asimmetrico, e quello giusto
Questi accordi non prevedono questa via;
perché in quantità di colori benedetti, vedeteli lì
secondo l'accordo, i colori dei colori corrispondono, chiunque
l'alurgon e le palme e pochi atta di questo, per
perché gli accordi sono pochi, ma non nei numeri
i colori dorati, o anche tutti i colori nei numeri, sono,
quelli disordinati e quelli disordinati, e questi stessi,
quando non sono puliti, cioè perché non sono numerici, lo sono
diventare.
      </p>
      <p lang="en">
       If, therefore, they hire more, it is time than the
white and black, but many for the reason, for three words
two, and three to four, and to other numbers
on the other hand, all four are, in a word, zero,
In a wonderful way, you don't want to be asymmetric, and the one
These agreements do not have this way;
for in numbers of blessed colors, see them there
according to agreement, the colors of the colors are matching, whosoever
the alurgon and the palm trees and a few atta of this, for
because the agreements are few, but not in numbers
golden colors, or even all colors in numbers are,
the unordered ones and the disorderly ones, and these same ones,
when they are not clean, that is, because they are not in numbers, they are
become.
      </p>
     </div>
     <div n="13" subtype="section" type="textpart">
      <p rend="cont">
       Εἷς μὲν οὖν τρόπος τῆς γενέσεως τῶν χρωμάτων
οὗτος, εἷς δὲ τὸ φαίνεσθαι δι’ ἀλλήλων, οἷον ἐνίοτε οἱ γραφῆς
ποιοῦσιν, ἑτέραν χρόαν ἐφ’ ἑτέραν ἐναργεστέραν
ἐπαλείφουσιν, ὥσπερ ὅταν ἐν ὕδατί τι ἢ ἐν ἀέρι βούλωνται
ποιῆσαι φαινόμενον, καὶ οἷον ὁ ἥλιος καθ’ αὑτὸν μὲν
λευκὸς φαίνεται, διὰ δ’ ἀχλύος καὶ καπνοῦ φοινικοῦς.
      </p>
      <p lang="it">
       Un modo per creare colori
questo, ma lo vedono gli altri, che a volte le scritture
chi sono, in un altro momento, in un altro momento
spalmato, come se immerso in acqua o aria
tu sei un fenomeno e chi è il sole stesso
sembra bianco, per la sporcizia e il fumo delle palme.
      </p>
      <p lang="en">
       A way of creating colors
this one, but it is seen by others, that sometimes the scriptures
who are they, at another time, at another time
smeared, as when immersed in water or air
you are a phenomenon, and who is the sun itself
it looks white, because of the dirt and smoke of the palm trees.
      </p>
     </div>
     <div n="14" subtype="section" type="textpart">
      <p rend="cont">
       Πολλαὶ
δὲ καὶ οὕτως ἔσονται χρόαι τὸν αὐτὸν τρόπον τῷ πρότερον
εἰρημένῳ· λόγος γὰρ ἂν εἴη τις τῶν ἐπιπολῆς πρὸς
       <pb n="253"/>
       τὰ ἐν βάθει, τὰ δὲ καὶ ὅλως οὐκ ἐν λόγῳ.
      </p>
      <p lang="it">
       Molto
E quindi sono come prima
alla pace; perché se fossero parole del nemico,



quelli in profondità, ma quelli e tutto non nella ragione.
      </p>
      <p lang="en">
       A lot
And so they are in the same way as before
to peace; for if it were the words of the enemy,



those in depth, but those and all not in reason.
      </p>
     </div>
     <div n="15" subtype="section" type="textpart">
      <p rend="cont">
       Τὸ μὲν οὖν,
ὥσπερ καὶ οἱ ἀρχαῖοι, λέγειν ἀπορροίας εἶναι τὰς
χροίας καὶ ὁρᾶσθαι διὰ τοιαύτην αἰτίαν ἄτοπον· πάντως
γὰρ δι’ ἁφῆς ἀναγκαῖον αὐτοῖς ποιεῖν τὴν αἴσθησιν, ὥστ’
εὐθὺς κρεῖττον φάναι τῷ κινεῖσθαι τὸ μεταξὺ τῆς αἰσθήσεως
ὑπὸ τοῦ αἰσθητοῦ γίνεσθαι τὴν αἴσθησιν, ἁφῇ καὶ μὴ ταῖς
ἀπορροίαις.
      </p>
      <p lang="it">
       Intendo,
proprio come gli antichi, dicono che sia aporrosi
carnagione e vista per questo motivo comunque;
poiché l'udito è necessario per coloro che hanno il sentimento, come
direttamente il cretino appare al movimento tra i sensi
sotto il senso diventa il senso, lasciare e non fare
conseguenze.
      </p>
      <p lang="en">
       I mean,
just like the ancients, they say it is aporrhosis
complexion and sight for that reason atopon; anyway
for by hearing it is necessary for those who have the feeling, as
directly cretin appears to the movement between the senses
under the sense becomes the sense, let and do not
consequences.
      </p>
     </div>
     <div n="16" subtype="section" type="textpart">
      <p rend="cont">
       Ἐπὶ μὲν οὖν τῶν παρ’ ἄλληλα κειμένων ἀνάγκη
ὥσπερ καὶ μέγεθος λαμβάνειν ἀόρατον, οὕτω καὶ χρόνον
ἀναίσθητον, ἵνα λάθωσιν αἱ κινήσεις ἀφικνούμεναι καὶ ἓν
δοκῇ εἶναι διὰ τὸ ἅμα φαίνεσθαι. Ἐνταῦθα δὲ οὐδεμία
ἀνάγκη, ἀλλὰ τὸ ἐπιπολῆς χρῶμα ἀκίνητον ὂν καὶ κινούμενον
ὑπὸ τοῦ ὑποκειμένου οὐχ ὁμοίαν ποιήσει τὴν κίνησιν.
Διὸ καὶ ἕτερον φαίνεται καὶ οὔτε λευκὸν οὔτε μέλαν.
      </p>
      <p lang="it">
       Da qui la necessità di altri testi
come ricevono dimensione e invisibilità, così anche il tempo
insensibile, così che i movimenti saranno sbagliati e uno
dimostrare che è per amore dell'apparenza. Ma non ce n'era
bisogno, ma il colore secondario di immobile e in movimento
sotto l'argomento non ha commesso il movimento in modo simile.
Per entrambi, non sembra né bianco né nero.
      </p>
      <p lang="en">
       Hence the need for other texts
as they receive size and invisibility, so also time
insensible, so that the movements will be mistaken and one
prove it is for the sake of appearance. But there was none
need, but the secondary color of immovable and moving
under the subject he did not similarly commit the movement.
For both, it seems neither white nor black.
      </p>
     </div>
     <div n="17" subtype="section" type="textpart">
      <p rend="cont">
       Ὥστ’ εἰ μὴ ἐνδέχεται μηδὲν εἶναι μέγεθος ἀόρατον, ἀλλὰ
πᾶν ἔκ τινος ἀποστήματος ὁρατόν, καὶ αὕτη τις ἂν εἴη
χρωμάτων μίξις. Κἀκείνως δ’ οὐδὲν κωλύει φαίνεσθαί
τινα χρόαν κοινὴν τοῖς πόρρωθεν· ὅτι γὰρ οὐκ ἔστιν οὐδὲν
μέγεθος ἀόρατον, ἐν τοῖς ὕστερον ἐπισκεπτέον.
      </p>
      <p lang="it">
       Se non può contenere zero, è una dimensione invisibile, ma
ovunque da un ascesso visibile, anche questo
miscelazione dei colori. Almeno non sembra intralciarci
quale colore è comune ai ladri, perché non c'è nulla
dimensioni mai viste, tra le ultime ad essere visitate.
      </p>
      <p lang="en">
       If it cannot contain zero, it is an invisible size, but
everywhere from a visible abscess, even this one
mixing colors. At least it doesn't seem to get in the way
what color is common to the thieves, because there is nothing
size unseen, among the last to be visited.
      </p>
     </div>
     <div n="18" subtype="section" type="textpart">
      <p rend="cont">
       Εἰ δ’ ἐστὶ
μίξις τῶν σωμάτων μὴ μόνον τὸν τρόπον τοῦτον ὅνπερ οἴονταί
τινες, παρ’ ἄλληλα τῶν ἐλαχίστων τιθεμένων, ἀδήλων
δ’ ἡμῖν διὰ τὴν αἴσθησιν, ἀλλ’ ὅλως πάντῃ πάντως, ὥσπερ
ἐν τοῖς περὶ μίξεως εἴρηται καθόλου περὶ πάντων.
      </p>
      <p lang="it">
       Sì
mescoli i corpi non solo in questo modo perché sono simili
quelli, tra gli altri, dei meno privilegiati, non dichiarati
d' noi per la sensazione, ma comunque lo stesso, come
In quelli sul mixaggio non si dice affatto di tutto.
      </p>
      <p lang="en">
       Yes, it is
you mix the bodies not only this way because they are similar
those, among others, of the least privileged, undeclared
d' us for the feeling, but all the same anyway, as
In those about mixing, it is not said at all about everything.
      </p>
     </div>
     <div n="19" subtype="section" type="textpart">
      <p rend="cont">
       Ἐκείνως
μὲν γὰρ μίγνυται ταῦτα μόνον ὅσα ἐνδέχεται διελεῖν εἰς τὰ
ἐλάχιστα, καθάπερ ἀνθρώπους ἵππους ἢ τὰ σπέρματα· τῶν
μὲν γὰρ ἀνθρώπων ἄνθρωπος ἐλάχιστος, τῶν δ’ ἵππων
ἵππος· ὥστε τῇ τούτων παρ’ ἄλληλα θέσει τὸ πλῆθος
       <pb n="254"/>
       μέμικται τῶν συναμφοτέρων· ἄνθρωπον δὲ ἕνα ἑνὶ ἵππῳ
οὐ λέγομεν μεμῖχθαι.
      </p>
      <p lang="it">
       A quel tempo
poiché li mescola solo con ciò che è capace di passare in essi
almeno, come gli uomini, i cavalli o lo sperma;
Perché senza le persone una persona è ben poca cosa, dei quattro cavalli
ἠπος; affinché la folla metta la folla dall'altra parte



mescolato con quelli della stessa specie; ma un uomo è un cavallo
non diciamo mix.
      </p>
      <p lang="en">
       At that time
for he mixes these only with what is capable of passing into them
at least, like men, horses, or sperm;
Because without people, a person is very little, of the four horses
ἠπος; so that the crowd will put the crowd on the other side



mixed with those of the same kind; but a man is a horse
we don't say mix.
      </p>
     </div>
     <div n="20" subtype="section" type="textpart">
      <p rend="cont">
       Ὅσα δὲ μὴ διαιρεῖται εἰς τὸ ἐλάχιστον,
τούτων οὐκ ἐνδέχεται μίξιν γενέσθαι τὸν τρόπον τοῦτον
ἀλλὰ τῷ πάντῃ μεμῖχθαι, ἅπερ καὶ μάλιστα μίγνυσθαι
πέφυκεν. Πῶς δὲ τοῦτο γίγνεσθαι δυνατόν, ἐν τοῖς
περὶ μίξεως εἴρηται πρότερον.
      </p>
      <p lang="it">
       Ma ciò che non è divisibile per il minimo,
non può essere miscelato in questo modo
ma si mescola con tutto, anche si mescola
caduto Ma come è possibile questo, tra loro?
sulla miscelazione è menzionata in precedenza.
      </p>
      <p lang="en">
       But what is not divisible by the minimum,
it cannot be mixed in this way
but it mixes with everything, even mixes
fell away But how is this possible, among them?
about mixing is mentioned earlier.
      </p>
     </div>
     <div n="21" subtype="section" type="textpart">
      <p rend="cont">
       Ἀλλ’ ὅτι ἀνάγκη μιγνυμένων
καὶ τὰς χρόας μίγνυσθαι, δῆλον, καὶ ταύτην τὴν αἰτίαν
εἶναι κυρίαν τοῦ πολλὰς εἶναι χροίας, ἀλλὰ μὴ τὴν
ἐπιπόλασιν μηδὲ τὴν παρ’ ἄλληλα θέσιν· οὐ γὰρ πόρρωθεν
μὲν ἐγγύθεν δ’ οὒ φαίνεται μία χρόα τῶν μεμιγμένων,
ἀλλὰ πάντοθεν.
      </p>
      <p lang="it">
       Ma perché c’è bisogno di persone miste
e i colori sono misti, Delon, e questo è il motivo
è una signora di molti, è di carnagione, ma non di lei
Non invaderanno la posizione, perché non potranno permetterselo
lì vicino, dove si vede un tempo del misto,
ma in ogni caso.
      </p>
      <p lang="en">
       But because there is a need for mixed people
and the colors are mixed, delon, and this reason
she is a lady of many, she is of complexion, but not of her
They will not overrun the position, for they will not be able to afford it
nearby, where is seen a time of the mixed,
but anyway.
      </p>
     </div>
     <div n="22" subtype="section" type="textpart">
      <p rend="cont">
       Πολλαὶ δ’ ἔσονται χρόαι διὰ τὸ κατὰ
πολλοὺς λόγους ἐνδέχεσθαι μίγνυσθαι ἀλλήλοις τὰ μιγνύμενα,
καὶ τὰ μὲν ἐν ἀριθμοῖς τὰ δὲ καθ’ ὑπεροχὴν μόνον.
      </p>
      <p lang="it">
       Ci sono molte volte per questo
molte ragioni possono essere mescolate tra loro, le cose mescolate,
e solo quelli in numeri e quelli in eccellenza.
      </p>
      <p lang="en">
       There are many times for this
many reasons can be mixed with each other the mixed things,
and the ones in numbers and the ones in excellence only.
      </p>
     </div>
     <div n="23" subtype="section" type="textpart">
      <p rend="cont">
       Καὶ τἆλλα δὴ τὸν αὐτὸν τρόπον ὅν περ ἐπὶ τῶν παρ’ ἄλληλα
τιθεμένων χρωμάτων ἢ ἐπιπολῆς, ἐνδέχεται λέγειν καὶ
περὶ τῶν μιγνυμένων· διὰ τίνα δ’ αἰτίαν εἴδη τῶν χρωμάτων
ἐστὶν ὡρισμένα καὶ οὐκ ἄπειρα, καὶ χυμῶν καὶ ψόφων,
ὕστερον ἐροῦμεν.
      </p>
      <p lang="it">
       E non farlo nello stesso modo in cui lo fai con altre persone
di determinati colori o epipoli, si potrebbe anche dire
riguardo a coloro che sono misti, a causa del colore ci sono diversi tipi di colori
sono definiti e non infiniti, e di succhi e di carne,
Siamo più tardi.
      </p>
      <p lang="en">
       And don't do it the same way as it does on other people
of given colors or epipolis, it may also be said
about those who are mixed; because of the color there are different kinds of colors
they are definite and not infinite, and of juices and of flesh,
We are later.
      </p>
     </div>
    </div>
    <div n="4" subtype="chapter" type="textpart">
     <div n="1" subtype="section" type="textpart">
      <p>
       Τί μὲν οὖν ἐστὶ χρῶμα καὶ διὰ τίν’ αἰτίαν πολλαὶ
χροιαί εἰσιν, εἴρηται· περὶ δὲ ψόφου καὶ φωνῆς εἴρηται πρότερον
ἐν τοῖς περὶ ψυχῆς· περὶ δὲ ὀσμῆς καὶ χυμοῦ νῦν λεκτέον.
Σχεδὸν γάρ ἐστι τὸ αὐτὸ πάθος, οὐκ ἐν τοῖς αὐτοῖς
δ’ ἐστὶν ἑκάτερον αὐτῶν.
      </p>
      <p lang="it">
       Cos’è allora il colore e perché esistono molte cause?
sono di colore, si dice; ma della voce e della voce si è detto prima
in quelli riguardanti l'anima; ma riguardo all'odore e al succo ora parla.
Quasi perché è una passione, non tra queste
È uno di questi.
      </p>
      <p lang="en">
       What, then, is color and why are there many causes?
they are of color, it is said; but about the voice and the voice it is said before
in those concerning the soul; but concerning smell and juice now speak.
Almost because it is a passion, not among them
It is one of them.
      </p>
     </div>
     <div n="2" subtype="section" type="textpart">
      <p rend="cont">
       Ἐναργέστερον δ’ ἐστὶν ἡμῖν τὸ τῶν
χυμῶν γένος ἢ τὸ τῆς ὀσμῆς. Τούτου δ’ αἴτιον ὅτι χειρίστην
ἔχομεν τῶν ἄλλων ζῴων τὴν ὄσφρησιν καὶ τῶν ἐν ἡμῖν
αὐτοῖς αἰσθήσεως, τὴν δ’ ἁφὴν ἀκριβεστάτην τῶν ἄλλων
       <pb n="255"/>
       ζῴων. Ἢ δὲ γεῦσις ἁφή τις ἐστίν.
      </p>
      <p lang="it">
       È il nostro turno di fare tardi
genere dei succhi o quello dell'olfatto. Questo perché se ne occupano
Abbiamo l'odore degli altri animali e quello di noi stessi
a questi sensi, il d'afen acrivestat degli altri



della vita. Ἢ Ma li assaggi.
      </p>
      <p lang="en">
       It's our turn to be late
genus of juices or that of smell. This is because they handle it
We have the smell of other animals and of ourselves
to these senses, the d'afen acrivestat of others



of life. Ἢ But you taste them.
      </p>
     </div>
     <div n="3" subtype="section" type="textpart">
      <p rend="cont">
       Ἢ μὲν οὖν τοῦ ὕδατος φύσις
βούλεται ἄχυμος εἶναι· ἀνάγκη δ’ ἢ ἐν αὑτῷ τὸ ὕδωρ
ἔχειν τὰ γένη τῶν χυμῶν ἀναίσθητα διὰ μικρότητα, καθάπερ
Ἐμπεδοκλῆς φησίν, ἢ ὕλην τοιαύτην ἐνεῖναι οἷον πανσπερμίαν
χυμῶν, καὶ ἅπαντα μὲν ἐξ ὕδατος γίγνεσθαι, ἄλλα
δ’ ἐξ ἄλλου μέρους, ἢ μηδεμίαν ἔχοντος διαφορὰν τοῦ ὕδατος
τὸ ποιοῦν αἴτιον εἶναι, οἷον εἰ τὸ θερμὸν καὶ τὸν ἥλιον
φαίη τις.
      </p>
      <p lang="it">
       Ἢ con ὖ di natura acquatica
se vuoi il succo lo è; non c'è bisogno di acqua
hanno i generi dei succhi insensibili per piccolezza, ecc
Empedocle è un panspermiano
succhi e tutto ciò che è fatto d'acqua, altro
d' da un altro luogo o senza differenza d'acqua
di chi è la causa, cioè il caldo e il sole
mangiali.
      </p>
      <p lang="en">
       Ἢ with ὖ of water nature
if you want juice it is; there is no need for water in it
have the genera of the juices insensitive due to smallness, etc
Empedocles is a panspermian
juices, and everything that is made of water, other
d' from another place, or having no water difference
whose cause is it, which is the heat and the sun
eat them.
      </p>
     </div>
     <div n="4" subtype="section" type="textpart">
      <p rend="cont">
       Τούτων δ’, ὡς μὲν Ἐμπεδοκλῆς λέγει, λίαν εὐσύνοπτον
τὸ ψεῦδος· ὁρῶμεν γὰρ μεταβάλλοντας ὑπὸ τοῦ
θερμοῦ τοὺς χυμοὺς ἀφαιρουμένων τῶν περικαρπίων εἰς τὸν
ἥλιον καὶ πυρουμένων, ὡς οὐ τῷ ἐκ τοῦ ὕδατος ἕλκειν τοιούτους
γινομένους, ἀλλ’ ἐν αὐτῷ τῷ περικαρπίῳ μεταβάλλοντας,
καὶ ἐξικμαζομένους δὲ καὶ κειμένους, διὰ τὸν χρόνον,
αὐστηροὺς ἐκ γλυκέων καὶ πικροὺς καὶ παντοδαποὺς
γινομένους, καὶ ἑψομένους, εἰς πάντα τὰ γένη τῶν χυμῶν
ὡς εἰπεῖν μεταβάλλοντας.
      </p>
      <p lang="it">
       Anche così, come dice Empedocle, in modo molto succinto
la falsità; poiché vediamo cambiando sotto di essa
scaldare nel
sole e bruciati, come se non guarissero dall'acqua
essendo stato fatto, ma in lui mutante,
e testi, nel tempo,
austero dal dolce all'amaro e onnipresente
fatto e allevato in tutti i tipi di succhi
come si suol dire cambiare.
      </p>
      <p lang="en">
       Even so, as Empedocles says, very succinctly
the falsehood; for we see by changing under it
heat the juices removed from the pericarps into the
sun and scorched, as if they did not heal from the water
having been made, but in him changing,
and texts, over time,
austere from sweet and bitter and ubiquitous
made, and raised, in all kinds of juices
as they say changing.
      </p>
     </div>
     <div n="5" subtype="section" type="textpart">
      <p rend="cont">
       Ὁμοίως δὲ καὶ τὸ πανσπερμίας
εἶναι τὸ ὕδωρ ὕλην ἀδύνατον· ἐκ τοῦ αὐτοῦ γὰρ ὁρῶμεν
ὡς ἐκ τῆς αὐτῆς τροφῆς γινομένους ἑτέρους χυμούς.
Λείπεται δὴ τῷ πάσχειν τι τὸ ὕδωρ μεταβάλλειν.
      </p>
      <p lang="it">
       Allo stesso modo, la panspermia
l'acqua è una sostanza impossibile, perché da essa vediamo
come altri succhi ricavati da questo alimento.
Al malato manca l'acqua che cambia.
      </p>
      <p lang="en">
       Similarly, panspermia
water is an impossible substance, for from it we see
as other juices made from this food.
The sufferer lacks what water they change.
      </p>
     </div>
     <div n="6" subtype="section" type="textpart">
      <p rend="cont">
       Ὅτι
μὲν τοίνυν οὐχ ὑπὸ τῆς τοῦ θερμοῦ δυνάμεως λαμβάνει ταύτην
τὴν δύναμιν ἣν καλοῦμεν χυμόν, φανερόν· λεπτότατον
γὰρ τῶν πάντων ὑγρῶν τὸ ὕδωρ ἐστί, καὶ αὐτοῦ τοῦ
ἐλαίου. Ἀλλ’ ἐπεκτείνεται ἐπὶ πλεῖον τοῦ ὕδατος τὸ
ἔλαιον διὰ τὴν γλισχρότητα. Τὸ δ’ ὕδωρ ψαθυρόν ἐστι·
διὸ καὶ χαλεπώτερον φυλάξαι ἐν τῇ χειρὶ ὕδωρ ἢ ἔλαιον.
      </p>
      <p lang="it">
       Quello
non sembrano riceverlo sotto il potere del calore
il potere che chiamiamo succo, ovvio e sottile;
poiché tutti i liquidi sono acqua, e anche questo
olio. Ma si espande su gran parte dell'acqua
olio per scivolosità. La quarta acqua è un fruscio;
tieni l'acqua o l'olio a portata di mano anche nel peggio.
      </p>
      <p lang="en">
       That
they do not seem to receive this under the power of heat
the power we call juice, obvious; subtle
for all liquids are water, and this one too
oil. But it expands over most of the water
oil for slipperiness. The fourth water is a rustle;
keep water or oil on hand for even worse.
      </p>
     </div>
     <div n="7" subtype="section" type="textpart">
      <p rend="cont">
       Ἐπεὶ δὲ θερμαινόμενον οὐδὲν φαίνεται παχυνόμενον τὸ ὕδωρ
αὐτὸ μόνον, δῆλον ὅτι ἑτέρα τις ἂν εἴη αἰτία· οἱ γὰρ χυμοὶ
       <pb n="256"/>
       πάντες πάχος ἔχουσι μᾶλλον· τὸ δὲ θερμὸν συναίτιον.
Φαίνονται δ’ οἱ χυμοὶ ὅσοιπερ καὶ ἐν τοῖς περικαρπίοις,
οὗτοι ὑπάρχοντες καὶ ἐν τῇ γῇ.
      </p>
      <p lang="it">
       Ma quando viene riscaldata, l'acqua non sembra addensarsi
solo questo, dicono, se fosse un'altra causa, perché i succhi



Tutti hanno una relazione grassa, ma calda.
I succhi sono visibili anche nei pericarpi,
questi esistono anche sulla terra.
      </p>
      <p lang="en">
       But when heated, the water does not seem to thicken
this alone, they say that if it were another cause, because the juices



Everyone has fat, but a warm relationship.
The juices are visible even in the pericarps,
these existing also in the earth.
      </p>
     </div>
     <div n="8" subtype="section" type="textpart">
      <p rend="cont">
       Διὸ καὶ πολλοί φασι
τῶν ἀρχαίων φυσιολόγων τοιοῦτον εἶναι τὸ ὕδωρ δι’ οἵας
ἂν γῆς πορεύηται. Καὶ τοῦτο δῆλόν ἐστιν ἐπὶ τῶν ἁλμυρῶν
ὑδάτων μάλιστα· οἱ γὰρ ἅλες γῆς τι εἶδός εἰσιν.
Καὶ τὰ διὰ τῆς τέφρας διηθούμενα πικρᾶς οὔσης πικρὸν
ποιεῖ τὸν χυμόν.
      </p>
      <p lang="it">
       A causa di molti fascisti
degli antichi fisiologi, cioè l'acqua per la quale
se la terra si muove. E questo Delon è su quelli salati
delle acque infatti; perché che tipo di terra sono?
E quelli filtrati attraverso le ceneri sono amari anche amari
fa bollire il succo.
      </p>
      <p lang="en">
       Because of many fascists
of the ancient physiologists, that is what water is for
if the earth moves. And this delon is on the salty ones
of waters indeed; for what kind of earth are they?
And those filtered through the ashes are bitter even bitter
boils the juice.
      </p>
     </div>
     <div n="9" subtype="section" type="textpart">
      <p rend="cont">
       Εἰσί τε κρῆναι πολλαὶ αἱ μὲν πικραί,
αἱ δ’ ὀξεῖαι, αἱ δὲ παντοδαποὺς ἔχουσαι χυμοὺς ἄλλους.
Εὐλόγως δ’ ἐν τοῖς φυομένοις τὸ τῶν χυμῶν γίνεται
γένος μάλιστα. Πάσχειν γὰρ πέφυκε τὸ ὑγρόν, ὥσπερ καὶ
τἆλλα, ὑπὸ τοῦ ἐναντίου· ἐναντίον δὲ τὸ ξηρόν. Διὸ καὶ
ὑπὸ τοῦ πυρὸς πάσχει τι· ξηρὰ γὰρ ἡ τοῦ πυρὸς φύσις.
      </p>
      <p lang="it">
       Tu sei quello che molti pensano con amarezza,
Quelli sono amari, ma quelli onnipresenti hanno altri succhi.
Fortunatamente, ci sono dei succhi in coloro che crescono
genere davvero. Dopotutto, il liquido è caduto, per così dire
dorato, al contrario; e contro il secco. Anche perché
ciò che soffre sotto il fuoco, perché la natura del fuoco è secca.
      </p>
      <p lang="en">
       You are the one whom many bitter think,
The ones are bitter, but the ubiquitous ones have other juices.
Fortunately, there are juices in those who grow
genus indeed. After all, the liquid fell, as it were
golden, under the contrary; and against the dry. Because also
what suffers under the fire, for the fire's nature is dry.
      </p>
     </div>
     <div n="10" subtype="section" type="textpart">
      <p rend="cont">
       Ἀλλ’ ἴδιον τοῦ πυρὸς τὸ θερμόν ἐστι, γῆς δὲ τὸ ξηρόν,
ὥσπερ εἴρηται ἐν τοῖς περὶ στοιχείων. Ἧι μὲν οὖν πῦρ
καὶ ᾗ γῆ, οὐδὲν πέφυκε ποιεῖν ἢ πάσχειν, οὐδ’ ἄλλο οὐδέν·
ᾗ δ’ ὑπάρχει ἐναντιότης ἐν ἐκάστῳ, ταύτῃ πάντα καὶ
ποιοῦσι καὶ πάσχουσιν.
      </p>
      <p lang="it">
       Ma il fuoco stesso è caldo, ma la terra è secca,
come affermato negli articoli sugli elementi. Sono uomini in fiamme
e sulla terra nessuno cadde né soffrì, né altro;
dove non c'è opposizione in ciascuno, nello stesso e in tutto
che stanno soffrendo.
      </p>
      <p lang="en">
       But fire itself is hot, but earth is dry,
as stated in the articles on elements. Ἧi men oὖn fire
and on earth, no one fell or suffered, nor anything else;
where there is no opposition in each, the same and everything
who are suffering.
      </p>
     </div>
     <div n="11" subtype="section" type="textpart">
      <p rend="cont">
       Ὥσπερ οὖν οἱ ἐναποπλύνοντες ἐν
τῷ ὑγρῷ τὰ χρώματα καὶ τοὺς χυμοὺς τοιοῦτον ἔχειν
ποιοῦσι τὸ ὕδωρ, οὕτω καὶ ἡ φύσις τὸ ξηρὸν καὶ τὸ γεῶδες,
καὶ διὰ τοῦ ξηροῦ καὶ γεώδους διηθοῦσα καὶ κινοῦσα τῷ
θερμῷ ποιόν τι τὸ ὑγρὸν παρασκευάζει.
      </p>
      <p lang="it">
       Ὥsper su coloro che lavano ἐν
il liquido ha i colori e i succhi di quello
come l'acqua, così la natura del secco e della terra,
e attraverso il secco e il terroso ho filtrato e sono passato al
θερμῷ chi prepara cosa il liquido.
      </p>
      <p lang="en">
       Ὥsper oὖn those who wash ἐν
the liquid has the colors and the juices of that
as the water, so the nature of the dry and the earth,
and through the dry and earthy I filtered and moved to the
θερμῷ who prepares what the liquid.
      </p>
     </div>
     <div n="12" subtype="section" type="textpart">
      <p rend="cont">
       Καὶ ἔστι τοῦτο
χυμὸς τὸ γιγνόμενον ὑπὸ τοῦ εἰρημένου ξηροῦ πάθος ἐν
τῷ ὑγρῷ τῆς γεύσεως τῆς κατὰ δύναμιν ἀλλοιωτικὸν εἰς ἐνέργειαν·
       <pb n="257"/>
       ἄγει γὰρ τὸ αἰσθητικὸν εἰς τοῦτο δυνάμει προϋπάρχον·
οὐ γὰρ κατὰ τὸ μανθάνειν ἀλλὰ κατὰ τὸ θεωρεῖν
ἐστὶ τὸ αἰσθάνεσθαι.
      </p>
      <p lang="it">
       E questo è tutto
succo ottenuto dalla passione secca disciolta
all'acqua del sapore della sua potenza che si trasforma in energia;



perché riconduce l'estetica a questa potenziale preesistenza;
non secondo quello che pensano, ma secondo quello che considerano
è la sensazione.
      </p>
      <p lang="en">
       And this is it
juice made by the dissolved dry passion in
to the water of the taste of its power altering into energy;



because it leads the aesthetic to this potential pre-existence;
not according to what they think, but according to what they consider
it's the feeling.
      </p>
     </div>
     <div n="13" subtype="section" type="textpart">
      <p rend="cont">
       Ὅτι δ’ οὐ παντὸς ξηροῦ ἀλλὰ τοῦ
τροφίμου οἱ χυμοὶ ἢ πάθος εἰσὶν ἢ στέρησις, δεῖ λαβεῖν
ἐντεῦθεν, ὅτι οὔτε τὸ ξηρὸν ἄνευ τοῦ ὑγροῦ οὔτε τὸ ὑγρὸν
ἄνευ τοῦ ξηροῦ· τροφὴ γὰρ οὐδὲν αὐτῶν τοῖς ζῴοις, ἀλλὰ
τὸ μεμιγμένον.
      </p>
      <p lang="it">
       Perché non tutto è asciutto tranne lui
il mio cibo sono i succhi o la passione o la privazione, lasciali prendere
quindi perché né il secco senza il liquido, né il liquido
senza il secco, perché nessuno di essi è cibo per gli animali, ma
il misto.
      </p>
      <p lang="en">
       Because not everything is dry but him
my food is the juices or passion or deprivation, let them take
therefore, because neither the dry without the liquid nor the liquid
without the dry, for none of them is food for the animals, but
the mixed.
      </p>
     </div>
     <div n="14" subtype="section" type="textpart">
      <p rend="cont">
       Καὶ ἔστι τῆς προσφερομένης τροφῆς τοῖς
ζῴοις τὰ μὲν ἁπτὰ τῶν αἰσθητῶν αὔξησιν ποιοῦντα καὶ φθίσιν·
τούτων μὲν γὰρ αἴτιον ᾗ θερμὸν καὶ ψυχρὸν τὸ
προσφερόμενον· ταῦτα γὰρ ποιεῖ καὶ αὔξησιν καὶ φθίσιν·
τρέφει δὲ ᾗ γευστὸν τὸ προσφερόμενον· πάντα γὰρ τρέφεται
τῷ γλυκεῖ, ἢ ἁπλῶς ἢ μεμιγμένως.
      </p>
      <p lang="it">
       E del cibo loro offerto
gli esseri viventi dei sensi aumentano e diminuiscono;
poiché questa è la causa del caldo e del freddo
essere offerti; poiché questi aumentano e diminuiscono;
ma si nutre del gusto di ciò che gli viene offerto, perché è sempre saziato
a piacere, semplici o misti.
      </p>
      <p lang="en">
       And of the food offered to them
the living things of the senses increase and decrease;
for this is the cause of the hot and the cold
being offered; for these do both increase and decrease;
but he feeds on the taste of what is offered, for he is always fed
to taste, either plain or mixed.
      </p>
     </div>
     <div n="15" subtype="section" type="textpart">
      <p rend="cont">
       Δεῖ μὲν οὖν διορίζειν
περὶ τούτων ἐν τοῖς περὶ γενέσεως, νῦν δ’ ὅσον
ἀναγκαῖον ἅψασθαι αὐτῶν. Τὸ γὰρ θερμὸν αὐξάνει καὶ
δημιουργεῖ τὴν τροφήν, καὶ τὸ μὲν κοῦφον ἕλκει, τὸ δ’
ἁλμυρὸν καὶ πικρὸν καταλείπει διὰ βάρος. Ὃ δὴ ἐν τοῖς
ἔξω σώμασι ποιεῖ τὸ ἔξω θερμόν, τοῦτο ἐν τῇ φύσει τῶν
ζῴων καὶ φυτῶν· διὸ τρέφεται τῷ γλυκεῖ.
      </p>
      <p lang="it">
       Vieni a trovarmi, poi nominano
su questi in quelli sulla genesi, ora quattro
Necessaria assenza di essi. Perché aumenta anche la temperatura
crea il cibo, e il sordo attira, il d'
il salato e l'amaro si perdono a causa del peso. Ὃ ὴ ἐν τοῖς
All'esterno del corpo produce il calore esterno, questo nella natura del
di animali e piante; si nutre di dolci.
      </p>
      <p lang="en">
       See me then they appoint
about these in those about genesis, now four
Necessary absence of them. Because it increases the temperature as well
creates the food, and the deaf attracts, the d'
salty and bitter is lost due to weight. Ὃ ὴ ἐν τοῖς
Outside the body does the outside heat, this in the nature of the
of animals and plants; it feeds on the sweet.
      </p>
     </div>
     <div n="16" subtype="section" type="textpart">
      <p rend="cont">
       Συμμίγνυνται
δ’ οἱ ἄλλοι χυμοὶ εἰς τὴν τροφὴν τὸν αὐτὸν τρόπον τῷ
ἁλμυρῷ καὶ ὀξεῖ, ἀντὶ ἡδύσματος. Ταῦτα δὲ διὰ τὸ ἀντισπᾶν
τῷ λίαν τρόφιμον εἶναι τὸ γλυκὺ καὶ ἐπιπολαστικόν.
Ὥσπερ δὲ τὰ χρώματα ἐκ λευκοῦ καὶ μέλανος
μίξεώς ἐστιν, οὕτως οἱ χυμοὶ ἐκ γλυκέος καὶ πικροῦ.
      </p>
      <p lang="it">
       Si mescolano
d' gli altri succhi presenti nel cibo allo stesso modo
salato e acido, invece di condimento. Ma questo è ciò a cui si oppongono
per la maggior parte il cibo è dolce e popolare.
Ma i colori sono il bianco e il nero
è una miscela, come i succhi di dolce e amaro.
      </p>
      <p lang="en">
       They mix
d' the other juices in the food in the same way
salty and sour, instead of dressing. But these are what they oppose
for the most food is the sweet and popular.
But the colors are white and black
it is a mixture, like the juices of sweet and bitter.
      </p>
     </div>
     <div n="17" subtype="section" type="textpart">
      <p rend="cont">
       Καὶ κατὰ λόγον δὴ τῷ μᾶλλον καὶ ἧττον ἕκαστοί εἰσιν,
       <pb n="258"/>
       εἴτε κατ’ ἀριθμούς τινας τῆς μίξεως καὶ κινήσεις, εἴτε καὶ
ἀορίστως. Οἱ δὲ τὴν ἡδονὴν ποιοῦντες μιγνύμενοι, οὗτοι
ἐν ἀριθμοῖς μόνον. Ὁ μὲν οὖν λιπαρὸς τοῦ γλυκέος ἐστὶ
χυμός, τὸ δ’ ἁλμυρὸν καὶ πικρὸν σχεδὸν τὸ αὐτό, ὁ δὲ αὐστηρὸς
καὶ δριμὺς καὶ στρυφνὸς καὶ ὀξὺς ἀνὰ μέσον.
      </p>
      <p lang="it">
       E con il passaparola sono ciascuno di loro,



o dai numeri del mix e dai movimenti, o da entrambi
indefinitamente. E quelli che si mescolano e si godono il piacere, questi sono
solo in numeri. Quindi il grasso è il dolce
succo, il quarto è quasi salato e amaro e il secondo è astringente
e duro, contorto e amaro nel mezzo.
      </p>
      <p lang="en">
       And by word of mouth they are each one of them,



either by numbers of the mix and movements, or both
indefinitely. And those who mingle and enjoy the pleasure, these are
in numbers only. So the fatty is the sweet
juice, the fourth is almost salty and bitter, and the second is astringent
and harsh and twisted and bitter in the middle.
      </p>
     </div>
     <div n="18" subtype="section" type="textpart">
      <p rend="cont">
       Σχεδὸν
γὰρ ἴσα καὶ τὰ τῶν χυμῶν εἴδη καὶ τὰ τῶν χρωμάτων
ἐστίν. Ἑπτὰ γὰρ ἀμφοτέρων εἴδη, ἄν τις τιθῇ, ὥσπερ
εὔλογον, τὸ φαιὸν μέλαν τι εἶναι· λείπεται γὰρ τὸ ξανθὸν
μὲν τοῦ λευκοῦ εἶναι ὥσπερ τὸ λιπαρὸν τοῦ γλυκέος, τὸ
φοινικοῦν δὲ καὶ ἁλουργὸν καὶ πράσινον καὶ κυανοῦν μεταξὺ
τοῦ λευκοῦ καὶ μέλανος, τὰ δ’ ἄλλα μικτὰ ἐκ τούτων.
      </p>
      <p lang="it">
       Quasi
poiché lo stesso vale per i succhi delle specie e dei colori
È Per sette tipi di entrambi, se li nomina, come
ragionevole, qual è il grigio e il nero, perché manca il biondo
con quello bianco è come quello grasso con quello dolce, il
e le palme sono sia argento che verdi e blu in mezzo
di bianco e nero, gli altri quattro mescolati di questi.
      </p>
      <p lang="en">
       Almost
for the same is true of the juices of species and of colors
is For seven kinds of both, if he names them, as
reasonable, what is the gray and black, because the blond is missing
with the white one it is like the fatty one with the sweet one, the
and palm trees are both silver and green and blue in between
of white and black, the other four mixed of these.
      </p>
     </div>
     <div n="19" subtype="section" type="textpart">
      <p rend="cont">
       Καὶ ὥσπερ τὸ μέλαν στέρησις ἐν τῷ διαφανεῖ τοῦ λευκοῦ,
οὕτω τὸ ἁλμυρὸν καὶ πικρὸν τοῦ γλυκέος ἐν τῷ τροφίμῳ
ὑγρῷ. Διὸ καὶ ἡ τέφρα τῶν κατακαομένων πικρὰ πάντων·
ἐξίκμασται γὰρ τὸ πότιμον ἐξ αὐτῶν. Δημόκριτος δὲ καὶ
οἱ πλεῖστοι τῶν φυσιολόγων, ὅσοι λέγουσι περὶ αἰσθήσεως,
ἀτοπώτατόν τι ποιοῦσιν· πάντα γὰρ τὰ αἰσθητὰ ἁπτὰ
ποιοῦσιν.
      </p>
      <p lang="it">
       E come nero ti manca la trasparenza del bianco,
quindi il salato e l'amaro del dolce nel cibo
ὑgrῷ. Perché le ceneri di tutte le cose bruciate sono amare;
poiché il potimon è ottenuto da loro. E anche Democrito
la maggior parte dei fisiologi, quelli che parlano di sensazione,
È impossibile scoprire cosa stanno facendo, perché tutti i sensi sono tangibili
Loro chi sono
      </p>
      <p lang="en">
       And as black you lack in the transparency of white,
thus the salty and bitter of the sweet in the food
ὑgrῷ. Because the ashes of all burnt things are bitter;
for the potimon is obtained from them. And Democritus too
the majority of physiologists, those who speak of sensation,
It is impossible to find what they are doing, because all the senses are tangible
who are they
      </p>
     </div>
     <div n="20" subtype="section" type="textpart">
      <p rend="cont">
       Καίτοι εἰ οὕτω τοῦτ’ ἔχει, δῆλον ὡς καὶ τῶν
ἄλλων αἰσθήσεων ἑκάστη ἁφή τις ἐστίν· τοῦτο δ’ ὅτι ἀδύνατον,
οὐ χαλεπὸν συνιδεῖν. Ἔτι δὲ τοῖς κοινοῖς τῶν αἰσθήσεων
πασῶν χρῶνται ὡς ἰδίοις· μέγεθος γὰρ καὶ σχῆμα καὶ
τὸ τραχὺ καὶ τὸ λεῖον, ἔτι δὲ τὸ ὀξὺ καὶ τὸ ἀμβλὺ τὸ
ἐν τοῖς ὄγκοις κοινὰ τῶν αἰσθήσεών ἐστιν, εἰ δὲ μὴ πασῶν,
ἀλλ’ ὄψεώς γε καὶ ἁφῆς.
      </p>
      <p lang="it">
       Ma se è così, lasciamo che facciano lo stesso
degli altri sensi, ciascuno ne ha coscienza;
non pensano male. E che dire del buon senso?
Sono tutti usati come individui, perché le dimensioni e la forma sono diverse
il ruvido e il liscio, l'amaro e il schietto
nei volumi i sensi sono comuni, ma se non in tutti,
ma della vista e dell'udito.
      </p>
      <p lang="en">
       But if this is the case, let them do the same
of other senses, each one is aware of them; this is impossible,
they don't think badly. What about the common senses?
They are all used as individuals, because size and shape are different
the rough and the smooth, and the bitter and the blunt
in the volumes the senses are common, but if not in all,
but of sight and hearing.
      </p>
     </div>
     <div n="21" subtype="section" type="textpart">
      <p rend="cont">
       Διὸ καὶ περὶ μὲν τούτων
ἀπατῶνται, περὶ δὲ τῶν ἰδίων οὐκ ἀπατῶνται, οἷον ὄψις
       <pb n="259"/>
       περὶ χρώματος καὶ ἀκοὴ περὶ ψόφων. Οἱ δὲ τὰ ἴδια εἰς
ταῦτα ἀνάγουσιν, ὥσπερ Δημόκριτος· τὸ γὰρ λευκὸν καὶ
τὸ μέλαν τὸ μὲν τραχύ φησιν εἶναι τὸ δὲ λεῖον, εἰς δὲ τὰ
σχήματα ἀνάγει τοὺς χυμούς. Καίτοι ἢ οὐδεμιᾶς ἢ μᾶλλον
τῆς ὄψεως τὰ κοινὰ γνωρίζειν.
      </p>
      <p lang="it">
       Per e riguardo a questi
si ingannano, ma non si ingannano su se stessi, chiunque tu veda



sul colore e sul sentire parlare di tetti. E lo stesso dentro
questi li generano, come Democrito: anche per i bianchi
quello nero a tessitura ruvida è quello liscio, e nel
le forme riducono i succhi. Mangi o non mangi o mangi
del punto di vista che il pubblico conosce.
      </p>
      <p lang="en">
       For and about these
they are deceived, but they are not deceived about themselves, whoever you see



about color and hearing about roofs. And the same in
these they bring forth, as Democritus: for the white also
the black one with a rough texture is the smooth one, and in the
shapes reduces the juices. You eat or you don't eat or you eat
of the view the public knows.
      </p>
     </div>
     <div n="22" subtype="section" type="textpart">
      <p rend="cont">
       Εἰ δ’ ἄρα τῆς γεύσεως
μᾶλλον, τὰ γοῦν ἐλάχιστα τῆς ἀκριβεστάτης ἐστὶν αἰσθήσεως
διακρίνειν περὶ ἕκαστον γένος, ὥστε ἐχρῆν τὴν γεῦσιν
καὶ τῶν ἄλλων κοινῶν αἰσθάνεσθαι μάλιστα καὶ τῶν σχημάτων
εἶναι κριτικωτάτην.
      </p>
      <p lang="it">
       Ecco il gusto
anzi, almeno le cose dei più raffinati sono sensuali
distinguere su ciascun genere, in modo che utilizzino il gusto
E degli altri sentimenti comuni, anche delle forme
lei è critica.
      </p>
      <p lang="en">
       Here is the taste
rather, at least the things of the most refined are sensual
distinguish about each genus, so that they use the taste
And of the other common feelings, even of the shapes
she is critical.
      </p>
     </div>
     <div n="23" subtype="section" type="textpart">
      <p rend="cont">
       Ἔτι τὰ μὲν αἰσθητὰ πάντα
ἔχει ἐναντίωσιν, οἷον ἐν χρώματι τῷ μέλανι τὸ λευκὸν καὶ ἐν
χυμοῖς τῷ γλυκεῖ τὸ πικρόν· σχῆμα δὲ σχήματι οὐ δοκεῖ
εἶναι ἐναντίον· τίνι γὰρ τῶν πολυγώνων περιφερὲς ἐναντίον;
      </p>
      <p lang="it">
       Questo l'ho sempre sentito
ha un'opposizione, che a colori è in bianco e nero e in
i succhi amari gli sono dolci, ma non ha il sapore amaro
è contro; infatti a cosa è contraria la circonferenza dei poligoni?
      </p>
      <p lang="en">
       That I always felt
has an opposition, who in color is black and white and in
bitter juices are sweet to him, but he does not taste bitter
it is against; for what is the circumference of polygons against?
      </p>
     </div>
     <div n="24" subtype="section" type="textpart">
      <p rend="cont">
       Ἔτι ἀπείρων ὄντων τῶν σχημάτων ἀναγκαῖον καὶ τοὺς
χυμοὺς εἶναι ἀπείρους· διὰ τί γὰρ ὁ μὲν ἂν ποιήσειεν
αἴσθησιν, ὁ δ’ οὐκ ἂν ποιήσειεν; Καὶ περὶ μὲν τοῦ γευστοῦ
καὶ χυμοῦ εἴρηται· τὰ γὰρ ἄλλα πάθη τῶν χυμῶν οἰκείαν
ἔχει τὴν σκέψιν ἐν τῇ φυσιολογίᾳ τῇ περὶ τῶν φυτῶν.
      </p>
      <p lang="it">
       A causa del numero infinito di forme, sono anche necessarie
I succhi sono infiniti, perché non dovrei scrivere?
sentimento, il d' oὐk ἑn poiếsien? E riguardo al gusto
e dei succhi si dice: perché le altre passioni dei succhi sono di casa
ha il pensiero nella sua fisiologia sulle piante.
      </p>
      <p lang="en">
       Because of the infinite number of shapes, they are also necessary
The juices are endless, for why should I not write?
feeling, the d' oὐk ἑn poiếsien? And about the taste
and of juice it is said: for the other passions of juices are at home
he has the thought in his physiology about plants.
      </p>
     </div>
    </div>
    <div n="5" subtype="chapter" type="textpart">
     <div n="1" subtype="section" type="textpart">
      <p>
       Τὸν αὐτὸν δὲ τρόπον δεῖ νοῆσαι καὶ περὶ τὰς ὀσμάς· ὅπερ
γὰρ ποιεῖ ἐν τῷ ὑγρῷ τὸ ξηρόν, τοῦτο ποιεῖ ἐν ἄλλῳ γένει
τὸ ἔγχυμον ὑγρόν, ἐν ἀέρι καὶ ὕδατι ὁμοίως. Κοινὸν δὲ
κατὰ τούτων νῦν μὲν λέγομεν τὸ διαφανές, ἔστι δ’ ὀσφραντὸν
οὐχ ᾗ διαφανές, ἀλλ’ ᾗ πλυντικὸν ἢ ῥυπτικὸν ἐγχύμου
ξηρότητος· οὐ γὰρ μόνον ἐν ἀέρι ἀλλὰ καὶ ἐν ὕδατι τὸ τῆς
ὀσφρήσεώς ἐστιν.
      </p>
      <p lang="it">
       Allo stesso modo va inteso anche per gli odori; cfr
Per ciò che è asciutto sul bagnato, questo viene fatto in un altro modo
il fluido fluido, sia nell'aria che nell'acqua. Non comune
secondo questi ora si dice il trasparente, è l'odore
Non trasparente, ma un infuso purificante o afrodisiaco
secchezza, non solo nell'aria ma anche nell'acqua
è puzzolente.
      </p>
      <p lang="en">
       The same way is also to be understood about smells; cf
For what is dry in the wet, this is done in another way
the fluid fluid, in air and water alike. Not a common one
according to these now we say the transparent, it is the smell
Not a transparent one, but a cleansing or aphrodisiac infusion
dryness, for not only in air but also in water
it's smelly.
      </p>
     </div>
     <div n="2" subtype="section" type="textpart">
      <p rend="cont">
       Δῆλον δ’ ἐπὶ τῶν ἰχθύων καὶ τῶν ὀστρακοδέρμων·
φαίνονται γὰρ ὀσφραινόμενα οὔτε ἀέρος ὄντος
       <pb n="260"/>
       ἐν τῷ ὕδατι (ἐπιπολάζει γὰρ ὁ ἀήρ, ὅταν ἐγγένηται) οὔτ’
αὐτὰ ἀναπνέοντα. Εἰ οὖν τις θείη καὶ τὸν ἀέρα καὶ τὸ
ὕδωρ ἄμφω ὑγρά, εἴη ἂν ἡ ἐν ὑγρῷ τοῦ ἐγχύμου ξηροῦ φύσις
ὀσμή, καὶ ὀσφραντὸν τὸ τοιοῦτον.
      </p>
      <p lang="it">
       Delon IV su pesce e crostacei;
poiché sembrano odorare, nemmeno un essere aereo



nell'acqua (perché l'aria galleggia quando nasce) né
questi traspiranti. Quindi le zie, l'aria e il
l'acqua è un liquido, se il liquido è la natura secca dell'infuso
Un odore, e un profumo che sia.
      </p>
      <p lang="en">
       Delon IV on fish and shellfish;
for they seem to be smelling, not even an airy being



in the water (for the air floats when it is born) nor
these breathable. So the aunts and the air and the
water is a liquid, if the liquid is the dry nature of the infusion
A smell, and a scent that is.
      </p>
     </div>
     <div n="3" subtype="section" type="textpart">
      <p rend="cont">
       Ὅτι δ’ ἅπαν χυμοῦ
ἐστὶ τὸ πάθος, δῆλον ἐκ τῶν ἐχόντων καὶ μὴ ἐχόντων
ὀσμήν· τά τε γὰρ στοιχεῖα ἄοσμα, οἷον πῦρ ἀὴρ ὕδωρ γῆ,
διὰ τὸ τά τε ξηρὰ αὐτῶν καὶ τὰ ὑγρὰ ἄχυμα εἶναι, ἐὰν μή
τι μιγνύμενον ποιῇ.
      </p>
      <p lang="it">
       Che non c'era succo
è passione, viene da chi ha e da chi non ha
ὀσμέν; poiché questi sono gli elementi di ἄοσμα, οἷον ῦρ ὀὴρ ὐδορ ῆ,
a causa del loro gusto secco e umido, in caso contrario
cosa mescolato con chi?
      </p>
      <p lang="en">
       That there was no juice
it is passion, it is from the haves and the have nots
ὀσμέν; for these are the elements of ἄοσμα, οἷον ῦρ ὀὴρ ὐδορ ῆ,
because of their dry and wet tastes, if not
what mixed with whom?
      </p>
     </div>
     <div n="4" subtype="section" type="textpart">
      <p rend="cont">
       Διὸ καὶ ἡ θάλαττα ἔχει ὀσμήν· ἔχει
γὰρ χυμὸν καὶ ξηρότητα. Καὶ ἅλες μᾶλλον λίτρου ὀσμώδεις·
δηλοῖ δὲ τὸ ἐξικμαζόμενον ἐξ αὐτῶν ἔλαιον· τὸ δὲ
λίτρον γῆς ἐστὶ μᾶλλον. Ἔτι λίθος μὲν ἄοσμον,
ἄχυμον γάρ, τὰ δὲ ξύλα ὀσμώδη, ἔγχυμα γάρ· καὶ τοῦτων
τὰ ὑδατώδη ἧττον.
      </p>
      <p lang="it">
       Perché anche la talatta ha un odore;
per succo e secchezza. E tutte le cose puzzolenti di un litro;
significa l'olio da essi estratto;
un litro di terra, forse. Che pietra senza odore,
Achymon gar, ma i boschi sono puzzolenti, infusi e così via
l'ἧtton acquoso.
      </p>
      <p lang="en">
       Because even the thalatta has an odor; it does
for juice and dryness. And all the smelly things of a liter;
it means the oil extracted from them;
a liter of earth, maybe. What a stone with no smell,
Achymon gar, but the woods are smelly, infused, and so on
the watery ἧtton.
      </p>
     </div>
     <div n="5" subtype="section" type="textpart">
      <p rend="cont">
       Ἔτι τῶν μεταλλευομένων χρυσὸς
ἄοσμον, ἄχυμον γάρ, ὁ δὲ χαλκὸς καὶ ὁ σίδηρος ὀσμώδη.
Ὅταν δ’ ἐκκαυθῇ τὸ ὑγρόν, ἀοσμότεραι αἱ σκωρίαι γίγνονται
πάντων. Ἄργυρος δὲ καὶ καττίτερος τῶν μὲν μᾶλλον
ὀσμώδη τῶν δ’ ἧττον· ὑδατώδη γάρ.
      </p>
      <p lang="it">
       Quella di chi estraeva l'oro
Puzzolente, puzzolente e puzzolente di rame e ferro.
Quando il liquido viene bruciato, le scorie diventano maleodoranti
Comunque. E Argyros e probabilmente peggio di me
odoroso di d'ἧtton gar acquoso.
      </p>
      <p lang="en">
       That of those who mined gold
Smelly, smelly, and copper and iron smelly.
When the liquid is burned, the slag becomes smelly
anyway. And Argyros and worse than me probably
odorous of d'ἧtton; watery gar.
      </p>
     </div>
     <div n="6" subtype="section" type="textpart">
      <p rend="cont">
       Δοκεῖ δ’ ἐνίοις ἡ
καπνώδης ἀναθυμίασις εἶναι ὀσμή, οὖσα κοινὴ γῆς τε καὶ
ἀέρος. Καὶ πάντες ἐπιφέρονται ἐπὶ τοῦτο περὶ ὀσμῆς· διὸ
καὶ Ἡράκλειτος οὕτως εἴρηκεν, ὡς εἰ πάντα τὰ ὄντα καπνὸς
γένοιτο, ῥῖνες ἂν διαγνοῖεν.
      </p>
      <p lang="it">
       Docei d'enioisἡ
il vapore fumoso è un odore, quindi un terreno comune e
aria E tutti se ne lamentano a causa dell'odore
Ed Eraclito parlava così, come se tutti gli esseri fossero fumo
genoito, ῥῖνες ἂν διαγνοῖεν.
      </p>
      <p lang="en">
       Docei d'eniois ἡ
smoky vapor is a smell, so common ground and
air And everyone complains about this because of the smell
And Heraclitus spoke thus, as if all beings were smoke
genoito, ῥῖνες ἂν διαγνοῖεν.
      </p>
     </div>
     <div n="7" subtype="section" type="textpart">
      <p rend="cont">
       Ἐπὶ δὲ τὴν ὀσμὴν πάντες
ἐπιφέρονται οἱ μὲν ὡς ἀτμίδα, οἱ δ’ ὡς ἀναθυμίασιν, οἱ δ’ ὡς
ἄμφω ταῦτα. Ἔστι δ’ ἡ μὲν ἀτμὶς ὑγρότης τις, ἡ δὲ
καπνώδης ἀναθυμίασις, ὥσπερ εἴρηται, κοινὸν ἀέρος καὶ γῆς·
καὶ συνίσταται ἐκ μὲν ἐκείνης ὕδωρ, ἐκ δὲ ταύτης γῆς τι
       <pb n="261"/>
       εἶδος.
      </p>
      <p lang="it">
       Per quanto riguarda l'odore, tutti quanti
le i appaiono come vapore, le d come vapore, le d come
Lo sto ascoltando. Esti d'o me atmîs ygrotis tis, o dé
vaporizzazione dei fumi, come detto, dell'aria e della terra comuni;
e consiste di quell'acqua, ma che dire di questa terra



Tipo.
      </p>
      <p lang="en">
       As for the smell, everyone
the i's appear as vapor, the d's as vapor, the d's as
I'm listening to this. Esti d' o me atmîs ygrotis tis, o dé
smoky vaporization, as mentioned, common air and earth;
and consists of that water, but what of this earth



kind.
      </p>
     </div>
     <div n="8" subtype="section" type="textpart">
      <p rend="cont">
       Ἀλλ’ οὐδέτερον τούτων ἔοικεν· ἡ μὲν γὰρ ἀτμίς
ἐστιν ὕδατος, ἡ δὲ καπνώδης ἀναθυμίασις ἀδύνατος ἐν ὕδατι
γενέσθαι. Ὀσμᾶται δὲ καὶ τὰ ἐν τῷ ὕδατι, ὥσπερ εἴρηται
πρότερον. Ἔτι ἡ ἀναθυμίασις ὁμοίως λέγεται ταῖς
ἀπορροίαις. Εἰ οὖν μηδ’ ἐκείνη καλῶς, οὐδ’ αὕτη καλῶς.
      </p>
      <p lang="it">
       Ma nessuno di questi è venuto; perché io sono un vapore
è acqua, ma la vaporizzazione fumosa è debole in acqua
accade. E anche le cose nell'acqua odorano, come detto
prima. Anche questa anatimiasi è chiamata tais
conseguenze. Se è così, non chiamarla, non chiamarla.
      </p>
      <p lang="en">
       But none of these have come; for I am a vapor
is water, but smoky vaporization weak in water
happens. And the things in the water also smell, as mentioned
earlier. That anathimiasis is likewise called tais
consequences. If so, don't call her, don't call her.
      </p>
     </div>
     <div n="9" subtype="section" type="textpart">
      <p rend="cont">
       Ὅτι μὲν οὖν ἐνδέχεται ἀπολαύειν τὸ ὑγρὸν καὶ τὸ ἐν τῷ
πνεύματι καὶ τὸ ἐν τῷ ὕδατι καὶ πάσχειν τι ὑπὸ τῆς ἐγχύμου
ξηρότητος, οὐκ ἄδηλον· καὶ γὰρ ὁ ἀὴρ ὑγρὸν τὴν
φύσιν ἐστίν. Ὅτι δ’ ὁμοίως ἐν τοῖς ὑγροῖς ποιεῖ καὶ ἐν
τῷ ἀέρι οἷον ἀποπλυνόμενον τὸ ξηρόν, φανερόν. Ἔτι δεῖ
ἀνάλογον εἶναι τὰς ὀσμὰς τοῖς χυμοῖς.
      </p>
      <p lang="it">
       Perché poi può godersi il liquido e il contenuto
spirito e ciò che è nell’acqua e soffri ciò che è sotto l’infusione
secchezza, non evidente, perché l'aria è umida
la natura è. Allo stesso modo scrive anche nei liquidi
all'aria che lavava via il secco, esposto. Ciò che vede
simili sono gli odori dei succhi.
      </p>
      <p lang="en">
       Because then he can enjoy the liquid and the in the
spirit and that which is in the water and suffer what is under the infusion
dryness, not obvious, because the air is wet
nature is. That in the same way in liquids he also writes in
to the air that washed away the dry, exposed. What he sees
similar are the odors to the juices.
      </p>
     </div>
     <div n="10" subtype="section" type="textpart">
      <p rend="cont">
       Ἀλλὰ μὴν τοῦτό
γε ἐπ’ ἐνίων συμβέβηκεν· καὶ γὰρ δριμεῖαι καὶ γλυκεῖαί εἰσιν
ὀσμαὶ καὶ αὐστηραὶ καὶ στρυφναὶ καὶ λιπαραί, καὶ τοῖς
πικροῖς τὰς σαπρὰς ἄν τις ἀνάλογον εἴποι. Διὸ ὥσπερ
ἐκεῖνα δυσκατάποτα, τὰ σαπρὰ δυσανάπνευστά ἐστιν. Δῆλον
ἄρα ὅτι ὅπερ ἐν τῷ ὕδατι ὁ χυμός, τοῦτ’ ἐν τῷ ἀέρι
καὶ ὕδατι ἡ ὀσμή.
      </p>
      <p lang="it">
       Ma non questo
È successo ai santi, e sono amari e dolci
Odori e astringenti e contorti e untuosi, e alle orecchie
amareggiano i sapras se li dico così. Per colpa di
Quelle cose sono difficili da digerire, sono davvero difficili da respirare. Delone
Pertanto, come il succo è nell'acqua, così nell'aria
e l'odore dell'acqua.
      </p>
      <p lang="en">
       But not this
It happened on the saints, and they are bitter and sweet
Odors and astringent and twisted and greasy, and to the ears
bitter the sapras if I say them like that. Because of
Those things are hard to swallow, they are really hard to breathe. Delon
Therefore, as the juice is in the water, so in the air
and the smell of water.
      </p>
     </div>
     <div n="11" subtype="section" type="textpart">
      <p rend="cont">
       Καὶ διὰ τοῦτο τὸ ψυχρὸν καὶ ἡ πῆξις
καὶ τοὺς χυμοὺς ἀμβλύνει καὶ τὰς ὀσμὰς ἀφανίζει· τὸ γὰρ
θερμὸν τὸ κινοῦν καὶ δημιουργοῦν ἀφανίζουσιν ἡ ψύξις καὶ
ἡ πῆξις. Εἴδη δὲ τοῦ ὀσφραντοῦ δύο ἐστίν· οὐ γὰρ ὥσπερ
τινές φασιν, οὐκ ἔστιν εἴδη τοῦ ὀσφραντοῦ, ἀλλ’ ἔστιν.
      </p>
      <p lang="it">
       E per questo il freddo e il gelo
e ammorbidisce i succhi e distrugge gli odori, perché
il calore lo muove e lo crea e il fresco lo annienta
il pêxis. Ma ci sono due tipi di odori;
una certa moda, non c'è nessun tipo di odore, ma lo è.
      </p>
      <p lang="en">
       And because of this the cold and the frost
and it softens the juices and destroys the odors, because
heat moves it and creates it and coolness annihilates it
the pêxis. But there are two kinds of smelling; for not as
some fashion, there is no kind of smell, but it is.
      </p>
     </div>
     <div n="12" subtype="section" type="textpart">
      <p rend="cont">
       Διοριστέον δὲ πῶς ἔστι καὶ πῶς οὐκ ἔστιν· τὸ μὲν γάρ
ἐστι κατὰ τοὺς χυμοὺς τεταγμένον αὐτῶν, ὥσπερ εἴπομεν,
καὶ τὸ ἡδὺ καὶ τὸ λυπηρὸν κατὰ συμβεβηκὸς ἔχουσιν· διὰ
γὰρ τὸ τοῦ θρεπτικοῦ πάθη εἶναι, ἐπιθυμούντων μὲν
ἡδεῖαι αἱ ὀσμαὶ τούτων εἰσί, πεπληρωμένοις δὲ καὶ μηδὲν
       <pb n="262"/>
       δεομένοις οὐχ ἡδεῖαι, οὐδ’ ὅσοις μὴ καὶ ἡ τροφὴ ἡ ἔχουσα
τὰς ὀσμὰς ἡδεῖα, οὐδὲ τούτοις.
      </p>
      <p lang="it">
       Nominalo come è e come non è;
è secondo i loro succhi, come diciamo,
E il qui e il triste lo hanno come cosa ovvia
perché è la passione nutriente di coloro che la desiderano
Ecco gli odori di queste cose, ma sono pieni di niente



quelli che hanno ricevuto non sono qui, non quelli che non ci sono e il cibo che avevo
gli odori qui, non questi.
      </p>
      <p lang="en">
       Appoint him as he is and as he is not;
it is according to their juices, as we say,
And the here and the sad they have as a matter of course
for the nourishing passion is, of those who desire it
Here are the smells of these things, but they are filled with nothing



those who were given are not here, not those who are not and the food that I had
the smells here, not these.
      </p>
     </div>
     <div n="13" subtype="section" type="textpart">
      <p rend="cont">
       Ὥστε αὗται μέν, καθάπερ
εἴπομεν, κατὰ συμβεβηκὸς ἔχουσι τὸ ἡδὺ καὶ λυπηρόν,
διὸ καὶ πάντων εἰσὶ κοιναὶ τῶν ζῴων· αἱ δὲ καθ’ αὑτὰς ἡδεῖαι
τῶν ὀσμῶν εἰσίν, οἷον αἱ τῶν ἀνθῶν· οὐδὲν γὰρ μᾶλλον οὐδ’
ἦττον πρὸς τὴν τροφὴν παρακαλοῦσιν, οὐδὲ συμβάλλεται
πρὸς ἐπιθυμίαν οὐδέν, ἀλλὰ τοὐναντίον μᾶλλον· ἀληθὲς γὰρ
ὅπερ Εὐριπίδην σκώπτων εἶπε Στράττις,
      </p>
      <p lang="it">
       Ὥste aὗtai men, ecc
diciamo che per convenzione hanno qui e dolore,
in ogni cosa siete partecipi della vita;
sono dei profumi, come dei fiori;
Stava chiedendo cibo, non è stato accettato
non a volontà, ma al contrario, perché è vero
Di Euripide il pensatore Stratti disse:
      </p>
      <p lang="en">
       Ὥste aὗtai men, etc
we say, by convention they have here and sorrow,
through and in all things you are partakers of the living;
they are of the scents, as of the flowers;
He was begging for food, it is not accepted
not at will, but on the contrary, because it is true
Of Euripides the thinker Strattis said,
      </p>
      <l>
       ὅταν φακῆν ἕψητε, μὴ ἐπιχεῖν μύρον.
      </l>
      <l lang="it">
       quando lo mangerai, non metterci sopra mirra.
      </l>
      <l lang="en">
       when you eat it, don't put myrrh on it.
      </l>
     </div>
     <div n="14" subtype="section" type="textpart">
      <p>
       Οἱ δὲ νῦν μιγνύντες εἰς τὰ πόματα τὰς τοιαύτας δυνάμεις
βιάζονται τῇ συνηθείᾳ τὴν ἡδονήν, ἕως ἂν ἐκ δύ’ αἰσθήσεων
γένηται τὸ ἡδὺ ὡς ἓν καὶ ἀπὸ μιᾶς.
      </p>
      <p lang="it">
       Ma quelli che ora mescolano in bocca tali forze
abitualmente affrettare il piacere, anche se proveniente da due sensi
il qui è fatto l'uno e l'altro.
      </p>
      <p lang="en">
       But the ones who are now mixing in their mouths such forces
habitually rush the pleasure, even if from two senses
the here is made as one and from each other.
      </p>
     </div>
     <div n="15" subtype="section" type="textpart">
      <p rend="cont">
       Τοῦτο μὲν οὖν τὸ
ὀσφραντὸν ἴδιον ἀνθρώπου ἐστίν, ἡ δὲ κατὰ τοὺς χυμοὺς
τεταγμένη καὶ τῶν ἄλλων ζῴων, ὥσπερ εἴρηται πρότερον·
κἀκείνων μέν, διὰ τὸ κατὰ συμβεβηκὸς ἔχειν τὸ ἡδύ, διῄρηται
τὰ εἴδη κατὰ τοὺς χυμούς, ταύτης δ’ οὐκέτι, διὰ τὸ τὴν φύσιν
αὐτῆς εἶναι καθ’ αὑτὴν ἡδεῖαν ἢ λυπηράν. Αἴτιον δὲ τοῦ
ἴδιον εἶναι ἀνθρώπου τὴν τοιαύτην ὀσμὴν διὰ τὴν ψύξιν
τὴν περὶ τὸν ἐγκέφαλον.
      </p>
      <p lang="it">
       Questo senza oὖn τὸ
È l'odore della stessa persona, ma secondo i succhi
anche di altri animali, come accennato prima;
di alcuni uomini, perché capita che abbiano il sole, lo è
la specie in base ai succhi non è la stessa, a causa della natura
è di per sé qui o tristemente. Per questo motivo
è l'odore proprio dell'uomo a causa del freddo
quello sul cervello.
      </p>
      <p lang="en">
       This without oὖn τὸ
It is the smell of the same person, but according to the juices
also of other animals, as mentioned before;
of some men, because they happen to have the sun, it is
the species according to the juices, this is not the same, because of the nature
it is in itself here or sadly. Because of that
it is a man's own smell because of the cold
the one about the brain.
      </p>
     </div>
     <div n="16" subtype="section" type="textpart">
      <p rend="cont">
       Ψυχροῦ γὰρ ὄντος τὴν φύσιν
τοῦ ἐγκεφάλου, καὶ τοῦ αἵματος τοῦ περὶ αὐτὸν ἐν τοῖς
φλεβίοις ὄντος λεπτοῦ μὲν καὶ καθαροῦ, εὐψύκτου δέ (διὸ
καὶ ἡ τῆς τροφῆς ἀναθυμίασις ψυχομένη διὰ τὸν τόπον
τὰ νοσηματικὰ ῥεύματα ποιεῖ), τοῖς ἀνθρώποις πρὸς βοήθειαν
ὑγιείας γέγονε τὸ τοιοῦτον εἶδος τῆς ὀσμῆς· οὐδὲν γὰρ
ἄλλο ἔργον ἐστὶν αὐτῆς ἢ τοῦτο.
      </p>
      <p lang="it">
       Essere freddo per natura
del cervello e del sangue che lo circonda negli occhi
venato essendo sottile ma pulito, non freddo (by
e quello del cibo evaporerà ispirato dal luogo
le parole malate, alle persone per chiedere aiuto
Questo tipo di odore non è salutare, perché non lo è
un'altra sua opera o questa.
      </p>
      <p lang="en">
       Being cold by nature
of the brain, and of the blood about it in the eyes
veined being thin but clean, not cold (by
and that of the food will evaporate inspired by the place
the diseased words, to the people for help
This kind of smell is not healthy, because it is not
another work of hers or this.
      </p>
     </div>
     <div n="17" subtype="section" type="textpart">
      <p rend="cont">
       Τοῦτο δὲ ποιεῖ φανερῶς·
ἡ μὲν γὰρ τροφὴ ἡδεῖα οὖσα, καὶ ἡ ξηρὰ καὶ ἡ ὑγρά,
       <pb n="263"/>
       πολλάκις νοσώδης ἐστίν, ἡ δ’ ἀπὸ τῆς ὀσμῆς τῆς καθ’ αὑτὴν
εὐώδους ὁπωσοῦν ἔχουσιν ὠφέλιμος ὡς εἰπεῖν ἀεί.
      </p>
      <p lang="it">
       Ma questo è chiaramente ciò che sta facendo;
perché c'è solo il cibo, sia secco che umido,



è spesso malaticcia, la quarta per l'odore del suo corpo
Beati come sono, lui è benefico come si suol dire, Ave.
      </p>
      <p lang="en">
       But this is clearly what he is doing;
for there is only food, both dry and wet,



she is often sickly, the fourth from the smell of her body
Blessed as they are, he is beneficial as they say, Hail.
      </p>
     </div>
     <div n="18" subtype="section" type="textpart">
      <p rend="cont">
       Καὶ
διὰ τοῦτο γίνεται διὰ τῆς ἀναπνοῆς, οὐ πᾶσιν ἀλλὰ τοῖς
ἀνθρώποις καὶ τῶν ἐναίμων οἷον τοῖς τετράποσι καὶ ὅσα
μετέχει μᾶλλον τῆς τοῦ ἀέρος φύσεως· ἀναφερομένων γὰρ
τῶν ὀσμῶν πρὸς τὸν ἐγκέφαλον διὰ τὴν ἐν αὐταῖς τῆς θερμότητος
κουφότητα, ὑγιεινοτέρως ἔχει τὰ περὶ τὸν τόπον
τοῦτον· ἡ γὰρ τῆς ὀσμῆς δύναμις θερμὴ τὴν φύσιν ἐστίν.
      </p>
      <p lang="it">
       E
quindi lo si fa respirando, non tutti ma loro
persone e del sangue da uno a quattro e tutti
piuttosto partecipa della natura dell'aria;
di odori al cervello a causa del calore in essi contenuto
sordità, sanamente ha cose sul posto
questo perché il potere dell'olfatto è calore per natura.
      </p>
      <p lang="en">
       And
therefore it is done by breathing, not all but to them
people and of the blood one to four and all
rather it partakes of the nature of air;
of odors to the brain due to the heat in them
deafness, healthily he has things about the place
this, for the power of smell is heat by nature.
      </p>
     </div>
     <div n="19" subtype="section" type="textpart">
      <p rend="cont">
       Κατακέχρηται δ’ ἡ φύσις τῇ ἀναπνοῇ ἐπὶ δύο, ὡς ἔργῳ μὲν
ἐπὶ τὴν εἰς τὸν θώρακα βοήθειαν, ὡς παρέργῳ δ’ ἐπὶ τὴν
ὀσμήν· ἀναπνέοντος γὰρ ὥσπερ ἐκ παρόδου ποιεῖται διὰ
τῶν μυκτήρων τὴν κίνησιν.
      </p>
      <p lang="it">
       La natura del respiro viene abusata da due, come opera di uno
sull'aiuto al petto, come sorpresa 4 sul
osmin; per respirare come se fosse di passaggio da cui è cantato
dei funghi il movimento.
      </p>
      <p lang="en">
       The nature of breathing is abused by two, as the work of one
on the help to the chest, as a surprise 4 on the
osmin; for breathing as if from passage it is sung by
of the fungi the movement.
      </p>
     </div>
     <div n="20" subtype="section" type="textpart">
      <p rend="cont">
       Ἴδιον δὲ τῆς τοῦ ἀνθρώπου φύσεώς
ἐστι τὸ τῆς ὀσμῆς τῆς τοιαύτης γένος διὰ τὸ πλεῖστον
ἐγκέφαλον καὶ ὑγρότατον ἔχειν τῶν ζῴων ὡς κατὰ
μέγεθος· διὰ γὰρ τοῦτο καὶ μόνον ὡς εἰπεῖν αἰσθάνεται τῶν
ζῴων ἄνθρωπος καὶ χαίρει ταῖς τῶν ἀνθῶν καὶ ταῖς τῶν
τοιούτων ὀσμαῖς· σύμμετρος γὰρ αὐτῶν ἡ θερμότης καὶ ἡ
κίνησις πρὸς τὴν ὑπερβολὴν τῆς ἐν τῷ τόπῳ ὑγρότητος καὶ
ψυχρότητός ἐστιν.
      </p>
      <p lang="it">
       Per quanto riguarda la natura umana stessa
è per la maggior parte l'odore di quel genere
Hanno un cervello e sono i più umidi tra tutti gli animali
dimensione; per questo e solo come dicono, viene percepita da loro
Un uomo vivo e si rallegra dei fiori e degli alberi
tali odori; per il calore e il
movimenti verso l'eccesso di umidità nel luogo e
la freddezza è.
      </p>
      <p lang="en">
       As for human nature itself
it is the smell of that genus for the most part
They have a brain and the wettest of all animals
size; because of this and only as they say it is felt by them
A living man and he rejoices in the flowers and the trees
such smells; for the warmth and the
movements towards the excess of moisture in the place and
coldness is.
      </p>
     </div>
     <div n="21" subtype="section" type="textpart">
      <p rend="cont">
       Τοῖς δ’ ἄλλοις ὅσα πλεύμονα ἔχει διὰ
τὸ ἀναπνεῖν τοῦ ἑτέρου γένους τῆς ὀσμῆς τὴν αἴσθησιν
ἀποδέδωκεν ἡ φύσις, ὅπως μὴ δύο αἰσθητήρια ποιῇ· ἀπόχρη
γάρ, ἐπείπερ καὶ ὣς ἀναπνέουσιν, ὥσπερ τοῖς ἀνθρώποις
ἀμφοτέρων τῶν ὀσφραντῶν, τούτοις τῶν ἑτέρων
μόνων ὑπάρχουσα ἡ αἴσθησις.
      </p>
      <p lang="it">
       Agli altri quattro, tanti polmoni quanti ne ha
il respiro dell'altro genere, l'olfatto
la natura accettata, come con due sensi;
poiché, inoltre, respirano, come negli uomini
di entrambi gli odoratori, questi degli altri
solo il sentimento esistente.
      </p>
      <p lang="en">
       To the other four, as many lungs as he has
the breathing of the other gender, the sense of smell
nature accepted, as with two senses;
for, moreover, they breathe, as in men
of both the smellers, these of the others
only the existing feeling.
      </p>
     </div>
     <div n="22" subtype="section" type="textpart">
      <p rend="cont">
       Τὰ δὲ μὴ ἀναπνέοντα ὅτι
μὲν ἔχει αἴσθησιν τοῦ ὀσφραντοῦ, φανερόν· καὶ γὰρ ἰχθύες
       <pb n="264"/>
       καὶ τὸ τῶν ἐντόμων γένος πᾶν ἀκριβῶς καὶ πόρρωθεν αἰσθάνεται,
διὰ τὸ θρεπτικὸν εἶδος τῆς ὀσμῆς, ἀπέχοντα πολὺ τῆς
οἰκείας τροφῆς, οἷον αἵ τε μέλιτται ποιοῦσι πρὸς τὸ μέλι
καὶ τὸ τῶν μικρῶν μυρμήκων γένος, οὓς καλοῦσί τινες κνίπας,
καὶ τῶν θαλαττίων αἱ πορφύραι, καὶ πολλὰ τῶν ἄλλων
τῶν τοιούτων ζῴων ὀξέως αἰσθάνεται τῆς τροφῆς διὰ τὴν
ὀσμήν.
      </p>
      <p lang="it">
       Ma quelli non traspiranti
a quanto pare non ha il senso dell'olfatto e pesca



e il genere degli insetti si fa sentire dovunque esattamente e dovunque,
dall'odore nutritivo, lontano da esso
di cibo familiare, che api per il miele
e la specie delle piccole formiche, che voi chiamate moscerini,
e delle razze marine quelle viola, e molte altre
di tali vite ne sente l'amarezza del cibo
ὀσμέν.
      </p>
      <p lang="en">
       But the non-breathable ones
he has no sense of smell, apparently; and fishes



and the genus of insects is felt everywhere exactly and everywhere,
by the nutritive kind of smell, far away from it
of familiar food, who bees for honey
and the genus of small ants, which you call gnats,
and of the sea-breeds the purple ones, and many of the others
of such lives he feels the bitterness of the food for it
ὀσμέν.
      </p>
     </div>
     <div n="23" subtype="section" type="textpart">
      <p rend="cont">
       Ὅτῳ δὲ αἰσθάνεται, οὐχ ὁμοίως φανερόν. Διὸ κἂν
ἀπορήσειέ τις τίνι αἰσθάνονται τῆς ὀσμῆς, εἴπερ ἀναπνέουσι
μὲν γίνεται τὸ ὀσμᾶσθαι μοναχῶς· τοῦτο γὰρ φαίνεται ἐπὶ
τῶν ἀναπνεόντων συμβαῖνον πάντων, ἐκείνων δ’ οὐθὲν ἀναπνεῖ
αἰσθάνεται μέντοι, εἰ μή τις παρὰ τὰς πέντε αἰσθήσεις ἑτέρα.
      </p>
      <p lang="it">
       Ma quando viene sentito, non appare allo stesso modo. Poiché il Sig
Chiedi ai denti di sentire l'odore, perché respirano
solo l'odore è fatto; perché questo si vede
degli avvenimenti respiratori di ogni cosa, quelli non respireranno
sembra menta, se non gli altri cinque sensi.
      </p>
      <p lang="en">
       But when it is felt, it does not appear in the same way. Because Mr
Ask the tines to sense the smell, because they breathe
only the smell is done; for this is seen on
of the breathing happenings of everything, those will not breathe
it feels minty, if not the other five senses.
      </p>
     </div>
     <div n="24" subtype="section" type="textpart">
      <p rend="cont">
       Τοῦτο δ’ ἀδύνατον· τοῦ γὰρ ὀσφραντοῦ ὄσφρησις, ἐκεῖνα
δὲ τούτου αἰσθάνονται, ἀλλ’ οὐ τὸν αὐτὸν ἴσως τρόπον,
ἀλλὰ τοῖς μὲν ἀναπνέουσι τὸ πνεῦμα ἀφαιρεῖ τὸ ἐπικείμενον
ὥσπερ πῶμά τι (διὸ οὐκ αἰσθάνεται μὴ ἀναπνέοντα), τοῖς δὲ
μὴ ἀναπνέουσιν ἀφῄρηται τοῦτο, καθάπερ ἐπὶ τῶν ὀφθαλμῶν
τὰ μὲν ἔχει βλέφαρα τῶν ζῴων, ὧν μὴ ἀνακαλυφθέντων οὐ
δύναται ὁρᾶν, τὰ δὲ σκληρόφθαλμα οὐκ ἔχει, διόπερ οὐ προσδεῖται
οὐδενὸς τοῦ ἀνακαλύψοντος, ἀλλ’ ὁρᾷ ἐκ τοῦ δυνατοῦ
ὁρᾶν αὐτῷ εὐθύς.
      </p>
      <p lang="it">
       Questo è impossibile, perché senti l'odore, quello
ma la pensano al riguardo, ma non allo stesso modo,
ma a chi non respira, lo spirito toglie ciò che è imminente
per quanto riguarda cosa (perché non ha la sensazione di non respirare),
Non respirano, tutto qui, perché è sugli occhi
Ho le palpebre dei vivi, che non sono state scoperte
può vedere, ma non ha la sclera, perché non è dotato
Niente dello scopritore, ma vede dal forte
lo vedono bene.
      </p>
      <p lang="en">
       This is impossible, because you smell the odor, that
but they feel about it, but not the same way,
but to those who do not breathe, the spirit takes away what is imminent
as for what (because he doesn't feel like he's not breathing),
They don't breathe, that's all, because it's on the eyes
I have the eyelids of the living, which have not been discovered
he can see, but he does not have sclera, because he is not gifted
Nothing of the discoverer, but he sees from the strong
they see him right.
      </p>
     </div>
     <div n="25" subtype="section" type="textpart">
      <p rend="cont">
       Ὁμοίως δὲ καὶ τῶν ἄλλων
ζῴων ὁτιοῦν οὐδὲν δυσχεραίνει τῶν καθ’ αὑτὰ δυσωδῶν τὴν
ὀσμήν, ἂν μή τι τύχῃ φθαρτικὸν ὄν. Ὑπὸ τούτων δ’ ὁμοίως
φθείρεται καθάπερ καὶ οἱ ἄνθρωποι ὑπὸ τῆς τῶν ἀνθράκων
ἀτμίδος καρηβαροῦσι καὶ φθείρονται πολλάκις· οὕτως ὑπὸ
τῆς τοῦ θείου δυνάμεως καὶ τῶν ἀσφαλτωδῶν φθείρεται
τἆλλα ζῷα, καὶ φεύγει διὰ τὸ πάθος.
      </p>
      <p lang="it">
       Allo stesso modo per gli altri
di animali che non mettono in difficoltà chi è puzzolente di per sé
ὀσμέν, ἂν ἂν τι τυχῃ φαρτικόν ὅν. Allo stesso modo per questi
si consuma così come le persone sotto la brace
vettore di vapore e si consumano spesso così sotto;
della potenza divina e l'asfalto si consuma
bella vita e se ne va per passione.
      </p>
      <p lang="en">
       Likewise for others
of animals that do not make it difficult for those that are stinky in themselves
ὀσμέν, ἂν ἂν τι τυχῃ φαρτικόν ὅν. Likewise for these
it wears out as well as the people under the coals
steam carrier and wear out often; thus under
of the divine power and the asphalt wears out
beautiful life, and leaves because of passion.
      </p>
     </div>
     <div n="26" subtype="section" type="textpart">
      <p rend="cont">
       Αὐτῆς δὲ καθ’
αὑτὴν τῆς δυσωδίας οὐδὲν φροντίζουσιν, καίτοι πολλὰ τῶν
       <pb n="265"/>
       φυομένων δυσώδεις ἔχει τὰς ὀσμάς, ἐὰν μή τι συμβάλληται
πρὸς τὴν γεῦσιν ἢ τὴν ἐδωδὴν αὐτοῖς.
      </p>
      <p lang="it">
       Quanto a lei
Non si prendono cura della puzza, anche se ce ne sono molti



ha piante maleodoranti, se nulla contribuisce
al gusto o al cibo per loro.
      </p>
      <p lang="en">
       As for her
They don't take care of the stench, although there are many of them



it has foul smelling plants, if nothing contributes
to the taste or the food to them.
      </p>
     </div>
     <div n="27" subtype="section" type="textpart">
      <p rend="cont">
       Ἔοικε δ’ ἡ
αἴσθησις ἡ τοῦ ὀσφραίνεσθαι περιττῶν οὐσῶν τῶν αἰσθήσεων
καὶ τοῦ ἀριθμοῦ ἔχοντος μέσον τοῦ περιττοῦ καὶ
αὐτὴ μέση εἶναι τῶν τε ἁπτικῶν, οἷον ἁφῆς καὶ γεύσεως
καὶ τῶν δι’ ἄλλου αἰσθητικῶν, οἷον ὄψεως καὶ ἀκοῆς.
      </p>
      <p lang="it">
       Casa IV
senso dell'olfatto essenze inutili dei sensi
e del numero che ha il centro dispari e
questo mezzo è tattile, del tatto e del gusto
e di quelli altrimenti estetici, quello della vista e dell'udito.
      </p>
      <p lang="en">
       House IV
sense of smell unnecessary essences of the senses
and of the number having an odd middle and
this medium is of the tactile, one of touch and taste
and of the otherwise aesthetic ones, one of sight and hearing.
      </p>
     </div>
     <div n="28" subtype="section" type="textpart">
      <p rend="cont">
       Διὸ
καὶ τὸ ὀσφραντὸν τῶν θρεπτικῶν ἐστὶ πάθος τι (ταῦτα δ’
ἐν τῷ ἁπτῷ γένει), καὶ τοῦ ἀκουστοῦ δὲ καὶ τοῦ ὁρατοῦ,
διὸ καὶ ἐν ἀέρι καὶ ἐν ὕδατι ὀσμῶνται. Ὤστ’ ἐστὶ τὸ
ὀσφραντὸν κοινόν τι τούτων ἀμφοτέρων, ὃ καὶ τῷ ἁπτῷ
ὑπάρχει καὶ τῷ ἀκουστῷ καὶ τῷ διαφανεῖ· διὸ εὐλόγως
παρείκασται ξηρότητος ἐν ὑγρῷ καὶ χυτῷ οἷον βαφή τις
εἶναι καὶ πλύσις.
      </p>
      <p lang="it">
       Perché
e l'odore delle sostanze nutritive è una passione cosa (questi
in quello tangibile), e quello udibile e visibile,
perché sia ​​nell'aria che nell'acqua odorano. Questo è quello che è
Odore comune ad entrambi, anche a occhio nudo
esiste sia per l'ascoltatore che per il trasparente;
appare secco nel liquido e colato chi lo dipinge
c'è anche la lavanderia.
      </p>
      <p lang="en">
       Why
and the smell of nutrients is a passion what (these
in the tangible kind), and the audible and the visible,
because both in air and in water they smell. That's what it is
Odor common to both of these, as well as to the naked eye
it exists both to the hearer and to the transparent;
it appears dry in liquid and cast whoever paints them
there is also laundry.
      </p>
     </div>
     <div n="29" subtype="section" type="textpart">
      <p rend="cont">
       Πῶς μὲν οὖν εἴδη δεῖ λέγειν καὶ πῶς οὐ
δεῖ τοῦ ὀσφραντοῦ, ἐπὶ τοσοῦτον εἰρήσθω. Ὃ δὲ λέγουσί
τινες τῶν Πυθαγορείων, οὐκ ἔστιν εὔλογον· τρέφεσθαι γάρ
φασιν ἔνια ζῷα ταῖς ὀσμαῖς.
      </p>
      <p lang="it">
       Perché no, come si suol dire, e perché no
vedi di Osfranto, sono arrabbiato con lui. Non parlare
quelli dei Pitagorici, non è ragionevole;
fasin ἔνια ῷa ἔσμαις ႖μαῖς.
      </p>
      <p lang="en">
       Why not, as they say, and why not
see of osfranto, I am angry with him. Don't speak
those of the Pythagoreans, it is not reasonable;
fasin ἔνια ῷa ἔσμαις ႖μαῖς.
      </p>
     </div>
     <div n="30" subtype="section" type="textpart">
      <p rend="cont">
       Πρῶτον μὲν γὰρ ὁρῶμεν ὅτι
τὴν τροφὴν δεῖ εἶναι σύνθετον· καὶ γὰρ τὰ τρεφόμενα οὐχ
ἁπλᾶ ἐστίν, διὸ καὶ περιττώματα γίνεται τῆς τροφῆς, ἢ
ἐν αὐτοῖς ἢ ἔξω, ὥσπερ τοῖς φυτοῖς. Ἔτι δ’ οὐδὲ τὸ ὕδωρ
ἐθέλει αὐτὸ μόνον ἄμικτον ὂν τρέφειν· σωματῶδες γάρ τι
δεῖ εἶναι τὸ συστησόμενον. Ἔτι πολὺ ἧττον εὔλογον τὸν
ἀέρα σωματοῦσθαι.
      </p>
      <p lang="it">
       Innanzitutto diciamo questo
il cibo è complesso e ciò che viene mangiato non lo è
è semplice, perché gli escrementi diventano cibo, oppure
ἐν αὐτοῖς ἢ ἔξω, come nelle piante. Perché non c'è acqua
lo vuole solo puro per essere nutrito;
ecco cosa è consigliato. Questo è molto ragionevole
l'aria diventa fisica.
      </p>
      <p lang="en">
       First of all, let's say that
food is complex, and what is eaten is not
it is simple, because excrement becomes food, or
ἐν αὐτοῖς ἢ ἔξω, as in plants. Because there is no water
he only wants it unmixed to be nourished;
here is what is recommended. That is very reasonable
air becomes physical.
      </p>
     </div>
     <div n="31" subtype="section" type="textpart">
      <p rend="cont">
       Πρὸς δὲ τούτοις, ὅτι πᾶσίν ἐστι
τοῖς ζῴοις τόπος δεκτικὸς τῆς τροφῆς, ἐξ οὗ ἕλκον λαμβάνει
τὸ σῶμα· τοῦ δ’ ὀσφραντοῦ ἐν τῇ κεφαλῇ τὸ αἰσθητήριον,
καὶ μετὰ πνευματώδους εἰσέρχεται ἀναθυμιάσεως, ὥστ’
εἰς τὸν ἀναπνευστικὸν βαδίζοι ἂν τόπον.
      </p>
      <p lang="it">
       Ma a questi, perché sono tutti
al vivente, luogo ricettivo al cibo, da cui riceve il cibo
il corpo; del quarto senso dell'olfatto nella testa,
e dopo lo spiritoso entra nel vapore, come
al respiro se cammini.
      </p>
      <p lang="en">
       But to these, because they are all
to the living, a place receptive to food, from which it receives food
the body; of the fourth sense of smell in the head,
and after witty he enters into vapor, as
to the breathing room if you walk.
      </p>
     </div>
     <div n="32" subtype="section" type="textpart">
      <p rend="cont">
       Ὅτι μὲν οὖν
       <pb n="266"/>
       οὐ συμβάλλεται εἰς τροφὴν τὸ ὀσφραντόν, ᾗ ὀσφραντόν,
δῆλον· ὅτι μέντοι εἰς ὑγίειαν, καὶ ἐκ τῆς αἰσθήσεως καὶ ἐκ
τῶν εἰρημένων φανερόν, ὥστε ὅπερ ὁ χυμὸς ἐν τῷ θρεπτικῷ
καὶ πρὸς τὰ τρεφόμενα, τοῦτ’ ἐστὶ πρὸς ὑγίειαν τὸ ὀσφραντόν.
Καθ’ ἕκαστον μὲν οὖν αἰσθητήριον διωρίσθω τὸν τρόπον
τοῦτον.
      </p>
      <p lang="it">
       Cosa succede se



non contribuisce al cibo del profumo,
delon; perché giacciono in salute, sia dai sensi che da
di quelli spezzati, come sopra il succo nel nutritivo
e alle cose che si nutrono, così che l'olfatto è alla salute.
Per ognuno, poi, emotivamente, distinguo la strada
Questo.
      </p>
      <p lang="en">
       What if



it does not contribute to the food of the scent,
delon; because they lie in health, both from the senses and from
of the broken ones, as above the juice in the nutritive
and to the things that are nourished, so that the sense of smell is to health.
For each one, then, emotionally, I distinguish the way
this one.
      </p>
     </div>
    </div>
    <div n="6" subtype="chapter" type="textpart">
     <div n="1" subtype="section" type="textpart">
      <p>
       Ἀπορήσειε δ’ ἄν τις, εἰ πᾶν σῶμα εἰς ἄπειρον διαιρεῖται,
ἆρα καὶ τὰ παθήματα τὰ αἰσθητά, οἷον χρῶμα καὶ χυμὸς
καὶ ὀσμὴ καὶ βάρος καὶ ψόφος καὶ ψυχρὸν καὶ θερμὸν
καὶ κοῦφον καὶ σκληρὸν καὶ μαλακόν; ἢ ἀδύνατον; ποιητικὸν
γάρ ἐστιν ἕκαστον αὐτῶν τῆς αἰσθήσεως· τῷ δύνασθαι γὰρ
κινεῖν αὐτὴν λέγεται πάντα.
      </p>
      <p lang="it">
       Chiedi loro se ogni corpo è infinitamente divisibile,
E le sofferenze dei sensi, che sono colore e succo
e l'odore, il peso, il sapore, il freddo e il caldo
e sordo e duro e molle? o impossibile? poetico
perché in ciascuno di essi c'è il senso, a causa della potenza
si dice sempre di spostarlo.
      </p>
      <p lang="en">
       Ask them if every body is infinitely divisible,
And the sufferings of the senses, which are color and juice
and smell and weight and taste and cold and hot
and deaf and hard and soft? or impossible? poetic
for it is in each of them of the sense, because of the power
it is always said to move it.
      </p>
     </div>
     <div n="2" subtype="section" type="textpart">
      <p rend="cont">
       Ὤστ’ ἀνάγκη τήν τε αἴσθησιν
εἰς ἄπειρα διαιρεῖσθαι καὶ πᾶν εἶναι μέγεθος αἰσθητόν·
ἀδύνατον γὰρ λευκὸν μὲν ὁρᾶν, μὴ ποσὸν δέ. Εἰ γὰρ μὴ
οὕτως, ἐνδέχοιτ’ ἂν εἶναί τι σῶμα μηδὲν ἔχον χρῶμα μηδὲ
βάρος μηδ’ ἄλλο τι τοιοῦτον πάθος. Ὤστ’ οὐδ’ αἰσθητὸν
ὅλως· ταῦτα γὰρ τὰ αἰσθητά.
      </p>
      <p lang="it">
       È necessario il sentimento
nella divisione infinita e ovunque c'è dimensione sensoriale;
Perché non riesco a vedere il bianco, non quanto. Perché no?
quindi, è possibile che se è un corpo pari a zero, abbia un colore pari a zero
peso nientemeno che quella passione. È inaudito
tutti; perché questi sono i sensi.
      </p>
      <p lang="en">
       Feeling is needed
into infinite division and everywhere is sense size;
Because I can't see white, not how much. Why not?
thus, it is possible that if it is a body of zero, it has a color of zero
weight none other than that passion. It's unheard of
all; for these are the senses.
      </p>
     </div>
     <div n="3" subtype="section" type="textpart">
      <p rend="cont">
       Τὸ ἄρ’ αἰσθητὸν
ἔσται συγκείμενον οὐκ ἐξ αἰσθητῶν. Ἀλλ’ ἀναγκαῖον· οὐ
γὰρ δὴ ἔκ γε τῶν μαθηματικῶν. Ἔτι τίνι κρινοῦμεν ταῦτα
ἢ γνωσόμεθα; ἢ τῷ νῷ; Ἀλλ’ οὐ νοητά, οὐδὲ νοεῖ ὁ νοῦς
τὰ ἐκτὸς μὴ μετ’ αἰσθήσεως ὄντα. Ἅμα δ’ εἰ ταῦτ’ ἔχει
οὕτως, ἔοικε μαρτυρεῖν τοῖς τὰ ἄτομα ποιοῦσι μεγέθη· οὕτω
γὰρ ἂν λύοιτο ὁ λόγος.
      </p>
      <p lang="it">
       L'insensato
essere cosciente e non dei sensi. Altrimenti è necessario no;
perché non si tratta di matematica. Perché lo giudichiamo?
oppure ci conosciamo? ἢ τῷ ῷ? Ma non è intelligibile, la mente non capisce
esseri esterni senza senso. Se solo ce l'avesse
così, le persone di tali dimensioni testimoniano così;
perché se il motivo fosse risolto.
      </p>
      <p lang="en">
       The senseless
be conscious not of senses. Otherwise, it is necessary; no
because it's not about mathematics. Why do we judge this?
or do we know each other? ἢ τῷ ῷ? But it is not intelligible, the mind does not understand
external non-sense beings. If only he has it
thus, let the persons of such sizes testify to them; thus
for if the reason were solved.
      </p>
     </div>
     <div n="4" subtype="section" type="textpart">
      <p rend="cont">
       Ἀλλ’ ἀδύνατα· εἴρηται δὲ περὶ
αὐτῶν ἐν τοῖς λόγοις τοῖς περὶ κινήσεως. Περὶ δὲ τῆς λύσεως
αὐτῶν ἅμα δῆλον ἔσται, καὶ διὰ τί πεπέρανται τὰ εἴδη
καὶ χρώματος καὶ χυμοῦ καὶ φθόγγων καὶ τῶν ἄλλων αἰσθητῶν.
Ὧν μὲν γάρ ἐστιν ἔσχατα, ἀνάγκη πεπεράνθαι τὰ
ἐντός· τὰ δ’ ἐναντία ἔσχατα.
      </p>
      <p lang="it">
       Ma è impossibile;
tra loro nei discorsi riguardanti il ​​movimento. Ma riguardo alla soluzione
di questi, se lo sono, e perché le specie sono scomparse
e il colore, il succo, i colori e gli altri sensi.
Se è la fine, il bisogno passerà
dentro; il quarto contro l'ultimo.
      </p>
      <p lang="en">
       But it is impossible; it is said about
among them in the discourses concerning movement. But about the solution
of these, if they are, and why are the species passed away
and color and juice and colors and the other senses.
If it is the end, the need will pass
within; the fourth against the last.
      </p>
     </div>
     <div n="5" subtype="section" type="textpart">
      <p rend="cont">
       Πᾶν δὲ τὸ αἰσθητὸν ἔχει
       <pb n="267"/>
       ἐναντίωσιν, οἷον ἐν χρώματι τὸ λευκὸν καὶ τὸ μέλαν, ἐν
χυμῷ γλυκὺ καὶ πικρόν· καὶ ἐν τοῖς ἄλλοις δὴ πᾶσίν ἐστιν
ἔσχατα τὰ ἐναντία. Τὸ μὲν οὖν συνεχὲς εἰς ἄπειρα τέμνεται
ἄνισα, εἰς δ’ ἴσα πεπερασμένα· τὸ δὲ μὴ καθ’ αὑτὸ
συνεχὲς εἰς πεπερασμένα εἴδη.
      </p>
      <p lang="it">
       Tutto ha il sentimento



opposizione, che a colori è bianco e nero, in
succo dolce e amaro; e in altri non è tutto
infine l'opposizione. Il me quindi si interseca continuamente all'infinito
anisa, in quattro parti finite, ma non in sé;
continua in specie finite.
      </p>
      <p lang="en">
       Everything has the feeling



opposition, which in color is white and black, in
sweet and bitter juice; and in others it is not all
finally the opposition. The me therefore intersects continuously at infinity
anisa, in four finite parts; but not in itself
continuous in finite species.
      </p>
     </div>
     <div n="6" subtype="section" type="textpart">
      <p rend="cont">
       Ἐπεὶ οὖν τὰ μὲν πάθη ὡς
εἴδη λεκτέον, ὑπάρχει δὲ συνέχεια ἀεὶ ἐν τούτοις, ληπτέον
ὅτι τὸ δυνάμει καὶ τὸ ἐνεργείᾳ ἕτερον· καὶ διὰ τοῦτο τὸ
μυριοστημόριον λανθάνει τῆς κέγχρου ὁρωμένης, καίτοι
ἡ ὄψις ἐπελήλυθεν, καὶ ὁ ἐν τῇ διέσει φθόγγος λανθάνει,
καίτοι συνεχοῦς ὄντος ἀκούει τοῦ μέλους παντός.
      </p>
      <p lang="it">
       Quindi, le mie passioni come
eidi lekteon, ma c'è una continuazione, ma tuttavia, lepteon
perché il potere e l'energia degli altri; e per questo
myriostimorion lanthanas di kenchros oromenis, però
la visione è compiuta e l'ombra nell'oscurità si nasconde,
benché un essere continuo ascolti il ​​membro del tutto.
      </p>
      <p lang="en">
       So, my passions as
eidi lekteon, but there is a continuance, but nevertheless, lepteon
because the power and energy of others; and because of this
myriostimorion lanthanas of kenchros oromenis, though
the vision is completed, and the shadow in the darkness is hidden,
although a continuous being listens to the member of everything.
      </p>
     </div>
     <div n="7" subtype="section" type="textpart">
      <p rend="cont">
       Τὸ δὲ
διάστημα τὸ τοῦ μεταξὺ πρὸς τοὺς ἐσχάτους λανθάνει.
Ὁμοίως δὲ καὶ ἐν τοῖς ἄλλοις αἰσθητοῖς τὰ μικρὰ πάμπαν·
δυνάμει γὰρ ὁρατά, ἐνεργείᾳ δ’ οὔ, ὅταν χωρισθῇ· καὶ
γὰρ ἐνυπάρχει δυνάμει ἡ ποδιαία τῇ δίποδι, ἐνεργείᾳ δ’
ἤδη διαιρεθεῖσα.
      </p>
      <p lang="it">
       IL
l'intervallo tra lui e l'ultimo è latente.
Allo stesso modo, negli altri sensi, fioriscono i piccoli;
poiché dal potere visibile, dall'energia, quando è separato e
poiché il piede del bipede esiste per forza, energia d'
Mi sono già rotto.
      </p>
      <p lang="en">
       The
the interval between him and the last is latent.
In the same way, in the other senses, the little ones flourish;
for by visible power, by energy, when it is separated; and
for the foot of the biped exists by force, energy d'
I already broke up.
      </p>
     </div>
     <div n="8" subtype="section" type="textpart">
      <p rend="cont">
       Χωριζόμεναι δ’ αἱ τηλικαῦται ὑπεροχαὶ
εὐλόγως μὲν ἂν καὶ διαλύοιντο εἰς τὰ περιέχοντα, ὥσπερ
καὶ ἀκαριαῖος χυμὸς εἰς τὴν θάλατταν ἐκχυθείς.
      </p>
      <p lang="it">
       Dividere quattro estremità è fantastico
fortunatamente, anche se si dissolvono nel contenuto, come ad es
E il succo istantaneo fu versato in mare.
      </p>
      <p lang="en">
       Dividing four ends are great
fortunately, even if they dissolve into the contents, such as
And instant juice was poured into the sea.
      </p>
     </div>
     <div n="9" subtype="section" type="textpart">
      <p rend="cont">
       Οὐ μὴν
ἀλλ’ ἐπειδὴ οὐδ’ ἡ τῆς αἰσθήσεως ὑπεροχὴ καθ’ αὑτὴν αἰσθητὴ
οὐδὲ χωριστή (δυνάμει γὰρ ἐνυπάρχει ἐν τῇ ἀκριβεστέρᾳ
ἡ ὑπεροχή), οὐδὲ τὸ τηλικοῦτον αἰσθητὸν χωριστὸν
ἔσται ἐνεργείᾳ αἰσθέσθαι, ἀλλ’ ὅμως ἔσται αἰσθητόν· δυνάμει
τε γάρ ἐστιν ἤδη, καὶ ἐνεργείᾳ ἔσται προσγενόμενον.
      </p>
      <p lang="it">
       No, no
ma perché il senso non è meraviglioso in sé
non separato (poiché può esistere nella forma più pura
la superiorità), non il sentimento finale separatamente
è energia, si sente, ma si sente comunque con la forza;
perché lo è già, e nell'energia sta nascendo.
      </p>
      <p lang="en">
       No, no
but because the sense is not wonderful in itself
not separate (for it can exist in the purest
the superiority), not the final feeling separately
it is energy, it is felt, but still it is felt; by force
because it is already, and in energy it is being born.
      </p>
     </div>
     <div n="10" subtype="section" type="textpart">
      <p rend="cont">
       Ὅτι μὲν οὖν ἔνια μεγέθη καὶ πάθη λανθάνει, καὶ διὰ τίν’
αἰτίαν, καὶ πῶς αἰσθητὰ καὶ πῶς οὔ, εἴρηται. Ὅταν δὲ δὴ
       <pb n="268"/>
       ἐνυπάρχοντα οὕτω πως ἄττα ᾖ ὥστε καὶ ἐνεργείᾳ αἰσθητὰ
εἶναι, καὶ μὴ μόνον ἐν τῷ ὅλῳ ἀλλὰ καὶ χωρὶς ᾖ
πεπερασμένα, ἀνάγκη εἶναι τὸν ἀριθμὸν καὶ χρώματα καὶ
χυμοὺς καὶ φθόγγους.
      </p>
      <p lang="it">
       Che, quindi, una dimensione e una passione sono latenti, e per cosa
viene detto perché, come è stato sentito e come no. Quando no



esistente come atta ḥ come anche nell'energia sensibilmente
lo è, e non solo nel suo insieme ma anche senza h
finito, il bisogno è il numero e anche i colori
succhi e succhi.
      </p>
      <p lang="en">
       That, then, one size and passion is latent, and for what
why, and how felt and how not, is said. When not



existing as atta ḥ as also in energy sensibly
it is, and not only in the whole but also without h
finite, need is the number and colors as well
juices and juices.
      </p>
     </div>
     <div n="11" subtype="section" type="textpart">
      <p rend="cont">
       Ἀπορήσειε δ’ ἄν τις, ἆρ’ ἀφικνοῦνται
ἢ τὰ αἰσθητὰ ἢ αἱ κινήσεις αἱ ἀπὸ τῶν αἰσθητῶν, ὁποτέρως
ποτὲ γίνεται ἡ αἴσθησις, ὅταν ἐνεργῶσιν, εἰς τὸ μέσον
πρῶτον, οἷον ἥ τε ὀσμὴ φαίνεται ποιοῦσα καὶ ὁ ψόφος·
πρότερον γὰρ ὁ ἐγγὺς αἰσθάνεται τῆς ὀσμῆς, καὶ ὁ ψόφος
ὕστερον ἀφικνεῖται τῆς πληγῆς.
      </p>
      <p lang="it">
       Chiedi loro se verranno
o rispettivamente i sensi o i movimenti dei sensi
quando avviene la sensazione, quando agiscono, nel mezzo
primo, chi ha un odore sembra uno stolto;
perché per primo sente l'odore il vicino, e anche il vecchio
Poi si tratta della ferita.
      </p>
      <p lang="en">
       Ask them if they are coming
or the senses or the movements of the senses, respectively
when does the sensation occur, when they act, in the middle
first, he who has a smell seems to be a fool;
for first the near one feels the smell, and so does the old one
Then it comes to the wound.
      </p>
     </div>
     <div n="12" subtype="section" type="textpart">
      <p rend="cont">
       Ἆρ’ οὖν οὕτω καὶ
τὸ ὁρώμενον καὶ τὸ φῶς; Καθάπερ καὶ Ἐμπεδοκλῆς
φησὶν ἀφικνεῖσθαι πρότερον τὸ ἀπὸ τοῦ ἡλίου φῶς εἰς
τὸ μεταξὺ πρὶν πρὸς τὴν ὄψιν ἢ ἐπὶ τὴν γῆν.
      </p>
      <p lang="it">
       Ἆρ' o così e così
la visione e la luce? Kathaper ed Empedocle
venga davanti a lui la luce del sole
la seta davanti agli occhi o per terra.
      </p>
      <p lang="en">
       Ἆρ' or so and so
the vision and the light? Kathaper and Empedocles
let the light of the sun come before him
the silk before the eye or on the ground.
      </p>
     </div>
     <div n="13" subtype="section" type="textpart">
      <p rend="cont">
       Δόξειε
δ’ ἂν εὐλόγως τοῦτο συμβαίνειν· τὸ γὰρ κινούμενον κινεῖταί
ποθέν ποι, ὥστ’ ἀνάγκη εἶναί τινα καὶ χρόνον ἐν ᾧ κινεῖται
ἐκ θατέρου πρὸς θάτερον· ὁ δὲ χρόνος πᾶς διαιρετός,
ὥστε ἦν ὅτε οὔπω ἑωρᾶτο ἀλλ’ ἔτ’ ἐφέρετο ἡ ἀκτὶς ἐν τῷ
μεταξύ.
      </p>
      <p lang="it">
       Bontà
Se è una fortuna che ciò accada, perché ciò che si muove si muove
chi desidera, poiché bisogno è cosa e tempo in cui si muove
dal passato al passato; ma il tempo è sempre divisibile,
avvenne così che non si potesse vederlo se non quando la riva fu portata dentro
fra.
      </p>
      <p lang="en">
       Goodness
If it is blessed that this happens, because what moves is moved
who desires, as need is what and time in which it moves
from the past to the past; but time is always divisible,
so it was that it could not be seen but when the shore was brought in the
between.
      </p>
     </div>
     <div n="14" subtype="section" type="textpart">
      <p rend="cont">
       Καὶ εἰ ἅπαν ἅμα ἀκούει καὶ ἀκήκοε καὶ ὅλως αἰσθάνεται
καὶ ᾔσθηται, καὶ μή ἐστι γένεσις αὐτῶν, ἀλλ’
εἰσὶν ἄνευ τοῦ γίνεσθαι ὅμως οὐδὲν ἧττον, ὥσπερ ὁ ψόφος
ἤδη γεγενημένης τῆς πληγῆς οὔπω πρὸς τῇ ἀκοῇ.
      </p>
      <p lang="it">
       E ovunque sente, sente e sente
E sorgerà, e tu non nascerai da loro, ma
ma senza di lui diventa nulla, come il vecchio
già nato dalla ferita o dall'orecchio.
      </p>
      <p lang="en">
       And everywhere he hears and hears and feels
And it will arise, and you will not be born of them, but
but without him, he becomes nothing, like the old man
already born of the wound or to the ear.
      </p>
     </div>
     <div n="15" subtype="section" type="textpart">
      <p rend="cont">
       Δηλοῖ
δὲ τοῦτο καὶ ἡ τῶν γραμμάτων μετασχημάτισις, ὡς γιγνομένης
τῆς φορᾶς ἐν τῷ μεταξύ· οὐ γὰρ τὸ λεχθὲν φαίνονται
ἀκηκοότες διὰ τὸ μετασχηματίζεσθαι φερόμενον τὸν
ἀέρα. Ἆρ’ οὖν οὕτω καὶ τὸ χρῶμα καὶ τὸ φῶς;
      </p>
      <p lang="it">
       De los
ma questo e la trasformazione delle lettere, come se fosse fatto
tu intanto li indossi, perché non mostrano quello che hanno detto
ascoltatori per la trasformazione che porta il
aria. E allora che dire del colore e della luce?
      </p>
      <p lang="en">
       Delos
but this and the transformation of the letters, as if done
you wear it in the meantime, because they don't show what they said
hearers for the transformation bearing the
air. So what about color and light?
      </p>
     </div>
     <div n="16" subtype="section" type="textpart">
      <p rend="cont">
       Οὐ γὰρ
δὴ τῷ πῶς ἔχειν τὸ μὲν ὁρᾷ τὸ δ’ ὁρᾶται, ὥσπερ ἴσα ἐστίν·
       <pb n="269"/>
       οὐθὲν γὰρ ἔδει που ἑκάτερον εἶναι· τοῖς γὰρ ἴσοις γινομένοις
οὐδὲν διαφέρει ἢ ἐγγὺς ἢ πόρρω ἀλλήλων εἶναι.
      </p>
      <p lang="it">
       No, no
guarda come hanno quello che dicono, quello che non si vede, poiché sono gli stessi;



poiché non vedeva dove fosse ciascuno;
Non importa se è vicino o lontano.
      </p>
      <p lang="en">
       No, no
see how they have what they say, what is not seen, as they are the same;



for he did not see where each one was;
It doesn't matter if it's close or far away.
      </p>
     </div>
     <div n="17" subtype="section" type="textpart">
      <p rend="cont">
       Ἣ
περὶ μὲν τὸν ψόφον καὶ τὴν ὀσμὴν τοῦτο συμβαίνειν εὔλογον·
ὥσπερ γὰρ ὁ ἀὴρ καὶ τὸ ὕδωρ συνεχῆ μέν, ἀλλ’
ὅμως μεμέρισται ἀμφοτέρων ἡ κίνησις. Διὸ καὶ ἔστι
μὲν ὡς τὸ αὐτὸ ἀκούει ὁ πρῶτος καὶ ὁ ὕστερος καὶ ὀσφραίνεται,
ἔστι δ’ ὡς οὔ.
      </p>
      <p lang="it">
       IL
quanto all'odore e all'olfatto, ciò avviene ragionevolmente;
proprio come l'aria e l'acqua sono costanti, ma
tuttavia, il movimento è condiviso da entrambi. Perchè è
ma come il primo e l'ultimo odono e odorano,
ἔsti d' as oὔ.
      </p>
      <p lang="en">
       The
as for the smell and the smell, this happens reasonably;
just as air and water are constant, but
however, the movement is shared by both. Because it is
but as the first and the last hear and smell,
ἔsti d' as oὔ.
      </p>
     </div>
     <div n="18" subtype="section" type="textpart">
      <p rend="cont">
       Δοκεῖ δέ τισιν εἶναι ἀπορία καὶ
περὶ τούτων· ἀδύνατον γάρ φασί τινες ἄλλον ἄλλῳ τὸ αὐτὸ
ἀκούειν ἢ ὁρᾶν καὶ ὀσφραίνεσθαι· οὐ γὰρ οἷόν τ’ εἶναι
πολλοὺς καὶ χωρὶς ὄντας ἀκούειν ἢ ὀσφραίνεσθαι· τὸ γὰρ
ἓν χωρὶς ἂν αὐτὸ αὑτοῦ εἶναι.
      </p>
      <p lang="it">
       È anche una domanda
riguardo a questi; è impossibile perché vi dite la stessa cosa
sentono, vedono e odorano, perché non c'è nessuno
molti e senza essere ascoltati o annusati;
uno senza se questo lo è.
      </p>
      <p lang="en">
       It is also a question
about these; it's impossible because you tell each other the same thing
they hear or see and smell; for there is no one
many and without being heard or smelled; for
one without if this one is.
      </p>
     </div>
     <div n="19" subtype="section" type="textpart">
      <p rend="cont">
       Ἢ τοῦ μὲν κινήσαντος
πρῶτον, οἷον τῆς κώδωνος ἢ λιβανωτοῦ ἢ πυρός, τοῦ αὐτοῦ
καὶ ἑνὸς ἀριθμῷ αἰσθάνονται πάντες, τοῦ δὲ δὴ ἰδίου ἑτέρου
ἀριθμῷ, εἴδει δὲ τοῦ αὑτοῦ, διὸ ἅμα πολλοὶ ὁρῶσι
καὶ ὀσμῶνται καὶ ἀκούουσιν. Ἔστι δ’ οὔτε σώματα ταῦτα,
ἀλλὰ πάθος καὶ κίνησίς τις (οὐ γὰρ ἂν τοῦτο συνέβαινεν),
οὔτ’ ἄνευ σώματος.
      </p>
      <p lang="it">
       Quello che non si è mosso
primo, uno della campana o dell'incenso o del fuoco, di lui
e ognuno sente un numero, ma non quello dell'altro
Αριθμῷ, e vide di persona, solo per molti mesi
e annusano e sentono. Non ci sono nemmeno questi corpi,
ma passione e spinta (non se ciò dovesse accadere),
né senza corpo.
      </p>
      <p lang="en">
       The one who didn't move
first, one of the bell or incense or fire, of him
and everyone feels one number, but not the other's own
Αριθμῷ, and he saw of himself, through but many months
and they smell and hear. There are not even these bodies,
but passion and drive them (not if this were to happen),
nor without a body.
      </p>
     </div>
     <div n="20" subtype="section" type="textpart">
      <p rend="cont">
       Περὶ δὲ τοῦ φωτὸς ἄλλος λόγος· τῷ
εἶναι γάρ τι φῶς ἐστίν, ἀλλ’ οὐ κίνησίς τις. Ὅλως δὲ
οὐδὲ ὁμοίως ἐπί τε ἀλλοιώσεως ἔχει καὶ φορᾶς· αἱ μὲν γὰρ
φοραὶ εὐλόγως εἰς τὸ μεταξὺ πρῶτον ἀφικνοῦνται (δοκεῖ δ’
ὁ ψόφος εἶναι φερομένου τινὸς κίνησις), ὅσα δ’ ἀλλοιοῦται,
οὐκέτι ὁμοίως· ἐνδέχεται γὰρ ἀθρόον ἀλλοιοῦσθαι, καὶ μὴ τὸ
ἥμισυ πρότερον, οἷον τὸ ὕδωρ ἅμα πᾶν πήγνυσθαι.
      </p>
      <p lang="it">
       Per quanto riguarda la luce, un'altra parola;
È a causa della luce, ma non spostarli. Affatto
Allo stesso modo, non c’è alcun cambiamento nel modo in cui lo indossi, perché sono io
a volte, per fortuna, arrivano prima al centro (vedi d'
la persona è in movimento), cosa non cambia,
non nello stesso modo; perché è suscettibile di essere cambiato, e non lo è
La metà prima dell'acqua che gela ovunque.
      </p>
      <p lang="en">
       As for the light, another word;
It's because of the light, but don't move them. Not at all
Similarly, there is no change in the way you wear it, because it is me
sometimes, fortunately, they reach the middle first (see d'
the person is in motion), what does not change,
not in the same way; for it is capable of being changed, and it is not
Half as early as the water that freezes everywhere.
      </p>
     </div>
     <div n="21" subtype="section" type="textpart">
      <p rend="cont">
       Οὐ
μὴν ἀλλ’ ἂν ᾖ πολὺ τὸ θερμαινόμενον ἢ πηγνύμενον, τὸ
ἐχόμενον ὑπὸ τοῦ ἐχομένου πάσχει, τὰ δὲ πρῶτον ὑπ’ αὐτοῦ
       <pb n="270"/>
       τοῦ ἀλλοιοῦντος μεταβάλλει, καὶ οὐκ ἀνάγκη ἅμα ἀλλοιοῦσθαι
καὶ ἀθρόον.
      </p>
      <p lang="it">
       Oὐ
non altrimenti, se è molto riscaldato o bollito, il
L'essere soffre di ciò che è, ma le prime cose soffrono di lui



chi cambia cambia, e non c'è bisogno che cambi
e Atrone.
      </p>
      <p lang="en">
       Oὐ
not otherwise, if it is very heated or boiled, the
Being is suffering from what is being, but the first things are suffering from him



the one who changes changes, and there is no need for it to change
and athroon.
      </p>
     </div>
     <div n="22" subtype="section" type="textpart">
      <p rend="cont">
       Ἦν δ’ ἂν καὶ τὸ γεύεσθαι ὥσπερ ἡ
ὀσμή, εἰ ἐν ὑγρῷ ἦμεν καὶ πορρωτέρω ἔτι πρὶν θιγεῖν αὐτοῦ
ᾐσθανόμεθα. Εὐλόγως δ’ ὧν ἐστὶ μεταξὺ τοῦ αἰσθητηρίου,
οὐχ ἅμα πάντα πάσχει, πλὴν ἐπὶ τοῦ φωτὸς διὰ
τὸ εἰρημένον. Διὰ τὸ αὐτὸ δὲ καὶ ἐπὶ τοῦ ὁρᾶν· τὸ γὰρ
φῶς ποιεῖ τὸ ὁρᾶν.
      </p>
      <p lang="it">
       Anche se ha il suo sapore
l'odore, se fossimo in acqua e lo annusassi prima che lo toccasse
Stiamo morendo. Benedetto sia dov'è tra l'auditorium,
no, soffre sempre, tranne che per la luce che passa
il citato. Per questo e alla vista perché;
la luce fa la vista.
      </p>
      <p lang="en">
       Even though it tastes like it
smell, if we were in water and I would smell it before it touched him
We are dying. Blessed be where it is between the auditorium,
no, he always suffers, except on the light through
the mentioned. Because of this and on the sight; because
light does the sight.
      </p>
     </div>
    </div>
    <div n="7" subtype="chapter" type="textpart">
     <div n="1" subtype="section" type="textpart">
      <p>
       Ἔστι δέ τις ἀπορία καὶ ἄλλη τοιάδε περὶ αἰσθήσεως,
πότερον ἐνδέχεται δυεῖν ἅμα αἰσθάνεσθαι ἐν τῷ αὐτῷ καὶ
ἀτόμῳ χρόνῳ, ἢ οὔ, εἰ δὴ ἀεὶ ἡ μείζων κίνησις τὴν ἐλάττω
ἐκκρούει· διὸ ἐπιφερομένων ἐπὶ τὰ ὄμματα οὐκ αἰσθάνονται,
ἐὰν τύχωσι σφόδρα τι ἐννοοῦντες ἢ φοβούμενοι ἢ ἀκούοντες
πολὺν ψόφον.
      </p>
      <p lang="it">
       Ecco le domande e altre cose sulla sensazione,
Dopodiché, ne accetta due se si sente in se stesso
tempo individuale, oppure no, se il movimento principale non lo è
bussa; essendo portato sui talloni non si sente,
se piove forte, cosa intendi per temere o sentire
molto triste
      </p>
      <p lang="en">
       Here are the questions and other things about sensation,
After that, he accepts two if he feels in himself
individual time, or not, if the main movement is not
it knocks; by being carried on the heels they are not felt,
if it rains heavily, what do you mean by fearing or hearing
very sad
      </p>
     </div>
     <div n="2" subtype="section" type="textpart">
      <p rend="cont">
       Τοῦτο δὴ ὑποκείσθω, καὶ ὅτι ἑκάστου
μᾶλλον ἔστιν αἰσθάνεσθαι ἁπλοῦ ὄντος ἢ κεκραμένου, οἷον
οἴνου ἀκράτου ἢ κεκραμένου, καὶ μέλιτος, καὶ χρόας, καὶ τῆς
νήτης μόνης ἢ ἐν τῷ διὰ πασῶν, διὰ τὸ ἀφανίζειν ἄλληλα.
      </p>
      <p lang="it">
       Non mi sottometterò a questo, e a causa di ciascuno
piuttosto è il sentimento di un essere semplice o di uno stato, che
di vino fermo o liquoroso, e di miele, e di colore, e di
threader da solo o in mezzo a tutto, perché si distruggono a vicenda.
      </p>
      <p lang="en">
       I will not submit to this, and because of each one
rather it is the feeling of a simple being or of a state, which
of still or fortified wine, and of honey, and of color, and of
threader alone or in the middle of everything, because they destroy each other.
      </p>
     </div>
     <div n="3" subtype="section" type="textpart">
      <p rend="cont">
       Τοῦτο δὲ ποιεῖ ἐξ ὧν ἕν τι γίνεται. Εἰ δὴ ἡ μείζων τὴν
ἐλάττω κίνησιν ἐκκρούει, ἀνάγκη, ἂν ἅμα ὦσι, καὶ αὐτὴν
ἧττον αἰσθητὴν εἶναι ἢ εἰ μόνη ἦν· ἀφαιρεῖται γάρ τι ἡ
ἐλάττων μιγνυμένη, εἴπερ ἅπαντα τὰ ἁπλᾶ μᾶλλον αἰσθητά
ἐστίν. Ἐὰν ἄρα ἴσαι ὦσιν ἕτεραι οὖσαι, οὐδετέρας
ἔσται αἴσθησις· ἀφανιεῖ γὰρ ἡ ἑτέρα ὁμοίως τὴν ἑτέραν.
       <pb n="271"/>
       Ἁπλῆς δ’ οὐκ ἔστιν αἰσθάνεσθαι.
      </p>
      <p lang="it">
       Ma questa poesia è da dove viene fatto qualcosa. Vediamo il maggiore
Sento un movimento che mette fuori combattimento, un bisogno, se di questo si tratta, e quello
si sente sola o era sola viene rimossa perché il
almeno confuso, su tutte le cose semplici e piuttosto insensate
È Se sei qui, allora sei un altro, allora non lo sei
essere un senso; poiché l'altro annienta parimenti l'altro.



Haplis d'oq estin esthanasthei.
      </p>
      <p lang="en">
       But this poem is from where something is done. Let's see the major
I get a movement that knocks out, a need, if that's what it is, and that
is she feeling alone or was she alone; it is removed because the
at least mixed up, over all the simple rather insensible things
is If you are here, then you are another, then you are not
be a sense; for the other annihilates likewise the other.



Haplis d' oq estin esthanasthei.
      </p>
     </div>
     <div n="4" subtype="section" type="textpart">
      <p rend="cont">
       Ὥστε ἢ οὐδεμία
ἔσται αἴσθησις ἢ ἄλλη ἐξ ἀμφοῖν. Ὅπερ καὶ γίνεσθαι
δοκεῖ ἐκ τῶν κεραννυμένων ἐν ᾧ ἂν μιχθῶσιν.
      </p>
      <p lang="it">
       Lo sei o nessuno
sia un senso o un altro da anfoina. Opera e lo sarà
provare tra quelli cosparsi di ᾧ se si mescolano.
      </p>
      <p lang="en">
       You are or none
be it a sense or another from amphoin. Opera and it will be
try from among those who are sprinkled in ᾧ if they mix.
      </p>
     </div>
     <div n="5" subtype="section" type="textpart">
      <p rend="cont">
       Ἐπεὶ
οὖν ἐκ μὲν ἐνίων γίνεταί τι, ἐκ δ’ ἐνίων οὐ γίνεται, τοιαῦτα δὲ
τὰ ὑφ’ ἑτέραν αἴσθησιν· μίγνυνται γὰρ ὧν τὰ ἔσχατα ἕν·
οὐκ ἔστι δ’ ἐκ λευκοῦ καὶ ὀξέος ἓν γενέσθαι ἀλλ’ ἢ κατὰ
συμβεβηκός, ἀλλ’ οὐχ ὡς ἐξ ὀξέος καὶ βαρέος συμφωνία· οὐκ
ἄρα οὐδ’ αἰσθάνεσθαι ἐνδέχεται αὐτῶν ἅμα.
      </p>
      <p lang="it">
       COSÌ
quindi, cosa si può fare da cento, ma non da duecento, ma questo
I due sono sensi diversi, perché si fondono dove le estremità sono una;
Non è fatto di bianco e acido, ma secondo
vincolante, ma non come da un accordo aspro e pesante;
quindi, non si sente capace neanche di loro.
      </p>
      <p lang="en">
       So
therefore, what can be done from one hundred, but not from two hundred, but this
The two are different senses, for they blend where the ends are one;
It is not made of white and sour, but according to
binding, but not as from a sour and heavy agreement; no
therefore, he does not feel that he is capable of them either.
      </p>
     </div>
     <div n="6" subtype="section" type="textpart">
      <p rend="cont">
       Ἴσαι μὲν γὰρ
οὖσαι αἱ κινήσεις ἀφανιοῦσιν ἀλλήλας, ἐπεὶ μία οὐ γίνεται
ἐξ αὐτῶν. Ἐὰν δ’ ἄνισοι, ἡ κρείττων αἴσθησιν ἐμποιήσει,
ἐπεὶ μᾶλλον ἅμα δυεῖν αἴσθοιτ’ ἂν ἡ ψυχὴ τῇ μιᾷ
αἰσθήσει ὧν μία αἴσθησις, οἷον ὀξέος καὶ βαρέος· μᾶλλον
γὰρ ἅμα ἡ κίνησις τῆς μιᾶς ταύτης ἢ τοῖν δυοῖν, οἷον ὄψεως
καὶ ἀκοῆς.
      </p>
      <p lang="it">
       Tu sei me
Quindi i movimenti scompaiono uno dopo l'altro, su uno non è possibile
da loro. Se non sei uguale, il senso di colpa ti colpirà,
D'altra parte, se due persone sentono che la loro anima è una
sentire un senso, piuttosto aspro e pesante;
sia per il movimento di uno stesso o di due, chiunque
e udito.
      </p>
      <p lang="en">
       You are me
So the movements disappear one after the other, on one it is not possible
from them. If you are not equal, the feeling of guilt will affect you,
On the other hand, if two people feel that their soul is one
feel a sense, one that is sour and heavy; rather
for whether the movement of one self or of two, whosoever
and hearing.
      </p>
     </div>
     <div n="7" subtype="section" type="textpart">
      <p rend="cont">
       Τῇ μιᾷ δὲ ἅμα δυοῖν οὐκ ἔστιν αἰσθάνεσθαι
ἂν μὴ μιχθῇ· τὸ γὰρ μῖγμα ἓν βούλεται εἶναι, τοῦ δ’ ἑνὸς
μία αἴσθησις, ἡ δὲ μία ἅμα αὑτῇ. Ὥστ’ ἐξ ἀνάγκης τῶν
μεμιγμένων ἅμα αἰσθάνεται, ὅτι μιᾷ αἰσθήσει κατ’ ἐνέργειαν
αἰσθάνεται· ἑνὸς μὲν γὰρ ἀριθμῷ ἡ κατ’ ἐνέργειαν μία, εἴδει
δὲ ἡ κατὰ δύναμιν μία. Καὶ εἰ μία τοίνυν ἡ αἴσθησις ἡ κατ’
ἐνέργειαν, ἓν ἐκεῖνα ἐρεῖ.
      </p>
      <p lang="it">
       Non c'è sentimento tra uno e due
se non è mescolato, perché l'unica mistura che si vuole è della quarta
un senso, ma un ama a὘ῇ. Non necessario
misto se lo si sente, perché non lo si sente dall'energia
lo si sente; perché uno nel numero è uno nell'energia, vedete
ma il potere è uno. E se il senso del
energia, una c'è.
      </p>
      <p lang="en">
       There is no feeling between one and two
if it is not mixed, because the only mixture that is wanted is, of the fourth one
one sense, but one ama a὘ῇ. Out of necessity
mixed if it is felt, because it is not felt by energy
it is felt; for one in number is one in energy, see
but the power is one. And if the sense of the
energy, one there is.
      </p>
     </div>
     <div n="8" subtype="section" type="textpart">
      <p rend="cont">
       Μεμῖχθαι ἄρα ἀνάγκη αὐτά.
Ὅταν ἄρα μὴ ᾖ μεμιγμένα, δύο ἔσονται αἰσθήσεις αἱ κατ’
ἐνέργειαν. Ἀλλὰ κατὰ μίαν δύναμιν καὶ ἄτομον χρόνον
μίαν ἀνάγκη εἶναι τὴν ἐνέργειαν· μιᾶς γὰρ εἰσάπαξ μία
κίνησις καὶ χρῆσις, μία δὲ ἡ δύναμις. Οὐκ ἄρα ἐνδέχεται
       <pb n="272"/>
       δυεῖν ἅμα αἰσθάνεσθαι τῇ μιᾷ αἰσθήσει.
      </p>
      <p lang="it">
       Quindi mescola queste cose.
Quando questi non sono mescolati, ci sono due sensi
energia. Ma con una forza e un tempo individuale
Un bisogno è l'energia, perché è uno alla volta
movimento e uso, ma un solo potere. Beh, può



due si sentono.
      </p>
      <p lang="en">
       So mix these things up.
When these are not mixed, there are two senses
energy. But with one force and one individual time
One need is the energy, because it is one at a time
motion and use, but one power. Well, he can



two feel each other.
      </p>
     </div>
     <div n="9" subtype="section" type="textpart">
      <p rend="cont">
       Ἀλλὰ μὴν εἰ
τὰ ὑπὸ τὴν αὐτὴν αἴσθησιν ἅμα ἀδύνατον, ἐὰν ᾖ δύο, δῆλον
ὅτι ἧττον ἔτι τὰ κατὰ δύο αἰσθήσεις ἐνδέχεται ἅμα αἰσθάνεσθαι,
οἷον λευκὸν καὶ γλυκύ. Φαίνεται γὰρ τὸ μὲν τῷ
ἀριθμῷ ἓν ἡ ψυχὴ οὐδενὶ ἑτέρῳ λέγειν ἀλλ’ ἢ τῷ ἅμα, τὸ
δὲ τῷ εἴδει ἓν τῇ κρινούσῃ αἰσθήσει καὶ τῷ τρόπῳ.
      </p>
      <p lang="it">
       Ma non farlo
in questo senso, se è impossibile, se sono due, lo faranno
perché nell'ottavo anno è possibile per entrambi i sensi, se si sente,
uno bianco e dolce. Dopotutto, sembra la stessa cosa
numero 1, l'anima non dice nulla a un altro se non a se stessa, il
Ma quando ne vide uno, sentì la stessa cosa.
      </p>
      <p lang="en">
       But don't
under this sense, if it is impossible, if there are two, they will
because in the eighth year it is possible for both senses, if it is felt,
one white and sweet. After all, it seems the same
number 1, the soul says nothing to another but to the self, the
But when he saw one, he felt the way.
      </p>
     </div>
     <div n="10" subtype="section" type="textpart">
      <p rend="cont">
       Λέγω
δὲ τοῦτο, ὅτι ἴσως τὸ λευκὸν καὶ τὸ μέλαν, ἕτερον τῷ εἴδει
ὄν, ἡ αὐτὴ κρίνει, καὶ τὸ γλυκὺ καὶ τὸ πικρόν, ἡ αὐτὴ μὲν
ἑαυτῇ, ἐκείνης δ’ ἄλλη, ἀλλ’ ἑτέρως ἑκάτερον τῶν ἐναντίων,
ὡς δ’ αὕτως ἑαυταῖς τὰ σύστοιχα, οἷον ὡς ἡ γεῦσις τὸ γλυκύ,
οὕτως ἡ ὄψις τὸ λευκόν· ὡς δ’ αὕτη τὸ μέλαν, οὕτως ἐκείνη
τὸ πικρόν.
      </p>
      <p lang="it">
       Dire
ma questo perché forse il bianco e il nero li vedeva diversamente
essendo, lei giudica, sia dolce che amara, lei
ἑαυτῇ, ὅκείνης δ' Αλλι, Αλλ' οπερος εκατερος εκατερος,
come se fossi lo stesso che mentre assaggi il dolce,
così vede il bianco; come vede il nero, così lei
l'amaro
      </p>
      <p lang="en">
       Say
but this, because perhaps the white and the black, he saw differently
being, she judges, both the sweet and the bitter, she
ἑαυτῇ, ὅκείνης δ' Αλλι, Αλλ' οπερος εκατερος εκατερος,
as if you are the same, who as you taste the sweet,
so she sees white; as she sees black, so she
the bitter
      </p>
     </div>
     <div n="11" subtype="section" type="textpart">
      <p rend="cont">
       Ἔτι εἰ αἱ τῶν ἐναντίων κινήσεις ἐναντίαι, ἅμα
δὲ τὰ ἐναντία ἐν τῷ αὐτῷ καὶ ἀτόμῳ οὐκ ἐνδέχεται ὑπάρχειν,
ὑπὸ δὲ τὴν αἴσθησιν τὴν μίαν ἐναντία ἐστίν, οἷον γλυκὺ πικρῷ,
τούτων οὐκ ἂν ἐνδέχοιτο αἰσθάνεσθαι ἅμα.
      </p>
      <p lang="it">
       Che se i movimenti degli avversari sono contrari, ama
Ma non possono esserci contraddizioni tra il sé e la persona,
ma sotto il senso ce n'è uno opposto, che va dal dolce all'amaro,
Di questo non è possibile sentirlo.
      </p>
      <p lang="en">
       That if the opponents' movements are against, ama
But there can be no contradictions between the self and the person,
but under the sense there is one opposite, which is sweet to bitter,
Of this, it is not possible to feel it.
      </p>
     </div>
     <div n="12" subtype="section" type="textpart">
      <p rend="cont">
       Ὁμοίως
δὲ δῆλον ὅτι οὐδὲ τὰ μὴ ἐναντία· τὰ μὲν γὰρ τοῦ λευκοῦ τὰ
δὲ τοῦ μέλανός ἐστιν, καὶ ἐν τοῖς ἄλλοις ὁμοίως, οἷον τῶν
χυμῶν οἱ μὲν τοῦ γλυκέος οἱ δὲ τοῦ πικροῦ. Οὐδὲ τὰ μεμιγμένα
ἅμα· λόγοι γάρ εἰσιν ἀντικειμένων, οἷον τὸ διὰ
πασῶν καὶ τὸ διὰ πέντε, ἂν μὴ ὡς ἓν αἰσθάνηται.
      </p>
      <p lang="it">
       Allo stesso modo
ma dicono che non sono contro di me, perché appartengono all'uomo bianco
ma il nero è, e parimenti tra gli altri, uno di questi
di succhi, quelli del dolce e quelli dell'amaro. Non quelli misti
ama; ragiona perché sono oggetti, che il diὰ
anche per cinque, se non ne ha voglia.
      </p>
      <p lang="en">
       Similarly
but they say that they are not against me, because they belong to the white man
but the black man is, and likewise among the others, one of them
of juices, those of the sweet and those of the bitter. Not the mixed ones
ama; reasons because they are objects, which the diὰ
even for five, if it doesn't feel like one.
      </p>
     </div>
     <div n="13" subtype="section" type="textpart">
      <p rend="cont">
       Οὕτως
δ’ εἶς λόγος ὁ τῶν ἄκρων γίνεται, ἄλλως δ’ οὔ· ἔσται
γὰρ ἅμα ὁ μὲν πολλοῦ πρὸς ὀλίγον ἢ περιττοῦ πρὸς ἄρτιον,
ὁ δ’ ὀλίγου πρὸς πολὺ ἢ ἀρτίου πρὸς περιττόν.
      </p>
      <p lang="it">
       Giusto
Non sei tu la ragione dei fini, altrimenti non è così
infatti, se chi ha molto con poco, o il superfluo con abbondanza,
il d' di poco a molto o anche a un eccesso.
      </p>
      <p lang="en">
       That's right
You are not the reason of the ends, otherwise it is not
for if he who has much to little, or what is superfluous to plenty,
the d' of a little to a lot or an even to an excess.
      </p>
     </div>
     <div n="14" subtype="section" type="textpart">
      <p rend="cont">
       Εἰ οὖν πλεῖον ἔτι ἀπέχει ἀλλήλων καὶ διαφέρει τὰ συστοίχως
μὲν λεγόμενα ἐν ἄλλῳ δὲ γένει τῶν ἐν τῷ αὐτῷ γένει
(λέγω δ’ οἷον τὸ γλυκὺ καὶ τὸ λευκὸν καλῶ σύστοιχα,
γένει δ’ ἕτερα· τὸ γλυκὺ δὲ τοῦ μέλανος πλεῖον ἔτι τῷ
       <pb n="273"/>
       εἴδει διαφέρει ἢ τὸ λευκόν), ἔτι ἂν ἧττον ἅμα ἐνδέχοιτο
αὐτὰ αἰσθάνεσθαι ἢ τὰ τῷ γένει ταὐτά.
      </p>
      <p lang="it">
       Se è a più di un anno di distanza l'uno dall'altro e differisce di conseguenza
ma con parole in un altro, i generi di quelli dello stesso genere
(Dico D'che chiamo rispettivamente il dolce e il bianco,
ne genera altri quattro; ma la dolcezza di quello nero è maggiore dell'anno



se è diverso o il bianco), ἔti ἥἧἧτον amma edechito
questi sentimenti o cose come queste.
      </p>
      <p lang="en">
       If it is more than a year away from each other and it differs accordingly
but with words in another, the genera of those in the same genera
(I say D'whom I call the sweet and the white respectively,
it gives birth to four others; but the sweetness of the black one is greater than the year



if it is different or the white), ἔti ἥἧἧτον amma edechito
these feelings or things like these.
      </p>
     </div>
     <div n="15" subtype="section" type="textpart">
      <p rend="cont">
       Ὥστ’ εἰ μὴ
ταῦτα, οὐδ’ ἐκεῖνα. Ὃ δὲ λέγουσί τινες τῶν περὶ τὰς συμφωνίας,
ὅτι οὐχ ἅμα μὲν ἀφικνοῦνται οἱ ψόφοι, φαίνονται
δέ, καὶ λανθάνει, ὅταν ὁ χρόνος ᾖ ἀναίσθητος, πότερον
ὀρθῶς λέγεται ἢ οὔ;
      </p>
      <p lang="it">
       Ὥστ’ εἰ ὴ
questo, non quello. Ma parlami degli accordi,
perché se i fantasmi non arrivano si vedono
no, ed è latente, quando il tempo è insensibile, dopo
Come si pronuncia ἢ ὔ?
      </p>
      <p lang="en">
       Ὥστ’ εἰ ὴ
this, not that. But tell me about the agreements,
because if the ghosts don't arrive, they can be seen
no, and it is latent, when time is insensible, later
How is it pronounced ἢ ὔ?
      </p>
     </div>
     <div n="16" subtype="section" type="textpart">
      <p rend="cont">
       Τάχα γὰρ ἂν φαίη τις καὶ νῦν
παρὰ τοῦτο δοκεῖν ἅμα ὁρᾶν καὶ ἀκούειν, ὅτι οἱ μεταξὺ
χρόνοι λανθάνουσιν. Ἢ τοῦτ’ οὐκ ἀληθές, οὐδ’ ἐνδέχεται
χρόνον εἶναι ἀναίσθητον οὐδένα οὐδὲ λανθάνειν, ἀλλὰ παντὸς
ἐνδέχεται αἰσθάνεσθαι.
      </p>
      <p lang="it">
       Dopotutto, se li mangia anche adesso
nonostante ciò, dimostrino, se vedono e sentono, che gli intercessori
i tempi si protraggono. Se questo non è vero, non è possibile
il tempo è inconscio, nulla è latente, ma tutto
può essere sentito.
      </p>
      <p lang="en">
       After all, if he eats them even now
in spite of this, let them prove, if they see and hear, that the intercessors
times linger. If this is not true, it is not possible
time is unconscious, nothing is latent, but everything
can be felt.
      </p>
     </div>
     <div n="17" subtype="section" type="textpart">
      <p rend="cont">
       Εἰ γὰρ ὅτε αὐτὸς αὑτοῦ
τις αἰσθάνεται ἢ ἄλλου ἐν συνεχεῖ χρόνῳ, μὴ ἐνδέχεται τότε
λανθάνειν ὅτι ἐστίν, ἔστι δέ τις ἐν τῷ συνεχεῖ καὶ τοσοῦτος
ὅσος ὅλως ἀναίσθητός ἐστι, δῆλον ὅτι τότε λανθάνοι ἂν
εἰ ἔστιν αὐτὸς αὑτόν, καὶ εἰ ὁρᾷ, καὶ οὐκ αἰσθάνεται· καὶ
εἰ αἰσθάνεται, ἔτι οὐκ ἂν εἴη οὔτε χρόνος οὔτε πρᾶγμα
οὐδὲν ὃ αἰσθάνεται ἢ ἐν ᾧ, εἰ μὴ οὕτως, ὅτι ἐν τούτου
τινὶ ἢ ὅτι τούτου τι ὁρᾷ, εἴπερ ἔστι τι μέγεθος καὶ
χρόνου καὶ πράγματος ἀναίσθητον ὅλως διὰ μικρότητα· εἰ
γὰρ τὴν ὅλην ὁρᾷ, καὶ αἰσθάνεται τὸν αὐτὸν συνεχῶς χρόνον,
οὐ τῶν νῦν τούτων τινί.
      </p>
      <p lang="it">
       Dopotutto, è lui
li sente oppure in un tempo continuo, non ne è capace
latenti perché sono, siano nel continuum e così via
Per quanto tu sia completamente inconscio, sembra che siano latenti
se è se stesso, e se vede, e non sente e
se sembra che non sia né il tempo né la cosa
nulla che si senta o in ᾧ, se non così, perché in questo
Qual è il significato e che dimensioni ha?
del tempo e della cosa del tutto insensibile per piccolezza eh
poiché vede tutto il tempo e sente continuamente lo stesso tempo,
non di questi giorni.
      </p>
      <p lang="en">
       After all, it's him
he feels them or else in a continuous time, he is not able to then
latent because they are, be them in the continuum and so
As much as you are completely unconscious, it seems that then they are latent if
if he is himself, and if he sees, and does not feel; and
if it feels like it is neither time nor thing
nothing that is felt or in ᾧ, if not so, because in this
What is the meaning of this, and what size is it?
of time and thing insensible entirely because of smallness; eh
for he sees the whole time, and feels the same time continuously,
not of these days.
      </p>
     </div>
     <div n="18" subtype="section" type="textpart">
      <p rend="cont">
       Ἀφῃρήσθω ἡ τὸ Γ Β, ἐν
ᾗ οὐκ ᾐσθάνετο. Οὐκοῦν ἐν ταύτης τινὶ ἢ ταύτης τι,
ὥσπερ τὴν γῆν ὁρᾷ ὅλην, ὅτι τοδὶ αὐτῆς, καὶ ἐν τῷ ἐνιαυτῷ
βαδίζει, ὅτι ἐν τῷδε τῷ μέρει αὐτοῦ. Ἀλλὰ μὴν ἐν τῷ
       <pb n="274"/>
       Β Γ οὐδὲν αἰσθάνεται. Τῷ ἄρα ἐν τούτου τινὶ τοῦ Α Β
αἰσθάνεσθαι λέγεται τοῦ ὅλου αἰσθάνεσθαι καὶ τὴν ὅλην.
      </p>
      <p lang="it">
       Estratto da C B, ἐν
Non è successo. Non c'è niente nella stessa cosa o nello stesso cosa,
quanto alla terra vede tutto, anche a causa di essa e in se stesso
cammina, perché dalle sue parti. Ma non nel



B C non sente nulla. Tῷ ara a questo proposito che dire di A B
il sentimento si dice dell'intero sentimento e del tutto.
      </p>
      <p lang="en">
       Abstract from C B, ἐν
It didn't happen. There is nothing in the same thing or the same what,
as to the earth he sees all, because even of it, and in himself
he walks, because in his part. But not in the



B C doesn't feel anything. Tῷ ara in this regard what of A B
feeling is said of the whole feeling and the whole.
      </p>
     </div>
     <div n="19" subtype="section" type="textpart">
      <p rend="cont">
       Ὁ δ’ αὐτὸς λόγος καὶ ἐπὶ τῆς Α Γ· ἀεὶ γὰρ ἐν τινὶ καὶ
τινός, ὅλου δ’ οὐκ ἔστιν αἰσθάνεσθαι. Ἅπαντα μὲν οὖν
αἰσθητά ἐστιν, ἀλλ’ οὐ φαίνεται ὅσα ἐστίν· τοῦ γὰρ ἡλίου
τὸ μέγεθος ὁρᾷ καὶ τὸ τετράπηχυ πόρρωθεν, ἀλλ’ οὐ
φαίνεται ὅσον, ἀλλ’ ἐνίοτε ἀδιαίρετον, ὁρᾷ δ’ οὐκ ἀδιαίρετον.
      </p>
      <p lang="it">
       Lo stesso vale per AC, perché in che modo
di uno, di tutti non c'è sentimento. Rispondi con oὖn
È percepibile, ma non si vede così com'è, a causa del sole
la dimensione si vede anche nel quadrilatero, ma no
sembra lungo quanto, ma a volte indivisibile, non è indivisibile.
      </p>
      <p lang="en">
       The same is true of A C, because in what way
of one, of all there is no feeling. Answer with oὖn
It is perceptible, but it is not seen as it is, because of the sun
the size is also seen in the quadrilateral, but not
it seems as long as, but sometimes indivisible, it is not indivisible.
      </p>
     </div>
     <div n="20" subtype="section" type="textpart">
      <p rend="cont">
       Ἡ δ’ αἰτία εἴρηται ἐν τοῖς ἔμπροσθεν περὶ τούτου.
Ὅτι μὲν οὖν οὐθείς ἐστι χρόνος ἀναίσθητος, ἐκ τούτων
φανερόν· περὶ δὲ τῆς πρότερον λεχθείσης ἀπορίας σκεπτέον,
πότερον ἐνδέχεται ἅμα πλειόνων αἰσθάνεσθαι ἢ οὐκ ἐνδέχεται.
Τὸ δ’ ἅμα λέγω ἐν ἑνὶ καὶ ἀτόμῳ χρόνῳ πρὸς ἄλληλα.
      </p>
      <p lang="it">
       Il quarto motivo è menzionato sopra a questo proposito.
Perché se non lo sei, il tempo è insensibile, di questi
ovvio; ma pensa alla domanda di cui sopra,
Può accettare di più se sente la maggioranza oppure non può.
Dico d'ama in un momento individuale agli altri.
      </p>
      <p lang="en">
       The fourth reason is mentioned above regarding this.
Because if you are not, time is insensible, of these
obvious; but think about the aforesaid question,
He can accept more if he feels the majority or he can't.
I say d'ama in one and individual time to others.
      </p>
     </div>
     <div n="21" subtype="section" type="textpart">
      <p rend="cont">
       Πρῶτον μὲν οὖν ἆρ’ ὧδ’ ἐνδέχεται, ἅμα μέν, ἑτέρῳ δὲ τῆς
ψυχῆς αἰσθάνεσθαι, καὶ οὐ τῷ ἀτόμῳ, οὕτω δ’ ἀτόμῳ ὡς
παντὶ ὄντι συνεχεῖ; Ἢ ὅτι πρῶτον μὲν τὰ κατὰ τὴν μίαν
αἴσθησιν, οἷον λέγω ὄψιν, εἰ ἔσται ἄλλῳ αἰσθανομένη ἄλλου
καὶ ἄλλου χρώματος, πλείω τε μέρη ἕξει εἴδει ταὐτά;
      </p>
      <p lang="it">
       In primo luogo, con oὖn ἆρ' ὧδ' è consentito, ama men, ma d'altra parte
è sentito dall'anima, e non dall'individuo, come
sta ancora succedendo tutto? Perché le cose prima di tutto
senso, che io chiamo ὄpsin, εἰ ἔσται ἔλῳ Ἀσθανομένει di un altro
e di altro colore, hai visto queste parti?
      </p>
      <p lang="en">
       First, with oὖn ἆρ' ὧδ' is allowed, ama men, but on the other hand
it is felt by the soul, and not by the individual, as
is everything still going on? Because first things first
sense, whom I call ὄpsin, εἰ ἔσται ἔλῳ Ἀσθανομένει of another
and of a different color, have you seen these parts?
      </p>
     </div>
     <div n="22" subtype="section" type="textpart">
      <p rend="cont">
       Καὶ γὰρ ἃ αἰσθάνεται, ἐν τῷ αὐτῷ γένει ἐστίν. Εἰ δὲ
ὅτι ὡς δύο ὄμματα φαίη τις, οὐδὲν κωλύει, οὕτω καὶ ἐν
τῇ ψυχῇ, ὅτι ἴσως ἐκ μὲν τούτων ἕν τι γίνεται καὶ μία ἡ
ἐνέργεια αὐτῶν· ἐκεῖ δέ, εἰ μὲν ἓν τὸ ἐξ ἀμφοῖν, ἐκεῖνο
τὸ αἰσθανόμενον ἔσται, εἰ δὲ χωρίς, οὐχ ὁμοίως ἕξει.
      </p>
      <p lang="it">
       E ciò che sente, in lui lo genera. Sega
poiché come due ommata li fanno, nulla li ostacola, così anche dentro
all'anima, perché forse uno di questi lo diventerà
la loro energia; lì, se è uno di loro, quello
ciò che si sente è, ma se è senza, non è altrettanto.
      </p>
      <p lang="en">
       And what he feels, in him he begets. Saw
for as two ommata faie them, nothing hinders, so also in
to the soul, because maybe one of these will become one
their energy; there, if it is one of them, that
what is felt is, but if it is without, it is not likewise.
      </p>
     </div>
     <div n="23" subtype="section" type="textpart">
      <p rend="cont">
       Ἔτι
αἰσθήσεις αἱ αὐταὶ πλείους ἔσονται, ὥσπερ εἴ τις ἐπιστήμας
διαφόρους φαίη· οὔτε γὰρ ἡ ἐνέργεια ἄνευ τῆς καθ’ αὑτὴν
ἔσται δυνάμεως, οὔτ’ ἄνευ ταύτης ἔσται αἴσθησις. Εἰ δὲ
       <pb n="275"/>
       τούτων ἐν ἑνὶ καὶ ἀτόμῳ αἰσθάνεται, δῆλον ὅτι καὶ τῶν
ἄλλων· μᾶλλον γὰρ ἐνεδέχετο τούτων ἅμα πλειόνων ἢ
τῶν τῷ γένει ἑτέρων.
      </p>
      <p lang="it">
       Eti
sono sentimenti, come la scienza
cose diverse; poiché nessuna delle due è energia senza se stessa
È con il potere, né senza di esso è sentimento. Sega



di questi in una stessa persona si sente, è vero che anche di loro
di altri; perché forse era capace di questi ma di più o
di altri.
      </p>
      <p lang="en">
       Eti
they are feelings, like science
different things; for neither is energy without itself
It is with power, nor without it is feeling. Saw



of these in one and the same person is felt, it is true that also of them
of others; for perhaps he was capable of these but more or
of others.
      </p>
     </div>
     <div n="24" subtype="section" type="textpart">
      <p rend="cont">
       Εἰ δὲ δὴ ἄλλῳ μὲν γλυκέος ἄλλῳ δὲ
λευκοῦ αἰσθάνεται ἡ ψυχὴ μέρει, ἤτοι τὸ ἐκ τούτων ἕν τί
ἐστιν ἢ οὐχ ἕν. Ἀλλ’ ἀνάγκη ἕν· ἓν γάρ τι τὸ αἰσθητικόν
ἐστι μέρος. Τίνος οὖν ἐκεῖνο ἑνός; Οὐδὲν γὰρ ἐκ
τούτων ἕν. Ἀνάγκη ἄρα ἕν τι εἶναι τῆς ψυχῆς, ᾧ ἅπαντα
αἰσθάνεται, καθάπερ εἴρηται πρότερον, ἄλλο δὲ γένος δι’
ἄλλου.
      </p>
      <p lang="it">
       Se non è per gli altri, ma dolce per gli altri
l'anima si sente in parte bianca, cioè una di queste
è o no uno. Ma c’è bisogno di una ragione estetica
ecco il posto Di chi è l'ἐκεῖνο ἑνος? Nessuno da
di questi La necessità, dunque, è qualcosa che è dell'anima, ovunque
si fa sentire, perché è detto prima, e un altro genere da
altrove.
      </p>
      <p lang="en">
       If it is not for others, but sweet for others
the soul feels partly white, i.e. one of these
is it or not one. But there is a need for an aesthetic reason
here's the place Whose oὖν ἐκεῖνο ἑνος? No one from
of these one Necessity, then, is something that is of the soul, everywhere
is felt, because it is said before, and another genus by
elsewhere.
      </p>
     </div>
     <div n="25" subtype="section" type="textpart">
      <p rend="cont">
       Ἆρ’ οὖν ᾗ μὲν ἀδιαίρετόν ἐστι κατ’ ἐνέργειαν, ἕν
τί ἐστι τὸ αἰσθητικὸν γλυκέος καὶ λευκοῦ, ὅταν δὲ διαιρετὸν
γένηται κατ’ ἐνέργειαν, ἕτερον; Ἢ ὥσπερ ἐπὶ τῶν
πραγμάτων αὐτῶν ἐνδέχεται, οὕτω καὶ ἐπὶ τῆς ψυχῆς. Τὸ
γὰρ αὐτὸ καὶ ἓν ἀριθμῷ λευκὸν καὶ γλυκύ ἐστι, καὶ ἄλλα
πολλά, εἰ μὴ χωριστὰ τὰ πάθη ἀλλήλων, ἀλλὰ τὸ εἶναι
ἕτερον ἑκάστῳ.
      </p>
      <p lang="it">
       Ἆρ' oὖn ᾗ me indivisibile è per energia, a
qual è l'estetica del dolce e del bianco, quando è divisibile
è fatto dall'energia, altrimenti? Come se su di loro
di queste cose è capace, così come dell'anima. IL
perché anche questo è un numero bianco e dolce, e altre cose
molti, se le passioni degli altri non sono separate, ma è così
l'un l'altro.
      </p>
      <p lang="en">
       Ἆρ' oὖn ᾗ me indivisible is by energy, a
what is the aesthetic of sweet and white, when it is divisible
is it done by energy, else? As if on them
of these things he is capable of, as well as of the soul. The
for this is also a white and sweet number, and other things
many, if the passions of others are not separated, but it is
each other.
      </p>
     </div>
     <div n="26" subtype="section" type="textpart">
      <p rend="cont">
       Ὁμοίως τοίνυν θετέον καὶ ἐπὶ τῆς ψυχῆς
τὸ αὐτὸ καὶ ἓν εἶναι ἀριθμῷ τὸ αἰσθητικὸν πάντων, τῷ
μέντοι εἶναι ἕτερον καὶ ἕτερον τῶν μὲν γένει τῶν δὲ εἴδει.
Ὥστε καὶ αἰσθάνοιτ’ ἂν ἅμα τῷ αὐτῷ καὶ ἑνί, λόγῳ δ’ οὐ
τῷ αὐτῷ. Ὅτι δὲ τὸ αἰσθητὸν πᾶν ἐστὶ μέγεθος καὶ οὐκ
ἔστιν ἀδιαίρετον αἰσθητόν, δῆλον.
      </p>
      <p lang="it">
       Allo stesso modo sono benefici anche per l’anima
questo e uno è il numero estetico di ogni cosa, τῷ
le zecche sono l'una e l'altra di quelle che generano e di quelle che non vedono.
Si ritiene inoltre che, se è la stessa cosa, perché no?
a lui Ma la sensazione riguarda sempre le dimensioni e non
È un senso indivisibile, un delirio.
      </p>
      <p lang="en">
       In the same way, they are also beneficial to the soul
this and one is the aesthetic number of everything, τῷ
mints are one and the other of those who beget and those who do not see.
It is also felt that if it is the same, why not?
to him But the feeling is always about size and not
It is an indivisible sense, a delusion.
      </p>
     </div>
     <div n="27" subtype="section" type="textpart">
      <p rend="cont">
       Ἔστι γὰρ ὅθεν μὲν
οὐκ ἂν ὀφθείη, ἄπειρον τὸ ἀπόστημα, ὅθεν δὲ ὁρᾶται, πεπερασμένον.
Ὁμοίως δὲ καὶ τὸ ὀσφραντὸν καὶ ἀκουστὸν
καὶ ὅσων μὴ αὐτῶν ἁπτόμενοι αἰσθάνονται. Ἔστι δέ
τι ἔσχατον τοῦ ἀποστήματος ὅθεν οὐχ ὁρᾶται, καὶ πρῶτον
ὅθεν ὁρᾶται.
      </p>
      <p lang="it">
       Perché è del posto in cui mi trovo io
Altrimenti l'ascesso è infinito, ma da dove lo si vede è finito.
Allo stesso modo, il senso dell'olfatto e dell'udito
e di chi non si sente toccato. È giusto?
cosa sia successo all'ascesso non è visibile, e prima di tutto
dove può essere visto
      </p>
      <p lang="en">
       Because he is from where I am
If not, the abscess is infinite, but from where it is seen, it is finite.
Similarly, the sense of smell and hearing
and of those who do not feel touched. Is that right?
what happened to the abscess is not visible, and first of all
where can be seen
      </p>
     </div>
     <div n="28" subtype="section" type="textpart">
      <p rend="cont">
       Τοῦτο δὴ ἀνάγκη ἀδιαίρετον εἶναι, οὗ ἐν μὲν
τῷ ἐπέκεινα οὐκ ἐνδέχεται αἰσθάνεσθαι ὄντος, ἐν δὲ τῷ ἐπὶ
ταδὶ ἀνάγκη αἰσθάνεσθαι. Εἰ δή τί ἐστιν ἀδιαίρετον αἰσθητόν,
       <pb n="276"/>
       ὅταν τεθῇ ἐπὶ τῷ ἐσχάτῳ ὅθεν ἐστὶν ὕστατον μὲν
οὐκ αἰσθητὸν πρῶτον δ’ αἰσθητόν, ἅμα συμβήσεται ὁρατὸν
εἶναι καὶ ἀόρατον· τοῦτο δ’ ἀδύνατον.
      </p>
      <p lang="it">
       Questo bisogno è indivisibile, dove in me
in quest'ultimo nessun essere è capace di sentire, mentre in quello
allora se ne sente il bisogno. Qual è infatti il ​​senso indivisibile,



quando è alla fine, dov'è?
Non lo sente prima, non lo sente, se succede lo vede.
è anche invisibile; questo è impossibile.
      </p>
      <p lang="en">
       This need is indivisible, where in me
in the latter, no being is capable of feeling, while in the
then the need is felt. For what is the indivisible sense,



when he is at the end, where is he?
He doesn't feel it first, he doesn't feel it, if it happens he sees it.
it is also invisible; this is impossible.
      </p>
      <p>
       Περὶ μὲν οὖν τῶν αἰσθητηρίων καὶ τῶν αἰσθητῶν τίνα
τρόπον ἔχει καὶ κοινῇ καὶ καθ’ ἕκαστον αἰσθητήριον εἴρηται·
      </p>
      <p lang="it">
       Di me, dunque, dei sensi e dei sensi
ha una via comune e si distingue per ciascun senso;
      </p>
      <p lang="en">
       About me, then, of the senses and of the senses
it has a common way and it is distinguished by each sense;
      </p>
     </div>
    </div>
   </div>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
