<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng"
    type="application/xml"
    schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title xml:lang="en">Bibliotheca Historica - Complements animaliers (Livre I ch. 30-41, Livre III ch. 1-34)</title>
        <author>
          <persName>DIODORE</persName>
          
        </author>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Encodage automatique TEI P5</resp>
          <name>zoomathia_encoder.py v3.0</name>
          <date when="2026-07-12">2026-07-12</date>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Projet Zoomathia (ANR-21-CE27-0012)</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Universite Cote d'Azur, Nice, France</pubPlace>
        <date when="2026-07-12">2026-07-12</date>
        <availability>
          <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0</licence>
        </availability>
        <idno type="zoomathia"></idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Encode automatiquement par zoomathia_encoder.py v3.0 - Projet Zoomathia</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language ident="en">anglais</language>
      </langUsage>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="zoomathia">
          <term>Zoomathia</term>
          <term>animaux</term>
          <term>inconnu</term>
          <term>anglais</term>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>Fichier encode automatiquement dans le cadre du projet Zoomathia (ANR).
        Encodage produit par zoomathia_encoder.py v3.0. Verification humaine recommandee.</p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>Balisage automatique des structures textuelles et des entites nommees
        pertinentes pour Zoomathia (animaux, plantes, personnes, lieux).</p>
        <correction status="unknown">
          <p>Encodage automatique - erreurs possibles, revision manuelle recommandee.</p>
        </correction>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
<div type="book" n="1">
  <div type="chapter" n="30">
    <p>Now the <persName>Ethiopians</persName>, as historians relate, were the first of all men and the proofs of this statement, they say, are manifest. For that they did not come into their land as immigrants from abroad but were natives of it and so justly bear the name of <quote>" autochthones "</quote>⁠ <note n="1"> is, they maintain, conceded by practically all men; furthermore, that those who dwell beneath the noon-day sun were, in all likelihood, the first to be generated by the earth, is clear to all; since, inasmuch as it was the warmth of the sun which, at the generation of the universe, dried up the earth when it was still wet and impregnated it with life,⁠ <note n="2"> it is reasonable to suppose that the region which was nearest the sun was the first to bring forth living creatures.</note></note></p>
    <p>2 And they say that they were the first to be taught to honour the <name type="deity">gods</name> and to hold sacrifices and processions and festivals and the other rites by which men honour the <name type="deity">deity</name>; and that in consequence their piety has been published abroad among all men, and it is generally held that the sacrifices practised among the <persName>Ethiopians</persName> are those which are the most pleasing to heaven.</p>
    <p>3 As witness to this they call upon the <persName>poet</persName> who is perhaps the oldest and certainly the most venerated among the <foreign xml:lang="grc">Greeks</foreign>; for in the <foreign xml:lang="grc">Iliad</foreign>⁠ <note n="3"> he represents both <name type="deity">Zeus</name> and the rest of the <name type="deity">gods</name> with him as absent on a visit to <placeName>Ethiopia</placeName> to share in the sacrifices and the banquet which were given annually by the <persName>Ethiopians</persName> for all the <name type="deity">gods</name> together:</note></p>
    <p>For <name type="deity">Zeus</name> had yesterday</p>
  </div>
</div>
<div type="book" n="1">
   <div type="chapter" n="30">
      <p>to <placeName>Ocean's bounds</placeName> Set forth to feast with <name type="placeName" xml:lang="en">Ethiop's</name> faultless men, And he was followed there by all the <name type="deity">gods</name>.</p>
      <p>4 And they state that, by reason of their piety towards the <name type="deity">deity</name>, they manifestly enjoy the favour of the <name type="deity">gods</name>, inasmuch as they have never experienced the rule of an invader from abroad; for from all time they have enjoyed a state of freedom and of peace one with another, and although many and powerful rulers have made war upon them, not one of these has succeeded in his undertaking.</p>
      <p>3 1 <persName>Cambyses</persName>, for instance, they say, who made war upon them with a great force, both lost all his army and was himself exposed to the greatest peril; <persName>Semiramis</persName> also, who through the magnitude of her undertakings and achievements has become renowned, after advancing a short distance into <name type="placeName" xml:lang="en">Ethiopia</name> gave up her campaign against the whole nation; and <persName>Heracles</persName> and <persName>Dionysus</persName>, although they visited all the inhabited earth, failed to subdue the <name type="placeName" xml:lang="en">Ethiopians</name> alone who dwell above <name type="placeName" xml:lang="en">Egypt</name>, both because of the piety of these men and because of the insurmountable difficulties involved in the attempt.</p>
      <p>They say also that the <name type="placeName" xml:lang="en">Egyptians</name> are colonists sent out by the <name type="placeName" xml:lang="en">Ethiopians</name>, <persName>Osiris</persName> having been the leader of the colony. 2 For, speaking generally, what is now <name type="placeName" xml:lang="en">Egypt</name>, they maintain, was not land but sea when in the beginning the universe was being formed; afterwards, however, as the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Nile</name> during the times of its inundation carried down the mud from <name type="placeName" xml:lang="en">Ethiopia</name>, land was gradually built up from the deposit.</p>
   </div>
</div>
<div type="book" n="1">
  <div type="chapter" n="30">
    <p>Also the statement that all the land of the <placeName>Egyptians</placeName> is alluvial silt deposited by the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">river</name> receives the clearest proof, in their opinion, from what takes place at the outlets of the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Nile</name>; <pb n="95"/> for as each year new mud is continually gathered together at the mouths of the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">river</name>, the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">sea</name> is observed being thrust back by the deposited silt and the land receiving the increase.</p>
    <p>And the larger part of the customs of the <placeName>Egyptians</placeName> are, they hold, <placeName>Ethiopian</placeName>, the colonists still preserving their ancient manners.</p>
    <p>For instance, the belief that their <persName>kings</persName> are <name type="deity">gods</name>, the very special attention which they pay to their burials, and many other matters of a similar nature are <placeName>Ethiopian</placeName> practices, while the shapes of their statues and the forms of their letters are <placeName>Ethiopian</placeName>;</p>
    <p>for of the two kinds of writing⁠ <pb n="96"/> which the <placeName>Egyptians</placeName> have, that which is known as "popular" (<foreign xml:lang="en">demotic</foreign>) is learned by everyone, while that which is called "sacred"⁠ is understood only by the priests of the <placeName>Egyptians</placeName>, who learn it from their fathers as one of the things which are not divulged, but among the <placeName>Ethiopians</placeName> everyone uses these forms of letters.</p>
    <p>Furthermore, the orders of the priests, they maintain, have much the same position among both peoples; for all are clean⁠ who are engaged in the service of the <name type="deity">gods</name>, keeping themselves shaven, like the <placeName>Egyptian</placeName> priests, and having the same dress and form of staff, which is shaped like a plough and is carried by their <persName>kings</persName>, who wear high felt hats which end</p>
  </div>
</div>
<div type="book" n="1">
  <div type="chapter" n="30">
    <p>in a knob at the top and are circled by the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">serpents</name> which they call <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">asps</name>; and this symbol appears to carry the thought that it will be the lot of those who shall dare to attack the king to encounter death-carrying stings.</p>
    <p>Many other things are also told by them concerning their own antiquity and the colony which they sent out that became the <placeName>Egyptians</placeName>, but about this there is no special need of our writing anything.</p>
  </div>
  <div type="chapter" n="41">
    <p>We must now speak about the <placeName>Ethiopian</placeName> writing which is called hieroglyphic among the <placeName>Egyptians</placeName>, in order that we may omit nothing in our discussion of their antiquities. Now it is found that the forms of their letters take the shape of <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">animals</name> of every kind, and of the members of the human body, and of implements and especially carpenters' tools; for their writing does not express the intended concept by means of syllables joined one to another, but by means of the significance of the objects which have been copied and by its figurative meaning which has been impressed upon the memory by practice.</p>
    <p>For instance, they draw the picture of a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">hawk</name>, a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">crocodile</name>, a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">snake</name>, and of the members of the human body — an eye, a hand, a face, and the like. Now the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">hawk</name> signifies to them everything which happens swiftly, since this animal is practically the swiftest of winged creatures. And the concept portrayed is then transferred, by the appropriate metaphorical transfer, to all swift things and to everything to which swiftness is appropriate, very much as if th</p>
  </div>
</div>
<div type="book" n="I">
  <div type="chapter" n="30">
    <p>ey had been named. 3 And the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">crocodile</name> is a symbol of all that is evil, and the eye is the warder of justice and the guardian of the entire body. And as for the members of the body, the right hand with fingers extended signifies a procuring of livelihood, and the left with the fingers closed, a keeping and guarding of property. 4 The same way of reasoning applies also to the remaining characters, which represent parts of the body and implements and all other things; for by paying close attention to the significance which is inherent in each object and by training their minds through drill and exercise of the memory over a long period, they read from habit everything which has been written.</p>
  </div>
  <div type="chapter" n="31">
    <p>5 1 As for the customs of the <placeName>Ethiopians</placeName>, not a few of them are thought to differ greatly from those of the rest of mankind, this being especially true of those which concern the selection of their kings. The priests, for instance, first choose out the noblest men from their own number, and whichever one from this group the <name type="deity">god</name> may select, as he is borne about in a procession in accordance with a certain practice of theirs, him the multitude take for their king; and straightway it both worships and honours him like a god, believing that the sovereignty has been entrusted to him by Divine Providence. 2 And the king who has been thus chosen both follows a regimen which has been fixed in accordance with the laws and performs all his other deeds in accordance</p>
  </div>
</div>
<div type="book" n="I">
  <div type="chapter" n="30">
    <p>rding neither favour nor punishment to anyone contrary to the usage which has been approved among them from the beginning. It is also a custom of theirs that the king shall put no one of his subjects to death, not even if a man shall have been condemned to death and is considered deserving of punishment, but that he shall send to the transgressor one of his attendants bearing a token of death; and the guilty person, on seeing the warning, immediately retires to his home and removes himself from life. Moreover, for a man to flee from his own into a neighbouring country and thus by moving away from his native land to pay the penalty of his transgression, as is the custom among the Greeks, is permissible under no circumstances.</p>
    <p>Consequently, they say, when a man to whom the token of death had been sent by the king once undertook to flee from Ethiopia, and his mother, on learning of this, bound his neck about with her girdle, he dared not so much as raise his <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">hands</name> against her in any way but submitted to be strangled until he died, that he might not leave a greater disgrace to his kinsmen.</p>
    <p>Of all their customs the most astonishing is that which obtains in connection with the death of their kings.</p>
    <p>For the priests at <placeName>Meroë</placeName> who spend their time in the worship of the gods and the rites which do them honour, being the greatest and most powerful order, whenever the idea comes to them, dispatch a messenger to the king with orders that he die.</p>
    <p>For the gods, they add,</p>
  </div>
</div>
<div type="book" n="1">
   <div type="chapter" n="30">
      <p>have revealed this to them, and it must be that the command of the <name type="deity">immortals</name> should in no wise be disregarded by one of mortal frame. And this order they accompany with other arguments, such as are accepted by a simple-minded nature, which has been bred in a custom that is both ancient and difficult to eradicate and which knows no argument that can be set in opposition to commands enforced by no compulsion.</p>
      <p>3 Now in former times the kings would obey the priests, having been overcome, not by arms nor by force, but because their reasoning powers had been put under a constraint by their very superstition; but during the reign of the second <persName>Ptolemy</persName> the king of the <placeName>Ethiopians</placeName>, <persName>Ergamenes</persName>, who had had a Greek education and had studied philosophy, was the first to have the courage to disdain the command.</p>
      <p>4 For assuming a spirit which became the position of a king he entered with his soldiers into the unapproachable place where stood, as it turned out, the golden shrine of the <placeName>Ethiopians</placeName>, put the priests to the sword, and after p103 abolishing this custom thereafter ordered affairs after his own will.</p>
   </div>
   <div type="chapter" n="31">
      <p>7 1 As for the custom touching the friends of the king, strange as it is, it persists, they said, <foreign xml:lang="grc">ἔφασαν</foreign> down to our own time. For the <placeName>Ethiopians</placeName> have the custom, they say, that if their king has been maimed in some part of his body through any cause whatever, all his companions suffer the same loss of their own choice; because they consider that it wou</p>
   </div>
</div>
<div type="book" n="I">
  <div type="chapter" n="30">
    <p>It would be a disgraceful thing if, when the king had been maimed in his leg, his friends should be sound of limb, and if in their goings forth from the palace they should not all follow the king limping as he did;</p>
    <p>for it would be strange that steadfast friendship should share sorrow and grief and bear equally all other things both good and evil, but should have no part in the suffering of the body.</p>
    <p>They say also that it is customary for the comrades of the kings even to die with them of their own accord and that such a death is an honourable one and a proof of true friendship.</p>
    <p>And it is for this reason, they add, that a conspiracy against the king is not easily raised among the Ethiopians, all his friends being equally concerned both for his safety and their own.</p>
    <p>These, then, are the customs which prevail among the Ethiopians who dwell in their capital⁠<pb n="105"/> and those who inhabit both the island of <placeName>Meroë</placeName> and the land adjoining <placeName>Egypt</placeName>.</p>
  </div>
</div>
<div type="book" n="III">
  <div type="chapter" n="1">
    <p>But there are also a great many other tribes of the Ethiopians, some of them dwelling in the land lying on both banks of the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Nile</name> and on the islands in the river, others inhabiting the neighbouring country of <placeName>Arabia</placeName>,</p>
    <p>and still others residing in the interior of <placeName>Libya</placeName>.</p>
    <p>The majority of them, and especially those who dwell along the river, are black in colour and have flat noses and woolly hair.</p>
    <p>As for their spirit they are entirely savage and display the nature of a wild beast, not so much, however, in their temper as in their ways of l</p>
  </div>
</div>
<div type="book" n="I">
  <div type="chapter" n="30">
    <p>iving; for they are squalid all over their bodies, they keep their nails very long like the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">wild beasts</name>, and are as far removed as possible from human kindness to one another;</p>
    <p>3 and speaking as they do with a shrill voice and cultivating none of the practices of civilized life as these are found among the rest of mankind, they present a striking contrast when considered in the light of our own customs.</p>
    <p>4 As for their arms, some of them use shields of raw <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">ox-hide</name> and short spears, others javelins without a slinging-thong and sometimes bows of wood, four cubits in length, with which they shoot by putting their foot against them, and after their arrows are exhausted they finish the fight with wooden clubs. They also arm their women, setting an age limit for their service, and most of these observe the custom of wearing a bronze ring in the lip.</p>
    <p>5 As for clothing, certain of them wear none whatsoever, going naked all their life long and making for themselves of whatever comes to hand a rude protection from the heat alone; others, cutting off the tails and the ends of the hides of their <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">sheep</name>, cover their loins with them, putting the tail before them to screen, after a p107 manner, the shameful part;⁠ 13 and some make use of the skins of their domestic <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">animals</name>, while there are those who cover their bodies as far as the waist with shirts, which they weave of hair, since their <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">sheep</name> do not produce wool by reason of the peculiar nature of the land.</p>
    <p>6 For food some gather the fruits w</p>
  </div>
</div>
<div type="book" n="I">
  <div type="chapter" n="30">
    <p>hich are generated in their waters and which grow wild in both the lakes and marshy places, certain of them pluck off the foliage of a very tender kind of <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">tree</name>, with which they also cover their bodies in the midday and cool them in this way, some sow <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">sesame</name> and <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">lotus</name>,<note n="14"> </note> and there are those who are nourished by the most tender roots of the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">reeds</name>. Not a few of them are also well trained in the use of the bow and bring down with good aim many <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">birds</name>, with which they satisfy their physical needs; but the greater number live for their entire life on the meat and milk and cheese of their herds.<note n="9"> </note></p>
  </div>
</div>
<div type="book" n="III">
  <div type="chapter" n="1">
    <p>With regard to the <name type="deity">gods</name>, the <persName>Ethiopians</persName> who dwell above <placeName>Meroë</placeName> entertain two opinions: they believe that some of them, such as the <name type="deity">sun</name> and the <name type="deity">moon</name> and the universe as a whole, have a nature which is eternal and imperishable, but others of them, they think, share a mortal nature and have come to receive immortal honours because of their virtue and the benefactions which they have bestowed upon all mankind;</p>
    <p>2 for instance, they revere <name type="deity">Isis</name> and <name type="deity">Pan</name>, and also <name type="deity">Heracles</name> and <name type="deity">Zeus</name>, considering that <foreign xml:lang="la">p109</foreign> these deities in particular have been benefactors of the race of men. But a few of the <persName>Ethiopians</persName> do not believe in the existence of any <name type="deity">gods</name> at all;<note n="15"> </note> consequently at the rising of the <name type="deity">sun</name> they utter imprecations against it as being most hostile to them, and flee to the marshes of those parts.</p>
    <p>3 Different also from those of other peoples are the customs they observe with respect to their dead</p>
  </div>
</div>
<div type="book" n="I">
  <div type="chapter" n="30">
    <p>for some dispose of them by casting them into the river, thinking this to be the best burial; others, after pouring glass about the bodies, keep them in their houses, since they feel that the countenances of the dead should not be unknown to their kinsmen and that those who are united by ties of blood should not forget their near relations; and some put them in coffins made of baked clay and bury them in the ground in a ring about their temples, and they consider that the oath taken by them is the strongest possible.</p>
    <p>4 The kingship some of them bestow upon the most comely, believing both supreme power and comeliness to be gifts of fortune, while others entrust the rule to the most careful keepers of <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">cattle</name>, as being the only men who would give the best thought to their subjects; some assign this honour to the wealthiest, since they feel that these alone can come to the aid of the masses because they have the means ready at hand; and there are those who choose for their kings men of unusual valour, judging that the most efficient in war are alone worthy to receive the meed of honour.</p>
  </div>
  <div type="chapter" n="31">
    <p>1 In that part of the country which lies along the <placeName>Nile</placeName> in <placeName>Libya</placeName> there is a section which is remarkable for its beauty; for it bears food in great abundance and of every variety and provides convenient places of retreat in its marshes where one finds protection against the excessive heat; consequently this region is a bone of contention between the <persName>Libyans</persName> and the <persName>Ethiopians</persName>, who</p>
  </div>
</div>
<div type="book" n="I">
  <div type="chapter" n="30">
    <p>wage unceasing warfare with each other for its possession. 2 It is also a gathering-place for a multitude of <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">elephants</name> from the country lying above it because, as some say, the pasturage is abundant and sweet; for marvellous marshes stretch along the banks of the river and in them grows food in great plenty and of every kind.</p>
    <p>3 Consequently, whenever they taste of the rush and the reed, they remain there because of the sweetness of the food and destroy the means of subsistence of the human beings; and because of this the inhabitants are compelled to flee from these regions, and to live as nomads and dwellers in tents — in a word, to fix the bounds of their country by their advantage.</p>
    <p>4 The herds of the wild beasts which we have mentioned leave the interior of the country because of the lack of food, since every growing thing in the ground quickly dries up; for as a result of the excessive heat and the lack of water from springs and rivers it comes to pass that the plants for food are rough and scanty.</p>
    <p>5 There are also, as some say, in the country of the wild beasts, as it is called, <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">serpents</name> which are marvellous for their size and multitude; these attack the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">elephants</name> at the water-holes, pit their strength against them, and winding themselves in coils about their legs continue squeezing them tighter and tighter in their bands until at last the beasts, covered with foam, fall to the ground from their weight. Thereupon the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">serpents</name> gather and devour the flesh of the falle</p>
  </div>
</div>
<div type="book" n="1">
  <div type="chapter" n="30">
    <p>n <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">elephant</name>, overcoming the beast with ease because it moves only with difficulty. 6 But since it still remains a puzzle why, in pursuit of their accustomed food, they do not follow the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">elephants</name> into the region along the river, which I have mentioned, they say that the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">serpents</name> of such great size avoid the level part of the country and continually make their homes at the foot of mountains in ravines which are suitable to their length and in deep caves; consequently they never leave the regions which are suitable to them and to which they are accustomed, Nature herself being the instructor of all the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">animals</name> in such matters. As for the <persName>Ethiopians</persName>, then, and their land, this is as much as we have to say.</p>
  </div>
  <div type="chapter" n="31">
    <p>1 Concerning the historians, we must distinguish among them, to the effect that many have composed works on both <placeName>Egypt</placeName> and <placeName>Ethiopia</placeName>, of whom some have given credence to false report and others have invented many tales out of their own minds for the delectation of their readers, and so may justly be distrusted.</p>
    <p>2 For example, <persName>Agatharchides</persName> of <placeName>Cnidus</placeName>⁠ 18 in the second Book of his work on <foreign xml:lang="la">Asia</foreign>, and the compiler of geographies, <persName>Artemidorus</persName> of <placeName>Ephesus</placeName>⁠ 19 in his eighth Book, and certain others whose homes were in <placeName>Egypt</placeName>, have recounted most of what I have set forth above and are, on the contrary, accurate in all they have written.</p>
    <p>3 Since, to bear witness ourselves, during the time of our visit to <placeName>Egypt</placeName>, we associated with many of its priests and conversed with not a few amb</p>
  </div>
</div>
<div type="book" n="1">
  <div type="chapter" n="30">
    <p>assadors from <placeName>Ethiopia</placeName> as well who were then in <placeName>Egypt</placeName>; and after inquiring carefully of them about each matter and testing the stories of the historians, we have composed our account so as to accord with the opinions on which they most fully agree.</p>
    <p>4 Now as for the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Ethiopians</name> who dwell in the west, we shall be satisfied with what has been said, and we shall discuss in turn the peoples who live to the South and about the <placeName>Red Sea</placeName>.</p>
    <p>20 However, we feel that it is appropriate first to tell of the working of the <name type="metal" xml:lang="en">gold</name> as it is carried on in these regions.</p>
  </div>
  <div type="chapter" n="31">
    <p>1 At the extremity of <placeName>Egypt</placeName> and in the contiguous territory of both <placeName>Arabia</placeName> and <placeName>Ethiopia</placeName> there lies a region which contains many large <name type="metal" xml:lang="en">gold</name> mines, where the <name type="metal" xml:lang="en">gold</name> is secured in great quantities with much suffering and at great expense.</p>
    <p>21 For the earth is naturally black and contains seams and veins of a <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">marble</name> which is unusually white and in brilliancy surpasses everything else which shines brightly by its nature, and here the overseers of the labour in the mines work recover the <name type="metal" xml:lang="en">gold</name> with the aid of a multitude of workers.</p>
    <p>2 For the kings of <placeName>Egypt</placeName> gather together and condemn to the mining of the <name type="metal" xml:lang="en">gold</name> such as have been found guilty of some crime and captives of war, as well as those who have been accused unjustly and thrown into prison because of their anger, and not only such persons but occasionally all their relatives as well, by this means not only p117 inflicting punishment upon those found guilty but also securing at</p>
  </div>
</div>
<div type="book" n="I">
  <div type="chapter" n="30">
    <p>the same time great revenues from their labours. 3 And those who have been condemned in this way — and they are a great multitude and are all bound in chains — work at their task unceasingly both by day and throughout the entire night, enjoying no respite and being carefully cut off from any means of escape; since guards of foreign soldiers who speak a language different from theirs stand watch over them, so that not a man, either by conversation or by some contact of a friendly nature, is able to corrupt one of his keepers.</p>
    <p>4 The <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">gold-bearing earth</name>⁠ <pb n="119"/> which is hardest they first burn with a hot fire, and when they have crumbled it in this way they continue the working of it by hand; and the soft rock which can yield to moderate effort is crushed with a sledge by myriads of unfortunate wretches.</p>
    <p>5 And the entire operations are in charge of a skilled worker who distinguishes the stone⁠ <note n="24">The Greek text reads λίθος ("stone").</note> and points it out to the labourers; and of those who are assigned to this unfortunate task the physically strongest break the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">quartz-rock</name>⁠ <note n="25">The Greek text reads σίδηρος ("iron").</note> with iron hammers, applying no skill to the task, but only force, and cutting tunnels through the stone, not in a straight line but wherever the seam of gleaming rock may lead.</p>
    <p>6 Now these men, working in darkness as they do because of the bending and winding of the passages, carry lamps bound on their foreheads; and since much of the time they change the position of their bodies to follow the particular character⁠ <note n="26">The Greek text reads ἰδιότητα ("characteristic").</note> of the stone they throw the</p>
  </div>
</div>
<div type="book" n="I">
  <div type="chapter" n="30">
    <p>locks, as they cut them out, on the ground; and at this task they labour without ceasing beneath the sternness and blows of an overseer. 13 1 <persName>The boys</persName> there who have not yet come to maturity, entering through the tunnels into the galleries formed by the removal of the rock, laboriously gather up the rock as it is cast down piece by piece and carry it out into the open to the place outside the entrance. Then those who are above⁠ 27 <persName>thirty years of age</persName> take this quarried stone from them and with iron pestles pound a specified amount of it in stone mortars, until they have worked it down to the size of a <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">vetch</name>.</p>
    <p>2 Thereupon the women and older men receive from them the rock of this size and cast it into mills of which a number stand there in a row, and taking their places in groups of two or three at the spoke or handle of each mill they grind it until they have worked down the amount given them to the consistency of the finest flour. And since no opportunity is afforded any of them to care for his body and they have no garment to cover their shame, no man can look upon unfortunate wretches without feeling pity for them because of the exceeding hardships they suffer.</p>
    <p>3 For no leniency or respite of any kind is given to any man who is sick, or maimed, or aged, or in the case of a woman for her weakness,⁠ 28 but all without exception are compelled by blows to persevere in their labours, until through ill-treatment they die in the midst of their tortures. Consequently the poor unfor</p>
  </div>
</div>
<div type="chapter" n="14">
   <p>tunates believe, <pb n="121"/> because their punishment is so excessively severe, that the future will always be more terrible than the present and therefore look forward to death as more to be desired than life.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="1">
   <p>In the last steps the skilled workmen receive the stone which has been ground to powder and take it off for its complete and final working; for they rub the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">marble</name>⁠</p>
   <p>29 which has been worked down upon a broad board which is slightly inclined, pouring water over it all the while; whereupon the earthy matter in it, melted away by the action of the water, runs down the inclined board, while that which contains the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">gold</name> remains on the wood because of its weight.</p>
   <p>2 And repeating this a number of times, they first of all rub it gently with their hands, and then lightly pressing it with sponges of loose texture they remove in this way whatever is porous and earthy, until there remains only the pure <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">gold</name>-dust.</p>
   <p>3 Then at last other skilled workmen take what has been recovered and put it by fixed measure and weight into earthen jars, mixing with it a lump of <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">lead</name> proportionate to the mass, lumps of <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">salt</name> and a little <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">tin</name>, and adding thereto <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">barley</name> bran; thereupon they put on it a close-fitting lid, and smearing it over carefully with mud they bake it in a kiln for five successive days and as many nights;</p>
   <p>4 and at the end of this period, when they have let the jars cool off, of the other matter they find no remains in the jars, but the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">gold</name> they recover in pure form, there being but</p>
</div>
<div type="book" n="1">
  <div type="chapter" n="30">
    <p>little waste. This working of the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">gold</name>, as it is carried on at the farthermost borders of <placeName>Egypt</placeName>, is effected through all the extensive labours here described; <pb n="123"/> 5 for Nature herself, in my opinion, makes it clear that whereas the production of <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">gold</name> is laborious, the guarding of it is difficult, the zest for it is very great, and that its use is half-way between pleasure and pain.</p>
    <p>Now the discovery of these mines is very ancient, having been made by the early <persName>kings</persName>. 6 But we shall undertake to discuss the peoples which inhabit the coast of the <placeName>Arabian Gulf</placeName>⁠ <note type="editorial">1 i.e. "sprung from the soil itself."</note> and that of the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Trogodytes</name> and the part of <placeName>Ethiopia</placeName> that faces the noon-day sun and the south wind.</p>
  </div>
</div>
<div type="chapter" n="30">
   <p>13 The obscure description of this custom may be clarified by a statement of <persName>Strabo</persName> (17.2.3) who apparently is greatly condensing the same source which <persName>Diodorus</persName> has used in the passage. <persName>Strabo</persName> writes to <placeName>Ethiopians</placeName>: "<quote>... and some go naked, or wear around their loins small <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">sheep</name>-skins or girdles of well-woven hair</quote>" (tr. of <persName>Jones</persName> in the L. C. L. ). When this statement is combined with that of <persName>Diodorus</persName>, it would appear that when the tail of the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">sheep</name> was cut off a portion of the hide was left attached to it and that this hide was put about the loins in such a way that the tail hung down in front.</p>
   <p>14 Cp. Book 1.34.6 .</p>
   <p>15 <persName>Strabo</persName> ( 17.2.3 , tr. by <persName>Jones</persName> in the L. C. L. ) says that these <placeName>Ethiopians</placeName> lived near the torrid zone.</p>
   <p>16 Cp. Book 2.15 for a fuller account of this custom.</p>
   <p>17 i.e. on the west bank.</p>
   <p>18 An historian and geographer of the second century B.C.</p>
   <p>19 His work in eleven books on the lands and people about the <placeName>Mediterranean Sea</placeName> was composed around 100 B.C.</p>
   <p>20 The <placeName>Persian Gulf</placeName>.</p>
   <p>21 Cp. the account of the mines in <placeName>Spain</placeName> (Book 5.35 ff.) .</p>
   <p>22 i.e. a quartz-rock; cp. below, § 5 .</p>
   <p>23 Here and below "earth" must be the equivalent of the "marble" mentioned before.</p>
   <p>24 i.e. picks out that which is gold-bearing.</p>
   <p>25 Literally, "the rock which contains the marble."</p>
   <p>26 i.e. as the gold-bearing stratum turns in one direction and another.</p>
</div>
<p>Agatharchides <quote>26 (ed. Müller)</quote>, whom Diodorus is following here, says <quote>º these workers were "under" thirty.</quote></p>
<p>Or <quote>"illness."</quote></p>
<div type="book" n="1">
   <div type="chapter" n="30">
      <p>Whenever they have collected a multitude of all kinds of <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">fish</name> they carry off their catch and bake the whole of it upon the rocks which are inclined towards the south. And since these stones are red-hot because of the very great heat, they leave the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">fish</name> there for only a short time and then turn them over, and then, picking them up bodily by the tail, they shake them.</p>
      <p>And the meat, which has become tender by reason of the warmth, falls away, but backbones are cast into a single spot and form a great heap, being collected for a certain use of which we shall speak a little later. Then placing the meat upon a smooth stone they carefully tread upon it for a sufficient length of time and mix with it the fruit of the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">Christ's thorn</name>;</p>
      <p>for when this has been thoroughly worked into the meat the whole of it becomes a glutinous mass, and it would appear that this takes the place among them of a relish. Finally, when this has been well trodden, they mould it into little oblong bricks and place them in the sun; and after these have become thoroughly dry they sit down and feast upon them, eating not according to any measure or weight but according to every man's own wish, inasmuch as they make their physical desire the bounds of their indulgence.</p>
      <p>For they have at all times stores which are unfailing and ready for use, as though <name type="deity">Poseidon</name> had assumed the task of <name type="deity">Demeter</name>.</p>
   </div>
</div>
<div type="book" n="3">
   <div type="chapter" n="1">
      <p>But at times a tidal wave of such size rolls in from the sea upon the land, a violent</p>
   </div>
</div>
<div type="book" n="I">
  <div type="chapter" n="30">
    <p>wave that for many days submerges the rocky shores, that no one can approach those regions.</p>
    <p>Consequently, being short of food at such times, they at first gather the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">mussels</name>, which are of so great a size that some of them are found that weigh four minas; that is, they break their shells by throwing huge stones at them and then eat the meat raw, its taste resembling somewhat that of <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">oysters</name>.</p>
    <p>And whenever it comes to pass that the ocean is high for a considerable period because of the continued winds, and the impossibility of coping with that state of affairs prevents them from making their usual catch of fish, they turn, as has been said, to the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">mussels</name>. But if the food from the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">mussels</name> fails them, they have recourse to the heap of backbones; that is, they select from this heap such backbones as are succulent and fresh and take them apart joint by joint, and then they grind some at once with their teeth, though the hard ones they first crush with rocks and thus prepare them before they eat them, their level of life being much the same as that of the wild beasts which make their homes in dens.</p>
  </div>
  <div type="chapter" n="31">
    <p>Now as for dry food they get an abundance of it in the manner described, but their use of wet food is astonishing and quite incredible. For they devote themselves assiduously for four days to the sea-food they have caught, the whole tribe feasting upon it merrily while entertaining one another with inarticulate songs; and furthermore, they lie at this time with any women</p>
  </div>
</div>
<div type="book" n="I">
  <div type="chapter" n="30">
    <p>they happen to meet in order to beget children, being relieved of every concern <pb n="131"/> because their food is easily secured and ready at hand.</p>
    <p>2 But on the fifth day the whole tribe hurries off in search of drink to the foothills of the mountains, where there are springs of sweet water at which the pastoral folk water their flocks and herds.</p>
    <p>3 And their journey thither is like that of herds of <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">cattle</name>, all of them uttering a cry which produces, not articulate speech, but merely a confused roaring. As for their children, the women carry the babies continually in their arms, but the fathers do this after they have been separated from their milk, while those above five years of age lead the way accompanied by their parents, playing as they go and full of joy, as though they were setting out for pleasure of the sweetest kind.</p>
    <p>4 For the nature of this people, being as yet unperverted, considers the satisfying of their need to be the greatest possible good, desiring in addition none of the imported pleasures. And so soon as they arrive at the watering-places of the pastoral folk and have their bellies filled with the water, they return, scarcely able to move because of the weight of it.</p>
    <p>5 On that day they taste no food, but everyone lies gorged and scarcely able to breathe, quite like a drunken man. The next day, however, they turn again to the eating of the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">fish</name>; and their way of living follows a cycle after this fashion throughout their lives. Now the inhabitants of the coast insid</p>
  </div>
</div>
<div type="book" n="1">
   <div type="chapter" n="30">
      <p>e the Straits lead the kind of life which has been described, and by reason of the simplicity of their food they rarely are subject to attacks of disease, although they are far shorter-lived than the inhabitants of our part of the world.</p>
      <p>18 1 But as for the inhabitants of the coast outside <placeName>the gulf</placeName>, we find that their life is far more astonishing than that of the people just described, it being as though their nature never suffers from thirst and is insensible to pain. For although they have been banished by fortune from the inhabited regions into the desert, they fare quite well from their catch of the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">fish</name>, but wet food they do not require.</p>
      <p>2 For since they eat the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">fish</name> while it is yet juicy and not far removed from the raw state, they are so far from requiring wet food that they have not even a notion of drinking. And they are content with that food which was originally allotted to them by fortune, considering that the mere elimination of that pain which arises from want (of food) is happiness.</p>
      <p>9 3 But the most surprising thing of all is, that in lack of sensibility they surpass all men, and to such a degree that what is recounted of them is scarcely credible. And yet many merchants of <placeName>Egypt</placeName>, who sail, as is their practice, through the <placeName>Red Sea</placeName> down to this day and have often sailed as far as the land of the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Ichthyophagi</name>, agree in their accounts with what we have said about the human beings who are insensible to pain.</p>
      <p>4 The third <persName>Ptolemy</persName></p>
   </div>
</div>
<div type="book" n="I">
  <div type="chapter" n="30">
    <p>fond of hunting the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">elephants</name> which are found in that region, sent one of his friends named <persName>Simmias</persName> to spy out the land; and he, setting out with suitable supplies, made, as the historian <persName>Agatharchides</persName> of <placeName>Cnidus</placeName> asserts, a thorough investigation of the nations lying along the coast. Now he⁠
    <note n="11">11</note> says that the nation of the "insensible" <placeName>Ethiopians</placeName>
    <note n="12">12</note> p135 makes no use whatsoever of drink and that their nature does not require it for the reasons given above.
    <note n="5">5</note> And as a general thing, he relates, they have no intercourse with other nations nor does the foreign appearance of people who approach their shores have any effect upon the natives, but looking at them intently they show no emotion and their expressions remain unaltered, as if there were no one present. Indeed when a man drew his sword and brandished it at them they did not turn to flight, nor, if they were subjected to insult or even to blows, would they show irritation, and the majority were not moved to anger in sympathy with the victims of such treatment; on the contrary, when at times children or women were butchered before their eyes they remained "insensible" in their attitudes, displaying no sign of anger or, on the other hand, of pity.
    <note n="6">6</note> In short, they remained unmoved in the face of the most appalling horrors, looking steadfastly at what was taking place and nodding their heads at each incident. Consequently, they say, they speak no language, but by movements of the hands which describe each object they point out
  </p>
</div>
</div>
<div type="book" n="I">
  <div type="chapter" n="30">
    <p>everything they need. 7 And the most marvellous fact of all is that <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">seals</name> live with these tribes and catch the fish for themselves in a manner similar to that employed by the human beings. Likewise with respect to their lairs and the safety of their offspring these two kinds of beings place the greatest faith in one another; for the association with animals of a different species continues without any wrongdoing and with peace and complete observance of propriety. Now this manner of life, strange as it is, has been observed by these tribes from very early times, whether it has been fashioned by habit over the long space of time or by a need imposed by necessity because of stress of circumstances.</p>
    <p>19 1 As for their dwelling-places, those used by these tribes are not all similar, but they inhabit homes modified to suit the peculiar nature of their surroundings. For instance, certain of them make their home in caves which open preferably towards the north and in which they cool themselves, thanks to the deep shade and also to the breezes which blow about them; since those which face the south, having as they do a temperature like that of an oven, cannot be approached by human beings because of the excessive heat. 2 But others who can find no caves fa­cing the north collect the ribs of the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">whales</name> which are cast up by the sea; and then, since there is a great abundance of these ribs, they interweave them</p>
  </div>
</div>
<div type="book" n="1">
   <div type="chapter" n="30">
      <p>and then weave fresh <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">seaweed</name> through them.⁠ <pb n="14"/></p>
      <p>Accordingly, when this vaulted structure is covered over, in it they gain relief from the heat when it is most intense, the necessity imposed by Nature suggesting to them a skill in which they were self-taught.</p>
      <p>3 A third method by which the <persName>Ichthyophagi</persName> find a dwelling for themselves is as follows. <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">Olive trees</name>⁠ <pb n="139"/> grow about these regions in very great numbers and their roots are washed by the sea, but they bear thick foliage and a fruit which resembles the sweet <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">chestnut</name>.</p>
      <p>4 These trees they interlace, forming in this way a continuous shade, and live in tents of this peculiar kind; for passing their days as they do on land and in the water at the same time, they lead a pleasurable life, since they avoid the sun by means of the shade cast by the branches and offset the natural heat of the regions with the continual washing of the waves against them, giving their bodies comfort and ease by the pleasant breezes which blow about them.</p>
      <p>We must speak also about the fourth kind of habitation.</p>
      <p>5 From time immemorial there has been heaped up a quantity of <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">seaweed</name> of tremendous proportions, resembling a mountain, and this has been so compacted by the unceasing pounding of the waves that it has become hard and intermingled with sand. Accordingly, the natives dig in these heaps tunnels the height of a man, leaving the upper portion for a roof, and in the lower part they construct passage-ways connected with each other by borings.⁠ <pb n="16"/></p>
   </div>
</div>
<div type="book" n="1">
  <div type="chapter" n="30">
    <p>s they cool themselves in these tunnels they free themselves from all troubles, and leaping forth from them at the times when the waves pour over the shore they busy themselves with the catching of the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">fish</name>; then, when the ebb-tide sets in, they flee back together into these same passage-ways to feast upon their catch. 6 Their dead, moreover, they "bury" by leaving the bodies just as they are cast out⁠ <pb n="141"/> at the ebb of the tide, and then when the flood-tide sets in they cast the bodies into the sea. Consequently, by making their own interment a nutriment of the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">fish</name>, they have a life which follows in singular fashion a continuous cycle throughout all eternity. 20</p>
  </div>
  <div type="chapter" n="31">
    <p>1 One tribe of the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Ichthyophagi</name> has dwellings so peculiar that they constitute a great puzzle to men who take a pride in investigating such matters; for certain of them make their home among precipitous crags which these men could not possibly have approached at the outset, since from above there overhangs a lofty rock, sheer at every point, while on the sides unapproachable cliffs shut off entrance, and on the remaining face the <placeName>sea</placeName> hems them in, which cannot be passed through on foot, and they do not use rafts at all, while of boats such as we have they have no notion.</p>
    <p>2 Such being the puzzle concerning them, the only solution left to us is that they are autochthonous, and that they experienced no beginning of the race they originally sprang from, but existed always from the beginning of time, as certain natur</p>
  </div>
</div>
<div type="book" n="1">
  <div type="chapter" n="30">
    <p>al philosophers have declared to be true of all the phenomena of nature.⁠ 18</p>
    <p>3 But since the knowledge of such matters is unattainable by us, nothing prevents those who have the most to say about them from knowing the least, inasmuch as, while plausibility may persuade the hearing, it by no means discovers the truth.</p>
    <p>21 1 We must speak also about the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Chelonophagi</name>,⁠ 19 as they are called, and the nature of their entire manner of life.</p>
    <p>There are islands in the ocean, which lie near the land, many in number, but small in size and low-lying, and bearing no food either cultivated or wild. Because these islands are so near to one another no waves occur among them, p143 since the surf breaks upon the outermost islands, and so a great multitude of <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">sea-turtles</name> tarry in these regions, resorting thither from all directions to gain the protection afforded by the calm.</p>
    <p>2 These animals spend the nights in deep water busied with their search for food, but during the days they resort to the sea which lies between the islands and sleep on the surface with their upper shells towards the sun, giving to the eye an appearance like that of overturned boats; for they are of extraordinary magnitude and not smaller than the smallest fishing skiffs.</p>
    <p>3 And the barbarians who inhabit the islands seize the occasion and swim quietly out to the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">turtles</name>; and when they have come near the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">turtle</name> on both sides, those on the one side push down upon it while those on the other side lift it up, until the animal i</p>
  </div>
</div>
<div type="book" n="I">
  <div type="chapter" n="30">
    <p>s turned over on its back. 4 Then the men, taking hold on both sides, steer the entire bulk of the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">creature</name>, to prevent it from turning over and making its escape into the deep water by swimming with the means with which Nature has endowed it, and one man with a long rope, fastening it to its tail, swims towards the land, and drawing the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">turtle</name> along after him he hauls it to the land, those who had first attacked it assisting him in bringing it in. 5 And when they have got the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">turtles</name> upon the shore of their island, all the inside meat they bake slightly for a short time in the sun and then feast upon it, but the upper shells, which are shaped like a boat, they use both for sailing over to the mainland, as they do in order to get water, and for their dwellings, by setting them right side up on elevations, so that it would appear that Nature, by a single act of favour, had bestowed upon these peoples the satisfaction of many needs; for the same gift constitutes for them food, vessel, house and ship. 6 Not far distant from these people the coast is inhabited by barbarians who lead an irregular life. For they depend for their food upon the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">whales</name> which are cast up by the land, at times enjoying an abundance of food because of the great size of the beasts which they discover, but at times, when interruptions of the supply occur, they suffer greatly from the shortage; and when the latter is the case they are forced by the scarcity of food to gnaw the cartilages of old bones a</p>
  </div>
</div>
<div type="book" n="I">
  <div type="chapter" n="30">
    <p>nd the parts which grow from the ends of the ribs. As for the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Ichthyophagi</name>, then this is the number of their tribes and such, speaking summarily, are the ways in which they live.</p>
    <p>22 1 But the coast of <placeName>Babylonia</placeName> borders on a land which is civilized and well planted and there is such a multitude of <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">fish</name> for the natives that the men who catch them are unable readily to keep ahead of the abundance of them.</p>
    <p>2 For along the beaches they set reeds close to one another and interwoven, so that their appearance is like that of a net which has been set up along the edge of the sea. And throughout the entire construction there are doors which are fixed close together and resemble basket-work in the way they are woven, but are furnished with hinges that easily yield to movements of the water in either direction.</p>
    <p>21 These doors are opened by the waves as they roll towards the shore at the time of flood-tide, and are closed at ebb-tide as they surge back.</p>
    <p>3 Consequently it comes about that every day, when the sea is at flood-tide, the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">fish</name> are carried in from the deep water with the tide and pass inside through the doors, but when the sea recedes they are unable to pass with the water through the interwoven reeds. As a result it is possible at times to see beside the ocean heaps being formed of gasping <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">fish</name>, which are being picked up unceasingly by those who have been appointed to this work, who have from their catch subsistence in abundance as well as large revenues.</p>
    <p>4 And some o</p>
  </div>
</div>
<div type="book" n="1">
  <div type="chapter" n="30">
    <p>f the inhabitants of these parts, because the country is both like a plain and low-lying, dig wide ditches leading from the sea over a distance of many <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">stades</name> to their private estates, and setting wicker gates at their openings they open these when the flood-tide is coming inland and close them when the tide changes to the opposite direction. Then, inasmuch as the sea pours out through the interstices of the gate but the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">fish</name> are held back in the ditches, they have a controlled store of <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">fish</name> and can take of them as many as they choose and at whatever time they please.</p>
    <p>23 1 Now that we have discussed the peoples who dwell on the coast from <placeName>Babylonia</placeName> to the <placeName>Arabian Gulf</placeName>,⁠ 22 we shall describe the nations who live next to them. For in the <placeName>Ethiopia</placeName> which lies above <placeName>Egypt</placeName> there dwells beside the river <placeName>Asa</placeName>⁠ 23 the nation of the <persName>Rhizophagi</persName>.</p>
    <p>24 For the barbarians here dig up the roots of the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">reeds</name> which grow in the neighbouring marshes and then thoroughly wash them; and after they have made them clean they crush them with stones until the stuff is without lumps and glutinous; and then, moulding it into balls as large as can be held in the hand, they bake it in the sun and on this as their food they live all their life long.</p>
  </div>
  <div type="chapter" n="31">
    <p>2 Enjoying as they do the unfailing abundance of this food and living ever at peace with one another, they are nevertheless preyed upon by a multitude of <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">lions</name>; for since the air about them is fiery hot, <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">lions</name> come out of the desert to them in search of shad</p>
  </div>
</div>
<div type="book" n="I">
  <div type="chapter" n="30">
    <p>e and in some cases in pursuit of the smaller <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">animals</name>. Consequently it comes to pass that when the <placeName>Ethiopians</placeName> come out of the marshy lands they are eaten by these beasts; for they are unable to withstand the might of the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">lions</name>, since they have no help in the form of weapons, and indeed in the end the race of them would have been utterly destroyed had not Nature provided them with an aid which acts entirely of itself.</p>
    <p>3 For at the time of the rising of the <foreign xml:lang="la">dog-star</foreign>,⁠ <pb n="25"/> whenever a calm unexpectedly comes on, there swarms to these regions such a multitude of <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">mosquitoes</name>, surpassing in vigour those that are known to us, that while the human beings find refuge in the marshy pools and suffer no hurt, all the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">lions</name> flee from those regions, since they not only suffer from their stings but are at the same time terrified by the sound of their humming. <pb n="24"/></p>
    <p>1 Next to these people are the <persName>Hylophagi</persName> <pb n="151"/> and the <persName>Spermatophagi</persName>,⁠ as they are called. The latter gather the fruit as it falls in great abundance from the trees in the summer season and so find their nourishment without labour, but during the rest of the year they subsist upon the most tender part of the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">plant</name> which grows in the shady glens; for this <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">plant</name>, being naturally stiff and having a stem like the <foreign xml:lang="la">bounias</foreign>,⁠ <pb n="28"/> as we call it, supplies the lack of the necessary food.</p>
    <p>2 The <persName>Hylophagi</persName>, however, setting out with children and wives in search of food, climb the trees and subsist off the tender branches. And this climbing of t</p>
  </div>
</div>
<div type="book" n="I">
  <div type="chapter" n="30">
    <p>heirs even to the topmost branches they perform so well as a result of their continued practice that a man can scarcely believe what they do; indeed they leap from one tree to another like <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">birds</name> and make their way up the weakest branches without experiencing dangers.</p>
    <p>3 For being in body unusually slender and light, whenever their feet slip they catch hold instead with their hands, and if they happen to fall from a height they suffer no hurt by reason of their light weight; and every juicy branch they chew so thoroughly with their teeth that their stomachs easily digest them.</p>
    <p>4 These men go naked all their life, and since they consort with their women in common they likewise look upon their offspring as the common children of all. They fight with one another for the possession of certain places, arming themselves with clubs, with which they also keep off enemies, and they dismember whomsoever they have overcome. Most of them die from becoming exhausted by hunger, when cataracts form upon <pb n="153"/> their eyes and the body is deprived of the necessary use of this organ of sense.</p>
  </div>
  <div type="chapter" n="31">
    <p>25 1 The next part of the country of the <name type="placeName">Ethiopians</name> is occupied by the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Cynegi</name>,⁠ 29 as they are called, who are moderate in number and lead a life in keeping with their name. For since their country is infested by wild beasts and is utterly worthless,⁠ 30 and has few streams of spring water, they sleep in the trees from fear of the wild beasts, but early in the morning, repairing with their weapons to the pool</p>
  </div>
</div>
<div type="book" n="1">
  <div type="chapter" n="30">
    <p>s of water, they secrete themselves in the woods and keep watch from their positions in the trees.</p>
    <p>2 And at the time when the heat becomes intense, <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">wild oxen</name> and <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">leopards</name> and a multitude of every other kind of <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">beast</name> come to drink, and because of the excessive heat and their great thirst they greedily quaff the water until they are gorged, whereupon the <persName>Ethiopians</persName>, the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">animals</name> having become sluggish and scarcely able to move, leap down from the trees, and by the use of clubs hardened in the fire and of stones and arrows easily kill them.</p>
    <p>3 They hunt in this way in companies and feed upon the flesh of their prey, and although now and then they are themselves slain by the strongest <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">animals</name>, yet for the most part they master by their cunning the superior strength of the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">beasts</name>.</p>
    <p>4 And if at any time they find lack of <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">animals</name> in their hunt they soak the skins of some which they had taken at former times and then hold them over a low fire; and when they have singed off the hair they divide the hides among themselves, and on such fare as has been forced upon them they satisfy their want. Their boys they train in shooting at a mark and give <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">food</name> only to those who hit it. Consequently, when they come to manhood, they are marvellously skilled in marksman ­ship, being most excellently instructed by the pangs of hunger.</p>
  </div>
  <div type="chapter" n="31">
    <p>26 1 Far distant from this country towards the parts to the west are <persName>Ethiopians</persName> known as <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Elephant</name>-fighters, hunters also. For dwelling as they do in regions close</p>
  </div>
</div>
<div type="book" n="I">
   <div type="chapter" n="30">
      <p>ether, they carefully observe the places where the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">elephants</name> enter and their favourite resorts, watching them from the tallest trees; and when they are in herds they do not set upon them, since they would have no hope of success, but they lay hands on them as they go about singly, attacking them in an astonishingly daring manner.</p>
      <p>2 For as the beast in its wandering comes near the tree in which the watcher happens to be hidden, the moment it is passing the spot he seizes its tail with his hands and plants his feet against its left flank; he has hanging from his shoulders an axe, light enough to that a blow may be struck with one hand and yet exceedingly sharp, and seizing this in his right hand he hamstrings the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">elephant</name>'s right leg, raining blows upon it and maintaining the position of his own body with his left hand. And they bring an astonishing swiftness to bear upon the task, since there is a contest between the two of them for their very lives; for all that is left to the hunter is either to get the better of the animal or to die himself, the situation not admitting another conclusion.</p>
      <p>3 As for the beast which has been hamstrung, sometimes being unable to turn about because it is hard for it to move and sinking down on the place where it has been hurt, it falls to the ground and causes the death of the <persName>Ethiopian</persName> along with its own, and sometimes squeezing the man against a rock or tree it crushes him with its weight until it has killed him.</p>
      <p>4 In some cases, however,</p>
   </div>
</div>
<div type="book" n="I">
  <div type="chapter" n="30">
    <p>the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">elephant</name> in the extremity of its suffering is far from thinking of turning on its attacker, but flees across the plain until the man who has set his feet upon it, striking on the same place with his axe, has severed the tendons and paralysed the beast. And as soon as the beast has fallen they run together in companies, and cutting the flesh off the hind-quarters of the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">elephant</name> while it is still alive they hold a feast.</p>
    <p>27 1 But some of the natives who dwell near by hunt the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">elephants</name> without exposing themselves to dangers, overcoming their strength by cunning. For it is the habit of this <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">animal</name>, whenever it has had its fill of grazing, to lie down to sleep, the manner in which it does this being different from that of all other four-footed <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">animals</name>; 2 for it cannot bring its whole bulk to the ground by bending its knees, but leans against a tree and thus gets the rest which comes from sleep.⁠ <quote>a</quote> Consequently the tree, by reason of the frequent leaning against it by the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">animal</name>, becomes both rubbed and covered with mud, and the place about it, furthermore, shows both tracks and many signs, whereby the <persName>Ethiopians</persName> who search for such traces discover where the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">elephants</name> take their rest.</p>
    <p>3 Accordingly, when they come upon such a tree, they saw it near the ground until it requires only a little push to make it fall; thereupon, after removing the traces of their own presence, they quickly depart in anticipation p159 of the approach of the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">animal</name>, and towards evening the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">elephant</name></p>
  </div>
</div>
<div type="book" n="I">
   <div type="chapter" n="30">
      <p>filled with food, comes to his accustomed haunt. But as soon as he leans against the tree with his entire weight he at once rolls to the ground along with the tree, and after his fall he remains there lying on his back the night through, since the nature of his body is not fashioned for rising.</p>
   </div>
   <div type="chapter" n="31">
      <p>Then the <name type="people">Ethiopians</name> who have sawn the tree gather at dawn, and when they have slain the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">beast</name> without danger to themselves they pitch their tents at the place and remain there until they have consumed the fallen <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">animal</name>.</p>
   </div>
   <div type="chapter" n="32">
      <p>The parts west of these tribes are inhabited by <name type="people">Ethiopians</name> who are called <name type="people">Simi</name>,</p>
   </div>
   <div type="chapter" n="33">
      <p>but those towards the south are held by the tribe of the <name type="people">Struthophagi</name>.</p>
      <p>For there is found among them a kind of <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">bird</name> having a nature which is mingled with that of the land <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">animal</name>, and this explains the compound name it bears.</p>
   </div>
   <div type="chapter" n="34">
      <p>This <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">animal</name> is not inferior in size to the largest <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">deer</name> and has been fashioned by Nature with a long neck and a round body, which is covered with feathers. Its head is weak and small, but it has powerful thighs and legs and its foot is cloven.</p>
      <p>It is unable to fly in the air because of its weight, but it runs more swiftly than any other <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">animal</name>, barely touching the earth with the tips of its feet; and especially when it raises its wings adown the blasts of the wind it makes off like a ship under full sail; and it defends itself against its pursuers by means of its feet, hurling, as if from a sling, in an astonishing manner, stones as large</p>
   </div>
</div>
<div type="book" n="I">
   <div type="chapter" n="30">
      <p>as can be held in the hand. 4 But when it is pursued at a time of calm, its <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">wings</name> quickly collapse, it is unable to make use of the advantages given it by nature, and being easily overtaken it is made captive.</p>
      <p>5 And since these <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">animals</name> abound in the land in multitude beyond telling, the barbarians devise every manner of scheme whereby to take them; moreover, since they are easily caught in large numbers, their meat is used for food and their skins for clothing and bedding.</p>
      <p>6 But being constantly warred upon by the <persName>Ethiopians</persName> known as "Simi," they are in daily peril from their attackers, and they use as defensive weapons the horns of <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">gazelles</name>; these horns, being large and sharp, are of great service and are found in abundance throughout the land by reason of the multitude of the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">animals</name> which carry them.</p>
   </div>
   <div type="chapter" n="31">
      <p>29 1 A short distance from this tribe on the edge of the desert dwell the <persName>Acridophagi</persName>,<pb n="163"/> men who are smaller than the rest, lean of body, and exceeding dark. For among them in the spring season strong west and south-west winds drive out of the desert a multitude beyond telling of <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">locusts</name>, of great and unusual size and with wings of an ugly, dirty colour.</p>
      <p>2 From these <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">locusts</name> they have food in abundance all their life long, catching them in a manner peculiar to themselves. For along the border of their land over many stades there extends a ravine of considerable depth and width; this they fill with wood from the forests, which is found in plenty in their land; and then,</p>
   </div>
</div>
<div type="book" n="I">
   <div type="chapter" n="30">
      <p>when the winds blow which we have mentioned and the clouds of the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">locusts</name> approach, they divide among themselves the whole extent of the ravine and set fire to the brush in it.</p>
      <p>3 And since a great volume of pungent smoke rises, the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">locusts</name>, as they fly over the ravine, are choked by the pungency of the smoke and fall to the ground after they have flown through it only a short space, and as the destruction of them continues over several days, great heaps of them are raised up; moreover, since the land contains a great amount of brine, all the people bring this to the heaps, after they have been gathered together, soak them to an appropriate degree with the brine and thus both give the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">locusts</name> a palatable taste and make their storage free from rot and lasting for a long time.⁠ 36</p>
      <p>4 Accordingly, the food of this people, at the moment and thereafter, consists of these <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">animals</name>; for they possess no herds nor do they live near the sea nor do they have at hand any other resources; and light in body and very swift of foot as they are, they are also altogether short-lived, the oldest among them not exceeding forty years of age.</p>
      <p>5 As for the manner in which they end their lives, not only is it astounding but extremely pitiful. For when old age draws near there breed in their p165 bodies winged <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">lice</name>, which not only have an unusual form but are also savage and altogether loathsome in aspect.</p>
      <p>6 The affliction begins on the belly and the breast and in a short time spreads over the whole bod</p>
   </div>
</div>
<div type="book" n="I">
  <div type="chapter" n="30">
    <p>And the person so affected is at first irritated by a kind of itching and insists on scratching himself a bit, the disease at this point offering a satisfaction combined with pain; but after this stage the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">animals</name>, which have been continuously engendered more and more in the body, break out to the surface and there is a heavy discharge of a thin humour, the sting of which is quite unbearable.</p>
    <p>Consequently the man who is in the grip of the disease lacerates himself with his nails the more violently, groaning and moaning deeply. And as his hands tear at his body, such a multitude of the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">vermin</name> pours forth that those who try to pick them off accomplish nothing, since they issue forth one after another, as from a kind of vessel that is pierced throughout with holes. And so these wretches end their lives in a dissolution of the body after this manner, a miserable fate, meeting with such a sudden reversal of fortune either by reason of the peculiar character of their food or because of the climate.</p>
  </div>
  <div type="chapter" n="31">
    <p>Along the borders of this people there stretches a country great in size and rich in its varied pasturage; but it is without inhabitants and altogether impossible for man to enter; not that it has from the first never known the race of men, but in later times, as a result of an unseasonable abundance of rain, it brought forth a multitude of <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">venomous spiders</name> and <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">scorpions</name>.</p>
    <p>For, as historians relate, so great a multitude of these <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">animals</name> came to abound that, although a</p>
  </div>
</div>
<div type="book" n="I">
   <div type="chapter" n="30">
      <p>At the outset the human beings dwelling there united in killing the natural enemy, yet, because the multitude of them was not to be overcome and their bites brought swift death to their victims, they renounced both their ancestral land and mode of life and fled from these regions. Nor is there any occasion to be surprised at this statement or to distrust it, since we have learned through trustworthy history of many things more astonishing than this which have taken place throughout all the inhabited world.</p>
      <p>3 In Italy, for instance, such a multitude of <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">field-mice</name> was generated in the plains that they drove certain people out of their native country; in Media birds, which came to abound beyond telling and made away with the seeds sown by the inhabitants, compelled them to remove into regions held by another people; and in the case of the <placeName>Autariatae</placeName>, as they are called, <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">frogs</name> were originally generated in the clouds, and when they fell upon the people in place of the customary rain, they forced them to leave their native homes and to flee for safety to the place where they now dwell.</p>
      <p>4 And who indeed has not read in history, in connection with the Labours which <persName>Heracles</persName> performed in order to win his immortality, the account of the one Labour in the course of which he drove out of the <placeName>Stymphalian Lake</placeName> the multitude of <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">birds</name> which had come to abound in it? Moreover, in <placeName>Libya</placeName> certain cities have become depopulated because a multitude of <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">lions</name> came out of the desert against them.</p>
   </div>
</div>
<div type="book" n="I">
   <div type="chapter" n="31">
      <p>Let these instances, then, suffice in reply to those <pb n="169"/> who adopt a sceptical attitude towards histories because they recount what is astonishing; and now we shall in turn pass on to what follows the subjects we have been treating.</p>
      <p>1 The borders of the parts to the south are inhabited by men whom the Greeks call <quote>"Cynamolgi,"</quote> but who are known in the language of the barbarians who live near them as <foreign xml:lang="grc">Agrii</foreign>.</p>
      <p>2 They wear great beards and maintain packs of savage <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">dogs</name> which serve to meet the needs of their life. For from the time of the beginning of the summer solstice until mid-winter, <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Indian cattle</name>, in a multitude beyond telling, resort to their country, the reason for this being uncertain; for no man knows whether they are in flight because they are being attacked by a great number of carnivorous beasts, or because they are leaving their own regions by reason of a lack of food, or because of some other reversal of fortune which Nature, that engenders all astonishing things, devises, but which the mind of the race of men cannot comprehend.</p>
      <p>3 However, since they have not the strength of themselves to get the better of the multitude of the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">cattle</name>, they let the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">dogs</name> loose on them, and hunting them by means of the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">dogs</name> they overcome a very great number of the animals; and as for the beasts which they have taken, some of them they eat while fresh and some they pack down with salt and store up. Many also of the other <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">animals</name> they hunt, thanks to the courage of their <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">dogs</name></p>
   </div>
</div>
<div type="book" n="I">
   <div type="chapter" n="41">
      <p>and so maintain themselves by the eating of <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">flesh</name>.</p>
      <p>4 Now the most distant tribes of those peoples who live to the south have indeed the forms of <persName>men</persName> but p171 their life is that of the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">beasts</name>; however, it remains for us to discuss two peoples, the <placeName>Ethiopians</placeName> and the <placeName>Trogodytes</placeName>.</p>
      <p>But about the <placeName>Ethiopians</placeName> we have written in other connections, and so we shall now speak of the <placeName>Trogodytes</placeName>.</p>
   </div>
   <div type="chapter" n="32">
      <p>1 The <placeName>Trogodytes</placeName>,⁠ 42 we may state, are called <foreign xml:lang="en">Nomads</foreign> by the <persName>Greeks</persName>, and living as they do a nomadic life off their flocks, each group of them has its tyrant, and their women, like their children, they hold in common, with the single exception of the wife of the tyrant; but if any man goes in to this woman the ruler exacts of him a fine of a specified number of <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">sheep</name>.</p>
      <p>2 At the time of the <foreign xml:lang="en">etesian</foreign> winds, when there are heavy rains in their country, they live off <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">blood</name> and <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">milk</name> which they mix together and seethe for a short while.</p>
      <p>But after this season the pasturage is withered by the excessive heat, and they retreat into the marshy places and fight with each other for the pasturage of the land.</p>
      <p>3 They eat the older <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">animals</name> of the flocks and such as are growing sick and maintain themselves on them at all times.</p>
      <p>Consequently they give the name of parents to no human being, but rather to a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">bull</name> and a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">cow</name>, and also to a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">ram</name> and a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">sheep</name>; these they call their fathers or their mothers, by reason of the fact that they ever secure their daily food from them, and not from those who had begotten them.</p>
   </div>
</div>
<div type="book" n="I">
  <div type="chapter" n="30">
    <p>And as a drink the common people make use of juice from the plant <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">Christ's-thorn</name>, but for the rulers there is prepared from a certain flower a beverage like the vilest of our sweet new wines.</p>
    <p>Following after their <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">herds</name> and <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">flocks</name> they move about from one <placeName>land</placeName> to another, avoiding any stay in the same regions.</p>
    <p>4 And they are all naked as to their bodies except for the loins, which they cover with <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">skins</name>; moreover, all the <name type="people">Trogodytes</name> are circumcised like the <name type="deity">Egyptians</name> with the exception of those who, because of what they have experienced, are called " <foreign xml:lang="la">colobi</foreign> ";⁠ <note>43</note> for these alone of all who live inside the <placeName>Straits</placeName>⁠ <note>44</note> have in infancy all that part cut completely off with the razor which among other peoples merely suffers circumcision.</p>
  </div>
  <div type="chapter" n="31">
    <p>33 1 As for the arms of the <name type="people">Trogodytes</name>, those who bear the name of <persName>Megabari</persName> have round shields covered with raw <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">ox-hide</name> and a club with iron knobs, but the rest of them have <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">bows</name> and <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">arrows</name> and <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">lances</name>.</p>
    <p>Again, the burials practised by them differ entirely from all others; 2 for after binding the bodies of the dead with withes of <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">Christ's-thorn</name> they tie the neck to the legs, and then placing the corpse upon a mound they cast at it stones as large as can be held in the hand, making merry the while, until they have built up a heap of stones and have hidden the bodies from sight; and finally they set up a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">goat's</name> <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">horn</name> on the heap and separate, having shown no fellow-feeling for the dead.</p>
    <p>3 And they fight with one another, not, as the <name type="people">Greeks</name> do</p>
  </div>
</div>
<div type="book" n="I">
   <div type="chapter" n="30">
      <p>o, for possession of land or because of some alleged misdeeds, but for pasturage as it comes up at one time and another. In their quarrels they at first hurl stones at each other, until some are wounded, and the rest of the time they resort to the struggle with bows and arrows. And it is but a moment before many are <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">dead</name>, since they are accurate shooters by reason of their practice in archery and the object at which they are aiming is bare of protective armour.</p>
      <p>4 The fighting is terminated by the older women, who rush into the fray and offer themselves as a protection to the fighters, and are the object of respect; for it is a custom with these people that they shall in no wise strike one of these women, and so at their appearance they cease shooting.</p>
      <p>5 Those who can no longer accompany the flocks by reason of old age bind the tail of an <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">ox</name> about their own necks and so put an end to their lives of their own free will; and if a man postpones his death, anyone who wishes has the authority to fasten the noose about his neck, as an act of good-will, and, after admonishing the man, to take his life.</p>
      <p>6 Likewise it is a custom of theirs to remove from life those who have become maimed or are in the grip of incurable diseases; for they consider it to be the greatest disgrace for a man to cling to life when he is unable to accomplish anything worth living for. Consequently, a man can see every <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Trogodyte</name> sound in body and of vigorous age, since no one of them lives beyond sixty ye</p>
   </div>
</div>
<div type="book" n="1">
  <div type="chapter" n="34">
    <p>But we have said enough about the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Trogodytes</name>; and if anyone of our readers shall distrust our histories because of what is strange and astonishing in the different manners of life which we have described, when he has considered and compared the climate of <placeName>Scythia</placeName> and that of the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Trogodyte</name> country and has observed the differences between them, he will not distrust what has been here related.</p>
    <p>1 So great, for instance, is the contrast between our climate and the climates which we have described that the difference, when considered in detail, surpasses belief.</p>
    <p>2 For example, there are countries where, because of the excessive cold, the greatest rivers are frozen over, the ice sustaining the crossing of armies and the passage of heavily laden wagons, the wine and all other juices freeze so that they must be cut with knives, yea, what is more wonderful still, the extremities of human beings fall off when rubbed by the clothing, their eyes are blinded, fire furnishes no protection, even bronze statues are cracked open, and at certain seasons, they say, the clouds are so thick that in those regions there is neither lightning nor thunder; and many other things, more astonishing than these, come to pass, which are unbelievable to such as are ignorant of them, but cannot be endured by any who have actually experienced them.</p>
    <p>3 But on the farthermost bounds of <placeName>Egypt</placeName> and the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Trogodyte</name> country, because of the excessive heat from the sun at midday, men who are standing side</p>
  </div>
</div>
<div type="book" n="I">
  <div type="chapter" n="30">
    <p>side are unable even to see one another by reason of the thickness of the air as it is condensed, and no one can walk about without foot-gear, since blisters appear at once on any who go barefoot.</p>
    <p>4 And as for drink, unless it is ready to hand to satisfy the need of it, they speedily perish, since the heat swiftly exhausts the natural moistures in the body. Moreover, whenever any man puts any food into a bronze vessel along with water and sets it in the sun, it quickly boils without fire or wood.</p>
    <p>5 Nevertheless, the inhabitants of both the lands which we have mentioned,⁠ <pb n="179"/> far from desiring to escape from the excessive evils which befall them, actually, on the contrary, give up their lives of their own accord simply to avoid being compelled to make trial of a different fare and manner of life.</p>
    <p>6 Thus it is that every country to which a man has grown accustomed holds a kind of spell of its own over him, and the length of time which he has spent there from infancy overcomes the hardship which he suffers from its climate.</p>
    <p>7 And yet countries so different in both ways⁠ are separated by no great interval of space. For from Lake Maeotis,⁠ near which certain Scythians dwell, living in the midst of frost and excessive cold, many sailors of merchant vessels, running before a favourable wind, have made Rhodes in ten days, from which they have reached Alexandria in four, and from that city many men, sailing by way of the Nile,⁠ have reached Ethiopia in ten, so that from</p>
  </div>
</div>
<div type="book" n="I">
   <div type="chapter" n="30">
      <p>the cold parts of the inhabited world to its warmest parts the sailing time is not more than twenty-four days, if the journey is made without a break.</p>
      <p>Consequently, the difference in climates in a slight interval being so great, it is nothing surprising that both the fare and the manners of life as well as the bodies of the inhabitants should be very different from such as prevail among us.</p>
      <p>The <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Fish-eaters</name>.</p>
      <p>Approximately modern south-eastern <placeName>Persia</placeName> and <placeName>Baluchistan</placeName>.</p>
      <p>Or "at their outlets"; cp. critical note. The critical note to the Greek text, ( τὰς ἐκτροπὰς καὶ διεξόδους συγκεχώκασι λίθοις μεγάλoις ), reads: For καὶ Capps suggests κατὰ τάς , "at their outlets."</p>
      <p>Perhaps the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">scorpaena scrofa</name>, which is described in <persName>Athenaeus</persName> <quote>320 D</quote> where Gulick (in the L. C. L.) suggests "<foreign xml:lang="en">sculpin</foreign>" as an "inexact but convenient" equivalent.</p>
      <p>Perhaps the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">phoca monachus</name> of <persName>Odyssey</persName> <quote>4.404</quote>.</p>
      <p>A shrub of the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">buckthorn</name> family.</p>
      <p>About five pounds.</p>
      <p>i.e. "solid."</p>
      <p>The Epicurean doctrine. Cp. <persName>Lucretius</persName> <quote>2.20‑1</quote>: <foreign xml:lang="la">ergo corpoream ad naturam pauca videmus esse opus omnino, quae demant cumque dolorem</foreign>. ( "Therefore we see that few things altogether are necessary for the bodily nature, only such in each case as take pain away"; tr. of Rouse.)</p>
      <p><persName>Ptolemy Euergetes I</persName>, who reigned <quote>246‑221 B.C.</quote></p>
      <p>i.e. <persName>Agatharchides</persName>, who is the chief source of <persName>Diodorus</persName> in this section of his work; cp. <persName>Agatharchides</persName>, <quote>41</quote> (Müller).</p>
   </div>
</div>
<div type="book" n="1">
  <div type="chapter" n="30">
    <p>12 The <placeName>Ethiopians</placeName> of the east; cp. Book 2.22.2 and note .</p>
    <p>13 <persName>Diodorus</persName> evidently refers to the interweaving of the rib-ends at the top, like the poles of the tepee or wigwam of the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">American Indian</name>.</p>
    <p>14 <persName>Strabo</persName> (15.2.2) also says that their dwellings were made of <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">whale</name> ribs; cp. his account (15.2.11‑13) of the "spouting <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">whales</name>" of the <placeName>Persian Gulf</placeName> (tr. by <persName>Jones</persName> in the L. C. L. ).</p>
    <p>15 Or "olive trees of a kind"; see critical note. Since the fruit is quite different the emendation seems justified. The critical note to the Greek text, ( <foreign xml:lang="grc">ἐλαῖαι φύονται</foreign> ), reads: <foreign xml:lang="grc">ἐλαῖαι</foreign> <persName>Casaubon</persName>, cp. <persName>Agatharchides</persName>, 43; <persName>Capps</persName> suggests <foreign xml:lang="grc">ἐλαῖαί τινες</foreign> for <foreign xml:lang="grc">ἐλάται</foreign> of the MSS.</p>
  </div>
  <div type="chapter" n="31">
    <p>16 This custom and the following about the disposal of the dead is recounted by <persName>Strabo</persName> (16.4.14) in connection with the "<name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Turtle-eaters</name>."</p>
    <p>17 i.e. without formal burial.</p>
    <p>18 Cp. Book 1.6.2 .</p>
    <p>19 <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Turtle-eaters</name>; cp. <persName>Strabo</persName> 16.4.14 ff.</p>
  </div>
  <div type="chapter" n="32">
    <p>20 In using the term "<placeName>Babylonia</placeName>" <persName>Diodorus</persName> must be thinking of the satrapy of that name, which included the north coast of the <placeName>Persian Gulf</placeName> and presumably extended down the west coast of the Gulf as far as "<placeName>the uninhabited portion of Arabia</placeName>" (cp. Book 18.6 and below ch. 23.1 ).</p>
  </div>
  <div type="chapter" n="33">
    <p>21 i.e. they are closely woven, so as to offer resistance to the water.</p>
  </div>
  <div type="chapter" n="34">
    <p>22 The <placeName>Red Sea</placeName>.</p>
    <p>23 Called <foreign xml:lang="grc">Astabara</foreign> by <persName>Agatharchides</persName> ( On the <placeName>Red Sea</placeName> , 50) and <foreign xml:lang="grc">Astaboras</foreign> by <persName>Strabo</persName> (16.4.8) .</p>
  </div>
</div>
<div type="book" n="3">
  <div type="chapter" n="1">
    <p>24 <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Root-eaters</name>.</p>
    <p>25 <name type="deity" xml:lang="en">Sirius</name>.</p>
    <p>26 <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Wood-eaters</name>.</p>
    <p>27 <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Seed-eaters</name>, called by <persName>Strabo</persName> (16.4.9) <foreign xml:lang="grc">Spermophagi</foreign>.</p>
  </div>
</div>
<pb n="28"/>
<p>“French turnip,” <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">Brassica Napus</name> . ❦</p>
<pb n="29"/>
<p><persName>Hunters</persName>. ❦</p>
<pb n="30"/>
<p>i.e. not suitable for agriculture. ❦</p>
<pb n="31"/>
<p><quote>Strabo (16.4.10) in a similar account of the hunting of <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">elephants</name> says this is because "its legs have a continuous and unbending bone"; cp. a similar account of how the Germans capture the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">elk</name> of the <placeName>Hercynian forest</placeName> in <persName>Caesar</persName>, <title>Gallic War</title>, 6.27 (tr. by <persName>Edwards</persName> in the L. C. L. ). <persName>J. E. Tennent</persName>, <title>The Natural History of Ceylon</title>, pp100‑106, gives examples of the prevalence of the idea, both in antiquity and the Middle Ages, that the legs of the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">elephant</name> had no joints.</quote> ❦</p>
<pb n="32"/>
<p>Flat-nosed. ❦</p>
<pb n="33"/>
<p>Bird-eaters; but see the following note. ❦</p>
<pb n="34"/>
<p>Probably a double compound stood above, such as " <foreign xml:lang="la">Struthocamelophagi</foreign>" (cp. the critical note). The <foreign xml:lang="la">struthocameli</foreign> (from <foreign xml:lang="grc">στροuthos</foreign>, "sparrow," and <foreign xml:lang="grc">καμηλος</foreign>, i.e. the "bird like a camel," or the "<name type="animal" xml:lang="en">ostrich</name>") are described in Book 2.50.3 . The critical note to the Greek text, ( <foreign xml:lang="grc">Στρουθοφάγων</foreign> ), reads: <persName>Bekker</persName> suggests <foreign xml:lang="grc">Στρουθοκαμηλοφάγων</foreign> .</p>
<pb n="35"/>
<p>Locust-eaters. ❦</p>
<pb n="36"/>
<p>A much shorter account of the same custom is in <persName>Strabo</persName> (16.4.12) . ❦</p>
<pb n="37"/>
<p>Cp. <persName>Strabo</persName> 16.4.12 ; <persName>Aelian</persName>, <title>History of Animals</title>, 17.40 <quote><persName>AELIAN</persName>:<persName>AN17</persName></quote>; <persName>Pliny</persName> 8.29 . ❦</p>
<pb n="38"/>
<p>A people of <placeName>Illyria</placeName>; <persName>Justin</persName> (15.2) also says that they were driven out in this way. ❦</p>
<pb n="39"/>
<p>Milkers of <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">bitches</name>. ❦</p>
<pb n="40"/>
<p>Savages. ❦</p>
<div type="chapter" n="41">
   <p><quote>Strabo</quote> (16.4.10) also says that the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">dogs</name> hunt the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">cattle</name>; but <persName>Agatharchides</persName> (60) and <persName>Aelian</persName> (<foreign xml:lang="la">History of Animals</foreign>, 16.31) <quote>AELIAN:AN16</quote> add that this people drink the milk of <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">bitches</name> when they have no meat.</p>
</div>
<div type="chapter" n="42">
   <p>Much of what follows is in <quote>Strabo</quote> (16.4.17). The spelling of <name type="placeName">Trogodytes</name>, without the λ, is supported by D, the oldest MS., and <persName>Vogel</persName> (I. LXXII) regrets that he did not adopt it. On further grounds for this spelling cp. <persName>Kallenberg</persName>, <foreign xml:lang="de">Textkritik u. Sprachgebrauch Diodors</foreign>, I.1.</p>
</div>
<div type="chapter" n="43">
   <p>The word means "mutilated" (<foreign xml:lang="en">persons whose sexual organs have been removed</foreign>).</p>
</div>
<div type="chapter" n="44">
   <p>At the entrance into the <placeName>Red Sea</placeName>.</p>
</div>
<div type="chapter" n="45">
   <p>i.e. <placeName>Scythia</placeName> and the <placeName>Trogodyte</placeName> land.</p>
</div>
<div type="chapter" n="46">
   <p>i.e. as to severe cold and severe heat.</p>
</div>
<div type="book" n="1">
  <div type="chapter" n="31">
    <p>47 The <placeName>Sea of Azof</placeName>. ❦31 1 Now that we have set forth the facts about the three regions which fortify <placeName>Egypt</placeName> by land we shall add to them the one yet remaining. 2 The fourth side, which is washed over its whole extent by waters which are practically harbourless, has for a defence before it the <placeName>Egyptian Sea</placeName>.⁠ 5 The voyage along the coast of this sea is exceedingly long, and any landing is especially difficult; for from <placeName>Paraetonium</placeName>⁠ 6 in <placeName>Libya</placeName> as far as <placeName>Iopê</placeName>⁠ 7 in <placeName>Coele-Syria</placeName>, a voyage along the coast of some five thousand stades, there is not to be found a safe harbour except <placeName>Pharos</placeName>.⁠ 8 3 And, apart from these considerations, a sandbank extends along practically the whole length of <placeName>Egypt</placeName>, not discernible to any p103 who approach without previous experience of these waters. 4 Consequently those who think that they have escaped the peril of the sea, and in their ignorance turn with gladness towards the shore, suffer unexpected shipwreck when their vessels suddenly run aground; 5 and now and then mariners who cannot see land in time because the country lies so low are cast ashore before they realize it, some of them on marshy and swampy places and others on a desert region. 6 The land of <placeName>Egypt</placeName>, then, is fortified on all sides by nature in the manner described, and is oblong in shape, having a coast-line of two thousand stades and extending inland about six thousand stades. In density of population it far surpassed of old all known regions of the inhabited world, and even in our own</p>
  </div>
</div>
<div type="book" n="1">
   <div type="chapter" n="30">
      <p>day is thought to be second to none other; 7 for in ancient times it had over eighteen thousand important villages and cities, as can be seen entered in their sacred records, while under <persName>Ptolemy</persName> son of <persName>Lagus</persName> these were reckoned at over thirty thousand, this great number continuing down to our own time. 8 The total population, they say, was of old about seven million and the number has remained no less down to our day. 11</p>
      <p>It is for this reason that, according to our historical accounts, the ancient kings of <placeName>Egypt</placeName> built great and marvellous works with the aid of so many hands and left in them immortal monuments to their glory. But these matters we shall set forth in detail a little later; now we shall tell of the nature of the river and the distinctive features of the country. 32</p>
   </div>
   <div type="chapter" n="31">
      <p>The <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Nile</name> flows from south to north, having its sources in regions which have never been seen, since they lie in the desert at the extremity of <placeName>Ethiopia</placeName> in a country that cannot be approached because of the excessive heat.</p>
      <p>Being as it is the largest of all rivers as well as the one which traverses the greatest territory, it forms great windings, now turning towards the east and <placeName>Arabia</placeName>, now turning towards the west and <placeName>Libya</placeName>; for its course from the mountains of <placeName>Ethiopia</placeName> to where it empties into the sea is a distance, inclusive of its windings, of some twelve thousand stades.</p>
      <p>In its lower stretches it is more and more reduced in volume, as the flow is drawn off to the two continents.</p>
   </div>
</div>
<div type="book" n="1">
   <div type="chapter" n="30">
      <p>Of the streams which thus break off from it, those which turn off into Libya are swallowed up by the <pb n="107"/> sand, which lies there to an incredible depth, while those which pour in the opposite direction into Arabia are diverted into immense fens and large marshes on whose shores dwell many peoples.</p>
      <p>5 But where it enters Egypt it has a width of ten stades, sometimes less, and flows, not in a straight course, but in windings of every sort; for it twists now towards the east, now towards the west, and at times even towards the south, turning entirely back upon itself.</p>
      <p>6 For sharp hills extend along both sides of the river, which occupy much of the land bordering upon it and are cut through by precipitous ravines, in which are narrow defiles; and when it comes to these hills the stream rushes rapidly backward through the level country, and after being borne southward over an area of considerable extent resumes once more its natural course.</p>
      <p>7 Distinguished as it is in these respects above all other streams, the Nile is also the only river which makes its way without violence or onrushing waves, except at the cataracts, as they are called.</p>
      <p>8 This is a place which is only about ten stades in length, but has a steep descent and is shut in by precipices so as to form a narrow cleft, rugged in its entire length and ravine-like, full, moreover, of huge boulders which stand out of the water like peaks. And since the river is split about these boulders with great force and is</p>
   </div>
</div>
<div type="book" n="I">
  <div type="chapter" n="30">
    <p>often turned back so that it rushes in the opposite direction because of the obstacles, remarkable whirlpools are formed; 9 the middle space, moreover, for its entire length is filled with foam <pb n="109"/> made by the backward rush of the water, and strikes those who approach it with great terror. And, in fact, the descent of the river is so swift and violent that it appears to the eye like the very rush of an <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">arrow</name>.</p>
    <p>10 During the flood-time of the <name type="placeName">Nile</name>, when the peaked rocks are covered and the entire rapids are hidden by the large volume of the water, some men descend the cataract when they find the winds against them,⁠ 15 but no man can make his way up it, since the force of the river overcomes every human device.</p>
    <p>11 Now there are still other cataracts of this nature, but the largest is the one on the border between <placeName>Ethiopia</placeName> and <placeName>Egypt</placeName>.</p>
  </div>
  <div type="chapter" n="31">
    <p>33 1 The <name type="placeName">Nile</name> also embraces islands within its waters, of which there are many in <placeName>Ethiopia</placeName> and one of considerable extent called <placeName>Meroë</placeName>, on which there also lies a famous city bearing the same name as the island, which was founded by <persName>Cambyses</persName> and named by him after his mother <persName>Meroë</persName>.</p>
    <p>2 This island, they say, has the shape of a long shield and in size far surpasses the other islands in these parts; for they state that it is three thousand stades long and a thousand wide. It also contains not a few cities, the most famous of which is <placeName>Meroë</placeName>.</p>
    <p>3 Extending the entire length of the island where it is washed by the river there are, on the side towards <placeName>Libya</placeName>,</p>
  </div>
</div>
<div type="book" n="1">
  <div type="chapter" n="30">
    <p>the dunes containing an infinite amount of sand, and, on the side towards Arabia, rugged cliffs. There are also to be found in it mines of gold, silver, iron, and copper, and it contains in addition much ebony and <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">p111</name> every kind of precious stone.</p>
    <p>4 Speaking generally, the river forms so many islands that the report of them can scarcely be credited; for, apart from the regions surrounded by water in what is called the Delta, there are more than seven hundred other islands, of which some are irrigated by the <name type="people">Ethiopians</name> and planted with <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">millet</name>, though others are so overrun by <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">snakes</name> and <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">dog-faced baboons</name>⁠ <foreign xml:lang="la">16</foreign> and other animals of every kind that human beings cannot set foot upon them.</p>
    <p>5 Now where the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Nile</name> in its course through <placeName>Egypt</placeName> divides into several streams it forms the region which is called from its shape the Delta.</p>
    <p>6 The two sides of the Delta are described by the outermost branches, while its base is formed by the sea which receives the discharge from the several outlets of the river.</p>
    <p>7 It empties into the sea in seven mouths, of which the first, beginning at the east, is called the <placeName>Pelusiac</placeName>, the second the <placeName>Tanitic</placeName>, then the <placeName>Mendesian</placeName>, <placeName>Phatnitic</placeName>, and <placeName>Sebennytic</placeName>, then the <placeName>Bolbitine</placeName>, and finally the <placeName>Canopic</placeName>, which is called by some the <placeName>Heracleotic</placeName>.</p>
    <p>8 There are also other mouths, built by the hand of man, about which there is no special need to write. At each mouth is a walled city, which is divided into two parts by the river and provided on each side of the mouth with</p>
  </div>
</div>
<div type="book" n="1">
  <div type="chapter" n="30">
    <p>ontoon bridges and guard-houses at suitable points. From the <placeName>Pelusiac</placeName> mouth there is an artificial canal to the <placeName>Arabian Gulf</placeName> and the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Red Sea</name>.</p>
    <p>9 The first to undertake the construction of this was <persName>Necho</persName> the son of <persName>Psammetichus</persName>, and after him <persName>Darius</persName> the <foreign xml:lang="la">Persian</foreign> made progress with the work for a time but finally left it unfinished;⁠ 17</p>
    <p>10 for he was informed by certain persons that if he dug through the neck of land he would be responsible for the submergence of <placeName>Egypt</placeName>, for they pointed out to him that the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Red Sea</name> was higher than <placeName>Egypt</placeName>.⁠ 18</p>
    <p>11 At a later time the second <persName>Ptolemy</persName> completed it and in the most suitable spot constructed an ingenious kind of a lock. This he opened, whenever he wished to pass through, and quickly closed again, a contrivance which usage proved to be highly successful.</p>
    <p>12 The river which flows through this canal is named <persName>Ptolemy</persName>, after the builder of it, and has at its mouth the city called <placeName>Arsinoë</placeName>.</p>
  </div>
  <div type="chapter" n="34">
    <p>3 1 The <placeName>Delta</placeName> is much like <placeName>Sicily</placeName> in shape, and its sides are each seven hundred and fifty stades long and its base, where it is washed by the sea, thirteen hundred stades.</p>
    <p>2 This island is intersected by many artificial canals and includes the fairest land in <placeName>Egypt</placeName>. For since it is alluvial soil and well watered, it produces many crops of every kind, inasmuch as the river by its annual rise regularly deposits on it fresh slime, and the inhabitants easily irrigate its whole area by means of a contrivance p115 which was invented by <persName>Archimedes</persName> of <placeName>Syracuse</placeName></p>
  </div>
</div>
<div type="book" n="1">
  <div type="chapter" n="30">
    <p>and is called, after its shape, a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">screw</name>.</p>
    <p>19 3 Since the <placeName>Nile</placeName> has a gentle current, carries down a great quantity of all kinds of earth, and, furthermore, gathers in stagnant pools in low places, marshes are formed which abound in every kind of <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">plant</name>.</p>
    <p>4 For tubers of every flavour grow in them and fruits and vegetables which grow on stalks, of a nature peculiar to the country, supplying an abundance sufficient to render the poor and the sick among the inhabitants self-sustaining.</p>
    <p>5 For not only do they afford a varied diet, ready at hand and abundant for all who need it, but they also furnish not a few of the other things which contribute to the necessities of life;</p>
    <p>6 the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">lotus</name>, for instance, grows in great profusion, and from it the <persName>Egyptians</persName> make a bread which is able to satisfy the physical needs of the body, and the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">ciborium</name>, which is found in great abundance, bears what is called the "Egyptian" <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">bean</name>.</p>
  </div>
  <div type="chapter" n="31">
    <p>20 7 There are also many kinds of trees, of which that called <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">persea</name>,</p>
    <p>⁠ 21 which was introduced from <placeName>Ethiopia</placeName> by the <persName>Persians</persName> when <persName>Cambyses</persName> conquered those regions, has an unusually sweet fruit,</p>
    <p>8 while of the <foreign xml:lang="la">ficus-morus</foreign>⁠ <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">trees</name> one kind bears the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">black mulberry</name> and another a fruit resembling the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">fig</name>; and since the latter produces throughout almost the whole year, the result is that the poor have a ready source to turn to in their need.</p>
    <p>9 The fruit called the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">blackberry</name> is picked at the time the river is p117 receding and by reason of its natural sweetness is eaten as a</p>
  </div>
</div>
<div type="book" n="1">
  <div type="chapter" n="30">
    <p>dessert. 10 The Egyptians also make a drink out of barley which they call <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">zythos</name>, the bouquet of which is not much inferior to that of wine.</p>
    <p>11 Into their lamps they pour for lighting purposes, not the oil of the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">olive</name>, but a kind which is extracted from a plant and called <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">kiki</name>.</p>
  </div>
  <div type="chapter" n="35">
    <p>Many other plants, capable of supplying men with the necessities of life, grow in <placeName>Egypt</placeName> in great abundance, but it would be a long task to tell about them.</p>
    <div type="section" n="1">
      <p>As for animals, the <name type="placeName" xml:lang="en">Nile</name> breeds many of peculiar form, and two which surpass the others, the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">crocodile</name> and what is called the "horse."</p>
      <div type="section" n="2">
        <p>Of these animals the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">crocodile</name> grows to be the largest from the smallest beginning, since this animal lays eggs about the size of those of a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">goose</name>, but after the young is hatched it grows to be as long as sixteen cubits. It is as long-lived as man, and has no tongue.</p>
        <div type="section" n="3">
          <p>The body of the animal is wondrously protected by nature; for its skin is covered all over with scales and is remarkably hard, and there are many teeth in both jaws, two being tusks, much larger than the rest.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section" n="4">
          <p>It devours the flesh not only of men but also of any land animal which approaches the river. The bites which it makes are huge and severe and it lacerates terribly with its claws, and whatever part of the flesh it tears it renders altogether difficult to heal.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section" n="5">
          <p>In early times the <persName>Egyptians</persName> used to catch these beasts with hooks baited with the flesh of <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">pigs</name>, but since then they have hunted them sometimes with heavy nets,</p>
        </div>
      </div>
    </div>
  </div>
</div>
<div type="book" n="1">
  <div type="chapter" n="30">
    <p>as they catch some kinds of <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">fish</name>, and sometimes from their boats with iron spears which they strike repeatedly into the head.</p>
    <p>6 The multitude of them in the river and the adjacent marshes is beyond telling, since they are prolific and are seldom slain by the inhabitants; for it is the custom of most of the natives of <placeName>Egypt</placeName> to worship the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">crocodile</name> as a god, while for foreigners there is no profit whatsoever in the hunting of them since their flesh is not edible.</p>
    <p>7 But against this multitude's increasing and mena­cing the inhabitants nature has devised a great help; for the animal called the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">ichneumon</name>, which is about the size of a small <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">dog</name>, goes about breaking the eggs of the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">crocodiles</name>, since the animal lays them on the banks of the river, and — what is most astonishing of all — without eating them or profiting in any way it continually performs a service which, in a sense, has been prescribed by nature and forced upon the animal for the benefit of men.</p>
    <p>8 The animal called the "<name type="animal" xml:lang="en">horse</name>" is not less than five cubits high, and is four-footed and cloven-hoofed like the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">ox</name>; it has tusks larger than those of the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">wild boar</name>, three on each side, and ears and tail and a cry somewhat like those of the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">horse</name>; but the trunk of its body, as a whole, is not unlike that of the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">elephant</name>, and its skin is the toughest of almost any beast's.</p>
    <p>9 Being a river and land animal, it spends the day in the streams exercising in the deep water, while at night it forages about the countryside on the gra</p>
  </div>
</div>
<div type="book" n="I">
  <div type="chapter" n="30">
    <p>in and hay, so that, if this <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">animal</name> were prolific and reproduced each year, it would entirely destroy the farms of Egypt.</p>
    <p>But even it is caught by the united work of many men who strike it with iron spears; for whenever it appears they converge their boats upon it, and gathering about it wound it repeatedly with a kind of chisel fitted with iron barbs, and then, fastening the end of a rope of tow to one of them which has become imbedded in the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">animal</name>, they let it go until it dies from loss of blood.</p>
    <p>Its meat is tough and hard to digest and none of its inward parts is edible, neither the viscera nor the intestines.</p>
  </div>
  <div type="chapter" n="31">
    <p>Beside the beasts above mentioned the <placeName>Nile</placeName> contains every variety of <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">fish</name> and in numbers beyond belief; for it supplies the natives not only with abundant subsistence from the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">fish</name> freshly caught, but it also yields an unfailing multitude for salting.</p>
    <p>Speaking generally, we may say that the <placeName>Nile</placeName> surpasses all the rivers of the inhabited world in its benefactions to mankind. For, beginning to rise at the summer solstice, it increases in volume until the autumnal equinox, and, since it is bringing down fresh mud all the time, it soaks both the fallow land and the seed land as well as the orchard land for so long a time as the farmers may wish.</p>
    <p>For since the water comes with a gentle flow, they easily divert the river from their fields by small dams of earth, and then, by cutting these, as easily let the river in again upon the land whenever</p>
  </div>
</div>
<div type="book" n="I">
  <div type="chapter" n="30">
    <p>they think this to be advantageous. 4 And in general the <name type="place">Nile</name> contributes so greatly to the lightening of labour as well as to the profit of the inhabitants, that the majority of the farmers, as they begin work upon the areas of the land which are becoming dry, merely scatter their seed, turn their <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">herds</name> and <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">flocks</name> in on the fields, and after they have used these for trampling the seed in return after four or five months to harvest it;⁠</p>
    <p>27 while some, applying light ploughs to the land, turn over no more than the surface of the soil after its wetting and then gather great heaps of grain without much expense or exertion. 5 For, generally speaking, every kind of field labour among other peoples entails great expense and toil, but among the <persName>Egyptians</persName> alone is the harvest gathered in with very slight outlay of money and labour. Also the land planted with the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">vine</name>, being irrigated as are the other fields, yields an abundant supply of <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">wine</name> to the natives. 6 And those who allow the land, after it has been inundated, to lie uncultivated and give it over to the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">flocks</name> to graze upon, are rewarded with flocks which, because of the rich pasturage, lamb twice and are twice shorn every year. 28</p>
    <p>7 The rise of the <name type="place">Nile</name> is a phenomenon which appears wonderful enough to those who have witnessed it, but to those who have only heard of it, quite incredible. For while all other <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">rivers</name> begin to fall at the summer solstice and grow steadily lower and lower during the course of the following s</p>
  </div>
</div>
<div type="book" n="1">
   <div type="chapter" n="30">
      <p>ummer, this one alone begins to rise at that time and increases so greatly in volume day by day that it finally overflows practically all <placeName>Egypt</placeName>. <pb n="125"/>
      </p>
      <p>And in like manner it afterwards follows precisely the opposite course and for an equal length of time gradually falls each day, until it has returned to its former level. And since the land is a level plain, while the cities and villages, as well as the farm-houses, lie on artificial mounds, the scene comes to resemble the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Cyclades Islands</name>.⁠
      </p>
      <p>9 The <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">wild land animals</name> for the larger part are cut off by the river and perish in its waters, but a few escape by fleeing to higher ground; the herds and flocks, however, are maintained at the time of the flood in the villages and farm-houses, where fodder is stored up for them in advance.
      </p>
      <p>10 The masses of the people, being relieved of their labours during the entire time of the inundation, turn to recreation, feasting all the whole and enjoying without hindrance every device of pleasure.
      </p>
      <p>11 And because of the anxiety occasioned by the rise of the river the kings have constructed a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Nilometer</name>⁠ at <placeName>Memphis</placeName>, where those who are charged with the administration of it accurately measure the rise and despatch messages to the cities, and inform them exactly how many cubits or fingers the river has risen and when it has commenced to fall.
      </p>
      <p>12 In this manner the entire nation, when it has learned that the river has ceased rising and begun to fall, is relieved of its anxiety, while at the same
      </p>
   </div>
</div>
<div type="book" n="I">
  <div type="chapter" n="37">
    <p>time all immediately know in advance how large the next harvest will be, since the Egyptians have kept an accurate record of their observations of this kind over a long period of terms.</p>
    <p><pb n="127"/>37 1 Since there is great difficulty in explaining the swelling of the river, many philosophers and historians have undertaken to set forth the causes of it; regarding this we shall speak summarily, in order that we may neither make our digression too long nor fail to record that which all men are curious to know.</p>
    <p>2 For on the general subject of the rise of the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Nile</name> and its sources, as well as on the manner in which it reaches the sea and the other points in which this, the largest river of the inhabited world, differs from all others, some historians have actually not ventured to say a single word, although wont now and then to expatiate at length on some winter torrent or other, while others have undertaken to speak on these points of inquiry, but have strayed far from the truth.</p>
    <p>3 <persName>Hellanicus</persName> and <persName>Cadmus</persName>, for instance, as well as <persName>Hecataeus</persName> and all the writers like them, belonging as they do one and all to the early school,<foreign xml:lang="la">⁠ 31</foreign> turned to the answers offered by the myths;</p>
    <p>4 <persName>Herodotus</persName>, who was a curious inquirer if ever a man was, and widely acquainted with history, undertook, it is true, to give an explanation of the matter, but is now found to have followed contradictory guesses; <persName>Xenophon</persName> and <persName>Thucydides</persName>, who are praised for the accuracy of their histories, completely refrained in their wr</p>
  </div>
</div>
<div type="book" n="I">
  <div type="chapter" n="30">
    <p>itings from any mention of the regions about Egypt; and Ephorus and Theopompus, who of all writers paid most attention to these matters, hit upon the truth the least. The p129 error on the part of all these writers was due, not to their negligence, but to the peculiar character of the country.</p>
    <p>5 For from earliest times until Ptolemy who was called Philadelphus,⁠ <persName>32</persName> not only did no <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Greeks</name> ever cross over into <placeName>Ethiopia</placeName>, but none ascended even as far as the boundaries of <placeName>Egypt</placeName> — to such an extent were all these regions inhospitable to foreigners and altogether dangerous; but after this king had made an expedition into <placeName>Ethiopia</placeName> with an army of <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Greeks</name>, being the first to do so, the facts about that country from that time forth have been more accurately learned.</p>
    <p>6 Such, then, were the reasons for the ignorance of the earlier historians; and as for the sources of the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Nile</name> and the region where the stream arises, not a man, down to the time of the writing of this history, has ever affirmed that he has seen them, or reported from hearsay an account received from any who have maintained that they have seen them.</p>
    <p>7 The question, therefore, resolves itself into a matter of guesswork and plausible conjecture; and when, for instance, the priests of <placeName>Egypt</placeName> assert that the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Nile</name> has its origin in the ocean which surrounds the inhabited world, there is nothing sound in what they say, and they are merely solving one perplexity by substituting another, and advancing as proof an explanation which i</p>
  </div>
</div>
<div type="book" n="I">
  <div type="chapter" n="30">
    <p>tself stands much in need of proof. <pb n="131"/>8 On the other hand, those <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Trogodytes</name>,⁠ 33 known as the <persName>Bolgii</persName>, who migrated from the interior because of the heat, say that there are certain phenomena connected with those regions, from which a man might reason that the body of the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Nile</name> is gathered from many sources which converge upon a single place, and that this is the reason for its being the most fertile of all known rivers.</p>
    <p>9 But the inhabitants of the country about the island called <placeName>Meroë</placeName>, with whom a man would be most likely to agree, since they are far removed from the art of finding reasons in accordance with what is plausible and dwell nearest the regions under discussion, are so far from saying anything accurate about these problems that they even call the river <foreign xml:lang="el">Astapus</foreign>, which means, when translated into <foreign xml:lang="grc">Greek</foreign>, "Water from Darkness."</p>
    <p>10 This people, then, have given the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Nile</name> a name which accords with the want of any first-hand information about those regions and with their own ignorance of them; but in our opinion the explanation nearest the truth is the one which is farthest from pure assumption.</p>
    <p>11 I am not unaware that <persName>Herodotus</persName>,⁠ 34 when distinguishing between the <placeName>Libya</placeName> which lies to the east and that which lies to the west of this river, attributes to the <persName>Libyans</persName> known as the <persName>Nasamones</persName> the exact observation of the stream, and says that the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Nile</name> rises in a certain lake and then flows through the land of <placeName>Ethiopia</placeName> for a distance beyond telling;⁠ a and yet assuredly no h</p>
  </div>
</div>
<div type="book" n="I">
   <div type="chapter" n="38">
      <p>asty assent should be given to the statements either of <persName>Libyans</persName>, even though they may have spoken truthfully, or of the historian when what he says does not admit of proof. <pb n="133"/> 38 1 Now that we have discussed the sources and course of the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Nile</name> we shall endeavour to set forth the causes of its swelling.</p>
      <p>2 <persName>Thales</persName>, who is called one of the seven wise men, says that when the <foreign xml:lang="en">etesian</foreign> winds
         <note xml:lang="en">35</note> blow against the mouths of the river they hinder the flow of the water into the sea, and that this is the reason why it rises and overflows <placeName>Egypt</placeName>, which is a low and level plain.</p>
      <p>3 But this explanation, plausible as it appears, may easily be shown to be false. For if what he said were true, all the rivers whose mouths face the <foreign xml:lang="en">etesian</foreign> winds would rise in a similar way; but since this is the case nowhere in the inhabited world the true cause of the swelling must be sought elsewhere.</p>
      <p>4 <persName>Anaxagoras</persName> the physical philosopher has declared that the cause of the rising is the melting snow in <placeName>Ethiopia</placeName>, and the poet <persName>Euripides</persName>, a pupil of his, is in agreement with him. At least he writes:
         <quote>
            <foreign xml:lang="en">36</foreign> He quit <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Nile</name>'s waters, fairest that gush from earth, The <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Nile</name> which, drawn from <placeName>Ethiop</placeName> land the black Man's home, flows with full flood when melts the snow.
         </quote>
      </p>
      <p>5 But the fact is that this statement also requires but a brief refutation, since it is clear to everyone that the excessive heat makes it impossible that any snow should fall in <placeName>Ethiopia</placeName>;</p>
      <p>6 for, speaking generally, in those regions there is no frost or cold or</p>
   </div>
</div>
<div type="book" n="I">
  <div type="chapter" n="30">
    <p>any sign whatsoever of winter, and this is especially true at the time of the rising of the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Nile</name>. And even <pb n="135"/> if a man should admit the existence of great quantities of snow in the regions beyond <placeName>Ethiopia</placeName>, the falsity of the statement is still shown by this fact:</p>
    <p>7 every river which flows out of the snow gives out cool breezes, as is generally agreed, and thickens the air about it; but the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Nile</name> is the only river about which no clouds form, and where no cool breezes rise and the air is not thickened.</p>
    <p>8 <quote><persName>Herodotus</persName> 37</quote> says that the size of the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Nile</name> at its swelling is its natural one, but that as the sun travels over <placeName>Libya</placeName> in the winter it draws up to itself from the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Nile</name> a great amount of moisture, and this is the reason why at that season the river becomes smaller than its natural size;</p>
    <p>9 but at the beginning of summer, when the sun turns back in its course towards the north, it dries out and thus reduces the level of both the rivers of <placeName>Greece</placeName> and those of every other land whose geographical position is like that of <placeName>Greece</placeName>.⁠ <quote><persName>Herodotus</persName> 38</quote></p>
    <p>10 Consequently there is no occasion for surprise, he says, in the phenomenon of the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Nile</name>; for, as a matter of fact, it does not increase in volume in the hot season and then fall in the winter, for the reason just given.</p>
    <p>11 Now the answer to be made to this explanation also is that it would follow that, if the sun drew moisture to itself from the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Nile</name> in the winter, it would also take some moisture from all the other rivers of <placeName>Libya</placeName> and reduce the fl</p>
  </div>
</div>
<div type="book" n="1">
  <div type="chapter" n="39">
    <p>ow of their waters. 12 But since nowhere in <placeName>Libya</placeName> is anything like this to be seen taking place, it is clear that the historian is caught inventing an explanation; for the fact is that the rivers of <placeName>Greece</placeName> increase in winter, not because the sun is farther away, but by reason of the enormous rainfall.</p>
    <p>39 1 <persName>Democritus</persName> of <placeName>Abdera</placeName> says that it is not the regions of the south that are covered with snow, but only those of the north, and that this is evident to everyone.</p>
    <p>2 The great quantities of heaped-up snow in the northern regions still remain frozen until about the time of the winter solstice, but when in summer its solid masses are broken up by the heat, a great melting sets up, and this brings about the formation of many thick clouds in the higher altitudes, since the vapour rises upwards in large quantities.</p>
    <p>3 These clouds are then driven by the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">etesian winds</name> until they strike the highest mountains in the whole earth, which, he says, are those of <placeName>Ethiopia</placeName>; then by their violent impact upon these peaks, lofty as they are, they cause torrential rains which swell the river, to the greatest extent at the season of the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">etesian winds</name>.</p>
    <p>4 But it is easy for anyone to refute this explanation also, if he will but note with precision the time when the increase of the river takes place; for the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Nile</name> begins to swell at the summer solstice, when the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">etesian winds</name> are not yet blowing, and commences to fall after the autumnal equinox, when the same winds have long since ceased.</p>
  </div>
</div>
<div type="book" n="1">
   <div type="chapter" n="30">
      <p>henever, therefore, the precise knowledge derived from experience prevails over the plausibility of mere argumentation, while we should recognize the man's ingenuity, yet no credence should be given to his statements. 6 Indeed, I pass over the further fact that the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">etesian</name> winds can be seen to blow just <pb n="139"/> as much from the west as from the north; since <persName>Borean</persName> and <persName>Aparctian</persName>⁠ winds are not the only winds which are called <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">etesian</name>, but also the <persName>Argestean</persName>, which blow from the direction of the sun's summer setting.⁠ 41 Also the statement that by general agreement the highest mountains are those of <placeName>Ethiopia</placeName> is not only advanced without any proof, but it does not possess, either, the credibility which is accorded to facts established by observation. 42</p>
   </div>
   <div type="chapter" n="31">
      <p>7 <persName>Ephorus</persName>, who presents the most recent explanation, endeavours to adduce a plausible argument, but, as may be seen, by no means arrives at the truth. For he says that all <placeName>Egypt</placeName>, being alluvial soil and spongy,⁠ 43 and in nature like <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">pumice-stone</name>, is full of large and continuous cracks, through which it takes up a great amount of water; this it retains within itself during the winter season, but in the summer season it pours this out from itself everywhere like sweat, as it were, and by means of this exudation it causes the flood of the river. 8 But this historian, as it appears to us, has not only never personally observed the nature of the country in <placeName>Egypt</placeName>, but has not even inquired with any care about it of those who are acquai</p>
   </div>
</div>
<div type="book" n="1">
  <div type="chapter" n="30">
    <p>nted with the character of this land. 9 For in the first place, if the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Nile</name> derived its increase from <placeName>Egypt</placeName> itself, it would then not experience a flood in its upper stretches, where it flows through a stony and solid country; yet, as a matter of fact, it floods while flowing over a course of more than six thousand stades through <placeName>Ethiopia</placeName> before it ever touches <placeName>Egypt</placeName>.</p>
    <p>10 Secondly, if the stream of the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Nile</name> were, on the one hand, lower than the rifts in the alluvial soil, the cracks would then be on the surface and so great an amount of water could not possibly remain in them; and if, on the other hand, the river occupied a higher level than the rifts, there could not possibly be a flow of water from the lower hollows to the higher surface.</p>
    <p>11 In general, can any man think it possible that the exudations from rifts in the ground should produce so great an increase in the waters of the river that practically all <placeName>Egypt</placeName> is inundated by it! For I pass over the false statements of <persName>Ephorus</persName> about the ground being alluvial and water being stored up in the rifts, since the refutation of them is manifest.</p>
    <p>12 For instance, the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Meander</name> river in <placeName>Asia</placeName> has laid down a great amount of alluvial land, yet not a single one of the phenomena attending the flooding of the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Nile</name> is to be seen in its case.</p>
    <p>13 And like the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Meander</name> the river in <placeName>Acarnania</placeName> known as the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Acheloüs</name>, and the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Cephisus</name> in <placeName>Boeotia</placeName>, which flows out of <placeName>Phocis</placeName>, have built up not a little land, and in the case of both there is c</p>
  </div>
</div>
<div type="book" n="I">
  <div type="chapter" n="40">
    <p>lear proof that the historian's statements are erroneous. However, under no circumstances would any man look for strict accuracy in <persName>Ephorus</persName>, when he sees that in many matters he has paid little regard for the truth.</p>
  </div>
  <div type="chapter" n="41">
    <p>1 Certain of the wise men in <placeName>Memphis</placeName> have undertaken to advance an explanation of the flooding, which is incapable of disproof rather than credible, and yet it is accepted by many.</p>
    <p>2 They divide the earth into three parts, and say that one part is that which forms our inhabited world, that the second is exactly opposed to these regions in its seasons, and that the third lies between these two but is uninhabited by reason of the heat.</p>
    <p>3 Now if the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Nile</name> rose in the winter, it would be clear that it was receiving its additional waters from our zone because of the heavy rains which fall with us in that season especially; but since, on the contrary, its flood occurs in the summer, it is probable that in the regions opposite to us the winter storms are being produced and that the surplus waters of those distant regions flow into our inhabited world.</p>
    <p>4 And it is for this reason that no man can journey to the sources of the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Nile</name>, because the river flows from the opposite zone through the uninhabited one. A further witness to this is the excessive sweetness of the water of the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Nile</name>; for in the course of the river through the torrid zone it is tempered by the heat, and that is the reason for its being the sweetest of all rivers, inasmuch as by the law of nature</p>
  </div>
</div>
<div type="book" n="1">
  <div type="chapter" n="30">
    <p>that which is fiery always sweetens⁠ <pb n="145"/> what is wet. 5 But this explanation admits of an obvious rebuttal, for plainly it is quite impossible for a river to flow uphill into our inhabited world from the inhabited world opposite to ours, especially if one holds to the theory that the earth is shaped like a sphere. And indeed, if any man makes bold to do violence, by means of mere words, to facts established by observation, Nature at least will in no wise yield to him. For, in general, such men think that, by introducing a proposition incapable of being disproved and placing the uninhabited region between the two inhabited ones, they will in this way avoid all precise refutations of their argument;</p>
    <p>6 but the proper course for such as take a firm position on any matter is either to adduce the observed facts as evidence or to find their proofs in statements which have been agreed upon at the outset. But how can the Nile be the only river which flows from that inhabited world to our parts? For it is reasonable to suppose that other rivers as well are to be found there, just as there are many among us.</p>
    <p>7 Moreover, the cause which they advance for the sweetness of the water is altogether absurd. For if the river were sweetened by being tempered by the heat, it would not be so productive as it is of life, nor contain so many kinds of <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">fishes</name> and <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">animals</name>; for all water upon being changed by the fiery element is quite incapable of generating life.</p>
    <p>8 Therefore, since by the "tempe</p>
  </div>
</div>
<div type="book" n="1">
  <div type="chapter" n="41">
    <p>ring" process which they introduce they entirely change the real nature of the Nile, the causes which they advance for its flooding must be considered false. <persName>Oenopides</persName> of <placeName>Chios</placeName>⁠ <quote>46</quote> says that in the summer the waters under the earth are cold, but in the winter, on the contrary, warm; and that this may be clearly observed in deep <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">wells</name>, for in midwinter their water is least cold, while in the hottest weather <pb n="147"/> the coldest water is drawn up from them.</p>
    <p>2 Consequently it is reasonable that the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Nile</name> should be small and should diminish in the winter, since the heat in the earth consumes the larger part of the moisture and there are no rains in <placeName>Egypt</placeName>; while in the summer, since there is no longer any consumption of the moisture down in the depths of the earth, the natural flow of the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">river</name> is increased without hindrance.</p>
    <p>3 But the answer to be given to this explanation also is that there are many <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">rivers</name> in <placeName>Libya</placeName>, whose mouths are situated like those of the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Nile</name> and whose courses are much the same, and yet they do not rise in the same manner as the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Nile</name>; on the contrary, flooding as they do in the winter and receding in the summer, they refute the false statement of any man who tries to overcome the truth with specious arguments.</p>
    <p>4 The nearest approach to the truth has been made by <persName>Agatharchides</persName> of <placeName>Cnidus</placeName>⁠ <quote>47</quote>. His explanation is as follows: Every year continuous rains fall in the mountains of <placeName>Ethiopia</placeName> from the summer solstice to the autumnal equinox;</p>
  </div>
</div>
<div type="book" n="I">
  <div type="chapter" n="30">
    <p>asonable that the Nile should diminish in the winter when it derives its natural supply of water solely from its sources, but should increase its volume in the summer on account of the rains which pour into it.</p>
    <p>6 And just because no one up to this time has been able to set forth the causes of the origin of the flood waters, it is not proper, he urges, that his personal explanation be rejected; for nature presents many contradictory phenomena, the exact causes of which are beyond the power of mankind p149 to discover.</p>
    <p>7 As to his own statement, he adds, testimony to its truth is furnished by what takes place in certain regions of Asia. For on the borders of Scythia which abut upon the <placeName>Caucasus</placeName> mountains, annually, after the winter is over, exceptionally heavy snow-storms occur over many consecutive days; in the northern parts of <placeName>India</placeName> at certain seasons <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">hailstones</name> come beating down which in size and quantity surpass belief; about the <placeName>Hydaspes</placeName> river continuous rains fall at the opening of summer; and in <placeName>Ethiopia</placeName>, likewise, the same thing occurs some days later, this climatical condition, in its regular recurrence, always causing storms in the neighbouring regions.</p>
    <p>8 And so, he argues, it is nothing surprising if in <placeName>Ethiopia</placeName> as well, which lies above <placeName>Egypt</placeName>, continuous rains in the mountains, beating down in the summer, swell the river, especially since the plain fact itself is witnessed to by the barbarians who inhabit these regions.</p>
    <p>9 And if what has been said is of a nature op</p>
  </div>
</div>
<div type="book" n="1">
  <div type="chapter" n="30">
    <p>posite to what occurs among us, it should not be disbelieved on that score; for the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">south wind</name>, for example, with us is accompanied by stormy weather, but in <placeName>Ethiopia</placeName> by clear skies, and in <placeName>Europe</placeName> the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">north winds</name> are violent, but in that land they are gentle and light.</p>
    <p>With regard, then, to the flooding of the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Nile</name>, though we are able to answer with more varied arguments all who have offered explanations of it, we shall rest content with what has been said, in order that we may not overstep the principle of brevity which we resolved upon at the beginning.</p>
    <p>And since we have divided this Book into two parts because of its length, inasmuch as we are aiming at due proportion in our account, at this point we shall close the first portion of our history, and in the second we shall set forth the facts in the history of <placeName>Egypt</placeName> which come next in order, beginning with the account of the former <persName>kings of Egypt</persName> and of the earliest manner of life among the <persName>Egyptians</persName>.</p>
  </div>
</div>
<div type="chapter" n="3">
   <p><quote>A gulf profound as that <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Serbonian</name> bog
      Betwixt <placeName>Damiata</placeName> and <placeName>Mount Casius</placeName> old,
      Where armies whole have sunk.</quote></p>
</div>
<div type="chapter" n="4">
   <p>An instance of the loss of part of an army is given in Book 16.46.</p>
</div>
<div type="chapter" n="5">
   <p>That part of the <name type="place">Mediterranean</name> lying off <placeName>Egypt</placeName>.</p>
</div>
<div type="chapter" n="6">
   <p>The first important city on the coast west of <placeName>Alexandria</placeName>.</p>
</div>
<div type="chapter" n="7">
   <p><placeName>Joppa</placeName>.</p>
</div>
<div type="chapter" n="8">
   <p>The island which lies before <placeName>Alexandria</placeName> and gave its name to the harbour.</p>
</div>
<div type="chapter" n="9">
   <p><persName>Ptolemy Lagus</persName>, general of <persName>Alexander the Great</persName>, was the founder of the line of the <name type="deity">Ptolemies</name>. He obtained the governor­ship of <placeName>Egypt</placeName> shortly after the death of <persName>Alexander</persName> in 323 B.C., assumed the title of king in 305, and reigned until 283.</p>
</div>
<div type="chapter" n="10">
   <p><persName>Herodotus</persName> (2.177) gives the number of "inhabited cities" in the time of <persName>Amasis</persName> (sixth century B.C.) as twenty thousand. The "over thirty thousand" of <persName>Diodorus</persName> may be approximately correct, when the "villages" are included, although he may be using the figures given by <persName>Theocritus</persName> (17.82 ff.), who was born about 305 B.C. and performed a feat of metrical juggling of the number 33,333: <quote>"The cities builded therein are three hundreds and three thousands and three tens of thousands, and threes twain and nines three, and in them the lord and master of all is proud <persName>Ptolemy</persName>"</quote> (tr. <persName>Edmonds</persName>, in L. C. L.).</p>
</div>
<div type="chapter" n="30">
   <p>U. Wilcken (cp. critical note) feels that this sum for the population of Egypt about the middle of first century B.C. is approximately correct. Josephus of <persName>Josephus</persName>' <name type="work" xml:lang="en">Wars of the Jews</name>'+Eng2+EngSearch+'seven millions ',WIDTH,195)" onMouseOut="nd();"> ( <name type="work" xml:lang="en">Jewish War</name> , 2.385) , writing a little more than a century later, gives the population as 7,500,000, exclusive of <placeName>Alexandria</placeName>.</p>
   <p>In Book 17.52.6 <persName>Diodorus</persName> says that the "free inhabitants" of that city numbered over 300,000. The critical note to the Greek text ( <foreign xml:lang="grc">καὶ καθ’ ἡμᾶς δὲ οὐκ ἐλάττους εἶναι τούτων</foreign> ) reads: All MSS. except M read τριακοσίων , which has been deleted by every editor since Dindorf. But U. Wilcken ( <foreign xml:lang="grc">Γραικικαὶ Ὀστρακα ἐξ Αἰγύπτου καὶ Νοβίας</foreign> , 1, pp489 f.) follows <persName>Ed. Meyer</persName> in feeling that τριακοσίων is a corruption and makes a strong case for τούτων , which I have adopted.</p>
</div>
<div type="chapter" n="31">
   <p>The earlier Greek writers made the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Nile</name> the dividing line between the continents of <placeName>Asia</placeName> and <placeName>Africa</placeName>. ❦</p>
</div>
<div type="chapter" n="32">
   <p><persName>Herodotus</persName> (2.32) speaks of "large marshes" on the upper course of the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Nile</name>. ❦</p>
</div>
<div type="chapter" n="33">
   <p>i.e. the valley which lies between the hills. ❦</p>
</div>
<div type="chapter" n="34">
   <p>i.e. and so are able to check their speed by using the sails. ❦</p>
</div>
<div type="chapter" n="35">
   <p>These are described in Book 3.35 . ❦</p>
</div>
<div type="chapter" n="36">
   <p><persName>Necho</persName> reigned from 609 to 593 B.C. , <persName>Darius</persName> from 521 to 485 B.C. ❦</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="80">
   <p>This canal, not to be confused with the Suez Canal, left the <name type="placeName" xml:lang="en">Nile</name> a little above <placeName>Bubastis</placeName>, followed the <placeName>Wadi Tûmilât</placeName> to the <name type="placeName" xml:lang="en">Bitter Lakes</name>, and then turned south, along the course of the present canal, to the <name type="placeName" xml:lang="en">Red Sea</name>.</p>
   <p>Its construction has been placed as far back as the 19th and even the 12th Dynasty. At any rate, it was again put in operation by <persName>Darius</persName>, as is clear from the inscription on best-preserved of the five stelae discovered: <quote>I am a Persian. From Persia I captured Egypt. I commanded this canal to be built from the <name type="placeName" xml:lang="en">Nile</name>, which flows in Egypt, to the <name type="placeName" xml:lang="en">Sea</name> which comes from Persia. So was this canal built, as I had commanded, and ships passed from Egypt through this canal to Persia, as was my purpose</quote> (translation in <persName>R. W. Rogers</persName>, <title>History of Ancient Persia</title> , p120).</p>
   <p>Remains show that it was about 150 feet wide and 16 to 17 feet deep.</p>
   <p>❦</p>
   <p>According to the description of <persName>Vitruvius</persName> (10.6) this was a screw with spiral channels, <quote>like those of a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">snail</name> shell</quote>, which turned within a wooden shaft. It was worked by man-power and did not raise the water so high as did the water-wheel.</p>
   <p><foreign xml:lang="la">Thayer's Note: For a comprehensive set of classical sources on Archimedes' screw, depictions of it in ancient art, modern diagrams, explanations, and applications, see Chris Rorres' excellent Archimedes site</foreign>.</p>
   <p>❦</p>
   <p>The <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">Nelumbium speciosum</name> ; <foreign xml:lang="la">cp. Theophrastus, Enquiry into Plants</foreign> , 4.8.7 (tr. by <persName>Hort</persName> in <title>L. C. L.</title> ) <foreign xml:lang="la">THEOPHRASTUS:HP--&gt;</foreign> .</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="81">
   <p>21 The <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">Mimusops Schimperi</name> ; cp. <persName>Theophrastus</persName>, ibid. 4.2.5 <quote>Theophrastus:HP</quote>.</p>
   <p>22 The <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">Ficus Sycamorus</name> ; cp. <persName>Theophrastus</persName>, ibid. 6.6.4 <quote>Theophrastus:HP</quote>.</p>
   <p>23 Castor-oil. Thayer's Note: See also <persName>Strabo</persName>, <placeName>XVII</placeName> .2.5 .</p>
   <p>24 Called by the Greeks also <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">hippopotamos</name> , "horse of the river," and "horse of the <placeName>Nile</placeName>."</p>
   <p>25 i.e. a harpoon.</p>
   <p>26 i.e. the heart, liver, lungs, kidneys.</p>
   <p>27 A monument of the Old Kingdom represents <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">sheep</name> treading in the seed (the reproduction appears in <persName>J. H. Breasted</persName>, A History of <placeName>Egypt</placeName> , p92).</p>
   <p>28 Cp. the <persName>Odyssey</persName> 4.86.</p>
   <p>29 These are small islands, some of which "cluster" (as the name signifies) about the island of <placeName>Delos</placeName>.</p>
   <p>30 The <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Nilometer</name> (Diodorus calls it in fact a "Niloscope") is described by <persName>Strabo</persName> (17.1.48) as a well on the bank of the <placeName>Nile</placeName> with lines on the wall to indicate the stage of the river.</p>
   <p>31 These early chroniclers belonged to the group whom <persName>Thucydides</persName> (1.21) called logographoi ("writers of prose") to distinguish them from the writers of epic. The two chief characteristics of the group were interest in mythology and lack of criticism. <persName>Hellanicus</persName> of <placeName>Mitylene</placeName> died soon after 406 B.C. ; the historical character of <persName>Cadmus</persName> of <placeName>Miletus</placeName> ( fl. sixth century B.C. ) is questioned by Schmid-Stählin ( Geschichte der griechischen Literatur , I pp691 f.); <persName>Hecataeus</persName> of <placeName>Miletus</placeName> visited <placeName>Egypt</placeName> before 526 B.C. and died soon after 494 B.C.</p>
</div>
<div type="chapter" n="32">
   <p>The second of the line, who reigned from 285 to 246 B.C. Following the custom of the Egyptian kings (cp. chap. 27) he married his sister <persName>Arsinoë</persName>, and upon her death (or possibly even before; cp. <quote>J. Beloch, Griechische Geschichte</quote>, IV.2 p586 n1 and 1 pp370 f.) established a cult of himself as ruler and of his sister-wife and consort as <name type="deity">theoi adelphoi</name> ("Brother-Sister Gods"). The epithet <foreign xml:lang="grc">philadelphos</foreign> ("sister-loving") was never borne by <persName>Ptolemy II</persName> during his lifetime; to his contemporaries he was known as "Ptolemy the son of Ptolemy" (cp. <quote>E. R. Bevan, A History of Egypt under the Ptolemaic Dynasty</quote>, p56, and <quote>Ferguson in Cambridge Ancient History</quote>, 7, p17).</p>
</div>
<div type="chapter" n="33">
   <p>Cp. p98, n1.</p>
</div>
<div type="chapter" n="34">
   <p>Book 2.32.</p>
</div>
<div type="chapter" n="35">
   <p><persName>Thales</persName> doubtless meant by "etesian" the north-west winds which blow in summer from the <placeName>Mediterranean</placeName>, but the term is not a precise one, as <persName>Diodorus</persName> shows in the following chapter.</p>
</div>
<div type="chapter" n="36">
   <p>Frg. 228, <quote>Nauck</quote> 2.</p>
</div>
<div type="chapter" n="37">
   <p>Book 2.25.</p>
</div>
<div type="chapter" n="38">
   <p>i.e. in the north latitude.</p>
</div>
<div type="chapter" n="39">
   <p><persName>Democritus</persName> was a contemporary of <persName>Socrates</persName> and the first Greek who attempted to embrace in his writings all the knowledge of his time.</p>
</div>
<div type="chapter" n="40">
   <p>Two names given to north winds.</p>
</div>
<div type="chapter" n="41">
   <p>i.e. the north-west.</p>
</div>
<div type="chapter" n="42">
   <p>i.e. there is no evidence from witnesses that they appear to be exceedingly high.</p>
</div>
<div type="chapter" n="43">
   <p>The words mean literally "poured out by a river" and "gaping."</p>
</div>
<p>44 i.e. , they postulated a south temperate zone, corresponding to the north temperate, and separated from it by the torrid zone. The <placeName>Nile</placeName>, according to them, rose in the south temperate zone. They were not in fact so far astray in the matter, the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">White Nile</name> rising just a little south of the equator, although the waters of the annual inundation come from the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Blue Nile</name>, which has its sources in the table-land of <placeName>Abyssinia</placeName>.</p>
<p>45 i.e. , water is freshened ("sweetened") by being heated.</p>
<p>46 Practically nothing more is known of <persName>Oenopides</persName> than that he was an astronomer and mathematician of the fifth century B.C.</p>
<p>47 <persName>Agatharchides</persName> was a historian and geographer of the second century B.C.</p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>