<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title xml:lang="en">Cynegetica</title>
        <author>
          <persName>GRATTIUS</persName>
          
        </author>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Encodage automatique TEI P5</resp>
          <name>zoomathia_encoder.py v3.0</name>
          <date when="2026-07-16">2026-07-16</date>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Projet Zoomathia (ANR-21-CE27-0012)</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Universite Cote d'Azur, Nice, France</pubPlace>
        <date when="2026-07-16">2026-07-16</date>
        <availability>
          <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0</licence>
        </availability>
        <idno type="zoomathia"/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Encode automatiquement par zoomathia_encoder.py v3.0 - Projet Zoomathia</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language ident="en">anglais</language>
      </langUsage>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="zoomathia">
          <term>Zoomathia</term>
          <term>animaux</term>
          <term>inconnu</term>
          <term>anglais</term>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>Fichier encode automatiquement dans le cadre du projet Zoomathia (ANR).
        Encodage produit par zoomathia_encoder.py v3.0. Verification humaine recommandee.</p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>Balisage automatique des structures textuelles et des entites nommees
        pertinentes pour Zoomathia (animaux, plantes, personnes, lieux).</p>
        <correction status="unknown">
          <p>Encodage automatique - erreurs possibles, revision manuelle recommandee.</p>
        </correction>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
<div type="section" n="1">
   <p>The beginning of hunting equipment consists in nets and the ropes of the snare.⁠ <pb n="155"/> First of all, experts prescribe that the rope along the edge of the net be twined, at the start, of <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">thin thread</name> and then fourfold strands be drawn tight to form the twist; that makes a length to stand its work; that will serve many a day.</p>
   <p>The snare itself, at the central mouth which it has when being made, you must entangle all round with six pouches so that in the whole cavity it may catch the savage <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">quarry</name>, however big he is. But I should have the whole net extend forty paces in length and rise ten full meshes in height from the ground. Nets likely to cost more outlay are unremunerative.</p>
   <p>The <placeName>Cinyphian marshes</placeName>, doubt it not, will yield excellent thread-material; there is fine produce from the <foreign xml:lang="la">Aeolian valley</foreign> of the <name type="deity">Sibyl</name>, and there is the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">flax harvest</name> on the sunny <placeName>Tuscan meadow</placeName> drinking in the neighbouring moisture from the river, where <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Tiber</name> that fertilises <placeName>Latium</placeName> glides through the shady silences and meets with mighty mouth the gulf of the sea. But on the other hand our <placeName>Falerians</placeName> have <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">flax-crops</name> unfit for conflict, and (those of) the <placeName>Spanish Saetabes</placeName> are tested by a different use.</p>
   <p>The dancing crowds of sultry <placeName>Canopus</placeName> are scarcely veiled by their transparent native <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">linen</name> when sacrifi­cing in the ritual at <placeName>Bubastis</placeName>: its very whiteness, ruinous in a material useless for nets, reveals the deceit afar off and frightens away the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">beasts</name>. Yet the poor guardian of a well-watere</p>
</div>
<div type="book" n="2">
   <p>d estate at <placeName>Alabanda</placeName> can rear a growth of <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">hemp</name>, right fitting equipment for this task of ours. Burdensome is the care needed, but you may entrap within such toils the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">bears</name> of <placeName>Thessaly</placeName>. Only, first take pains that no moisture, worst of plagues, steal thereon: <pb n="157"/> in damp equipment there is no use, no dependence.</p>
   <p>Therefore, whether streams in a narrow valley and sluggish swamps have wrought harm amid the hunter's task, or unforeseen rain from heaven shall have drenched their nets, either unfold them to face the northern breezes of serene <foreign xml:lang="la">Helice</foreign> or set them in murky smoke to slacken. For such reasons too it is forbidden to touch the first crops of <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">flax</name> before the <name type="deity">Pleiad</name> had kindled the year with ripening fires and appeared in its brilliant rising.</p>
   <p>If nets drink in breeze or smoke, their longer service answers accordingly. The chase is a mighty task, unfit to be handled, save it is mastered by pains.</p>
   <p>Do you not see the demigods whom old mythic lore records (they dared on proud-piled mountains to essay the way to heaven and assault the mothers of the gods) — at what mighty cost they hunted the woodlands without the boon of my teaching? <name type="deity">Venus</name>, baffled, still weeps and long will weep <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Adonis</name>: <persName>Ancaeus</persName> fell, arms in hand (yet was he right skilful and imposing with the double axe). The god himself, he of <placeName>Tiryns</placeName>, who civilised a barbarous world, <pb n="159"/> to whom sea and earth and the sheer gateway of <name type="deity">Pluto</name> yielded as he essayed all things where glory's path lay</p>
</div>
<div type="book" n="3">
  <p>open, even he (<persName>Hercules</persName>) won from the chase the chiefest ornament and honour of his fame. Consider, then, what benefit, derived from the arts I treat, can trick the strong <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">beasts</name> when matched against them.</p>
  <p>Some hunters have found in plumes plucked from the filthy <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">vulture</name> a handy means of working and no slight help. Only, at intervals along the line there must be added the down of the snow-white <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">swan</name>, and that is implement enough: the white feathers glitter in clear sunlight, formidable appearances for <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">game</name>,</p>
  <p>whereas the dread stench from the black <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">vulture</name> disturbs the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">forest-creatures</name>; and the contrast of colour works the better effect.</p>
  <p>But, while the plumage hanging from your device has its bright gleam or heavy scent, let it be at the same time soft to handle and not very closely entwined, so that the cord when pulled in will not entangle you with its feathers in your hurry and by its faultiness convict you in the very using.</p>
  <p>This device of terror has more use against <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">stags</name>; but when the pliant feathers are sometimes dyed with African vermilion and the flaxen cord gleams from its projecting forks,</p>
  <p>it is rare for any <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">beast</name> to escape the counterfeit terrors.</p>
  <p>Yes, and there is also some use in "running" <foreign xml:lang="la">nooses</foreign>:</p>
  <p>it is recommended to compose these of <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">deer</name>'s leather preferably: the deceit will cloak the snare through falsely suggesting a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">creature</name> of the wild.</p>
  <p>What of the hunter who to his toothed springe adds an oaken stake? How often, thanks to these tricksom</p>
</div>
<div type="book" n="4">
  <p>e devices, does one unexpectedly reap the fruit of another's toil! 24 Fortunate the man whose industry made him first inventor of arts so great! Was he a god or was that mind close kin to the gods which mightily sped its clear gaze into blind darkness and flooded the uninstructed crowd with light? Come speak, <name type="deity">Diana</name>, for 'tis heaven's will, unto a servant of the <name type="deity">Muses</name>. The story stands secure that it was an old <placeName>Arcadian</placeName> whom you, <persName>Maenalus</persName>, his witness, and you, <persName>Amyclae</persName> of <placeName>Lacedaemon</placeName>, first saw laying out hunting-nets in unaccustomed vales — <persName>Dercylos</persName> his name. Never did man bear himself more justly than he: on earth there was no other more regardful of the gods. He then it was whom the goddess fashioned in primeval fields,⁠ 25 and deigning to inscribe him as author of a mighty work, she enjoined him to go and unfold her own arts to the nations. He was the first also to dress hunting-spears with a strong <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">tooth</name>, and, controlling the angry onslaught of a forward thrust, to receive all the (<name type="animal" xml:lang="en">boar</name>'s) weight on projecting spear-guards. 26</p>
  <p>Later, there succeeded to them weapons furnished with spit-like teeth and twofold fork, and some gave their spear-ends a ring of sharp points to prevent the thick steel remaining inactive in the wounded quarry.⁠ 27 You are to shun the allurements of fleeting novelty: in this same field of hunting they do harm by a small or excessive size of spear. But slippery fashion goes its wandering round, and all men are in haste to discard usages which hav</p>
</div>
<div type="book" n="5">
   <div type="section" n="28">
      <p>e been tried. What if I choose to speak of the enormous <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Macedonian pikes</name>? How long are the shafts and how small the teeth which furnish their spikes! Or, on the other hand, how does nimble <placeName>Lucania</placeName> overload with a huge point thin rods stripped of their tender bark! All weapons have been the better fashioned by healthy moderation. Wherefore for javelins too we weigh thoroughly their manageable handling, lest their wounding power speed lightly or the weapon's force fall short.</p>
   </div>
   <div type="section" n="29">
      <p><persName>Diana</persName> herself armed her own comrades with bow and <foreign xml:lang="la">Lycian</foreign> quiver: abandon ye not the weapons of the goddess: once on a day great work was wrought by swift arrows. Now, moreover, learn the whole range of choice for strong spears.</p>
   </div>
   <div type="section" n="30">
      <p>The <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">cornel tree</name> grows abundantly in the <placeName>Thracian</placeName> valleys of the <placeName>Hebrus</placeName>; there are shady <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">myrtles</name> along the shores of <persName>Venus</persName>; there are <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">yew trees</name> and <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">pines</name> and the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">broom-plants</name> of <placeName>Altinum</placeName>, and the lopped bough more likely to help with its service the uncouth country-folk. From the <placeName>Arabians</placeName> in the East comes the branch that is far the fairest mother of fragrant <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">frankincense</name>: it draws from the laws of its birth (so have the <name type="deity">goddesses of the groves</name> ordained) its own uses and its natural shapeliness; but it is only with much toil that the other stems widely grown in our western woods are fashioned into spear-shafts. Never did bough of its own accord rise tall into the air; and the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">broom</name> curves even in its lower stem. Come, then, strip off at once the excessive growth and h</p>
   </div>
</div>
<div type="book" n="6">
  <div type="chapter" n="35">
    <p>armful branches: indulgence overloads trees with leaves. Later, when the tree proves its goodliness in its tall stems and the shapely branches tend starwards, cut round the places where suckers start and remove the rows of sprouting branches. If any sap of an injurious sort causes harm,<note xml:id="a1" type="footnote">a</note> it will flow out of these wounds and so harden the weak veins. When the shafts have risen to a height of five feet, cut them with full grasp, while the year approaches the season of fruit-laden leafage and autumn holds back the warm showers.</p>
    <p>But why do we traverse these wide rounds amidst small details? The foremost care is that of <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">dogs</name>;<note xml:id="a31" type="footnote">31</note> no other care comes before that throughout the whole system of hunting, whether you energetically pursue the untamed quarry with bare force or use skill to manage the conflict.</p>
    <p><name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Dogs</name> belong to a <foreign xml:lang="la">p167</foreign> thousand lands<note xml:id="a32" type="footnote">32</note> and they each have characteristics derived from their origin. The <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Median</name> <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">dog</name>, though undisciplined, is a great fighter, and great glory exalts the far-distant <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Celtic</name> <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">dogs</name>. Those of the <placeName>Geloni</placeName>,<note xml:id="a33" type="footnote">33</note> on the other hand, shirk a combat and dislike fighting, but they have wise instincts: the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Persian</name> is quick in both respects.<note xml:id="a34" type="footnote">34</note></p>
    <p>Some rear <placeName>Chinese</placeName><note xml:id="a35" type="footnote">35</note> <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">dogs</name>, a breed of unmanageable ferocity; but the <placeName>Lycaonians</placeName>, on the other hand, are easy-tempered and big in limb. The <placeName>Hyrcanian</placeName> <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">dog</name>, however, is not content with all the energy belonging to his stock: the females of their own will seek unions with wild beasts in the woods: <name type="deity">Venus</name> grants them meeting</p>
  </div>
</div>
<div type="book" n="7">
   <div type="section" n="35">
      <p>s and joins them in the alliance of love. Then the savage <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">paramour</name> wanders safely amid the pens of tame <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">cattle</name>, and the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">bitch</name>, freely daring to approach the formidable <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">tiger</name>, produces offspring of nobler blood. The <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">whelp</name>, however, has headlong courage: you will find him a‑hunting in the very yard and growing at the expense of much of the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">cattle</name>'s blood. Still you should rear him: whatever enormities he has placed to his charge at home, he will obliterate them as a mighty combatant on gaining the forest.</p>
      <p>But that same <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Umbrian dog</name> which has tracked wild <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">beasts</name> flees from fa­cing them. Would that with his fidelity and shrewdness in scent he could have corresponding courage and corresponding will-power in the conflict!</p>
      <p>What if you visit the straits of the <placeName>Morini</placeName>, tide-swept by a wayward sea, and choose to penetrate even among the <placeName>Britons</placeName>? <pb n="169"/>O how great your reward, how great your gain beyond any outlays! If you are not bent on looks and deceptive graces (this is the one defect of the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">British whelps</name>), at any rate when serious work has come, when bravery must be shown, and the impetuous War-god calls in the utmost hazard, then you could not admire the renowned <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Molossians</name>⁠</p>
      <p>With these last⁠ <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">cunning Athamania</name> compares her breeds; as also do <placeName>Azorus</placeName>, <placeName>Pherae</placeName> and the furtive <placeName>Acarnanian</placeName>: just as the men of <placeName>Acarnania</placeName> steal secretly into battle, so does the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">bitch</name> surprise her foes without a sound. But any <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">bitch</name> of <placeName>Aetolian</placeName> pedigree rouses with her yelps the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">boars</name> which s</p>
   </div>
</div>
<div type="book" n="8">
   <div type="section" n="35">
      <p>he does not yet see — a mischievous service, whether it is that fear makes these <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">savage sounds</name> break out or excessive eagerness speeds on uselessly. And yet you must not despise that breed as useless in all the accomplishments of the chase; they are marvellously quick, marvellously efficient in scent; besides, there is no toil to which they yield defeated.</p>
      <p>Consequently, I shall cross the advantages of different breeds:— one day an <placeName>Umbrian</placeName> mother will give to the unskilled <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Gallic</name> pups<note xml:id="n39" type="footnote">39</note> a smart disposition: <pb n="171"/>puppies of a <placeName>Gelonian</placeName> mother have drawn spirit from a <placeName>Hyrcanian</placeName> sire<note xml:id="n40" type="footnote">40</note>; and <placeName>Calydonia</placeName><note xml:id="n41" type="footnote">41</note>, good only at pointless barking, will lose the defect when improved by a sire from <placeName>Molossis</placeName>.</p>
      <p>In truth, the offspring cull the best from all the excellence of the parents, and kindly nature attends them.</p>
      <p>But if in any wise a light sort of hunting captivates you, if your taste is to hunt the timid <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">antelope</name> or to follow the intricate tracks of the smaller <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">hare</name>, then you should choose <persName>Petronian</persName><note xml:id="n42" type="footnote">42</note> dogs (such is their reputation) and swift <persName>Sycambrians</persName><note xml:id="n43" type="footnote">43</note> and the <persName>Vertraha</persName><note xml:id="n44" type="footnote">44</note> coloured with yellow spots — swifter than thought or a winged bird it runs, pressing hard on the beasts it has found, though less likely to find them when they lie hidden; this last is the well-assured glory of the <persName>Petronians</persName>.</p>
      <p>If only the latter could restrain their transports until the completion of their sport, if they could affect not to be aware of their prey and approach without barking, they would be as</p>
   </div>
</div>
<div type="section" n="9">
   <p>sured all the honour which you <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">dogs</name> of the metagon ⁠ <foreign xml:lang="la">45</foreign> breed now hold: as it is, in the forest ineffectual spirit means loss. But you metagontes have no ignoble pedigree or home.</p>
   <p><placeName>Sparta</placeName>,⁠ <foreign xml:lang="la">46</foreign> by common report, and <placeName>Crete</placeName>⁠ <foreign xml:lang="la">47</foreign> alike claim you as their own nurslings. But, <persName>Glympic</persName>⁠ <foreign xml:lang="la">48</foreign> <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">hound</name>, you were the first to wear leash on high-poised neck and he that followed you in the forest was the <placeName>Boeotian</placeName> <persName>Hagnon</persName>, <persName>Hagnon</persName> son of <persName>Astylos</persName>, <persName>Hagnon</persName>, to whom our abundant gratitude shall bear witness as pre-eminent in our practice of the chase. He saw where the easier road lay to a calling as yet nervously timorous and owing to its newness scarce established: he brought together no band of followers or implements in long array: his single metagon was taken as his guard, as the high promise of the longed-for spoil; it roams across the fields which are the haunts of <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">beasts</name>, over the wells and through the lurking-places frequented by them.</p>
   <p>’Tis the work of early dawn then, while the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">dog</name> is picking out the trail as yet unspoiled by another <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">animal</name>'s scent, if there is any confusion of tracks in that place whereby he is thrown off, he runs an outside course in a wider circle and, at last discovering beyond mistake the footprints coming out, pounces on the track like the fourfold team, the pride of <placeName>Thessaly</placeName>, which is launched forth on the <placeName>Corinthian</placeName> race-course, stirred by ancestral glory and by hopes covetous of the first prize. But lest loss be the outcome of excessive zeal, the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">dog</name>'s dutie</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="10">
   <p>s are regulated: he must not assail his foe with barking;⁠ <num type="line" n="49">49</num> he must not seize on some trivial prey or on signs of a nearer catch and so blindly lose the fruit of his first activities. When, however, better fortune already attends the outlay of toil, and the sought-for lair of the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">wild beasts</name> is near, he must both know his enemies are hidden and prove this by signs: either he shows his new-won pleasure by lightly wagging the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">tail</name>, or, digging in his own footprints with the nails of his <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">paws</name>, he gnaws the soil and sniffs the air with nostril raised high. And yet to prevent the first signs from misleading the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">dog</name> in his keenness, the hunter bids him run all about the inner space encircled by rough ground and nose the paths by which the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">beasts</name> come and go; then, if it happens that the first expectation has failed him in the place,⁠ <num type="line" n="50">50</num> he turns again to his task in wide coursings; but, if the scent was right, he will make for the first trail again as the quarry has not crossed the circle. Therefore, when full success has arrived with its proper issue, the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">dog</name> must come as comrade to share the prey and must recognise his own reward: thus let it be a delight to have given ungrudging service to the work.</p>
   <p>Such was the mighty benefit, such the surpassing prize of triumph granted to thee, great <persName>Hagnon</persName>, by favour of the <name type="deity">gods</name>: so shalt thou live for ever, as long p177 as my songs shall last, as long as the woods keep their treasures and <persName>Diana</persName>'s weapons abide on earth. 'Twas he too who d</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="11">
   <p>eveloped a species with a wild strain from the blood of the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">thoes</name> .⁠ 51 Beneath no other breast is there higher courage, whether you call them to the leash or to the test of open conflict. The <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">thoes</name> (their reputation is famous) can steal craftily on <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">lions</name> pitted against them⁠ 52 and overcome them with their short legs; for it is a small-sized breed, and one may scruple to own how ugly: it has a fox-like look: still its resolution is perfect. But there is no other breed which you could wish to train for tasks so important; or else your own mistake will find you out in the hunt when loss of game makes late-learned wisdom vain.</p>
   <p>Now then couple well-matched mates⁠ 53 and mark the offspring with the pledge of their pedigree, letting the parents who produce this wonderful progeny in the vigour of their youth yield you a fine <foreign xml:lang="grc">metagon</foreign> . First I shall mate <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">dogs</name> tried in courage, the foremost quality: the next care in the apportionment is that outward appearance shall not belie descent or lower any of its merits. They should have the face high, they should have shaggy ears by their foreheads, the mouth big, and they should breathe fiery blasts from wide nostrils; a neat belly should gird their flanks below; tail should be short and sides long, hair parted on the neck, and that</p>
   <p>neither too shaggy nor yet unable to stand cold; and then from strong limbs⁠ 54 must rise a breast capable of drawing deep breaths, and with strength left for more. Avoid the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">dog</name> that spreads its steps with</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="12">
   <p>a broad foot: he is weak in hunting-duty. I should want hardy legs with firm muscles and I should want solid feet for such struggles. But zealous and prolonged trouble is all in vain unless the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">bitch</name> is shut up in some deep retreat and secluded for a single male: otherwise she cannot at the time of coupling maintain unspoilt the pedigree of a fine sire or the pitch of past distinction won. The first unions, the first pleasure is sweetest: such frenzy has uncontrolled nature given to love. If the attendant has kept her shut up and the pregnant <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">bitch</name> has no unions with other <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">dogs</name>,</p>
   <p>give her rest and remit her usual tasks: she is barely sufficient for her own burden. Then later I shall suggest, to prevent an unruly litter of <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">whelps</name> from wearing their mother out, that you examine them by their points and thereupon pick out the inferior ones. They will themselves give indications. The puppy that one day will not fail your pride in him is scarcely yet firm in his tender limbs, and already his vigour, impatient of equality with the rest, has raised him above them: he aims at sovereignty beneath his mother's belly, keeps her teats wholly to himself, his back unencumbered</p>
   <p>and unpressed by the others so long as the genial warmth of the heavens is kind to earth; but when the evening has shrivelled him with north-western chilliness, his bad temper flags and this strong pup lets himself be snugly covered by the sluggish crowd (of the rest). It must be your care thoroug</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="13">
   <p>hly to weigh his promised strength in your hands: he will humble his <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">light brothers</name> with his weight.</p>
   <p>In these signs my poems will mislead neither myself nor you. As soon as she has produced young, you are to offer the mother different treatment and the comforts due to her, and to attend her carefully as she deserves. Exactly as she is kindly treated, she will maintain her little ones until a long service of nurture has been rendered.</p>
   <p>Then finally, when the mothers fail their offspring and their assiduity in the task of suckling has shattered them, let all your concern pass over to the deserted whelps. You must sustain the young brood with milk and a simple pap: they must not know other luxuries and the outlays of a gluttonous life: such indulgence comes home at a mighty cost. Nor is this surprising: no other life eats more into the senses of mankind, unless reason banishes it and bars the way against the approach of vices.</p>
   <p>Such was the fault that ruined Egyptian kings, as they drank old Mareotic wines in goblets of precious stone, reaping the perfumes of nard-bearing <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">Ganges</name> and ministering to vice. By this sin fell you too, <placeName>Lydia</placeName>, beneath Persian <persName>Cyrus</persName>; and yet you were rich and golden in the veins of your river.</p>
   <p>In good truth, so that nothing might be left to crown the possession of wealth, how much and how often, O <placeName>Greece</placeName>, did you too fall short of ancestral honour by gathering together the arts which luxury fashioned and by madly following the faults of <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">ot</name></p>
</div>
<div type="book" n="14">
   <div type="section" n="35">
      <p>her nations! But of what sort, how simple, was the table of our <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Camilli</name>! <pb n="185"/></p>
      <p>What was your dress, <persName>Serranus</persName>, after all your triumphs!</p>
      <p>These were the men who, in accord with the bearing and character of ancient virtue, set o'er the world <placeName>Rome</placeName> as its head; and by them was virtue exalted to heaven, and so she reached highest honours.</p>
      <p>In truth, taught by great precedent you will be able to provide for small details, finding the right system and the limits which should govern them.</p>
      <p>Therefore rule is imposed on the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">whelps</name> in the shape of a single keeper: he must control their food and punishments, their service and rest: the young pack that is to master the woods must look to him.</p>
      <p>It is no trumpery charge: whosoever has such power dedicated to him should be a youth picked by you from young folk of merit, at once prudent and, when he grasps his weapons, unflagging.</p>
      <p>But unless he knows the right ways of approach and the right moments for attack and can protect his allies when unequal to their enemy, then either the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">dogs</name> will run away or the victory so won is after all too dear.</p>
      <p>So then be wakeful for your work and attend equipped</p>
      <p>with weapons fully. Weapons make the way of the chase more keen:</p>
      <p>let bandaging protect the lower parts of the leg: the leather should be <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">calf</name>'s leather, and tawny <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">pig</name>-<name type="animal" xml:lang="en">skin</name> is fit for the march: the caps should gleam with the grey of the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">badger</name>:</p>
      <p>close under the hunter's flanks should be girt a knife of <placeName>Toledo</placeName> steel: a missile weapon brandi</p>
   </div>
</div>
<div type="book" n="15">
   <div type="section" n="35">
      <p>shed in the right hand should give a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">terrifying sound</name>, while curved reaping-hooks must break through thickets which block the way. Such is your active service in the chase. But especially is it your concern to care for the martial <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">wounds</name> suffered in fight, the maladies which stray along so many different paths, their causes and the symptoms shown by your <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">dogs</name>.</p>
      <p>Above stands Fate: the insatiable <name type="deity">Death-god</name> devours everything and echoes round the world on sable wings. Clearly for a great task still greater care must be employed, nor will the <foreign xml:lang="la">deity</foreign> play the experienced false: for this our care too there is another <name type="deity">divinity</name> easy to be entreated who can guarantee the work of healing.</p>
      <p>Nor is aid far distant, though the lips of a deep <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">wound</name> have parted and the fibres are dripping with dark blood: thereupon seize from the very enemy that has dealt the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">wound</name> some of his fetid urine, sprinkling it with the hand over the mouth of the torn <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">wound</name>, till the acid juice compresses the veins: for the avenues of death lie open.</p>
      <p>Then my advice will be to go round the lips till they are clean and sew them fast with a slender thread. But if deadly danger battens in a narrow <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">wound</name>, contrariwise, widen the outlet and expose the treacherous causes of corruption; the remedy is easy in a newly-found mischief; but the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">beasts</name> which are infected they soothe with strokes of the hands (that is enough), or seal the sore around with an ointment of black pitch: if, however, there is merely a trivial</p>
   </div>
</div>
<div type="section" n="16">
   <p>hurt in a slight wound, the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">dog</name> has the natural remedy of efficacious saliva.⁠ <note n="69">It is a serious plague, too deep for the treatments mentioned, when hidden causes have sped the malady through all the bodies of the pack and the damage is only discovered in its final consummation.</note></p>
   <p>Then has pestilence been let loose, and by contagion deaths have come upon the pack at large, and the great host alike perishes beneath an infection that falls on all: neither is there indulgence granted for any strength or service, nor is there hope of escape in answer to prayer.</p>
   <p>But whether it be that <name type="deity">Proserpina</name> has brought death forth from <placeName>Stygian</placeName> darkness, satisfying her wrath for some offence entrusted to the <name type="deity">Furies</name> to avenge, whether the infection is from on high and <foreign xml:lang="la">ether</foreign> breathes with contagious vapours, or whether <name type="placeName">earth</name> is devastating her own fair products,⁠ <note n="70">remove the source of the evil.</note></p>
   <p>I warn you to lead the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">dogs</name> over the high mountain-paths: you are to cross the broad <name type="placeName">river</name> in your flight. This is your first escape from destruction: thereafter the aids we have devised will avail and some service is secured from our lore.</p>
   <p>But varied are the onsets of disease, nor is there the same force in all of them: learn their phases and make trial of the medicine which is most available.</p>
   <p><name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Rabies</name>, prevalent among young <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">dogs</name> and uncontrollable for those who delay treatment, launches a deadly evil: it must be safer then to forestall it with remedies and overcome its first causes. For the mischie</p>
</div>
<div type="book" n="17">
   <div type="section" n="35">
      <p>vous and barbarous plague — it has been described as a tiny <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">worm</name> — steals in where the tongue is rooted to its firm ligaments. When the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">worm</name> has seized on the inwards briny with prolonged thirst, darting its sweltering fires with fevers aflame, it works its escape and spurns its bitter⁠ <pb n="71"/> quarters. Impelled, it is plain, by its activity and potent goads, <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">dogs</name> turn frantic. So, when they are quite young, it is usual to cut out with the knife the deep-seated elements and causes of disease. Prolonged treatment is not needed for the wound so made: sprinkle clean salt and soothe the affected part with a little olive-oil: before returning night can well complete her shadows, look, the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">dog</name> will be on the scene, and, forgetting the wound made, is actually fawning at table and pleading for bread⁠ <pb n="72"/> with his mouth.</p>
      <p>What need to record primitive devices and the inventions of an unsophisticated age? Of no groundless fear were those the consolations: so lasting a confidence have they prolonged.⁠ <pb n="73"/></p>
      <p>Thus there are some whose prescription has been to fasten <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">cock</name>'s combs upon the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">dog</name>-collars made from the light-shunning <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">badger</name>,⁠ <pb n="74"/> or they twine necklets around, strung of sacred shells,⁠ <pb n="75"/> and the stone of living fire⁠ <pb n="76"/> and red coral from <placeName>Malta</placeName> and <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">herbs</name> aided by magic incantations. And so the peace of the <name type="deity">gods</name> won by the protective amulet is found to vanquish baleful influences and the venom of the evil eye. But if the mange pursues a body torn with the ugly itch for scratching, i</p>
   </div>
</div>
<div type="section" n="18">
   <p>t is the cruellest road of slow death: at the first onset, the remedy is a melancholy one, but destruction must be brought off by the one life <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">of the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">dog</name></name> which has first been contaminated with the infectious disease, to prevent the whole pack from contracting the dread contagion.</p>
   <p>If, however, the ailment is slight, giving time and forewarnings at the start, learn the methods of cure and by skilled devices escape wherever feasible.</p>
   <p>Then fire is found to blend and into one whole unite p193 doses of <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">bitumen</name>, mixed with fragrant <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">wine</name>, and portions of <placeName>Bruttian</placeName>⁠ <note type="footnote" n="77">pitch and ointment from the unregarded dregs of <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">olive-oil</name>.</note></p>
   <p>Therewith they bathe the ailing <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">dogs</name>: then the anger of the malady is curbed and its severity relaxed.</p>
   <p>Let not this treatment, for all your anxiety, distract you <foreign xml:lang="la">(from further precautions)</foreign>: the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">dogs</name> must avoid both <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">rains</name> and the chills of the <placeName>north-west wind</placeName>: rather, when sultry heats hang over the bare <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">valleys</name>, take them <foreign xml:lang="la">(to heights)</foreign> away from the wind to meet the rays of the bright <name type="deity">sun</name>, so that they may sweat out all the infection and moreover that the healing which has been effected may steal into their hidden veins.⁠ <note type="footnote" n="78"/></p>
   <p>Besides the <name type="deity">Healing-God</name>, kindly disposed to our skill, fails not to regard favourably and to aid him who dips⁠ <note type="footnote" n="79"/> his <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">whelps</name> in the tide of the foaming <name type="placeName">beach</name>.</p>
   <p><name type="deity">O Experience</name>, foreseeing in affairs, how much material benefit hast thou lavished on the mass of <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">men</name>, if they make it their care to overcome <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">sloth</name> and by vigorous action to get a grip</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="19">
   <p>of fair ideals! There is in <placeName>Sicily</placeName> a grotto enormous in its rocky mass — with hollow windings which return upon themselves; high ramparts of black woodland enclose it around and streams bursting from volcanic jaws — <pb n="195"/> <name type="deity">Vulcan</name>'s acknowledged haunt. As one passes beneath, the pools lie motionless oozing in veins of natural bituminous oil.</p>
   <p>I have often seen <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">dogs</name> dragged hither fordone from mischievous wasting, and their custodians overcome by still heavier suffering.</p>
   <p>"Thee first, O <name type="deity">Vulcan</name>, and thy peace, holy dweller in this place, do we entreat: grant final aid to our wearied fortunes, and, if no guilt is here deserving penalty so great, pity these many lives and suffer them, holy one, to attain to thy fountains" — thrice does each one call, thrice they offer rich incense on the fire, and the altar is piled with fruitful branches.</p>
   <p>Hereat (wondrous to tell and a portent elsewhere unknown) from the confronting caves and the mountain's riven breast there has come, exultant in southern gales and darting forth 'mid a full flood of flame, the God himself: his priest, waving in pallid hand the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">olive</name> branch, proclaims aloud: "In the presence of the God, in the presence of the altars, I ordain that all go out of the land far from here, who have put their hands to crime or contemplated it in their heart": forthwith droop their spirits and their nervous limbs.</p>
   <p>Oh! whoso has ever impaired heaven's law in the case of a wretched suppliant, whoso for a price has dared to aim at the life of</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="20">
   <p>brothers or of faithful friend or to outrage ancestral gods — if such a man be impelled hither by audacity, the comrade of unutterable sin, he will learn how mighty is the power of <name type="deity">God</name> who followeth after as the avenger in wrath for crime committed.⁠ <pb n="197"/></p>
   <p>But he whose mind is good at heart and is reverent to the <name type="deity">God</name>, has his altar-gift gently caressed by the <name type="deity">Fire-god</name>, who himself, when the flame has reached the sacrifices offered in his honour, retreats from the holy ritual and again conceals himself in his cave. For such a one 'tis right to attain relief and <name type="deity">Vulcan</name>'s kindliness. Let there be no delay: if the malady has gnawed right into the fibres, bathe with the remedies specified⁠</p>
   <p>and soothe the suffering bodies: so will you expel the tyrannous disease. The <name type="deity">God</name> lends support, and nature herself nourishes her own skilful remedy.⁠</p>
   <p>What plague is sharper than <foreign xml:lang="la">robur</foreign>⁠ or what path nearer to death? But still for it there comes here assistance more active than the powerful anger of the ailment. Yet if a lost opportunity baffles first aid, then you must attack the furious pestilence where prospects are likeliest: sudden disturbance calls for sudden relief. The nostrils must be cut slightly with the steel, as well as the two muscles of the shoulders, and blood is to be drawn off from both ears: from the blood comes the corruption, from the blood the violence of the insatiate plague. Forthwith you will comfort the wearied body with palliatives, and you must sprinkle</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="21">
   <p>on the wounds the sediment of oil-dregs and <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">Massic</name> wine outpoured from its ancient cask — <name type="deity">Bacchus</name> expels light cares from the heart: <name type="deity">Bacchus</name> also is healing for the fury of disease. Why mention coughs, why the afflictions of a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">sluggish</name> <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">lethargy</name> or any prophylactic there is for gout that twists the limbs? A thousand plagues hold their victims, and their power transcends our care. Come, dismiss such cares (our confidence is not so great in our own resources) — dismiss them, my mind: the deity must be summoned from high <placeName>Olympus</placeName> and the protection of the <name type="deity">gods</name> invoked by suppliant ritual. For that reason we construct cross-road shrines in groves of soaring trees⁠ <pb n="199"/>84 and set our sharp-pointed torches hard by the woodland precinct of <name type="deity">Diana</name>, and the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">whelps</name> are decked with the wonted wreath, and at the centre of the cross-roads in the grove the hunters fling down among the flowers the very weapons which now keep holiday in the festal peace of the sacred rites. Then the wine-cask and cakes steaming on a green-wood tray lead the procession, with a young <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">goat</name> thrusting horns forth from tender brow, and fruit even now clinging to the branches, after the fashion of a lustral ritual at which all the youth both purify themselves in honour of the <name type="deity">Goddess</name> and render sacrifice for the bounty of the year. Therefore, when her grace is won, the <name type="deity">Goddess</name> answers generously⁠ <pb n="200"/>85 in those directions where you sue for help: whether your greater anxiety is to master the forest or to elude the plague</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="22">
   <p>s and threats of destiny, the Maiden is your mighty affiance and protection. It remains to define by their characteristics the horses which Diana's equipment can accept as useful.⁠ <pb n="201"/></p>
   <p>Not every breed has the courage needed for my profession. Some show deficiency on the score of spirit; some have feeble bodies to play them false; at times excessive mettle is unsuitable. Bethink you — what sort of <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Thessalian horse</name> bathes in <placeName>Peneus</placeName>' stream, or what is the grey sort on which its native <placeName>Mycenae</placeName> fixes its gaze? Assuredly it is huge, assuredly it will throw its legs high in air. What better steed ever traversed the race-course in <placeName>Elis</placeName>?⁠</p>
   <p>Yet let it not touch our hunting-work: its vigour is too impetuous for an attack on the hard fighting of the forests. Doubtless <placeName>Syene</placeName>⁠ <pb n="202"/> on the level plain has horses to admire which are not wild, and those of <placeName>Parthia</placeName> have kept their reputation in their own flat country: if such a horse comes to the crags of <placeName>Taburnus</placeName> near the <placeName>Caudine Forks</placeName> or to rugged <placeName>Garganus</placeName> or over the <placeName>Ligurian Alps</placeName>, he will collapse before his task with hoofs battered.⁠</p>
   <p>And yet he has spirit and will mould himself to my methods if ordered: but heaven alongside of merit imposes defects. On the other hand, you find the horses of the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Callaeci</name>⁠ <pb n="203"/> can traverse the jagged <placeName>Pyrenees</placeName>. I should not, however, venture to try the conflict with a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Spanish steed</name> to serve me: amid sharp stones they scarce yield their stubborn mouths to the steel; but all <placeName>Nasamonia</placeName> control
</p>
<div type="section" n="23">
   <p>er horses with light switches. The bold and hard-toiling <name type="people">Numidian</name> folk free theirs even <pb n="203"/> from halters: the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">horse</name> will show his vigour careering in a hundred race-courses and will work off his temper in the contest. Nor does his keep cost much: whatsoever of its own the barren earth or the small rivulet doth yield, is enough to support him. So too maintenance is easy for <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">horses</name> of the <name type="people">Bisaltae</name>⁠ <note n="93">near the <placeName>Strymon</placeName></note>:
   <quote>oh, that they could career along the highlands of the <placeName>Aetna</placeName>, the sport which <name type="people">Sicilians</name> make their own!</quote> What then, though their necks are ugly or though they have a thin spine curving along their back? Thanks to such steeds <placeName>Acragas</placeName> was praised in song by the <name type="people">Greeks</name>⁠ <note n="94"/>, thanks to such, the vanquished creatures of the wild quitted craggy <placeName>Nebrodes</placeName>⁠ <note n="95"/>.</p>
   <p>Oh, how stalwart will he be in hunting whose herds shall yield colts that can be trained! Who could dare pit against them the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">horses</name> of <placeName>Epirus</placeName>, which are distinguished by <name type="people">Greece</name> with honour scarce deserved? The chestnut-brown <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">horses</name> of <name type="place">Macedonian</name> <placeName>Ceraunus</placeName>⁠ <note n="96"/> have scanty worth as hunters: but the herds of <placeName>Cyrrha</placeName>⁠ <note n="97"/>, sacred to thee, <name type="deity">O Apollo</name>, have won high honour, whether the need be to yoke light vehicles or pull our (image-laden) cars in procession to <pb n="205"/> the shrines. For the hunter the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">horse</name>'s colour is a better ally (than its origin). His legs had best be black: let brown <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">steeds</name> be chosen . . . and those whose backs resemble spent embers. Oh, how much do the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">mares</name> of <placeName>Italy</placeName> (such is heaven's will) excel in their</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="24">
   <p>foals; how much have we outstripped the world in every practice of life; and how active the young <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">breed</name> which brightens our meadows! . . . 98</p>
   <p>The Editor's Notes: 1 Like <persName>Xenophon</persName> or the pseudo-<persName>Xenophon</persName>, <quote><foreign xml:lang="grc">Cyn. ad init. τὸ μὲν εὕρημα θεῶν κ.τ.λ.</foreign></quote>, <persName>Grattius</persName> claims a divine origin for hunting. ❦</p>
   <p>2 Good sense is got without taking <foreign xml:lang="la">armis</foreign> from <foreign xml:lang="la">armi</foreign>, "members," as <persName>Vollmer</persName> does with <persName>Barth</persName>, <persName>Burman</persName> and others. <persName>A. E. Housman</persName>, <quote>Cl. Rev. 14 (1900), 465‑66</quote>, and <persName>P. J. Enk</persName>, in his edn. 1918, take <foreign xml:lang="la">armis</foreign> from <foreign xml:lang="la">arma</foreign>. ❦</p>
   <p>3 <foreign xml:lang="la">Nuda virtute</foreign> : cf. 153 <foreign xml:lang="la">nudo marte</foreign> contrasted with <foreign xml:lang="la">ex arte</foreign>. ❦</p>
   <p>4 i.e. by training they attained to a more convenient and suitable method (<foreign xml:lang="la">via</foreign>) than the old haphazard hunting. For sense of <foreign xml:lang="la">propior</foreign> cf. <quote><foreign xml:lang="la">'WIDTH,195)" onMouseOut="nd();"&gt;Cic. ad Att. XIV . XIX</foreign></quote>, <quote>nos alium portum <foreign xml:lang="la">propiorem</foreign> huic aetati videbamus</quote>. ❦</p>
   <p>5 <persName>Herter</persName>, <quote>Rhein. Mus., 78 (1929), p366</quote>, takes <foreign xml:lang="la">centum</foreign> with <foreign xml:lang="la">divae</foreign>. ❦</p>
   <p>6 With lines 24‑60, 75‑94, on hunting-nets, cf. <persName>Xenophon</persName> <quote>Cyn. II .3‑8</quote>; <persName>Arrian</persName>, <quote>Cyn. 1</quote>; <persName>Pollux</persName>, <quote>Onomast. V .26‑32</quote>; <persName>Oppian</persName>, <quote>Cyn. I .150‑51</quote>; <persName>Nemesius</persName>, <quote>Cyn. 299 sqq.</quote> The Latin <foreign xml:lang="la">rete</foreign> ( <foreign xml:lang="grc">δίκτυον</foreign> ) means net in general, or specifically a large "hay"; <foreign xml:lang="la">plaga</foreign> ( <foreign xml:lang="grc">ἐνόδιον</foreign> ) means a net placed in the known run or track of the game; <foreign xml:lang="la">cassis</foreign> ( <foreign xml:lang="grc">ἄρκυς</foreign> ) means a funnel-shaped net resembling, according to <persName>Pollux</persName>, º a <foreign xml:lang="grc">κεκρύφαλος</foreign> ( <foreign xml:lang="la">reticulum</foreign> ) — which may be applied either to a network cap for the hair or to the bag-shaped reticule, pouch or belly of a hunting-net. ❦</p>
</div>
<p>7 Limbus , the rope along the edge of the net, corresponds to the <foreign xml:lang="grc">τόνος</foreign> in <persName>Xen.</persName> <quote>Cyn.</quote> X .2, <persName>Pollux</persName> V .27 . <persName>Grattius</persName> uses <name type="animal" xml:lang="la">limbi</name> , the plural, for the <name type="plant" xml:lang="la">fila linea</name> out of which the <name type="animal" xml:lang="la">limbus</name> is made ( <quote>Limbus grandis et capitalis linea illa est cui minores limbi quadrangulo sinuamine circumstringuntur</quote> , <persName>Barth</persName>).</p>
<p>8 <name type="animal" xml:lang="la">Ingrati</name> is predicative: "Thankless ( i.e. profitless) will be the nets that demand greater expense."</p>
<p>9 In <placeName>North Africa</placeName> between the two <name type="placeName">Syrtes</name>.</p>
<p>10 At <placeName>Cumae</placeName> on the Bay of <placeName>Naples</placeName>.</p>
<p>11 i.e. are unsuitable for nets.</p>
<p>12 In <placeName>Egypt</placeName>.</p>
<p>13 In <placeName>Caria</placeName>, <placeName>Asia Minor</placeName>.</p>
<p>14 <name type="animal" xml:lang="la">Ursa Major</name>.</p>
<p>15 Summer began with the rising of the constellation of the Seven <name type="deity" xml:lang="la">Pleiades</name> (Lat. <foreign xml:lang="la">Vergiliae</foreign> ), and winter with their setting.</p>
<p>16 i.e. <foreign xml:lang="la">si lina imbiberint flatus vel fumum</foreign> : cf. 55‑56 .</p>
<p>17 Lines 61‑74 are by some editors transposed to follow either 23 or 24.</p>
<p>18 Unsatisfying attempts have been made to read <foreign xml:lang="la">ire freta</foreign> and explain it as applicable either to the <name type="deity">giants</name> traversing the ocean of the sky in their account on heaven or even to the <persName>Argonauts</persName> crossing the sea, which is <persName>Curcio</persName>'s strange suggestion.</p>
<p>19 A son of <name type="deity">Neptune</name> and an <persName>Argonaut</persName>, who, like <persName>Adonis</persName>, was killed by a <name type="animal" xml:lang="la">boar</name>.</p>
<div type="section" n="20">
   <p>The <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">linea</name> <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">pinnis</name> districta intended to drive game into snares was called a "formido" (cf. <foreign xml:lang="la">metus</foreign>, 85); <persName>Sen.</persName>, <quote>Dial. IV.11.5</quote>; <persName>Phaedra</persName> 46‑48; <persName>Virg.</persName> <foreign xml:lang="la">G.</foreign> III.372; of the <placeName>Pharsalia</placeName><foreign xml:lang="la">formidine</foreign>, <persName>Lucan</persName> IV.437‑38. ❦</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="21">
   <p>The <foreign xml:lang="grc">ἀγκών</foreign> was a forked pole on which to spread nets. A pure Latin term for a similar trestle was the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">ames</name> of <persName>Hor.</persName> <foreign xml:lang="la">Epod.</foreign> II.33: cf. <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">varae</name>, of the <placeName>Pharsalia</placeName><foreign xml:lang="la">varis</foreign>, <persName>Lucan</persName>, <foreign xml:lang="la">Phars.</foreign> IV.439; and in Greek <foreign xml:lang="grc">στάλικες</foreign>, <foreign xml:lang="grc">σταλίδες</foreign>, or <foreign xml:lang="grc">σχαλίδες</foreign>; <persName>Xen.</persName> <foreign xml:lang="la">Cyn.</foreign> II.7, <persName>Oppian</persName>, <foreign xml:lang="la">Cyn.</foreign> I.151. ❦</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="22">
   <p><persName>Enk</persName>, pp36‑38, has a full note on different interpretations of <foreign xml:lang="la">laquei curraces</foreign>. ❦</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="23">
   <p>i.e. the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">cervinus nervus</name> will have the smell of the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">cervus</name>. ❦</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="24">
   <p>An animal partly lamed or dragging with it the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">robur</name> would be easily caught. ❦</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="25">
   <p><placeName>Arcadia</placeName>. ❦</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="26">
   <p>The term <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">morae</name> is applied to projecting metal <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">alae</name> or <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">orbes</name> fixed behind the spear-head so as to hinder the spear from going too deeply into the beast. ❦</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="27">
   <p>The sharp points would make the wound worse. ❦</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="28">
   <p><name type="weapon">Vulnus</name> is used of the weapon which wounds in <persName>Virgil</persName>. <foreign xml:lang="la">Aen.</foreign> <quote><foreign xml:lang="la">IX</foreign> .745</quote>, of <persName>Vergil</persName>'s <foreign xml:lang="la">Aeneid</foreign> <quote><foreign xml:lang="la">X</foreign> .140</quote> ; of <persName>Silius Italicus</persName> <quote><foreign xml:lang="la">Sil. Ital.</foreign> I .397</quote> ; of the <foreign xml:lang="la">Argonautica</foreign> <quote><foreign xml:lang="la">Val. Flacc.</foreign> III .197</quote> . Illi sc. <name type="weapon">vulneri</name> i.e. <name type="weapon">iaculo</name> . ❦</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="29">
   <p>i.e. in <placeName>Cyprus</placeName> . ❦</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="30">
   <p>On the <placeName>Adriatic</placeName> shore, not far from <placeName>Venice</placeName> . ❦</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="31">
   <p>On <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">dogs</name> generally see <persName>Xenophon</persName> <foreign xml:lang="grc">Cyn.</foreign> III‑IV , VII ; <persName>Aristotle</persName>, <foreign xml:lang="la">Hist. An.</foreign> 574 A 16 sqq. and passim ; <persName>Arrian</persName> <foreign xml:lang="grc">Cyn.</foreign> 2 sqq. ; <persName>Pollux</persName> <foreign xml:lang="grc">Onom.</foreign> V .37 sqq. ; <foreign xml:lang="la">Geoponica</foreign> (10th cent.) XIX .1 sqq. ; <persName>Virgil</persName> <foreign xml:lang="la">G.</foreign> III .404 sqq. ; <persName>Varro</persName>, <foreign xml:lang="la">R. R.</foreign> II .9 ; <persName>Pliny</persName> <foreign xml:lang="la">N. H.</foreign> VIII .142 sqq. ; <persName>Columella</persName> <foreign xml:lang="la">R. R.</foreign> VII .12‑13 ; <persName>Nemesius</persName> <foreign xml:lang="la">Cyn.</foreign> 103 sqq. ; <persName>Oppian</persName>, <foreign xml:lang="grc">Cyn.</foreign> I .368‑588 ; <persName>Claudian</persName> <foreign xml:lang="la">Stil.</foreign> III .298‑301 . ❦</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="32">
   <p>i.e. the breeds are innumerable: cf. <persName>Oppian</persName>, <foreign xml:lang="grc">Cyn.</foreign> I .400 , <foreign xml:lang="grc">τὰ δὲ μυρία φῦλα πέλονται</foreign> . ❦</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="33">
   <p>A <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Sarmatian</name> tribe in the region of the modern <placeName>Ukraine</placeName> . ❦</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="34">
   <p>In <name type="quality">pugnacity</name> and <name type="quality">sagacity</name> . ❦</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="35">
   <p>Or, possibly, <placeName>Tibetan</placeName> . ❦</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="36">
   <p><name type="animal" xml:lang="en">British</name> <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">dogs</name> were, <persName>Strabo</persName> tells us, <foreign xml:lang="la">IV . V .2</foreign> ( <foreign xml:lang="la">C 199</foreign>) , exported as <foreign xml:lang="grc">εὐφυεῖς πρὸς τὰς κυνηγεσίας</foreign> . Cf. <persName>Nemesius</persName> 225 , <quote>divisa Britannia mittit / Veloces nostrique orbis venatibus aptos</quote> : <persName>Claudian</persName> <foreign xml:lang="la">Stil.</foreign> III .301 , <quote>magnaque taurorum fracturae colla Britannae</quote> . The <name type="ethnic">Morini</name> were northern <name type="ethnic">Gauls</name> whose chief town <placeName>Gesoriacum</placeName> became <placeName>Bononia</placeName> (<placeName>Boulogne</placeName>) . ❦</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="28">
   <p>37 <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Molossian dogs</name> are frequently mentioned in ancient literature: e.g. <persName>Aristophanes</persName>. <foreign xml:lang="grc">Θεσμοφοριάζουσαι</foreign> 416; <persName>Pollux</persName> <foreign xml:lang="grc">Ὀνομαστικόν</foreign> V .37; <persName>Oppian</persName> <foreign xml:lang="grc">Κυνηγετικά</foreign> I .375; <persName>Plautus</persName> <foreign xml:lang="la">Captivi</foreign> 86; of the <foreign xml:lang="la">de Natura Rerum</foreign> <persName>Lucretius</persName> V .1063; <persName>Virgil</persName> <foreign xml:lang="la">Georgica</foreign> III .405; <persName>Horace</persName> <foreign xml:lang="la">Epodes</foreign> VI .5; <foreign xml:lang="la">Satires</foreign> II . VI .114; of the <foreign xml:lang="la">Pharsalia</foreign> <persName>Lucan</persName> IV .440; <persName>Seneca</persName> <foreign xml:lang="la">Phaedra</foreign> 33; <persName>Statius</persName> <foreign xml:lang="la">Thebaid</foreign> III .203, of <persName>Statius</persName> <foreign xml:lang="la">Silvae</foreign> II . VI .19; of <persName>Statius</persName> <foreign xml:lang="la">Achilleid</foreign> I .747; of the <foreign xml:lang="la">Epigrams</foreign> of <persName>Martial</persName> XII . I .1; <persName>Claudian</persName> <foreign xml:lang="la">Stilicho</foreign> II .215, III .293; <persName>Nemesianus</persName> <foreign xml:lang="la">Cynegetica</foreign> 107 . ❦</p>
   <p>38 It seems appropriate to take his of <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Molossian dogs</name> rather than of British, as the proper names refer to neighbouring districts of <placeName>Epirus</placeName>, <placeName>Thessaly</placeName>, <placeName>Aetolia</placeName> and <placeName>Acarnania</placeName>. <placeName>Athamania</placeName> is a district in <placeName>Epirus</placeName> near the <placeName>Pindus</placeName> range. ❦</p>
   <p>39 Cf. the qualities suggested in 171‑73, and 156. "Gallic" in 194 may mean "Galatian": see Introduction . ❦</p>
   <p>40 Cf. 157‑58 and 161‑63 . ❦</p>
   <p>41 i.e. <placeName>Aetolia</placeName>: cf. 186‑92 . ❦</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="29">
   <p>42 <persName>Petroni</persName>: possibly <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">dogs</name> workable on stony ground ( <foreign xml:lang="la">petra</foreign> ). ❦</p>
   <p>43 <name type="placeName">Sycambri</name>, a tribe of Western Germany near the <name type="placeName">Rhine</name>. ❦</p>
   <p>44 Perhaps <foreign xml:lang="la">Vertagra</foreign>: cf. Italian <foreign xml:lang="it">veltro</foreign>, a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">greyhound</name>. MSS. of of the <persName>Epigrams</persName> of <persName>Martial</persName>, XIV . CC .1 give the forms <foreign xml:lang="la">vertrăcus</foreign>, <foreign xml:lang="la">vertăgus</foreign>, <foreign xml:lang="la">vetrăgus</foreign>. The word seems to be Celtic: <persName>Arrian</persName>, <foreign xml:lang="la">Cyneg.</foreign> 3.6, <quote>αἱ δὲ ποδώκεις κύνες αἱ Κελτικαὶ καλοῦνται μὲν οὐέρτραγοι φωνῇ τῇ Κελτῶν</quote> . . . It has sometimes been explained as a "tumbler" <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">dog</name> that inveigled game by rolling himself into a heap to disguise his appearance. ❦</p>
   <p>45 The <foreign xml:lang="la">μετάγων</foreign> is mentioned only by <persName>Grattius</persName>. <persName>Burman</persName> suggested the word implied the tracking of game: <persName>Ulitius</persName> and <persName>Curcio</persName> take it of the cross-breeding of the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">dog</name>. ❦</p>
   <p>46 For <name type="placeName">Spartan</name> or <name type="placeName">Lacedaemonian</name> <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">dogs</name> cf. <persName>Soph.</persName> <foreign xml:lang="la">Aj.</foreign> 8; <persName>Xen.</persName> <foreign xml:lang="la">Cyn.</foreign> III .1; <persName>Opp.</persName> <foreign xml:lang="la">Cyn.</foreign> I .372; <persName>Pollux</persName>, V .37 ; <persName>Virg.</persName> <foreign xml:lang="la">G.</foreign> III .405 ; <persName>Hor.</persName> <foreign xml:lang="la">Epod.</foreign> VI .5 ; <persName>Ov.</persName> <foreign xml:lang="la">Met.</foreign> III .208 , of <persName>Ovid</persName>'s <foreign xml:lang="la">Metamorphoses</foreign> 233 ; <persName>Sen.</persName> <foreign xml:lang="la">Phaedra</foreign> , 35 ; of the <persName>Pharsalia</persName> <persName>Lucan</persName>, IV .441 ; <persName>Claud.</persName> <foreign xml:lang="la">Stil.</foreign> III .300 ( <foreign xml:lang="la">tenuesque Lacaenae</foreign> ); <persName>Nemes.</persName> <foreign xml:lang="la">Cyn.</foreign> 107 , etc. ❦</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="30">
   <p>For <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Cretan dogs</name> cf. <persName>Xen.</persName> <name type="work">Cyn.</name> X .1; <persName>Poll.</persName> V .37; <persName>Opp.</persName> <name type="work">Cyn.</name> I .373; <persName>Ov.</persName> <name type="work">Met.</name> III .</p>
   <p><quote>of Ovid's Metamorphoses <foreign xml:lang="la">'Cnosius '</foreign></quote> 208 , <quote>of Ovid's Metamorphoses <foreign xml:lang="la">'vulnera fecit '</foreign></quote> 233 ; <quote><persName>Sen.</persName> <name type="work">Phaedra</name> , 34 ; <persName>Claud.</persName> <name type="work">Stil.</name> III .300 ( <foreign xml:lang="la">hirsutae Cressae </foreign> ), etc.</quote></p>
   <p>The reference is to a locality on the <placeName>Argive</placeName> and <placeName>Laconian</placeName> border.</p>
   <p>Cf. <persName>Lucan</persName>, <name type="work">Phars.</name> IV .441 , <quote><foreign xml:lang="la">nec creditur ulli Silva cani nisi qui presso vestigia rostro Colligit et praeda nescit latrare reperta</foreign></quote> , and <persName>Pliny</persName>'s description of the silent tracking of game, <persName>Plin.</persName> <name type="work">N. H.</name> VIII .147 , <quote><foreign xml:lang="la">quam silens et occulta sed quam significans demonstratio est cauda primum deinde rostro</foreign></quote> .</p>
   <p>i.e. if the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">animal</name> has already escaped and is no longer lying hidden there.</p>
   <p>The <foreign xml:lang="grc">θῶες</foreign> of <persName>Oppian</persName>, <name type="work">Cyneg.</name> III .336‑38 , are <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">jackals</name> sprung from a union of <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">wolves</name> with <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">leopards</name>. The <foreign xml:lang="grc">θώς</foreign> of <persName>Aristotle</persName> is perhaps rather a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">civet</name> than a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">jackal</name>. <persName>Pliny</persName>, <name type="work">N. H.</name> VIII .123 , mentions <foreign xml:lang="grc">thoes</foreign> as a kind of <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">wolf</name>.</p>
   <p>e.g. in the public games at <placeName>Rome</placeName>.</p>
   <p>For the mating of <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">dogs</name>, with 263 sqq. cf. <persName>Nemesianus</persName>, <name type="work">Cyn.</name> 103 sqq. ; <persName>Oppian</persName>, <name type="work">Cyn.</name> I .376 sqq.</p>
   <p>The shoulder-blades should be broad, as in <persName>Oppian</persName>, <name type="work">Cyn.</name> I .409 , <foreign xml:lang="grc">εὐρέες ὠμοπλάται</foreign> ; cf. <persName>Xen.</persName> <name type="work">Cyn.</name> IV .1; <persName>Pollux</persName>, V .58 ; <persName>Arr.</persName> <name type="work">Cyn.</name> 5.9; <persName>Colum.</persName> <name type="work">R. R.</name> VII . XII .4</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="31">
   <p>Vollmer's inclusion of the <foreign xml:lang="la">si tenuit</foreign> clause in the preceding sentence, with <foreign xml:lang="la">hunc . . . furorem</foreign> as a parenthesis, is unsatisfactory.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="32">
   <p>Cf. note on <foreign xml:lang="la">illum . . . mergentem</foreign>, 424‑5.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="33">
   <p>Or "high tasks to which you may call him."</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="34">
   <p>i.e. during the sunny day.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="35">
   <p>Cf. <persName>Livy</persName> IX.34 . . . <quote>ad servorum ministerium deduxisti</quote> (= brought down, degraded). The reference is not to exact weighing in a <name type="object">trutina</name> or <name type="object">balance</name>.</p>
   <p>The text is uncertain; but the sense required is that the greater the care lavished on the mother, the longer she will be able to give milk to her <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">pups</name>.</p>
   <p>The river <placeName>Pactolus</placeName> was famous for its golden sands. Postgate's <foreign xml:lang="la">Pactolique aurea venis</foreign> suggests that <foreign xml:lang="la">fluminis</foreign> was a gloss on the original reading.</p>
   <p>The plural alludes rhetorically to <persName>M. Fulvius Camillus</persName>, the conqueror of <placeName>Veii</placeName>, who saved <placeName>Rome</placeName> after the Allian disaster: for his poverty cf. <persName>Horace</persName> <quote>Odes</quote>, Book I, <foreign xml:lang="la">paupertas</foreign>, 185.</p>
   <p><persName>C. Atilius Regulus Serranus</persName> was consul in 257 and in 250 B.C. He was summoned from farm-work to undertake a military command, <persName>Valerius Maximus</persName> IV.IV.5; of <persName>Virgil</persName>'s <quote>Aeneid</quote> <foreign xml:lang="la">tu Maximus</foreign>, 195.</p>
   <p><foreign xml:lang="la">factus</foreign>, if sound, must have the force of <foreign xml:lang="la">instructus</foreign>.</p>
   <p><foreign xml:lang="la">Via</foreign> is the method of the hunt, cf. 5. Johnson's <foreign xml:lang="la">virum</foreign> is attractive, "make the hunter keen."</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="66">
   <p>The nose, chin, lower sides of the cheeks and the mid forehead of the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">badger</name> ( <foreign xml:lang="la">maeles</foreign> ) are white: the ends of the hairs on the body are at bottom yellowish-white, in the middle black, and at the ends ash-coloured or grey: hence the proverb "as grey as a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">badger</name>." The skin dressed without removing the hair can be used for caps or pouches.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="67">
   <p><name type="deity">Diana</name>.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="68">
   <p><name type="deity">Paean</name>.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="69">
   <p>i.e. he licks the wound.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="70">
   <p>i.e. with the result that they rot and cause disease.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="71">
   <p>With the meaning of <foreign xml:lang="la">amaram</foreign> compare <foreign xml:lang="la">salsa</foreign> in 388.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="72">
   <p>The goddess' name is put by metonymy for bread; cf. <quote><persName>Nemesius</persName> <name type="work">Cynegetica</name> 154</quote>, <quote><persName>Virgil</persName> <name type="work">Georgics</name> I.297</quote>; <quote><persName>Cicero</persName> <name type="work">De Natura Deorum</name> II.23.60</quote>; <quote><persName>Aetna</persName> 10</quote>.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="73">
   <p>The omission of a punctuation mark after <foreign xml:lang="la">falsi</foreign> would imply in <persName>Grattius</persName> an Epicurean disdain for primitive superstition: "those consolations of a groundless fear did not continue to command such a lasting belief." According to the text here accepted, <persName>Grattius</persName> seems to admit that superstitious cures soothed reasonable fears, and remained long in vogue.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="74">
   <p>The <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">badger</name> burrows under ­ground, confining itself to its hole during the day and feeding at night.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="75">
   <p>Among prophylactic amulets the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">conchae</name> were sacred to <name type="deity">Venus</name>. <persName>Pliny</persName>, <quote>N. H. XXXII .2‑6</quote>, mentions the shell <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">echeneis</name> or <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">remora</name>, believed to have power to stop ships by adhering to the hull. The marvellous properties of such shells, he considers, became the more credible because they were preserved and consecrated in the temple of <name type="deity">Venus</name> at <placeName>Cnidos</placeName>.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="76">
   <p><name type="plant" xml:lang="en">Pyrites</name> : cf. <persName>Pliny</persName>, <quote>N. H. XXXVI .137</quote>, <foreign xml:lang="la">molarem quidam pyriten vocant</foreign> : cf. <quote>Aetna</quote>, 454.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="77">
   <p><foreign xml:lang="grc">Ἱππώνιον</foreign> is <placeName>Vibo Valentia</placeName> on the <placeName>Via Popilia</placeName> in the territory of the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Bruttii</name>. <persName>Curcio</persName> thinks that <placeName>Hippo</placeName> in <placeName>Numidia</placeName> is meant.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="78">
   <p><name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Vadis</name> is also explained as (1) pores (<persName>Enk</persName>), (2) intestines (<persName>Radermacher</persName>). <persName>Vollmer</persName> imagines a contrast between <foreign xml:lang="la">latentibus vadis</foreign>, meaning <foreign xml:lang="la">ex aquis reconditis</foreign>, and the open sea of the next sentence.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="79">
   <p>The Latin of <foreign xml:lang="la">illent mergentem</foreign> in the sense of <foreign xml:lang="la">illent qui mergit</foreign> is questionable; but cf. <foreign xml:lang="la">ille . . . defecturus</foreign>, 291. <persName>Vollmer</persName> proposes tentatively <foreign xml:lang="la">illic</foreign> or <foreign xml:lang="la">ullum</foreign>.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="80">
   <p><foreign xml:lang="la">ira commissa</foreign> (a curious consideration recalling <foreign xml:lang="la">commissa piacula</foreign>, of <persName>Vergil</persName>'s <quote>Aeneid</quote> <quote>VI .569</quote>) is here taken with <persName>Wernsdorf</persName> to mean <foreign xml:lang="la">ira quae commissis sceleribus provocata est</foreign>. The sense is different in 374, <foreign xml:lang="la">Furiis commissam . . . iram</foreign>, unless 455 can imply "in wrath assigned to him to vent."</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="81">
   <p>e.g. the oil from the bituminous lake of 434.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="82">
   <p>In the form of fire and <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">bitumen</name>.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="83">
   <p>The disease has the symptoms of tetanus according to veterinary writers: <persName>Vegetius</persName>, <quote>Mulomedicina</quote> 2, 88; <persName>Chiron</persName>, 315; <persName>Pelagonius</persName>, ed. <persName>Ihm</persName>, 294.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="84">
   <p>483‑96, description of an <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Ambarval</name> sacrifice to <name type="deity">Diana</name>, with allusion to her worship near <placeName>Aricia</placeName>.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="85">
   <p><name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Multa</name>, nom. sing. fem., agreeing with <foreign xml:lang="la">dea</foreign> understood: i.e. "in full force" (like <foreign xml:lang="grc">πολὺς ῥεῖ</foreign> in Greek). <persName>Enk</persName> thinks <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">multa</name> neut. plur.; <persName>Vollmer</persName> takes it for <foreign xml:lang="la">mulcta</foreign> in the sense of "mollified."</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="86">
   <p><name type="deity">Dianae</name> <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">arma</name> = the chase. For <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">horses</name> in general see <persName>Xen.</persName> <quote>Cyn.</quote> 1; <persName>Pollux</persName>, <quote>Onom.</quote> I .188 sqq. ; <persName>Virg.</persName> <quote>G.</quote> III .72 sqq. ; <persName>Varro</persName> <quote>R. R.</quote> II .7 ; <persName>Columella</persName>, VI .26‑29 ; <persName>Plin.</persName> <quote>N. H.</quote> VIII .154 ; <persName>Nemes.</persName> <quote>Cyn.</quote> 240 sqq. ; <persName>Oppian</persName>, <quote>Cyn.</quote> I .158‑367 .</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="87">
   <p>i.e. at the Olympic games.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="88">
   <p><placeName>Syene</placeName> (<placeName>Assouan</placeName>) in Upper Egypt below the First Cataract.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="89">
   <p><placeName>Taburnus</placeName> was in <placeName>Samnium</placeName>: <placeName>Garganus</placeName> in <placeName>Apulia</placeName>.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="90">
   <p>i.e. owing to the stony nature of the ground.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="91">
   <p>The <persName>Callaeci</persName> were a people of <placeName>Hispania Tarraconensis</placeName>.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="92">
   <p>The <persName>Nasamonian</persName> tribe dwelt in the eastern part of the <placeName>Syrtis Major</placeName> in N. Africa.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="93">
   <p>In <placeName>Thrace</placeName>. <persName>Grattius</persName> proceeds to express a wish that these <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">horses</name> of <placeName>Thrace</placeName> could have the chance of showing their powers on the mountains of <placeName>Sicily</placeName>. The <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">horses</name> of <placeName>Sicily</placeName> are mentioned for their swiftness, <quote><persName>Oppian</persName>, <foreign xml:lang="la">Cyn.</foreign> I .272</quote>. Their victories in horse-racing and chariot-racing are the themes of many of <persName>Pindar</persName>'s odes: e.g. <foreign xml:lang="la">Pyth.</foreign> I celebrates a victory won by <persName>Hieron</persName> of <placeName>Aetna</placeName> ( cf. <persName>Grattius</persName> 524 ). Qualities of speed and surefootedness requisite in Sicilian sport ( cf. <foreign xml:lang="la">qui ludus Siculis</foreign>, 525, and <foreign xml:lang="la">fragosum Nebroden</foreign>, 527‑528 ) explained to <persName>Grattius</persName>' mind how, though not of prepossessing appearance, these <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">horses</name> could be trained to win glory in the games of <placeName>Greece</placeName> ( <foreign xml:lang="la">cantatus Graiis Acragas</foreign>, 527 ).</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="94">
   <p><persName>Pindar</persName>, <foreign xml:lang="la">Olymp.</foreign> III .2, <foreign xml:lang="grc">κλεινὰν Ἀκραγάντα</foreign> (= <placeName>Agrigentum</placeName> in <placeName>Sicily</placeName>, now <placeName>Girgenti</placeName>). <foreign xml:lang="la">Olympian</foreign> Odes II and III celebrate victories won by <persName>Theron</persName> of <placeName>Acragas</placeName> in chariot-racing; <foreign xml:lang="la">Pyth.</foreign> VI and <foreign xml:lang="la">Isthm.</foreign> II similar victories by <persName>Xenocrates</persName> of <placeName>Acragas</placeName>.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="95">
   <p>A <placeName>Sicilian</placeName> mountain. <foreign xml:lang="la">Fragosum</foreign> indicates the serviceability of <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">horses</name> of <placeName>Sicily</placeName> as hunters on rocky ground.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="96">
   <p>The fact that <placeName>Pella</placeName> was in <placeName>Macedonia</placeName> and the <placeName>Ceraunian</placeName> range in <placeName>Epirus</placeName> does not justify the epithet <foreign xml:lang="la">Pellaei</foreign>; but, as <persName>Enk</persName> says, "<quote>poeta parum curat geographiam.</quote>"</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="97">
   <p><placeName>Cyrrha</placeName> or <placeName>Cirrha</placeName>, a seaport in <placeName>Phocia</placeName>, near <placeName>Parnassus</placeName> on which was the Delphic oracle of <name type="deity">Apollo</name>.</p>
</div>
    </div>
  </body>
</text></TEI>
