<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng"
    type="application/xml"
    schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title xml:lang="en">Θηριακά</title>
        <title type="alt" xml:lang="fr">Les thériaques</title>
        <title type="alt" xml:lang="en">On Venomous Animals</title>
        <author>
          <persName>NICANDER COLOPHONIUS</persName>
          <idno type="zoomathia">tlg0022</idno>
        </author>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Encodage automatique TEI P5</resp>
          <name>zoomathia_encoder.py v3.0</name>
          <date when="2026-07-02">2026-07-02</date>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Projet Zoomathia (ANR-21-CE27-0012)</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Universite Cote d'Azur, Nice, France</pubPlace>
        <date when="2026-07-02">2026-07-02</date>
        <availability>
          <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0</licence>
        </availability>
        <idno type="zoomathia">tlg0022</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Encode automatiquement par zoomathia_encoder.py v3.0 - Projet Zoomathia</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language ident="en">anglais</language>
      </langUsage>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="zoomathia">
          <term>Zoomathia</term>
          <term>animaux</term>
          <term>antique (800 av. J.-C. - 300 ap. J.-C.)</term>
          <term>anglais</term>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>Fichier encode automatiquement dans le cadre du projet Zoomathia (ANR).
        Encodage produit par zoomathia_encoder.py v3.0. Verification humaine recommandee.</p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>Balisage automatique des structures textuelles et des entites nommees
        pertinentes pour Zoomathia (animaux, plantes, personnes, lieux).</p>
        <correction status="unknown">
          <p>Encodage automatique - erreurs possibles, revision manuelle recommandee.</p>
        </correction>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
Voici l'encodage TEI P5 strictement conforme à vos exigences pour le premier morceau (1/43) des *Thériaka* de Nicandre de Colophon, en respectant toutes les règles Zoomathia :


<div type="book" n="1">
   <milestone unit="section" n="1"/>
   <p>Nicander: <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Alexipharmaca</name> and <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Georgica</name></p>

   <p><pb n="1"/>
   <persName>Nicander</persName> of <placeName>Colophon</placeName> was a Greek poet, who probably lived in the middle of the 2nd century B.C.  He was the author of two surviving poems, <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Theriaca</name> and <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Alexipharmaca</name>, and also of several other poems that are now lost.  Some excerpts from his <foreign xml:lang="la">Georgica</foreign> have been preserved by <persName>Athenaeus</persName>; it is likely that this poem influenced <persName>Vergil</persName> when he wrote his <foreign xml:lang="la">Georgics</foreign> ( see <quote><persName>Quintilian</persName>, 10.1.56</quote> ), but to what extent is unknown.</p>

   <p>This translation is by <persName>A.S.F.Gow</persName> &amp; <persName>A.F.Scholfield</persName> (1953). Because all of <persName>Nicander</persName>'s poems contain a bewildering number of <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">plant</name> names, wherever possible links have been provided to the relevant <placeName>wikipedia</placeName> articles, in line with the translators' notes in their <foreign xml:lang="en">'Index of Fauna, Flora etc.'</foreign>.</p>

   <p><foreign xml:lang="la">Georgica</foreign> →</p>

   <p><persName>NICANDER</persName>, <quote>'<name type="animal" xml:lang="en">ALEXIPHARMACA</name>'</quote></p>

   <p>The Greek text of the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Alexipharmaca</name> can be found on the <placeName>Poesia Latina</placeName> website.</p>
</div>
<div type="book" n="2">
   <div type="section" n="2/43">
      <p>Even though the peoples from whom you and I, <persName>Protagoras</persName>, have derived our births did not set up the walls of their strong towers side by side in Asia, and a great space separates us, yet I can easily instruct you in the remedies for those draughts of poison which attack men and bring them low.</p>
      <p>You indeed have made your home by the tempestuous sea beneath bossy <foreign xml:lang="grc">Ἄρκτος</foreign>, where are the caverns of <placeName>Lobrinian Rhea</placeName> and the place of the secret rites of <name type="deity">Attes</name>; while I dwell where the sons of the far-famed <persName>Creusa</persName> divided among themselves the richest portion of the mainland, settling by the tripods of <name type="deity">Apollo</name> in <placeName>Clarus</placeName>.</p>
      <p>You must, to be sure, learn of the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">aconite</name>, bitter as gall, deadly in the mouth, which the banks of <placeName>Acheron</placeName> put forth. There is the abyss of the Wise Counsellor {<name type="deity">Hades</name>} whence few escape, and there the towns of <placeName>Priolas</placeName> fell crashing in ruins.</p>
   </div>
</div>
Voici l'encodage TEI P5 strictement conforme à vos exigences pour le texte de Nicander Colophonius (Θηριακά, section 3/43) :


<div type="book" n="3">
  <div type="section" n="3">
    <p>All the drinker's jaws and the roof of his mouth and his gums are constricted by the bitter draught, as it wraps itself about the top of the chest, crushing with evil choking the man in the throes of heartburn. The top of the belly is gripped with pain - <milestone unit="section" n="20"/> the swelling, open mouth of the lower stomach, which some call the <quote>'heart'</quote> of the digestive vessel, others the <quote>'receiver'</quote> of the stomach - and the gate is closed immediately upon the beginning of the intestines where a man's food in all its abundance is carried in. And all the while from his streaming eyes drips the moisture; and his belly sore shaken vainly throws up wind, and much of it settles below about his mid-navel; and in his head is a grievous weight, and there ensues a rapid throbbing beneath his temples, and with his eyes he sees things double, like a man at night overcome with unmixed wine.</p>
    <p><milestone unit="section" n="30"/> And as when the Silens, the nurses of the <name type="deity">Dionysus</name> with the horns, crushed the wild grapes, and having for the first time fortified their spirits with the foaming drink, were confused in their sight and on reeling feet rushed madly about the hill of <placeName>Nysa</placeName>, even so is the sight of these men darkened beneath the weight of evil doom.</p>
    <p>This <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">plant</name> men call also <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">Mouse-bane</name>, for it utterly destroys troublesome, nibbling <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">mice</name>; but some call it <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">Leopard's-choke</name>, since cowherds and goatherds with it contrive the death of those great <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">beasts</name> amid the glades of <placeName>Ida</placeName> in the vale of <placeName>Phalacra</placeName>. Again they name it <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">Woman-killer</name> and <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Crayfish</name>. An</p>
  </div>
</div>
<pb n="4"/>
<p>d the deadly <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">aconite</name> flourishes amid the <placeName>Aconaean</placeName> mountains.</p>
Voici l'encodage TEI P5 strictement conforme à vos exigences pour le passage de Nicandre de Colophon, *Thériaques* 5/43 :


<div type="book" n="5">
  <div type="section" n="43">
    <p>For one so poisoned <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">gypsum</name> to the weight of a handful will perhaps be a protection, if you draw thereto <foreign xml:lang="en">tawny</foreign> <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">wine</name> in due measure with the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">gypsum</name> reduced to fine powder - let it be a full <foreign xml:lang="en">cotyle</foreign> of <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">wine</name> - and add stalks of <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">wormwood</name>, cutting them from the shrub, or of bright green <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">horehound</name> which they call <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">Honeyleaf</name>; administer also a shoot of the herbaceous, evergreen <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">spurge-olive</name> and <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">rue</name>, quenching in <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">vinegar</name> and <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">honey</name> <milestone unit="section" n="50"/> a red-hot lump of metal between the jaws of the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">fire-tongs</name>, or <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">dross</name> of <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">iron</name> which the flame of the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">fire</name> has separated within the melting-pot in the furnace; or sometimes just after warming in the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">fire</name> a lump of <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">gold</name> or <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">silver</name> you should plunge it in the turbid draught.</p>
    <p>Or again you should take leaves, half a handful's weight, of the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">ground pine</name>; or a dry sprig of <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">pot marjoram</name> from the hills, or cut a fresh spray of <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">field basil</name>, and cover them in four <foreign xml:lang="en">cyathi</foreign> of <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">honey-sweet wine</name>. Or you may take some broth, still meaty and undiluted, made from a domestic <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">fowl</name> <milestone unit="section" n="60"/> when the forcible glow of the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">fire</name> beneath the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">pot</name> reduces the body to pieces. Also you should render down the fresh meat of an <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">ox</name> abounding in fat and satisfy the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">stomach</name> to its full capacity with the soup. Again, sometimes you should pour the juice of <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">balsam</name> into some drops of <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">milk</name> from a young girl, or else into <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">water</name>, until the patient discharges from his throat the undigested food. Sometimes too you should cut out the curd from the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">stomach</name> of the nimble beast that sleeps open-eyed <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">hare</name>.</p>
  </div>
</div>
<div type="book" n="6">
   <div type="section" n="43">
      <p>of a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">fawn</name>, and give it mixed in wine; at other times cast the roots of the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">purple mulberry</name> into the hollow of a mortar, <milestone unit="section" n="70"/> bray them mingled with wine, and give them boiled in the labours of the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">bee</name>. Thus may you ward off loathsome sickness though it threaten to master a man, and he may once again walk on unfaltering feet.</p>
      <p>In the second place consider the hateful brew compounded with gleaming, deadly <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">white lead</name> whose fresh colour is like milk which foams all over when you milk it rich in the springtime into the deep pails. Over the victim's jaws and in the grooves of the gums is plastered an astringent froth, and the furrow of the tongue turns rough on either side, <milestone unit="section" n="80"/> and the depth of the throat grows somewhat dry, and from the pernicious venom follows a dry retching and hawking, for this is severe; meanwhile his spirit sickens and he is worn out with mortal suffering. His body too grows chill, while sometimes his eyes behold strange illusions or else he drowses; nor can he bestir his limbs as heretofore, and he succumbs to the overmastering fatigue.</p>
   </div>
</div>
<div type="book" n="7">
   <milestone unit="section" n="7/43"/>
   <p>Give the patient at once a cupful of oil of the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">Premadia</name>- or <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">Orchis</name>- or <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">Myrtle</name>- <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">olive</name>, so that the stomach being lubricated may void the evil drug; <pb n="90"/> or else you may readily milk the udder's swelling teat and give it him; but skim the oily surface from the draught.</p>
   <p>And you may infuse sprigs or leaves of the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">mallow</name> in fresh sap and dose the sufferer with as much as he can take.</p>
   <p>Or again pound <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">sesame</name> seeds and administer them also in <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">wine</name>; or else heat and cleanse in water the ashes of <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">vine</name> twigs, and strain the lye through the interstices of a newly woven basket, for this will retain the sediment.</p>
   <p>Moreover if you rub down the hard stones of the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">persea</name> in gleaming <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">olive</name> oil, they will ward off injury - <pb n="100"/> the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">persea</name> which once on a time <persName>Perseus</persName>, when his feet bore him from the land of <placeName>Cepheus</placeName> and he had cut off the teeming head of <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Medusa</name> with his falchion, readily made to grow in the fields of <placeName>Mycenae</placeName> (it was a recent gift of <persName>Cepheus</persName>) on the spot where the scabbard-chape of his falchion fell, beneath the topmost summit of <placeName>Melanthis</placeName>, where a <name type="deity">Nymph</name> revealed to the son of <name type="deity">Zeus</name> the famed spring of <placeName>Langeia</placeName>.</p>
   <p>Or else you should break up in roasted <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">barley</name> the sap which congeals upon the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">frankincense</name> bushes of <placeName>Gerrha</placeName>; also as helpful you should dissolve in warm water the tears from the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">walnut</name>-tree or from the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">plum</name> or those which ever drip in plenty on the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">elm</name>-twigs, <pb n="110"/> and drops of gum, so that he may vomit up part of the poison, and part render wholesome as he yields to the hot</p>
</div>
<div type="book" n="8">
  <div type="section" n="43">
    <p>water when the sweat moistens his body. And again he might sate himself with a meal which he has taken or with strong wine and so escape an inglorious death.</p>
    <p>When a liquid smells of the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">corn-eating blister-beetle</name>, that is to say, like liquid pitch, refuse it, for on the nostrils it weighs like pitch and in the mouth like freshly eaten berries of the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">juniper</name>. Sometimes in a weak infusion these creatures produce a biting sensation upon the lips, <milestone unit="section" n="120"/> or again deep down about the mouth of the stomach; at other times the middle of the belly or the bladder is gnawed and seized with griping pains, while discomfort attacks men where the cartilage of the chest rests over the hollow of the stomach. And the victims are distressed in themselves: swooning delusions hold in bondage what is human in them, and the victim is brought down unexpectedly by pain, like the freshly scattered <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">thistledown</name> which roams the air and is fluttered by every breeze.</p>
  </div>
</div>
Voici l'encodage TEI P5 strictement conforme à vos exigences pour le texte de Nicander Colophonius (Thériaques, section 9/43) :


<div type="book" n="9">
   <div type="section" n="130">
      <p>At times administer to the patient doses of <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">pennyroyal</name> mixed with river water, making a posset of them in a mug.</p>
      <p>This was the rich draught of the fasting <name type="deity">Deo</name>; once with this did <name type="deity">Deo</name> moisten her throat in the city of <placeName>Hippothoōn</placeName> by reason of the unchecked speech of <persName>Thracian Iambe</persName>.</p>
   </div>
   <div type="section" n="140">
      <p>At other times take from your pot and mix with the round seeds of <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">flax</name> a rich draught brewed from the head of a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">hog</name> or of a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">lamb</name> or from the horned head of a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">goat</name> which you have but lately cut off, or even, maybe, from a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">goose</name>, and give it until the man is sick; and let him by tickling his throat stir up in the gullet below the entire mass of polluted food still undigested.</p>
      <p>At times you should draw the fresh milk of a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">sheep</name> in a clyster-pipe, administer a clyster and so empty the useless faeces from the bowel.</p>
   </div>
   <div type="section" n="150">
      <p>At another time a draught of creamy milk will help the sufferer; or you should lop the green tendrils of the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">vine</name> when they are fresh-burdened with leaves and chop them up in grape-syrup; or take from crumbling soil the ever sting-shaped roots of <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">scorpius</name> and steep in the bees' produce. The plant grows high like <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">asphodel</name> but sheds its stalks when withered.</p>
      <p>Also you should take four drachmas' weight of <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">Parthenian earth</name> which <persName>Phyllis</persName> brings forth under her mountain-spurs, the snow-white earth of the <placeName>Imbrasus</placeName> which a horned <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">lamb</name> first revealed to the <name type="deity">Chesiad Nymphs</name> beneath the rush-grown river-banks of snowcapped <placeName>Cercetes</placeName>.</p>
      <p>Or brew a drink of boiled-down must of twice that quantity,</p>
   </div>
</div>
<div type="section" n="10">
   <p>and into it shred some sprigs of <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">rue</name>, kneading the herbs with <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">rose-oil</name>, or sometimes soak it in <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">iris-oil</name>, which has often cured an illness.</p>
</div>
Voici l'encodage TEI P5 strict du texte de Nicandre Colophonius (Thériaques, section 11/43) selon les règles du projet Zoomathia :


<div type="book" n="1">
  <div type="section" n="11">
    <p>If however a man thoughtlessly taste from loathsome cups a draught, deadly and hard to remedy, of <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">coriander</name>, the victims are struck with madness <milestone unit="line" n="160"/> and utter wild and vulgar words like lunatics, and like crazy <name type="deity">Bacchanals</name> bawl shrill songs in frenzy of the mind unabashed.</p>
    <p>To such a case you should administer a cupful of <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">hedanian</name> wine, <foreign xml:lang="grc">'Pramnian'</foreign>, unmixed, just as it gushed from the vat. Or cast a cupful of <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">salt</name> into water and let it dissolve. Or else you should empty the fragile egg of a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">chicken</name> and mix with it the sea-foam upon which the swift <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">petrel</name> feeds. It is with this that it sustains life, and also meets its doom, when the fishermen's destructive children assail with their tricks the swimming fowl; and it falls into the boys' hands as it chases the fresh and whitening surge of foam.<milestone unit="line" n="170"/></p>
    <p>Do you also draw from the bitter, violet-hued sea - the sea, which, with fire too, the <name type="deity">Earth-Shaker</name> has enslaved to the winds. For fire is vanquished by hostile blasts: the undying fire and the expanse of waters tremble before the north-west winds; though the unruly sea, swift to anger, lords it over ships and over the men who perish in it, while to the rule of the abhorred fire the forest is obedient.</p>
    <p>Again, common oil mingled with wine or a drink of <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">grape-syrup</name> mixed with <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">snow</name> will stay the pain,<milestone unit="line" n="180"/> what time the reapers with their pruning-hooks lop the heavy, wrinkled vintage of the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">hedanian</name> and the <foreign xml:lang="grc">psithian</foreign> vine and crush it, while with a humming sound <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">bees</name> and the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">tree-wasp</name>, wa</p>
  </div>
</div>
<div type="section" n="12">
  <p>sps and buzzers from the hills fall upon the grapes and feast their fill of sweetness, and the mischievous <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">fox</name> ravages the richer clusters.</p>
  <milestone unit="section" n="12.1"/>
  <p>Take note too of the noxious draught which is <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">hemlock</name>, for this drink assuredly looses disaster upon the head bringing the darkness of night: the eyes roll, and men roam the streets with tottering steps and crawling upon their hands;
  <milestone unit="section" n="12.2"/> a terrible choking blocks the lower throat and the narrow passage of the windpipe; the extremities grow cold; and in the limbs the stout arteries are contracted; for a short while the victim draws breath like one swooning, and his spirit beholds <name type="deity">Hades</name>.</p>
  <milestone unit="section" n="12.3"/>
  <p>Give the patient his fill of oil or of unmixed <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">wine</name> until he vomit up the evil, painful poison; or prepare and insert a clyster; or else give him draughts of unmixed <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">wine</name>, or cut and bring him twigs of sweet <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">bay</name> or <foreign xml:lang="grc">βᾶς</foreign> of <placeName>Tempe</placeName>
  <milestone unit="section" n="12.4"/> (this was the first plant to crown the Delphian locks of <name type="deity">Phoebus</name>); or else pound some <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">pepper</name> with <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">nettle</name> seeds and administer them, or again infuse <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">wine</name> with the bitter juice of <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">silphium</name>. Sometimes you may offer him a measure of scented <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">iris</name>-<name type="plant" xml:lang="en">oil</name> and <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">silphium</name> shredded in with gleaming <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">oil</name>. Also give him a draught of honey-sweet <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">grape</name>-<name type="plant" xml:lang="en">syrup</name>, and a foaming vessel of <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">milk</name> which you have slightly warmed over the fire.</p>
</div>
<div type="book" n="13">
  <div type="section" n="210">
    <p>There are even means of promptly averting the oppression caused by deadly <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">arrow-poison</name>, when a man is overcome with anguish from drinking it. First, his <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">tongue</name> begins to thicken from the root</p>
    <milestone unit="section" n="210"/>
    <p>and weighs upon the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">lips</name> which are heavy and swollen about the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">mouth</name>; he suffers from a dry expectoration, and his <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">gums</name> break open from the base. Often too his <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">heart</name> is smitten with palpitations, and it is his fate that all his <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">wits</name> are stunned and overthrown by the evil <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">poison</name>; and he makes bleating noises, babbling endlessly in his frenzy; often too in his distress he cries aloud even as one whose <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">head</name>, the body's master, has just been cut off with the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">sword</name>;</p>
  </div>
  <div type="section" n="220">
    <p>or as the <persName>acolyte</persName> with her tray of <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">offerings</name>, <name type="deity">Rhea</name>'s <persName>priestess</persName>, appearing in the public <placeName>highways</placeName> on the ninth day of the <foreign xml:lang="grc">μήν</foreign>, raises a great shout with her voice, while the people tremble</p>
    <milestone unit="section" n="220"/>
    <p>as they hearken to the horrible yelling of the votary of <placeName>Ida</placeName>. Even so the man in his frenzy of <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">mind</name> bellows and howls incoherently, and as he glances sidelong like a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">bull</name>, he whets his white <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">teeth</name> and foams at the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">jaws</name>.</p>
  </div>
</div>
<div type="book" n="14">
  <div type="section" n="14.43">
    <p>You must even bind him fast with twisted ropes and make him drunk with wine, with gentle force filling him to satiety even against his will; then force his gnashing teeth apart in order that under your mastering hand he may vomit up the deadly stuff.</p>
    <p>Or divide up and boil till soft over a bright fire the young <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">gosling</name> of a free-feeding <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">goose</name>; <milestone unit="section" n="230"/> you should also give him the wild fruit of the rough-barked <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">apple-tree</name> grown upon the hills after cutting off the inedible parts; or even those kinds that pertain to the fields, such as the spring seasons bring forth for girls to sport with; or again <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">pear-quinces</name>, or else the famed fruit of the grim <placeName>Cydon</placeName>, which <placeName>Cretan</placeName> torrents have fostered.</p>
    <p>Or sometimes, after sufficiently pounding all these with a mallet, you should soak them in water and then throw in some fresh and fragrant <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">pennyroyal</name> and stir in together with <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">apple-pips</name>. Also you may soak up some fragrant <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">rose-oil</name> or <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">iris-oil</name> into wool <milestone unit="section" n="240"/> and let it drip into his parted lips.</p>
    <p>Yet hardly may a man after countless sufferings at the end of many days launch with safety his unsteady steps, while his startled gaze roams this way and that.</p>
    <p>This is the poison with which the nomads of <placeName>Gerrha</placeName> and they who plough their fields by the river <placeName>Euphrates</placeName> smear their brazen arrow-heads. And the wounds, quite past healing, blacken the flesh, for the stinging poison of the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Hydra</name> eats its way in, while the skin, turning putrid with the infection, breaks into open sores.</p>
  </div>
</div>
<div type="book" n="15">
  <div type="section" n="43">
    <p>But if a man taste the loathsome fire of <name type="deity">Colchian Medea</name>, <milestone unit="section" n="250"/> the notorious <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">meadow-saffron</name>, an incurable itching assails: his lips all over as he moistens them, such as comes upon those whose skin is defiled with the snow-white juice of the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">fig-tree</name> or by the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">stinging nettle</name> or by the many-coated head of the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">squill</name>, which fearfully inflames the flesh of children.</p>
    <p>But if he retain the poison, there settles in his gullet a pain which at first eats into it and presently lacerates it from below with desperate retching as he disgorges the poison from his throat; and at the same time the belly also voids the polluted scourings, even as a carver pours off the turbid water in which the meat was washed.</p>
  </div>
</div>
Voici l'encodage TEI P5 strictement conforme à vos règles pour le passage des *Thériaka* de Nicandre de Colophon (section 16/43) :


<div type="book" n="16">
  <milestone unit="section" n="16"/>
  <p>Now sometimes you should cut and administer the crinkled leaves of the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">oak</name>, or else those of the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">Valonia oak</name> together with the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">acorns</name>; or you should draw fresh milk in a pail and then let the man swallow his fill of the milk after retaining it in his mouth.</p>
  <p>At times to be sure shoots of <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">knot-grass</name> will help, or else the roots boiled in milk.</p>
  <p>You should also infuse <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">vine-tendrils</name> in water, or equally well shoots of <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">bramble</name> which you have chopped.</p>
  <p>Further, you should strip the green hulls of a well-grown <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">chestnut-tree</name> that cover the thin-skinned <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">nut</name> 270 where the dry husk encloses the inner flesh of the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">nut</name> so hard to peel which the land of <placeName>Castanea</placeName> brings forth.</p>
  <p>You may suitably extract the inmost pith of the giant <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">fennel</name> which received the spoils of <name type="deity">Prometheus</name>'s thieving, and at the same time throw in a quantity of leaves of the evergreen tufted <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">thyme</name> and of the berries of the styptic <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">myrtle</name>; or you might perhaps soak the rind of the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">chamaeleon-thistle</name>, 280 which has a smell like that of <foreign xml:lang="grc">βασιλικόν</foreign> .</p>
  <p>The furrow of the victim's <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">tongue</name> grows rough at the base and inflamed from below, and his <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">heart</name> wanders within him.</p>
  <p>In his frenzy he gnaws his <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">tongue</name> with his <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">dog-teeth</name>, for at times his madness overmasters his wits, while the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">stomach</name> blinds with wanton obstruction the two channels of liquid and solid food, and rumbles with the wind it has penned within, which circulating in a confined track often seems like the thunder of stormy <name type="deity">Olympus</name>, or again like the wicked roaring of the s</p>
</div>
Voici l'encodage TEI P5 strictement conforme aux règles du projet Zoomathia pour le texte de Nicander Colophonius (Thériaques, section 17/43) :


<div type="book" n="17">
  <milestone unit="section" n="17"/>
  <p>ea 290 as it booms beneath rocky cliffs. Distressed though he is, despite his efforts scarce can the wind escape upward; yet medicinal draughts can at once make him void egg-shaped stools, like the shell-less lumps which the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">fowl</name>, when brooding her warlike <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">chicks</name>, sometimes under stress of recent blows drops from her belly in their membranes; sometimes under stress of sickness she will cast out her ill-fated offspring upon the earth.</p>
  <p>The familiar astringent draught of <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">wormwood</name> steeped in freshly pressed <foreign xml:lang="la">grape-syrup</foreign> will check his pain; 300 sometimes too you may cut up the resin of the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">terebinth-tree</name>, or else the tears of the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">Corsican pine</name>, or again of the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">Aleppo pine</name> which makes moan on the spot where <name type="deity">Phoebus</name> stripped the skin from the limbs of <persName>Marsyas</persName>; and the tree, lamenting in the glens his far-famed fate, alone utters her passionate plaint unceasingly. Give him also plenty of the flowers of the bright <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">hulwort</name>, fatal to <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">mice</name>, or strip the low-growing shoots of <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">rue</name>, and <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">spikenard</name>, and take also the testicle of the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">beaver</name> that dwells in the lake; or rub down an obol of <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">silphium</name> with a toothed scraper, or else cut off the same quantity of its gum. 310 Sometimes too he may be given his fill of the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">wild goat's marjoram</name>, or of milk just curdling in the pail after milking.</p>
</div>
Voici l'encodage TEI P5 strictement conforme à vos exigences pour le passage de Nicandre (Thériaka 18) :


<div type="book" n="18">
  <milestone unit="section" n="18"/>
  <p>But if a man in his folly taste the fresh blood of a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">bull</name> he falls heavily to the ground in distress, overmastered by pain, when, as it reaches the chest, the blood congeals easily, and, in the hollow of his stomach, clots; the passages are stopped, the breath is straitened within his clogged throat, while, often struggling in convulsions on the ground, he gasps bespattered with foam.</p>
  <p>You should cut off for him some juicy <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">wild figs</name>, 320 soak in <foreign xml:lang="en">vinegar</foreign>, and then mingle the whole with water, stirring together the water and the astringent draught of vinegar; or drain away the burden of his surcharged belly. Also you should strain through a porous bag of fine <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">linen</name> some stirred curd either from a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">fawn</name> of <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">roe</name> or <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">red deer</name> or from a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">kid</name>; or again if you take some from the nimble <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">hare</name> you will bring healing and help to the sufferer. Or give him three obols' weight of well-powdered <foreign xml:lang="en">soda</foreign>, and mix it in a sweet draught of <foreign xml:lang="en">wine</foreign>; mix too a pound weight with equal parts of <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">silphium</name> and of its gum, 330 and seed of <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">cabbage</name> soaked thoroughly in <foreign xml:lang="en">vinegar</foreign>. And give him a sprig of <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">flea-bane</name> with its ill-coloured leaves. Or you should bruise some <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">pepper</name> and buds of the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">bramble-bush</name>; then you will easily dissipate a mass of congealing blood, or break it up if it has lodged in the vessels.</p>
</div>
<div type="book" n="19">
  <milestone unit="section" n="19.43"/>
  <p>Do not let the agonising drink of the hateful <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">buprestis</name> escape your knowledge; and you should recognise a man overcome by it. In truth, when bitten, its contact with the jaws seems that of soda; it has an evil smell; and all about the mouths of the stomach arise shifting pains; 340 the urine is stopped and the lowest part of the bladder throbs, while the whole belly is inflated, as when a tympanitic dropsy settles in abundance about the mid navel, and all over the man's limbs the skin is visibly taut.</p>
  <p>This creature too, I fancy, causes swelling in plump-bellied heifers or calves, whenever they bite it as they graze. For this reason herdsmen name it <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">buprestis</name> {"cow-inflater"}.</p>
</div>
Voici l'encodage TEI P5 strictement conforme à vos règles pour le texte de Nicander Colophonius (Thériaques, section 20/43) :


<div type="book" n="1">
  <div type="chapter" n="20">
    <milestone unit="section" n="20"/>
    <p>Mix for the patient a draught of well-dried <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">navel-figs</name> from a flourishing tree in <foreign xml:lang="en">wine</foreign> three years old; or you might also crush them together with a mallet, <pb n="350"/> dissolve them over a fire, and give as an antidote to his sickness.</p>
    <p>And when he recovers his appetite give him again his fill of this honey-sweet drink, sometimes adding <foreign xml:lang="en">milk</foreign> to the mixture; or else cast in and mix with <foreign xml:lang="en">wine</foreign> the dry fruit of the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">date-palm</name> or <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">wild pears</name> that have long been dried, or the fruit of the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">common pear</name>, or of the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">cordate pear</name>, or sometimes <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">myrtle-berries</name>; or let him even, like a new-born child, put his lips to the nipple, and calf-like draw a draught from the breast, even as a new-born calf fresh from the womb, butting the udder, forces out the quickening flow from the teat.</p>
    <p><pb n="360"/> Or else you may give him his fill of some warm and greasy drink and compel him to vomit unwilling though he be, forcing him with your fingers or with a feather; or cut and twist from <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">papyrus</name> a curved throat-tickler.</p>
  </div>
</div>
<div type="book" n="21">
   <milestone unit="section" n="370"/>
   <p>But if fresh milk turn cheesy in the hollow of a man's stomach, then, as it collects, suffocation overcomes him. Give him three draughts, one of <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">vinegar</name> between two of <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">grape-syrup</name>, and purge his costive bowels. Or further, grate into a draught the root of <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">silphium</name> from <placeName>Libya</placeName>, or else some of its gum, and administer it dissolved in <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">vinegar</name>. Or again, you may add to the mixture dispersive lye or a fresh-blooming sprig of <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">Cretan thyme</name>. Sometimes the clustered fruit of the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">eucnemus</name> well-steeped in <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">wine</name> is a help. Also a drink of <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">curd</name>, they say, disperses the clots; so too the green leaves of <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">mint</name> mixed either with a draught of <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">honey</name> or with an astringent one of <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">vinegar</name>.</p>
   <milestone unit="section" n="380"/>
   <p>Consider now the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">thorn-apple</name>, whose aspect and whose taste upon the lips are like <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">milk</name>. At once unwonted retchings agitate the throat of the drinker, and by reason of the pain at the mouth of his stomach he either vomits up his food stained with blood, or else he voids it, foul and fill of mucus, from his bowels, like one suffering from the spasms of <foreign xml:lang="en">dysentery</foreign>. Sometimes worn out with the parching struggle his limbs give way and he falls to the ground, yet has no wish to moisten his dry mouth.</p>
</div>
Voici l'encodage TEI P5 strictement conforme à vos exigences pour le texte de Nicander Colophonius, *Thériaques* (section 22/43) :


<div type="book" n="22">
  <div type="section" n="390">
    <p>You must either administer draughts of milk, or else perhaps grape-syrup, slightly warmed and mixed with it in his cup. Moreover the flesh from the plump breast of a sleek <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">fowl</name>, softened on the fire and eaten, can be a help; so too is gruel if swallowed by the bowlful; also the creatures which beneath the roaring of the rocky sea ever feed about the weed-clad crags: some of these he should devour raw, others boiled, many of them after broiling over a fire; but dishes of <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">sea-snails</name> or of the purple <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">limpet</name>, of <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">crayfish</name> and <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">pinna</name> and of the brown <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">sea-urchin</name> will be far more helpful, and <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">scallops</name>; neither . . . the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">trumpet-shell</name> or <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">sea-squirts</name> that revel in the seaweed.</p>
  </div>
  <div type="section" n="400">
    <p>Let not the hateful draught of <foreign xml:lang="grc">φαρικόν</foreign> escape your memory - for you are not ignorant of it: it causes grievous suffering in the jaws. Know that to the taste it is like <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">spikenard</name>; but it sends men reeling or sometimes out of their senses, and in a single day it can easily kill a strong man.</p>
  </div>
</div>
Voici l'encodage TEI P5 du texte selon les règles strictes du projet Zoomathia :


<div type="section" n="23">
   <p>Now you may either weigh out and administer some of the purse-like root of the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">fair-flowering mountain nard</name> which the headlands of <placeName>Cilicia</placeName> nourish by the brimming <placeName>Cestrus</placeName>, or else well-ground <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">Cretan alexanders</name>.</p>
   <p>Take also the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">iris</name> itself and the head of the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">lily</name>, abhorred of <name type="deity">Aphrodite</name>, seeing that it was her rival for colour; wherefore in the midst of its petals she attached a thing of shame to vex it, making to grow there the shocking yard of an <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">ass</name>.</p>
   <milestone unit="section" n="410"/>
   <p>Or else you may shave his head, and having cut the hair from the roots with a keen-edged razor, take it, and after heating along with it fresh barley-meal and the dry leaves of <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">rue</name>, which in its feeding the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">caterpillar</name> is quickest to spoil, soak in vinegar and plaster thickly about his temples.</p>
   <p>Let no man in ignorance fill his belly with <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">henbane</name>, as men often do in error, or as children who, having lately put aside their swaddling-clothes and head-bindings, and their perilous crawling on all fours, and walking now upright with no anxious nurse at hand, <milestone unit="section" n="420"/> chew its sprays of baleful flowers through witlessness, since they are just bringing to light the incisor teeth in their jaws, at which time itching assails their swollen gums.</p>
</div>
Voici l'encodage TEI P5 strictement conforme à vos exigences pour le texte de Nicander Colophonius (Thériaka, section 24/43) :


<div type="book" n="24">
   <div type="section" n="43">
      <milestone unit="section" n="24.43"/>
      <p>Give the patient either pure <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">milk</name> to drink as a remedy or else <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">fenugreek</name>, which is grown for fodder and puts forth curving horns amid its windswept leaves - a great boon when it floats in common oil. Or else you should give him dried <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">nettle</name> seed, or even the raw leaves of the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">nettle</name> itself in plenty to suck, or <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">chicory</name> and <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">garden-cress</name> and what they call <foreign xml:lang="grc">perseum</foreign>, 430 and besides these, <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">mustard</name> and <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">radishes</name> in plenty, and mingled with them slender <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">spring onions</name>. A head of <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">garlic</name> with well-grown cloves just taken in a drink also averts disaster.</p>
      <p>Learn further that when men drink the tears of the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">poppy</name>, whose seeds are in a head, they fall fast asleep ; for their extremities are chilled; their eyes do not open but are bound quite motionless by their eyelids. With the exhaustion an odorous sweat bathes all the body, turns the cheeks pale, and causes the lips to swell; the bonds of the jaw are relaxed, 440 and through the throat the laboured breath passes faint and chill. And often either the livid nail or wrinkled nostril is a harbinger of death; sometimes too the sunken eyes.</p>
   </div>
</div>
Voici l'encodage TEI P5 strictement conforme à vos exigences pour le passage de Nicandre de Colophon (Thériaka, 25/43) :


<div type="section" n="25">
   <p>Of all these symptoms you must not be afraid, but devote yourself entirely to succour, filling the failing man with boiling-hot wine and grape-syrup. Or else make haste to break in pieces the labour of the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">bee</name> of <placeName>Hymettus</placeName>.</p>
   <p>(<name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Bees</name> were born from the carcase of a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">calf</name> that had fallen dead in the glades, and there in some hollow <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">oak</name> they first, maybe, united to build their nest, and then, bethinking themselves of work, 450 wrought round it in <name type="deity">Demeter</name>'s honour their many-celled combs, as with their feet they gathered <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">thyme</name> and flowering <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">heath</name>.)</p>
   <p>There are times when, prizing open his <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">dog</name>-<name type="animal" xml:lang="en">teeth</name>, or into his drooping jaws, you should squeeze with a tuft of fleecy wool some fresh, fragrant <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">rose</name>-<name type="plant" xml:lang="en">oil</name> or <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">iris</name>-<name type="plant" xml:lang="en">oil</name> or again <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">oil</name> of the sleek <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">olive</name>; and let him drain a thick flock saturated with it.</p>
   <p>And forthwith rouse him with slaps on either cheek, or else by shouting, or again by shaking him as he sleeps, in order that the swooning man may dispel the fatal drowsiness and may then vomit, ridding himself of the grievous affliction.</p>
   <p>460 And dip cloths first in <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">wine</name> and then in warm <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">oil</name>, and rub and chafe his chilled limbs with the liquid; or again, mix them in a bath-tub and dip his body in it, and at once immerse him in the hot bath and so thaw his blood and soften his taut, dry skin.</p>
</div>
<div type="book" n="26">
  <p>Also you should learn to know the dire and fateful drink of the deadly <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">sea-hare</name>, offspring of the waves of the pebbly sea. Its odour is that of fishes' scales and of the water in which they have been scoured; its taste is fishy like that of rotten fish, or of unwashed when scales taint the dish. <milestone unit="section" n="470"/></p>
  <p>A sordid creature with its slim tentacles, it resembles the new-born young of the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">calamary</name> or of the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">octopus</name> or the fugitive <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">cuttlefish</name>, which stains the sea black with its gall directly it perceives the fisherman's crafty assault. Over the limbs of the poisoned spreads the dusky pallor of jaundice, and piecemeal their flesh melts away and dwindles, and food is utterly loathsome. At times the surface of the flesh swells and grows puffy about the ankles; the eyes are swollen, and as it were luxuriant blossoms settle upon the cheeks. For there follows a scantier flow of urine, which is sometimes red, <milestone unit="section" n="480"/></p>
  <p>at others still more bloody in colour. Then the sight of every fish is hateful to his eyes and in his disgust he loathes food from the sea.</p>
</div>
<div type="book" n="27">
  <milestone unit="section" n="27.43"/>
  <p>Give the patient a sufficient draught of <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">Phocian hellebore</name> or the gum of new-grown <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">scammony</name> in order that he may void both the draught and the filth of the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">evil fish</name>; or else he should milk a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">she-ass</name> and drink the milk, or he should dissolve smooth-skinned sprigs of the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">mallow</name> in a pot. Then again he is given an obol's weight of <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">cedar pitch</name>; or else let him eat his fill of the scarlet fruit of the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">pomegranate</name>, the <placeName>Cretan</placeName> kind, <foreign xml:lang="en">the wine-red</foreign>, and the sort they call <name type="deity">Promenean</name>, also that from <placeName>Aegina</placeName>, and all those which partition hard, red grains into sections by a covering like a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">spider</name>'s web. Or else you should squeeze the flesh of <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">grapes</name> through a strainer, like <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">olives</name> oozing beneath the presses.</p>
</div>
<div type="book" n="28">
  <milestone unit="section" n="28.43"/>
  <p>But if a man whose throat is constrained by parching thirst fall on his knees and draw water from a stream like a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">bull</name>, parting with his hand the delicate, moss-like <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">plants</name>, then, approaching eagerly along with the water there rushes upon him in its desire for food the blood-loving <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">leech</name>, 500 long flaccid and yearning for gore.</p>
  <p>Or when a man's eyes are shrouded beneath dark night, and without thinking he drinks from a pitcher, tipping it up and pressing his lips to its, the creature floating on the surface of the water passes down his throat.</p>
  <p>At the point to which first the stream drives and collects them, the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">leeches</name> fasten on in numbers and suck the body's blood, settling now at the entrance where the breath always gathers to pour through the narrow pharynx, and sometimes one clings about the mouths of the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">stomach</name> inflicting pain, 510 and swallows a fresh repast.</p>
  <p>You should administer to the patient a draught of <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">vinegar</name> mixed in his cup, and sometimes with it <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">snow</name> to eat, or <foreign xml:lang="en">ice</foreign> fresh frozen by the north winds.</p>
  <p>Or you should dig up some moist, brackish <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">soil</name> and brew therewith a turbid potion to give him strength; or draw actual <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">salt</name> water, and either warm it at once beneath the late summer sun or heat it steadily over a fire.</p>
  <p>Or else you should give him <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">rock salt</name> in plenty or the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">salt flakes</name> which a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">salter</name> ever gathers 520 as they settle at the bottom when he mingles <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">water</name> with <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">water</name>.</p>
</div>
<div type="book" n="29">
  <div type="section" n="43">
    <milestone unit="section" n="29.43"/>
    <p>Let not the evil ferment of the soil injure a man; it will often swell up in his chest, at other times it will choke him, when it is fostered over the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">viper</name>'s coil deep in its lair, sucking up the monster's venom and the noxious breath from its mouth. This is the evil ferment which they call <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">Fungi</name> in general, for to different kinds different names have been assigned.</p>
    <p>Now do you cut off either the head of a <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">cabbage</name> with its coats of leaves or the green fronds of <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">rue</name>, and administer them. Or else crumble the bloom of <foreign xml:lang="en">copper</foreign> that has had long use, or ashes of the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">vine</name> in <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">vinegar</name>. Sometimes grate the root of <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">bindweed</name> or some <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">soda</name> into an infusion of <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">vinegar</name>, or a leaf of the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">cress</name> which grows in garden-plots; and <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">citron</name> too, and the biting <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">mustard</name>. You should also reduce to ashes in the fire the lees of <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">wine</name> or the droppings of the domestic <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">fowl</name>, and then let the man thrust his hand hard down his throat and vomit up the deadly poison.</p>
  </div>
</div>
<div type="book" n="30">
   <p>But if hurt come from a draught, hard to cure, of the sorcerer's <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">lizard</name>, slippery-skinned and utterly reckless, which they call the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">salamander</name>, and which not even a fierce flame can harm, <milestone unit="line" n="540"/> then on a sudden the base of the tongue is inflamed and then the victims are overcome with chill, and a fearful trembling burdens and loosens their joints. They stagger and crawl upon all fours like an <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">infant</name>, for the faculties of the mind are utterly blunted, and livid weals spreading thick over the skin blotch the extremities as the poison is diffused.</p>
</div>
<pb n="550"/>
<p>Give the sufferer frequent doses of the tears stripped from the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">pine-tree</name> mingled with the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">bee</name>'s rich produce; or boil down the leaves of the budding <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">ground-pine</name> together with the cones which the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">pine</name> puts forth.</p>
<p>And sometimes mix the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">nettle</name>'s seed with the finely ground meal of <foreign xml:lang="la">bitter vetch</foreign>, and dry them. Sometimes too you should sprinkle cooked <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">nettles</name> with crumbling <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">barley-groats</name>, dress well in oil, and force the patient to eat in plenty even against his will.</p>
<p>Again, <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">pine-resin</name> and the sacred produce of the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">bee</name> and the root of <foreign xml:lang="la">all-heal</foreign> and the delicate eggs of the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">tortoise</name> are curative when you mix them on a hot fire; curative too the flesh of a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">hog</name> abounding in fat when boiled down together with the limbs of the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">sea-turtle</name> which swims at large with weak flippers; or else with those of the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">mountain tortoise</name> that feeds on <foreign xml:lang="la">tree-medick</foreign>, the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">creature</name> <milestone unit="section" n="560"/> that <persName>Hermes</persName> the <name type="deity">Gracious</name> endowed with a voice though voiceless, for he separated the chequered shell from the flesh and extended two arms from its edges.</p>
<p>Further, either you should bend to your service the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">tadpoles</name>' impudent parents and <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">eryngo</name> roots with them, or you should throw into a pot a sufficient quantity of <foreign xml:lang="la">scammony</foreign> and cook it. With these feed the sick man to satiety, and though he be near to death, you will save him.</p>
Voici l'encodage TEI P5 strictement conforme aux règles du projet Zoomathia pour le passage demandé de Nicandre de Colophon (Thériaka, section 32/43) :


<div type="book" n="32">
  <div type="section" n="32">
    <milestone unit="section" n="32"/>
    <p>If a man imbibe a draught from the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">toad</name> <foreign xml:lang="grc">φρύνης</foreign> or from the dumb and green-hued <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">toad</name> which in the springtime cling to the bushes, sleek, and licking up the dew, <pb n="570"/> one of them, the sun-lover, induces a pallor like <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">fustic</name> and causes swellings in the limbs while the breath issues continually in long gasps and forced, and smells foul at the mouth.</p>
    <p>Whereas the voiceless one that frequents the reeds sometimes diffuses the yellowness of <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">boxwood</name> over the limbs, <pb n="580"/> and sometimes bedews the mouth with a flow of bile. Sometimes too a man suffers from heart-burn, and persistent hiccups convulse him. And it causes the seed, now of <persName>man</persName> now of <persName>woman</persName>, to drip on, and often scattering it over their limbs it renders it infertile.</p>
    <p>But you should give the patient the flesh of a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">frog</name> boiled or roasted; sometimes <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">pitch</name> which you have mixed with <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">sweet wine</name>. And the spleen of the deadly <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">toad</name> averts the grievous oppression - the vocal <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">toad</name> of the fen, which cries on the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">sedge</name>, the first harbinger of delightful spring.</p>
    <p>Further, for such patients you should sometimes pour out <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">wine</name> in abundance, cup after cup, and induce the <persName>man</persName> to vomit, reluctant though he be; or else heat over a fire a big-bellied vessel and keep the sick <persName>man</persName> always warm, and let him sweat profusely. Also you should clip and mix with <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">wine</name> the roots of tall-growing <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">reeds</name> which are nourished by the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">toads</name>' native marsh, <pb n="590"/> where as tiny creatures they swim about with their feet, or roots of the life-loving <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">galingale</name>, female an</p>
  </div>
</div>
<div type="section" n="33">
   <p>d male; and dry the man's body by ceaseless exercise, keeping him from all food and drink, and exhaust his limbs.</p>
   <p>Also do not neglect litharge, which brings suffering when its hateful burden sinks into the stomach and wind circulates and rumbles about the mid navel, as in a violent colic which overpowers men, smiting them with sudden pains. The victim's flow of urine fails; then the limbs swell <milestone unit="line" n="600"/> and the skin has the appearance of lead.</p>
   <p>Give the patient either a double obol's weight of <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">myrrh</name> or a fresh infusion of <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">sage</name>, or else cut him <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">hypericum</name> from the hills, or sprigs of <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">hyssop</name>, or again a spray of the wild <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">fig</name> and seed of <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">celery</name> from the <placeName>Isthmus</placeName>, beneath which the sons of <persName>Sisyphus</persName> buried the youthful <name type="deity">Melicertes</name>, slain by the sea, and established games. Or else you should roast <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">pepper</name> along with <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">rue</name> and grate them into <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">wine</name>, and so rescue him from deadly sickness. You should also give him fresh buds of <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">henna</name>, or the firstling fruit of the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">pomegranate</name> <milestone unit="line" n="610"/> with the flower still upon it.</p>
   <p>[See that you do not pluck the dangerous, pine-like <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">yew</name> of <placeName>Oeta</placeName>: it is the giver of lamentable death, and only a copious draught of unmixed <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">wine</name> can bring instant help when it chokes the pharynx and the narrow passage of a man's throat.]</p>
</div>
Voici l'encodage TEI P5 strictement conforme à vos règles pour le passage de Nicander Colophonius :


<div type="book" n="1">
  <div type="chapter" n="68">
    <p>Some remedies medicinal for a man against noxious fungi <persName>Nicander</persName> in fact set down in his <name type="book" xml:lang="en">Georgica</name>, but in addition to these the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">myrtle</name> whose twigs <name type="deity">Dictynna</name> abhors, and which <name type="deity">Hera</name> of the <placeName>Imbrasus</placeName> alone receives not for her garland, <milestone unit="section" n="620"/> seeing that it adorned the <name type="deity">Cyprian</name> queen on <placeName>mount Ida</placeName>, when the goddesses were roused to compete in beauty with one another - from this in some watered glade take as a healing boon the scarlet fruit that waxes and is warmed with the wintry rays of the sun, and pounding them with a pestle strain the juice over fine linen or with a rush sieve and administer a cup containing a cyathus - or more, for a larger dose is serviceable since this draught is not harmful to men - for that is in fact sufficient cure if you drink it.</p>
    <p>And now hereafter you will treasure the memory of <persName>Nicander</persName> the singer, <milestone unit="section" n="630"/> and observe the command of <name type="deity">Zeus</name>, Protector of Friendships.</p>
  </div>
</div>
<div type="book" n="2">
  <p><quote><foreign xml:lang="grc">Nicander in the first book of his two <name type="book" xml:lang="en">Georgica</name> showing the use of groats also mentions the word <foreign xml:lang="grc">mystron</foreign> [spoon hollowed out of bread] in the following words :</foreign></quote></p>
</div>
Voici l'encodage TEI P5 strictement conforme à vos exigences pour le morceau 35/43 des *Thériaka* de Nicandre de Colophon :


<div type="book" n="2">
   <div type="section" n="35">
      <p>But when you prepare for eating a freshly-killed <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">kid</name> or <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">lamb</name> or even a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">chicken</name>, sprinkle the bottom of hollow vessels with unripe wheaten groats and pound them down; then stir up together with fragrant oil. And when the broth seethes, pour it over them . . . but smother by clapping on the lid, for as it stewes the coarse meal swells. And when it simmers gently, eat it with hollow scoops of bread.</p>
      <milestone unit="section" n="69"/>
      <p><quote>Oaks, the delight of <name type="deity">Pan</name>,</quote></p>
      <p>says <persName>Nicander</persName> in the second book of the <foreign xml:lang="la">Georgica</foreign>.</p>
      <milestone unit="section" n="70"/>
      <p><quote>(a) <persName>Nicander</persName> in his <foreign xml:lang="la">Georgica</foreign> mentions the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">French turnip</name>. (b) And that to whet the appetite they also ate turnips treated with vinegar and mustard <persName>Nicander</persName> makes plain in the second book of his <foreign xml:lang="la">Georgica</foreign>, saying . . . (c) <persName>Nicander</persName> of <placeName>Colophon</placeName> mentioned mustard {in <foreign xml:lang="grc">Th.</foreign> 921} and in his <foreign xml:lang="la">Georgica</foreign>.</quote></p>
   </div>
</div>
Voici l'encodage TEI P5 strictement conforme aux règles du projet Zoomathia pour le texte fourni :


<div type="book" n="2">
   <div type="chapter" n="36">
      <milestone unit="section" n="36.1"/>
      <p>But sow turnips on a threshing-floor levelled with a roller, so that they may grow to the shape of low kneading-tables. The turnip . . . for two stocks, <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">turnip</name> and <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">French turnip</name>, both of them long and solid, are to be seen in our garden-plots. <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">French turnips</name> you should wash and dry in the north winds;  they are welcome in winter to those who stay idle indoors, and if soaked in hot water they revive.</p>

      <p>But the roots of the  <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">turnip</name> you should cut into fine slices after gently washing the dry outer skin, and then let them parch for a little while in the sun; or else dip a number of them in boiling water, and then plunge them into bitter brine; or again pour white must and vinegar into the same vessel in equal quantities, and then immerse them in it and cover with salt. Again, you may pound <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">raisins</name> and the mordant seed of <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">mustard</name> with a pestle and pour them in. And at the same time moist lees of <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">vinegar</name> . . .</p>

      <pb n="71"/>

      <quote>
         <p>Athen. 9.371 B :   Greek text</p>
         <p>Nicander in the second book of his <foreign xml:lang="en">Georgica</foreign> says:</p>
         <p>And along with them a tall stem of <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">fennel</name>, along with them too roots of <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">stone sperage</name>, and even the slatternly <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">carrot</name> as well, <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">Cretan alexanders</name>, and <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">sow-thistle</name>, and <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">hound's tongue</name>, and <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">endive</name>; with them pound also the bitter leaves of <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">cuckoo-pint</name> and the plant which is called 'bird's milk'.</p>
      </quote>

      <pb n="72"/>

      <quote>
         <p>Athen. 9.372 E :   Greek text</p>
      </quote>
   </div>
</div>
Voici l'encodage TEI P5 strictement conforme à vos exigences pour le texte fourni :


<div type="book" n="2">
   <p>Nicander of Colophon in the second book of <foreign xml:lang="en">his</foreign> <name type="work">Georgica</name> makes mention of this practice, calling <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">kolokyntae</name> {<name type="plant" xml:lang="en">gourds</name>} '<foreign xml:lang="grc">sikyae</foreign>', for, as we have said before, that was what they used to be called. And this is what he says:</p>

   <p>But as to the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">gourds</name> themselves, when you cut them, put cords through them and dry them in the open air. Then hang them up in the smoke so that in winter your servants may fill a sufficiently ample pot and may gobble them up with no need to work .  .  . the woman who grinds corn pours in pulse of all  kinds. Into it men cast strings of <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">gourds</name> after a thorough cleansing, and <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">mushrooms</name> too, and ropes long since plaited of dried vegetables . . .</p>

   <milestone unit="section" n="73"/>

   <p><quote><persName> Athen.</persName> 9.395 C</quote> :   <foreign xml:lang="grc">Greek text</foreign></p>

   <p>Nicander in the second book of his <name type="work">Georgica</name> speaking of <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Sicilian doves</name> says</p>

   <p>And you should rear in your home <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Dracontian doves</name> which lay two eggs at a time, or <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">doves</name> of Sicily; for it is said that neither <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">kites</name> harm them, nor (?) <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">snakes</name> their eggs.</p>

   <milestone unit="section" n="74"/>

   <p><quote><persName> Athen.</persName> 15.683 A - 684 F</quote> :   <foreign xml:lang="grc">Greek text</foreign></p>

   <p>Nicander in the second book of his <name type="work">Georgica</name>, likewise enumerating flowers which are suitable for wreaths, speaks of the <name type="deity">Ioniad Nymphs</name> and of <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">roses</name> as follows :</p>
</div>
Voici l'encodage TEI P5 strictement conforme aux règles Zoomathia pour le texte de Nicandre Colophonius (Thériaques, section 38/43) :


<div type="book" n="1">
  <milestone unit="section" n="38"/>
  <p>But the flowers of <placeName>Ionia</placeName> you should sow, and all such as come to full growth you should transplant. Of <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">gilliflowers</name> there are two kinds, one is yellow and like gold to look upon; the others, those which the <name type="deity">Ioniad Nymphs</name> proffered in their yearning as a pure chaplet to <persName>Ion</persName> in the lands of <placeName>Pisa</placeName>; for, pursuing a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">wild boar</name> with his hounds, he had overtaken it, and in <placeName>Alpheius</placeName>'s stream he washed the bloodstains from his limbs at eve before passing the night with the <name type="deity">Ioniad Nymphs</name>.</p>

  <p>But from the thorny <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">rose</name> you should cut shoots and plant them in trenches making them two full palms in length. First, those which <persName>Midas</persName> of <placeName>Odonia</placeName>, when he forsook his kingdom in <placeName>Asia</placeName>, raised in the lands of <placeName>Emathia</placeName>, ever crowned with full sixty petals in a ring. Second, the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">roses</name> of <placeName>Nisaea</placeName> by <placeName>Megara</placeName>; neither is <placeName>Phaselis</placeName> nor the city which reveres the <name type="deity">White-browed Goddess</name> to be spurned, the flourishing city by the waters of <placeName>Magnesian Lethaeus</placeName>.</p>

  <p>Sometimes plant shoots of the strong-rooted <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">ivy</name> in trenches, sometimes even a spray of the white-berried <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">ivy</name> from <placeName>Thrace</placeName> or else the white kind or that with wandering tendrils. They should be plucked as young shoots, and you should strengthen and make them to grow into a single head, fastening the twisted ends deep in freshly plaited baskets in order that two golden clusters may unite and be linked right up to the flaunting crown, the green foliage sheltering them on either side.</p>
</div>
Voici l'encodage TEI P5 strictement conforme à vos exigences pour le texte de Nicander Colophonius (Thériaques, section 39/43) :


<div type="book" n="39">
   <div type="section" n="39">
      <p>From seed no doubt spring the cupped flowers <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">lilies</name> that put forth heads, whose petals are white, whose centres saffron-stained. These some poets style <foreign xml:lang="grc">κρῖνα</foreign>, and others <foreign xml:lang="grc">λείρια</foreign>, others again <foreign xml:lang="grc">ἀμβροσία</foreign>, and many <name type="deity">Aphrodite</name>'s Joy, for the lily rivalled the hue of her skin. But the thing of shame uprising in its midst has been named the yard of a braying <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">ass</name>.</p>
      <milestone unit="section" n="39"/>
      <p>The <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">iris</name> however is grown from roots - the dwarf <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">iris</name> and that which is like the mourning <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">hyacinth</name> but grows with blossoms swallow-hued, keeping pace with the swallows' coming; and both kinds put forth in folds their ruthless leaves, and the new-born flower-cups seem ever to have drooping lips. So too grow the flowers of dazzling hue, <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">corn-cockle</name> and <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">plantain</name>; nor shall the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">camomile</name> in bloom be counted nought, nor the well-known <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">ox-eyes</name> which uplift their head so high, nor the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">wallflower</name> that vies with the rising beams of the <name type="deity">Sun god</name>. But tufted <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">thyme</name> you will plant on . . . in order that, as its long sprays creep forward, the wind may blow through them or that it may hang downwards in its desire for draughts of water.</p>
   </div>
</div>
Voici l'encodage TEI P5 strictement conforme à vos exigences pour le texte de Nicander Colophonius (Thériaka, section 40/43) :


<div type="book" n="1">
  <div type="section" n="40">
    <p>But of the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">poppy</name> itself . . . cast away the petals, in order that you may preserve its capsule undevoured by caterpillars, for in truth all creeping things settle upon the petals as they open and feed upon the capsule which is like dewdrops, full as it is of honey-sweet fruit. But when the petals are gone, the heat or else the buffeting winds easily harden the flesh, and the creatures get no firm foothold when they hope to find food, and often their footsteps slip when they essay the solid heads . . .</p>
    <p>A good depth of <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">manure</name> in the pot brings on the shoots of <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">marjoram</name> and the young sprigs of the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">frankincense-tree</name>, and all other plants which gardens furnish to make chaplets for toiling men . . .</p>
    <p>Yes, and delicate <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">ferns</name> and the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">acanthus</name> which resembles the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">white poplar</name>, and the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">crocus</name> which closes in the spring, <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">henna</name> too and scented <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">bergamot-mint</name> and all other lovelinesses that unsown a meadow rears in hollow, watered spots, <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">ox-eye</name> and fragrant <foreign xml:lang="en">flower-of-Zeus</foreign>, <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">chrysanthemums</name> and also <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">hyacinth</name> and low-growing <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">violets</name>, dark, and abhorred of <name type="deity">Persephone</name> among flowers. And of their company are the towering <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">all-scent</name> and the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">cornflags</name> which encircle the graves of virgins lately dead, and sparkling <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">anemones</name> which with their dazzling colours lure living maidens from afar.</p>
  </div>
</div>
Voici l'encodage TEI P5 strictement conforme à vos exigences pour le texte de Nicander Colophonius (Thériaques, morceaux 41/43) :


<div type="section" n="41">
   <p>And everybody plucks <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">elecampane</name> or gleaming <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">blue-daisy</name> and sets it down by the roadside shrines of <name type="deity">gods</name> or upon the  statues themselves, as soon as he sees them, gathering sometimes,  too, fair <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">lupins</name>, or else the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">gold-flower</name> and <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">lilies</name> that fade upon  the tombstones of the dead, and <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">salsify</name> with its grey beard, and modest <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">cyclamens</name> and <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">garden-cress</name>, which men call the garland of the <persName>Netherworld Captain</persName>.</p>

   <milestone unit="section" n="75"/>

   <p><quote>Greek text</quote></p>
   <p>And <persName>Nicander</persName> besides in his <foreign xml:lang="en">Georgica</foreign> explains also that it (the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">mulberry</name>) appears earlier than other fruits, and he always calls the tree <foreign xml:lang="el">morea</foreign>, as do the <placeName>Alexandrian</placeName> writers too.</p>

   <p>And of the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">mulberry</name>, which is the delight of little boys and is the harbinger to man of the pleasant season of fruit.</p>

   <milestone unit="section" n="76"/>

   <p><quote>Greek text</quote></p>
   <p>The <placeName>Euboeans</placeName> named it {i.e. the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">sweet chestnut</name>} <foreign xml:lang="el">lopimon</foreign> and <foreign xml:lang="el">karyon</foreign>, but others <foreign xml:lang="el">balanos</foreign>,</p>
   <p>says <persName>Nicander</persName> of <placeName>Colophon</placeName> in his <foreign xml:lang="en">Georgica</foreign>.</p>

   <milestone unit="section" n="78"/>

   <p>And <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">fungi</name> are generated from the soil, and only a few of them are edible, for the majority choke the eater . . . And <persName>Nicander</persName> in his <foreign xml:lang="en">Georgica</foreign> states also which are the deadly ones, and says</p>

   <p>Horrid pains are in store from the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">olive</name> and from the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">pomegranate</name> and the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">holm-oak</name> and the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">oak</name> . . .  the choking weight of puffy <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">fungi</name> that cling to . . .</p>

   <p>And he says also,</p>
</div>
Voici l'encodage TEI P5 strictement conforme à vos exigences pour le texte fourni, en respectant toutes les règles et priorités :


<div type="section" n="42">
  <p>When you bury the foot of a <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">fig-tree</name> deep in dung and moisten it with a constant flow of water, there will grow on the roots fungi of the harmless kind. You may gather any of these cultivated on the root, but not those which grow on the ground.</p>
  <p>(The remainder could not be read.)</p>
  <milestone unit="section" n="79"/>
  <p><persName> Athen. 2.61 A</persName>
  :   <foreign xml:lang="grc">Greek text</foreign></p>
  <p>And then you will cook some <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">champignons</name> with them,</p>
  <quote>
    <p>says <persName>Nicander</persName> in the same passage.</p>
  </quote>
  <milestone unit="section" n="80"/>
  <p><persName> Athen. 2.71 D</persName>
  :   <foreign xml:lang="grc">Greek text</foreign></p>
  <quote>
    <p><persName>Nicander</persName> in his <foreign xml:lang="la">Georgica</foreign> says</p>
    <p>At the same time they lop off the side-growths of the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">date-palm</name> and bear away the 'cabbage', which children delight to eat.</p>
  </quote>
  <milestone unit="section" n="81"/>
  <p><persName> Athen. 3.72 A</persName>
  :   <foreign xml:lang="grc">Greek text</foreign></p>
  <quote>
    <p><persName>Nicander</persName> in his <foreign xml:lang="la">Georgica</foreign> says</p>
    <p>Of <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">beans</name> sow the <placeName>Egyptian</placeName>, so that in summer you may contrive garlands with its flowers, and that, when the pods of ripe fruit have fallen off, you may hand them to youths who have long craved for them as they feast. But the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">tubers</name> I boil down and serve at banquets.</p>
  </quote>
  <milestone unit="section" n="82"/>
  <p><persName> Athen. 3.72 A</persName>
  :   <foreign xml:lang="grc">Greek text</foreign></p>
  <quote>
    <p>What <persName>Nicander</persName> calls 'tubers' <persName>Alexandrian</persName> writers call <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">colocasia</name>; as the same writer has it</p>
    <p>Having stripped the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">colocasium</name> from its <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">bean</name> and shredded it into . . .</p>
  </quote>
  <milestone unit="section" n="83"/>
  <p><persName> Athen. 3.92 D</persName>
  :   <foreign xml:lang="grc">Greek text</foreign></p>
  <quote>
    <p>And <persName>Nicander</persName> of <placeName>Colophon</placeName> in his <foreign xml:lang="la">Georgica</foreign> enumerates the following kinds of shell-fish :</p>
    <p>Or all such shell-fish also as feed in the depths of the brine - <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">sea-snails</name> and <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">whelks</name> and <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">clams</name> and <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">mussels</name>, the clinging children of the <name type="deity">sea-goddess</name>, and the den of the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">pinna</name> itself.</p>
  </quote>
</div>
Voici l'encodage TEI P5 strict du texte fourni, en respectant toutes les règles et priorités :


<div type="chapter" n="43">
   <p><quote><persName>Nicander of Colophon</persName> mentions <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">mustard</name> and in his <foreign xml:lang="en">Georgica</foreign> says,</quote></p>
   <p><quote>And the mordant seeds of <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">mustard</name>.</quote></p>
   <p><quote><name type="plant" xml:lang="en">Garden-cress</name> and <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">pepper-grass</name> and the dark-leaved <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">mustard</name>.</quote></p>
   <milestone unit="section" n="85"/>
   <p><quote><persName>Nicander</persName> in his <foreign xml:lang="en">Georgica</foreign> says :</quote></p>
   <p>The <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">cabbage</name> is smooth, but at times the wild form may intrude into sown gardens and flourish with an abundance of leaves, either the curled kind. . . with leaves, or the green, which turns red and looks parched, and the ill-coloured <foreign xml:lang="en">Cumaean</foreign> which is like the soles wherewith men cobble second-hand sandals. This men of an older generation style a prophet for vegetables.</p>
   <milestone unit="section" n="86"/>
   <p><quote><persName>Nicander of Colophon</persName> says that wine <foreign xml:lang="en">{oinos}</foreign> was so called after <persName>Oineus</persName> :</quote></p>
   <p>And <persName>Oeneus</persName> squeezed it out into hollow cups and called it <foreign xml:lang="en">oinos</foreign>.</p>
   <milestone unit="section" n="87"/>
   <p><quote><persName>Nicander</persName>,</quote></p>
   <p>The fruit they call the <foreign xml:lang="en">cuckoo's</foreign>.</p>
   <milestone unit="section" n="90"/>
   <p><quote><persName>Schol. Ther. 349</persName></quote></p>
   <p>The word <foreign xml:lang="grc">ἀμορβεύειν</foreign> signifies 'to attend' and 'to minister to'. <persName>Nicander</persName> in another work writes:</p>
   <p><name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Oxherds</name> attend to the teams of <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">mules</name>.</p>
   <milestone unit="section" n="91"/>
   <p><quote><persName>Schol. Alex. 298</persName></quote></p>
   <p>For he habitually calls bitter, pungent things 'astringent'. For example, he describes unripe grapes as 'drawing up', 'astringent'.</p>
   <p>When a draught of unripe grapes draws up the lip.</p>
</div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>