<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title xml:lang="en">Theriaca et Alexipharmaca</title>
        <author>
          <persName>NICANDER COLOPHONIUS</persName>
          
        </author>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Encodage automatique TEI P5</resp>
          <name>zoomathia_encoder.py v3.0</name>
          <date when="2026-07-12">2026-07-12</date>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Projet Zoomathia (ANR-21-CE27-0012)</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Universite Cote d'Azur, Nice, France</pubPlace>
        <date when="2026-07-12">2026-07-12</date>
        <availability>
          <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0</licence>
        </availability>
        <idno type="zoomathia"/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Encode automatiquement par zoomathia_encoder.py v3.0 - Projet Zoomathia</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language ident="en">anglais</language>
      </langUsage>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="zoomathia">
          <term>Zoomathia</term>
          <term>animaux</term>
          <term>inconnu</term>
          <term>anglais</term>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>Fichier encode automatiquement dans le cadre du projet Zoomathia (ANR).
        Encodage produit par zoomathia_encoder.py v3.0. Verification humaine recommandee.</p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>Balisage automatique des structures textuelles et des entites nommees
        pertinentes pour Zoomathia (animaux, plantes, personnes, lieux).</p>
        <correction status="unknown">
          <p>Encodage automatique - erreurs possibles, revision manuelle recommandee.</p>
        </correction>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
<div type="book" n="1">
   <p>'<name type="work" xml:lang="en">Theriaca</name>' is the longest surviving poem by <persName>Nicander</persName> of <placeName>Colophon</placeName>; it deals with the bites and stings of venomous creatures, and describes antidotes to them. Translations of <persName>Nicander</persName>'s other surviving poems can be found elsewhere on this site.</p>
   <p>This translation is by <persName>A.S.F.Gow</persName>  <persName>A.F.Scholfield</persName> (1953). Because all of <persName>Nicander</persName>'s poems contain a bewildering number of <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">plant</name> names, wherever possible links have been provided to the relevant <foreign xml:lang="la">wikipedia</foreign> articles, in line with the translators' notes in their 'Index of Fauna, Flora etc.' The Greek text of the '<name type="work" xml:lang="en">Theriaca</name>' can be found on the <foreign xml:lang="la">Poesia Latina</foreign> website.</p>
   <p>Readily, dear <persName>Hermesianax</persName>, most honoured of my many kinsmen, and in due order will I expound the forms of savage <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">creatures</name> and their deadly injuries which smite one unforeseen, and the countering remedy for the harm. And the toiling <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">ploughman</name>, the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">herdsman</name>, and the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">woodcutter</name>, whenever in forest or at the plough one of them fastens its deadly fang upon him, shall respect you for your learning in such means for averting sickness.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="2">
   <p>Now I would have you know, men say that noxious <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">spiders</name>, together with the grievous <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">reptiles</name> and <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">vipers</name> and the earth's countless burdens, are of the <name type="deity">Titans'</name> blood—<pb n="10"/> if indeed he spoke the truth, <persName>Ascraean Hesiod</persName> on the steeps of secluded <placeName>Melissēeis</placeName> by the waters of <placeName>Permessus</placeName>.</p>
   <p>And it was the <name type="deity">Titan's</name> daughter who sent forth the blighting <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">scorpion</name> with sharpened sting, when she compassed an evil end for <persName>Boeotian Orion</persName>, and attacked him after he had laid violent hands upon the immaculate raiment of the <name type="deity">goddess</name>.</p>
   <p>Thereupon the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">scorpion</name>, which had lurked unobserved beneath a small stone, struck him in the ankle of his strong foot. But <persName>Orion's</persName> wondrous sign is set conspicuous, fixed there amid the constellations,<pb n="20"/> as of one hunting, dazzling to behold.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="3">
   <p>You for your part will easily chase and dispel all <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">creeping things</name> from farmstead and cottage, or from steep bank, or from couch of natural herbage, in the hour when, to shun parching summer's fiery breath, beneath the sky you make your bed on straw at nightfall in the fields and sleep, or else beside some unwooded hill or on the edge of a glen, where <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">poisonous creatures</name> feed in multitudes upon the forest, or beside the levelled perimeter of the threshing-floor, and where the grass at its first burgeoning brings bloom to the shady water-meadows, at the time when the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">snake</name> sloughs the withered scales of age, moving feebly forward, when in spring he leaves his den, and his sight is dim; but a meal of the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">fennel</name>'s sappy shoots makes him swift and bright of eye.</p>
</div>
<div type="book" n="4">
   <p>You may expel the hot and harmful doom that <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">snakes</name> bring, if you char the tined horn of a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">stag</name>, or else set fire to dry <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">lignite</name>, which not even the violence of a fierce flame consumes.</p>
   <p>Cast also upon the fire the foliage of the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">male fern</name> with its cloven fronds,</p>
   <p>or take the heated root of the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">frankincense-tree</name> mixed with an equal measure of <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">garden-cress</name>; and mingle the fresh, pungent horn of a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">roe</name>, putting an equal weight of it in the balance.</p>
   <p>Burn also a portion no less heavy of the strong-smelling <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">black cumin</name>, or else of <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">sulphur</name>, or again of <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">bitumen</name>.</p>
   <p>Or you may ignite in the fire the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">Thracian stone</name>, which when soaked in water glows, yet quenches its brightness at the least smell of a drop of oil.</p>
   <p>Herdsmen gather it for themselves from the river of <placeName>Thrace</placeName> which they call <foreign xml:lang="la">Pontus</foreign>, where the Thracian shepherds</p>
   <p>who eat <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">ram</name>'s flesh so follow after their leisurely flocks.</p>
   <p>Again, the heavy-scented juice of <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">all-heal</name> stimulated over a fire, and the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">stinging nettle</name>, and <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">cedar</name> cut with saws and ground to dust by their many-toothed jaws, produce in burning a smoky and repellent stench.</p>
   <p>With these means you may clear hollow clefts and couches in the woods, and may sink upon the ground and take your fill of sleep.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="5">
   <p>But if these things involve trouble, and night brings bed-time near, and you are longing for rest when your work is done, then gather to yourself among the eddies of some rushing <name type="river" xml:lang="en">river</name> <pb n="60"/> the water-loving, leafy <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">mint</name>, for it grows in plenty by streams and is fed with the moisture about their edges, as it delights in gleaming <name type="river" xml:lang="en">rivers</name>.</p>
   <p>Or you should cut and strew beneath you the flowering <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">willow</name>, or the strong-smelling <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">hulwort</name>, which has a most offensive odour; so too have <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">viper's bugloss</name> and the leaves of <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">marjoram</name>, aye, or of <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">wormwood</name>, which grows wild upon the hills in some chalky glen, or of <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">tufted thyme</name> from pasture-lands: tenacious of life it draws sustenance from a damp soil, deep-rooted, ever furnished with hairy leaves. <pb n="70"/></p>
   <p>And you should mark the pale spikes of the low-growing <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">fleabane</name> and of the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">agnus castus</name>, and the pungent <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">stinking bean-trefoil</name>. Likewise cut the rough twigs of the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">pomegranate</name>, or else young and flourishing shoots of the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">asphodel</name>, and <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">deadly nightshade</name>, and the horrid <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">hypericum</name> which injures the herdsman in the springtime when his <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">cows</name> are poisoned by eating the stalks; and further stems of the heavy-scented <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">sulphurwort</name> whose very odour scares <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">snakes</name> and chases them away should they approach you. so place some of these by you wherever you make a casual couch in the fields; others where <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">snakes</name> lurk, and a double quantity at their holes.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="6">
   <p>Now make in an earthen vessel or an oil-flask a paste of
      <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">juniper berries</name>
      and anoint your supple limbs - or of the heavy-scented
      <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">sulphurwort</name>
      ; or else pound thoroughly in oil the dried leaves of
      <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">fleabane</name>
      from the hills, and likewise the healing
      <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">salvia</name>
      , adding the root of
      <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">silphium</name>
      , which the grater's teeth should grind small - many a time too have noxious creatures fled in terror from the scent of a man's spittle. But if you rub a
      <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">caterpillar</name>
      from the garden in a little vinegar, the dewy caterpillar with a green back, or if you anoint your limbs all about with the teeming fruit of the
      <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">marsh mallow</name>
      ,
   </p>
   <p>then you will pass the night unscathed. Also cast in and rub down in the stony heart of a mortar two leafy sprays of
      <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">wormwood</name>
      mixed with
      <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">garden cress</name>
      - an
      <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">obol</name>
      's weight is suitable - and with a pestle pound therein to smoothness a handful of fresh berries from the
      <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">bay</name>
      ; then mould into rounds and put to dry in a shady, wind-swept spot; when dry break them in pieces in an oil-flask, and you can anoint your limbs with it at once.
   </p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="7">
   <p>If however you can cast <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">snakes</name> coupled at a crossroads, alive and just mating, into a pot, and the following medicaments besides, <foreign xml:lang="en">100</foreign> you have a preventive against deadly disasters. Throw in thirty <foreign xml:lang="en">drachmas</foreign> ' weight of the marrow of a freshly killed <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">stag</name> and one-third of a <foreign xml:lang="en">chous</foreign> of rose-oil, - essence which perfumers style 'prime' and 'medium' and 'well-ground' - and pour on an equal measure of raw, gleaming <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">oil</name> and one-quarter of <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">wax</name>. These you must quickly heat in a round, bellying pot until the fleshy portions are softened and come in pieces about the spine. Next take a shaped, well-made pestle and pound up these many ingredients in a mixture with the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">snakes</name>; <foreign xml:lang="en">110</foreign> but cast aside the vertebrae, for in them a venom no less deadly is engendered. Then anoint all your limbs, be it for a journey or for a sleep or when you gird yourself after work at the threshing-floor in summer's drought and with pronged forks winnow the high pile of <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">grain</name>.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="8">
   <p>But if you should chance to come upon <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">biting creatures</name> when your skin is un-medicined and you are fasting - that is the time when disaster strikes a man - you may readily save yourself by our precepts.</p>
   <p>It is the female <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">snake</name> that attacks with its bite those who encounter it; besides, it is thicker right down to the trailing tail,</p>
   <p>and for that reason the doom of death will come more swiftly.</p>
   <p>But chiefly in summer must you be on your guard against harmful <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">snakes</name>, observing the rising of the <foreign xml:lang="la">Pleiads</foreign>, those smaller stars which graze the tail of the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">bull</name> in their course, when the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">dipsas</name> either sleeps unfed with the young it broods, lurking in the recesses of its hole, or when it makes eagerly for its feeding-ground, or when therefrom, sated with the forest, it goes sleepily to its lair.</p>
   <p>Beware of meeting at the crossroads the dusky male <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">viper</name> when he has escaped from her bite and is maddened by the blow of the smoke-hued female,</p>
   <p>in the season when, as the male covers her, the lustful female fastens upon him, tearing him with her foul fang, and cuts off the head of her mate; but forthwith in the act of birth the young <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">vipers</name> avenge their sire's destruction, since they gnaw through their mother's thin flank and thereby are born motherless.</p>
   <p>For alone of <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">snakes</name> the female <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">viper</name> is burdened with pregnancy, whereas oviparous <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">snakes</name> of the forest warm a membrane-enclosed brood.</p>
   <p>Beware too when the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">viper</name>, having doffed the wrinkled scales of age, comes abroad again exu</p>
</div>
<div type="book" n="9">
   <div type="section" n="90">
      <p>lting in his new-found youth; beware when, after escaping in his hole from the trampling feet of <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">deer</name>,</p>
      <p>he darts in fury his limb-corroding venom at men; for <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">red deer</name> and <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">roe</name> cherish a special anger towards long reptiles and track them down, exploring on every side stone-heaps, walls, and lurking-places, following hard after them with the dreadful breath of their nostrils.</p>
      <p>Furthermore the snow-capped crags of <placeName>Othrys</placeName> too bear deadly <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">serpents</name>, and hollow gully and rough crags and woodland scaur, where haunts the thirst-provoking <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">seps</name>.</p>
      <p>It has a varying hue and not one alone, ever taking the colour of the place wherein it has made its hole.</p>
      <p>Those that live in stony ground and cairns are smaller but fierce and irascible: no bite of theirs can fail of effect on man, but is malignant.</p>
      <p>Another's body is like a land-<name type="animal" xml:lang="en">snail</name>; yet another has scales of greenish hue which variegate its huge coil; and many there are that frequent dusty places and make their coils rough by wriggling in the sand.</p>
   </div>
</div>
<div type="section" n="10">
   <p>Consider now the murderous <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">asp</name>, bristling with dry scales, the most sluggish of all <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">snakes</name>. 160 Its form is terrifying, but when in movement, it uncoils its weight slowly and ever seems to wear a fixed look in its drowsy eyes. Yet when it hears some strange noise or sees a bright light, it throws off from its body dull sleep and wreathes its coil in a circular ring upon the ground, and in the midst it rears its head, bristling in deadly fashion. Its length, horrible beyond that of any other of earth's creatures, measures a fathom, and its thickness is seen to be that 170 which a spear-maker fashions for a hunting-spear for fighting <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">bulls</name> and deep-voiced <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">lions</name>. Sometimes the colour spread over its back is dust-like, sometimes it is the yellow of a <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">quince</name> and sheeny, at other times an ashen hue, but often, when it grows dark with <placeName>Aethiop</placeName> soil, a smoky brown like the sludge which the many-mouthed <placeName>Nile</placeName> in flood pours into the sea, as it dashes against the waves. Above the brow over the eyes there appear, as it were, two calluses, while its eye beneath them glows bright red aloft over its coil and its dust-coloured neck swells up as it hisses continuously, 180 when in the violence of its wrath it fastens death upon wayfarers who meet it. It has four fangs, their underside hollow, hooked, and long, rooted in its jaws, containing poison, and at their base a covering of membranes hides them. Thence it belches forth poison unassuageable on a body. Be they no friends of mine</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="11">
   <p>whose heads these monsters assail. For no bite appears on the flesh, no deadly swelling with inflammation, but the man dies without pain, and a slumberous lethargy brings life's end.</p>
   <p>Now the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">ichneumon</name> alone escapes unharmed the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">asp</name>'s onset, both when it comes to fight and when it breaks on the ground all the baneful eggs which the deadly <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">serpent</name> is brooding, as it shakes them out from their membranes by biting them and crushes them in its destroying teeth. The form of this snake-tracking creature is that of the puny <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">marten</name> which seeks the destruction of domestic fowls, snatching them from their perches as they sleep, where they roost upon a beam or foster their feeble chicks, keeping them warm beneath their breast.</p>
   <p>But when amid <placeName>Egypt</placeName>'s rush-grown water-meadows they join with the wriggling <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">asps</name> in a fearsome struggle, forthwith the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Ichneumon</name> leaps into the river, strikes the slimy bottom with its paws, and rolling its small body smears its limbs at once with the mud, against the time when the <name type="deity">Dog-Star</name>'s heat has dried its fur and made it so that no fang may rend it. And then it either springs upon the frightful head of the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">reptile</name> with the flickering tongue and bites it, or seizing it by the tail, sends it rolling into the weedy river.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="12">
   <p>You would do well to mark the various forms of the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">viper</name>. It may be long, it may be short; for so Europe and Asia breed them, but you will not find them alike.</p>
   <p>Thus, in Europe they are smaller, and above the tip of their nostrils they are horned and white, those, that is, beneath the mountains of <placeName>Sciron</placeName> and the <placeName>Pambonian</placeName> steeps, <placeName>Rhype</placeName>, and the hill of <placeName>Corax</placeName> and hoary <placeName>Aselenus</placeName>; whereas Asia breeds <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">snakes</name> a fathom long and even more, such as are about rugged <placeName>Bucarterus</placeName> or are contained within the strong headland of <placeName>Aesagea</placeName> and in <placeName>Cercaphus</placeName>.</p>
   <p>The front of their heads is flat, and at the trailing end of its coil the creature wriggles a stunted tail which is abundantly rough with dry scales. And this way and that through the brakes it strays with sluggish coil.</p>
   <p>But every male <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">viper</name> is seen to have a pointed head. In length he is sometimes larger, sometimes short, and in breadth of belly he is slimmer, while his tail stretches tapering away, and may be flattened towards the end of its trailing length or rubbed smooth of scales.</p>
   <p>But the eyes in his face turn blood-red when he is angered, and as his forked tongue flickers rapidly, he lashes the end of his tail. Wayfarers call him the snaky <name type="deity">Cocytus</name>.</p>
   <p>Two fangs in his upper jaw, as they spit poison, leave their mark upon the skin, but of the female always more than two, for she lays hold with her whole mouth, and you can easily observe that the jaws have opened wide about the flesh. And from the wound she m</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="13">
   <p>akes there oozes a discharge like oil or, it may be, bloody or colourless, while the skin around starts up into a painful lump, often greenish, now crimson, or again of livid aspect. At other times it engenders a mass of fluid, and about the wound small pimples <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">240</name> like slight blisters rise flabbily from the skin, which looks scorched. And all around spread ulcers, some at a distance, others by the wound, emitting a dark blue poison; and over the whole body the piercing bane eats its way with its acute inflammation; and in the throat and about the uvula retchings following fast upon one another convulse the victim. The body is oppressed also with failures of sense in every part, and forthwith in the limbs and loins is seated a burdening, dangerous weakness, and heavy darkness settles in the head. Meantime the sufferer <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">250</name> at one moment has his throat parched with dry thirst, often too he is seized with cold from the finger-tips, while all over his frame an eruption with wintry rage lies heavy upon him. And again a man often turns yellow all over his body and vomits up the bile that lies upon his stomach, while a moist sweat, colder than the falling snow, envelops his limbs. In some cases his colour is that of sombre lead, in others his hue is murky, or again it is like flowers of copper.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="14">
   <p>You would do well also to learn of the crafty <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">cerastes</name>, who attacks like the male viper, which he resembles in equality of size. <pb n="260"/></p>
   <p>True, the viper is hornless, whereas the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">cerastes</name> boasts sometimes four horns sometimes two, and his dust-coloured skin is rough, and it is his habit to sleep in the sand or in the ruts down a road. The viper writhing himself darts swiftly forward on a straight course with the long winding of his belly, whereas the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">cerastes</name> rolls on with clumsy movements of his middle, meandering on a crooked path with his scaly back, like to the dinghy of a merchantman dipping its whole side in the brine when the wind is contrary, <pb n="270"/> as it forces its way to windward when driven back by the south-westerly gale.</p>
   <p>When the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">cerastes</name> bites, the disfiguring wound turns callous all around like a wart, and livid blisters like drops of rain move round about the bite, dimly discernible to the eye. True, the man in whom the deadly <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">cerastes</name> strikes his mischief-working fang goes through less acute pain, but nine suns of suffering does he behold. And in either groin and the hams the trouble festers persistent ever, while his skin has a livid appearance. <pb n="280"/></p>
   <p>And from their suffering little strength is left in the joints of those afflicted, and with difficulty do they escape death.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="15">
   <p>Next I will tell you what marks the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">blood-letting snake</name>, which always sleeps in rocky ascents, making a small, rough lair under a hedge. There it has its lurking-place when it has gorged its fill. It equals a footprint in length, but as to breadth it dwindles tapering from the fiery head down. At times it is of a sooty hue, or again a reddish brown. It narrows moderately at the neck, and its tail is sharply compressed <pb n="290"/> and stretches flattened from the middle onward. In its forehead beneath its snow-white horns are planted two eyes, of which the irises are somewhat like those of <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">locusts</name>, and on high rises terrible its devouring head. And with an oblique and halting movement it ever steers its little body on its brief journeys from the middle of the back like the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">cerastes</name>, scraping its belly over the earth, and with its scaly body it makes a slight rustling as though crawling through a heap of straw.</p>
   <p>But when first it bites, a swelling of dark, unhealthy hue rises, and a sore pain freezes the heart, <pb n="300"/> and the stomach's content turned to water gushes out, while on the first night after, blood wells from the nostrils and throat and ears, freshly infected with the bile-like venom; urine escapes all bloody; wounds on the limbs break open, hastened by the destruction of the skin.</p>
   <p>May no female blood-letter ever inject its venom into you! For when it has bitten, all together the gums swell from the very bottom, and from the finger nails the blood drips unstaunchable, whi</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="16">
   <p>le the teeth, clammy with gore, become loose.</p>
   <p>If the tale be true, <persName>Bane-Helen</persName> coming from <placeName>Troy</placeName> was angered with this species <foreign xml:lang="la">310</foreign> when her company beached their vessel by the tumultuous <name type="place">Nile</name> as they fled before the dread onset of the north wind, what time she beheld <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Canobus</name>, the helmsman, swooning on the sands of <placeName>Thonis</placeName>; for as he slept a female <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">blood-letter</name>, on which he had pressed, struck him in the neck and belched forth its deadly poison into him, turning his rest to ruin.</p>
   <p>Therefore <persName>Helen</persName> crushed the middle of its trailing shape, breaking the ligatures of the back about the spine, so that the backbone started from its body. From that day forward the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">blood-letter</name> and the crooked-roving <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">cerastes</name> alone of snakes move haltingly, oppressed by their injury.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="17">
   <p>You would do well to recognise the form of the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">sepedon</name>, which in other respects resembles the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">blood-letter</name> in appearance, but it steers a straightforward path; moreover it is almost without horns, and its colour, like that of a carpet, is spread over a rough surface. Its head is heavy, but its tail appears short as it moves, for it curls the end like the rest of its body. Truly the wound of the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">sepedon</name> is deadly and agonising, and its black, destroying poison pervades the entire body: upon the parched skin everywhere the hair withers and is dispersed like the down of a <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">thistle</name> when it is rubbed.</p>
   <p>For from the head and the brows of the man who has been bitten the hairs break off and from the eyelids the dark lashes perish, while round spots bespeckle his limbs and leprous eruptions swiftly spread a chalk-like rash.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="18">
   <p>Again, the form of the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">dipsas</name> will always resemble that of a small <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">viper</name>; yet death will come quicker to those whom this grim <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">snake</name> assails. Its thin tail, darkish throughout, grows blacker from the end forward. From its bite the heart is inflamed utterly, and in the fever the dry lips shrivel with parching thirst.</p>
   <p>Meanwhile the victim, bowed like a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">bull</name> over a stream, absorbs with gaping mouth drink past measuring, until his belly bursts his navel, spilling the too heavy load.</p>
   <p>Now there is a tale of ancient days current among men how, when the first-born seed of <name type="deity">Cronus</name> became lord of heaven, he apportioned to his brothers severally their illustrious realms, and in his wisdom bestowed upon mortals youth, honouring them because they had denounced the fire-stealer. The fools, they got no good of their imprudence: for, being sluggards and growing weary, they entrusted the gift to an <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">ass</name> for carriage,</p>
   <p>and the beast, his throat burning with thirst, ran off skittishly, and seeing in its hole the deadly, trailing <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">brute</name>, implored it with fawning speech to aid him in his sore plight. Whereat the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">snake</name> asked of the foolish <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">creature</name> as a gift the load which he had taken on his back; and the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">ass</name> refused not its request. Ever since then do trailing <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">reptiles</name> slough their skin in old age, but grievous eld attends mortals. The affliction of thirst did the deadly <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">brute</name> receive from the braying <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">ass</name>, and imparts it with its feeble blows.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="19">
   <p>Come now and learn that the forms of the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">chersydrus</name> and of the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">asp</name> are alike in appearance. <pb n="360"/> Signs of a malignant nature follow on his bite: all the skin upon the flesh, dry, loathsome, and bloated with putrid sores, breaks out from below, disclosing a clammy wound, while innumerable and fiery are the pangs which overcome the man, and sudden swellings are raised upon his limbs, plaguing him by turns now in this quarter now in that. This is the snake that first beneath some shallow mere wreaks his truceless malice upon the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">frogs</name>; but when the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Dog-Star</name> dries up the water and drought is upon the floor of the lake, then upon dry land he becomes dust-like and shabby, <pb n="370"/> as he warms his grim body in the sunshine, and with hissing tongue he haunts the thirsting ruts along the highways.</p>
   <p>After him you shall learn of the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">amphisbaena</name>, less in bulk and slow of gait, two-headed, ever dull of eye. From either end a blunt chin protrudes, the one far from the other. Its body is earth-coloured and wears a skin ragged, speckled, and sheeny. This snake, when it comes to full growth, do wood-cutters, as though they had cut for a walking-stick a stem of twisted <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">wild-olive</name>, strip of its skin as soon as it appears, <pb n="380"/> before the note of the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">cuckoo</name> in spring. The <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">amphisbaena</name> benefits those with afflicted skin when crippling chilblains break out upon the hands of men overcome with cold, also when the bonds of their sinews slacken and weary.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="20">
   <p>You shall learn too of the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">scytale</name>, like in appearance to the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">amphisbaena</name>, though thick, and bulkier down to its useless tail, for the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">skytale</name> is of the thickness that men make the haft of a mattock, while the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">amphisbaena</name>'s bulk is that of a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">maw-worm</name> or of such <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">earth-worms</name> as the earth breeds after a shower.</p>
   <p>Nor at spring's oncoming, after it has quitted gully and hollow cleft <pb n="390"/> in the season when earth brings reptiles to light, does it browse upon the waving shoots on the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">fennel</name>'s branch, when it clothes its limbs with their new skin beneath the sun; rather does it retire to hedges and glades and lurk deep in slumber and feed upon what the earth may chance to yield, nor does it stave off its thirst for all its desire.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="21">
   <p>Consider too the king of snakes <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">basilisk</name>, small indeed yet far excelling all others: his head is pointed; he is golden-hued and three palms' width in outstretched length. Truly none of the heavy-coiled monsters of earth <pb n="400"/> abide his hissing when to feeding-ground or forest or in craving for a watering-place they dart forth at noontide, but they turn and flee. His bite swells a man's body, and from the limbs the flesh falls away livid and blackening. Nor even will a bird pursuing its track above the corpse, be it <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">eagle</name> or <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">vulture</name> or <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">raven</name> that croaks of rain, nor yet any species of wild beast that pastures upon the hills, feed upon it; such the terrible stench that it sends forth. Yet if so be that fatal greed draws one of them near in ignorance, <pb n="410"/> death and a swift ending are wrought for it on the spot.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="22">
   <p>Learn now the doom inflicted by the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">dryinas</name>, which others call <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">chelydrus</name>. It makes its home in oaks or maybe <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">Valonia oaks</name> and dwells in mountain glens. For after it has deserted the water-weeds, the marsh, and the congenial lake, and is hunting <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">molurides</name> and small frogs in the meadows, it is sent speeding in expectation of the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">gadfly</name>'s distasteful onslaught; whereat slipping swiftly into the stem of some hollow oak it coils itself and builds its lair in the depths of the wood.</p>
   <p>Its back is of a smoky hue, but in the flatness of its head it resembles the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">hydrus</name>, and from its skin exhales a hateful air, as when about the damp horse-skins and hides the scraps of leather ooze beneath the paring of the tanner's knives. And truly, when it strikes the hollows of the knee or on the sole of the foot, a stifling smell is diffused from the flesh; also there rises up a dark swelling about the victim's wound; moreover he is distraught, hateful distress shackles his mind, and his body is parched with suffering. His skin hangs loose about him, so consuming is the fierce poison which feeds ever upon him. and an encircling mist, veiling his eyes, overcomes him in his sore affliction.</p>
   <p>Some men scream and choke, and their urine is stopped; or again they fall asleep and snore, oppressed with frequent retchings, or from their throat discharging a bilious or sometimes a bloody vomit; and last of all a dreadful plague of thirst sheds a trembling upon their limbs.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="23">
   <p>Learn and consider the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">dragon</name>, which once on a time the <name type="deity">god</name> of healing fostered in a leafy <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">oak</name> upon snow-capped <placeName>Pelion</placeName> in the vale of <placeName>Pelethronius</placeName>.</p>
   <p>Radiant indeed does he appear, but in his jaw above and below are arrayed three rows of teeth; gleaming eye are beneath his brows, and lower down beneath his chin there is ever a beard of yellow stain.</p>
   <p>Yet when he fastens on a man he does not hurt as other <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">snakes</name>, even though his rage be violent, for the wound upon the skin of one whose blood is drawn by his slender fang seems slight as that of a meal-nibbling <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">mouse</name>.</p>
   <p>From his earliest days the king of birds, the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">eagle</name>, grows up cherishing fierce wrath against him, and against him with his beak he wages a war of hate whenever he espies him moving through the forest, for every nest he lays desolate, devouring alike the young and the cherished eggs of <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">birds</name>.</p>
   <p>Nevertheless when the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">eagle</name> has just snatched in his talons a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">lamb</name> or a swift <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">hare</name>, the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">dragon</name> will easily rob him, springing up from a thicket.</p>
   <p>The <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">eagle</name> avoids him: and then there is a battle for the feast. But as the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">eagle</name> hovers round, the writhing <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">snake</name> is after him without cease, watching him with sidelong glance and grim eyes.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="24">
   <p>Should you chance to walk in some valley of limping <name type="deity">Hephaestus</name>'s isle { <placeName>Lemnos</placeName> } or go to storm-beaten <placeName>Samothrace</placeName> - these lie far off in the <placeName>Thracian</placeName> Gulf, <pb n="460"/>{ 460 } where are <placeName>Hebrus</placeName>, the river of <name type="deity">Hera</name> of <placeName>Rhescynthium</placeName>, and the snow-crested mountains of <placeName>Zone</placeName> and the oaks of <persName>Oeagrus</persName>'s son, where too is the cave of <placeName>Zerynthus</placeName> - you will find the long monster <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">cenchrines</name>, which men call the spangled lion, dappled with scales. His bulk and his length vary, but in a twinkling he sends upon the flesh a shower of putrid sores which will not heal, and these with their consuming poison feed upon the limbs; and ever deep in the belly the dropsy with its load of pain settles about the mid-navel.</p>
   <p>At the hour when the sun's rays are at their hottest <pb n="470"/>{ 470 } this <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">snake</name> eagerly resorts to rugged mountains, athirst for blood and on the watch for the gentle <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">sheep</name>, while beneath the tall pines of <placeName>Saüs</placeName> or <placeName>Mosychlus</placeName> the shepherds cool themselves, forsaking the tasks of herdsmen.</p>
   <p>Do you not dare, bold though you be, to face him in his fury, for fear he wind about and strangle you as he lashes your body all around with his tail, and gorge your blood after he has broken both your collar-bones. But in fleeing weave ever a crooked, manifold track, and baulk the beast's course by starting aside. <pb n="480"/>{ 480 } For by the many turnings and twistings of the spine he injures its ligaments; whereas he moves rapidly and at his swiftest when his path is straight. Such is the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">serpent</name> which haunts the i</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="25">
   <p>sles of Thrace.</p>
   <p>There too are the bites of the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">gecko</name>, hateful, though he is of no account. Of him the tale is current how the Sorrowing <name type="deity">Demeter</name> did him injury when she marred the limbs of him as a boy by the well <placeName>Callichorum</placeName>, after wise <persName>Metaneira</persName> of old had received the goddess in the dwelling of <placeName>Celeus</placeName>.</p>
   <p>Harmless reptiles also there are however which feed in the forest, the brakes and thickets and gullies in the country; <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">490</name> and men call these <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Elopes</name>, <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Libyans</name>, and curling <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Mouse-hunters</name>; and with them all the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Darters</name> and <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Moluri</name> and <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Blind-eyes</name> too which are reported innocuous.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="26">
   <p>Now all the simples and remedies for these ills, the herbs and the time to cut their roots, I will expound to mankind thoroughly and in straightforward fashion,—herbs by whose aid a man may heal the urgent pain of sickness. While the wound is still bleeding and painful, pluck your herbs freshly (this excels all other remedies) from some place where <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">snakes</name> feed in the thick wood.</p>
   <p>Choose first the medicinal root of <name type="person">Chiron</name> { <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">centaury</name> }; it bears the name of the <name type="person">Centaur</name> son of <name type="deity">Cronus</name>, and <name type="person">Chiron</name> once on a snow-covered col of <placeName>Pelion</placeName> found and took notice of it. Its waving leaves, like <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">sweet marjoram</name>, encompass it about, and its blossoms are golden to view; its root, at the surface and not deep-set, is native in the dell of <placeName>Pelethronius</placeName>. This when dry or while still green, after crushing in a mortar, mingle in a <foreign xml:lang="grc">cotyle</foreign> of pleasant wine, and drink. It is of service in every case; therefore men call it Panacea {"all-healing"}.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="27">
   <p>Assuredly let <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">birth-wort</name> which grows in the shade be commended; <pb n="510"/> the leaves it bears are like those of the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">woodbine</name> with its ivy-shaped leaves, but its flowers are red with scarlet, while the odour diffused from it is heavy, and the fruit in the midst you will see to be like the wild pear upon the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">cordate pear-tree</name> or the common pear. The root of the female shrub is rounded into a lump, but that of the male is lengthy and extends down as much as a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">cubit</name>, and in colour it resembles the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">boxwood</name> of <placeName>Oricus</placeName>. This you will search after as a surpassing aid against the dread blow of male and female <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">viper</name>. From it let a portion of a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">drachma</name>'s weight be mixed in a draught of tawny wine.</p>
   <p>Furthermore take to yourself the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">treacle-clover</name> as a protection against <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">snakes</name>, be it on some stony hill or in some steep glen (some call it <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">Brief-flower</name>, others would call it <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">Trefoil</name>); its leaves are like the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">melilot</name>, but its scent is like <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">rue</name>. When however it sheds all its blossoms and its mottled leaves, it exhales a smell of <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">bitumen</name>. Then cut off enough seeds to fill the sauce-boat on your table, pound them in a mortar, and take to drink as a remedy against <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">snakes</name>.</p>
</div>
<div type="book" n="28">
   <div type="section" n="90">
      <p>Attend now and I will rehearse some compound remedies against disease. Grind down and take the strength-giving <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">Sicilian</name> root of <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">fustic</name>; <pb n="530"/> add a heap of the seed of the bright-flowered <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">agnus castus</name>, <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">savin</name>, and the luxuriant <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">rue</name>, and pluck a shoot of the earth-pillowed <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">savory</name>, which in the forest spreads abroad fronds like those of the tufted <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">thyme</name>. Again take the root of the double-flowered <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">asphodel</name>, or else the upper portion of its stem; often with them too the seed which the enclosing pod ripens; or else <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">helxine</name>, which men call <foreign xml:lang="grc">Clybatis</foreign> and which delights in streams and flourishes ever in water-meadows. Drink them after crumbling them into a <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">cotyle</name> of vinegar or of wine which you have drawn. <pb n="540"/> Even with water you might easily escape death.</p>
      <p>Consider now the excellent root of <persName>Alcibius</persName>'s <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">bugloss</name>: its prickly leaves grow ever thick upon it, and it puts out a coronal of flowers like violets, but beneath them in the soil the root grows deep and slender. <persName>Alcibius</persName> a male <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">viper</name> wounded above the lowest part of his groin as he lay asleep upon a mound of uncleansed grain by the margin of a piled threshing-floor, straightway rousing him by the violence of the pain. Whereat he pulled the root from the ground and first broke it small with his close-set teeth as he sucked it, and then spread the skin upon his wound.</p>
   </div>
</div>
<div type="book" n="29">
   <p>Again, if you pluck off the shoots of the sprouting <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">horehound</name> and drink them with bright wine you may ward of <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">snakes</name> : this is the plant which draws down the udder of a young <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">cow</name> which mothers not her first-born <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">calf</name>, and anon, swollen with milk, she cares for it. Herdsmen call it <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">Meliphyllon</name> {"honey-leaf"}, others <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">Melictaena</name>, for all about its leaves the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">bees</name> lured by the fragrance of honey buzz busily.</p>
   <p>Or else you should peel off the thin membranes of the brain of a domestic <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">fowl</name>, or pare fine some <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">field basil</name> and <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">marjoram</name>, or cut from a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">boar</name>'s liver the tip of the lobe which grows from the 'table' and inclines towards the gall-bladder and the portal fissure. These then you should drink, mixed together or separate, with a draught of vinegar or wine, though a fuller cure will attend wine.</p>
   <p>And snip the foliage from the evergreen <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">cypress</name> for a potion, or <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">all-heal</name>, or the testicle which is fatal to the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">beaver</name>, or that of the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">river-horse</name> which the <placeName>Nile</placeName> beyond <placeName>Sais</placeName> with its black soil nurtures, and launches, a ruinous sickle indeed, upon the plough-lands. (For the beast, emerging from the muddy ooze of the river when the pastures grow green and the fallow has put forth grass, tramples and leaves behind a deep track as long as that which it devours with its jaws as it cuts its returning swathe.) From it cut off a <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">drachma</name>'s weight to match, and soak in water, shredding all together in a vessel.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="30">
   <p>And do not forget the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">wormwood</name> or the berries of the slenderer <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">bay</name> ; very serviceable too would <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">sweet marjoram</name> be, which flourishes in garden-plots and borders. And include <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">curd</name> from a nimble <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">leveret</name> or from a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">fawn</name> of <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">roe</name> or <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">red deer</name> after separating the impurities, or the seminal purse which you have cut from a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">stag</name>, or his paunch, which some indeed call the '<foreign xml:lang="en">urchin</foreign>' but others the '<foreign xml:lang="en">intestinal snood</foreign>'. <pb n="580"/>
   Take of them portions of two <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">drachmas</name> ' weight and throw them into four <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">cyathi</name> of old <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">wine</name> and mix well. And do not overlook the succour afforded by the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">hulwort</name> and the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">cedar-tree</name>, the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">juniper berry</name> and the catkins of the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">plane</name> that invites to sleep in summer, and the seeds of the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">bishop's weed</name> and the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">cypress</name> of <placeName>Ida</placeName> ; for all these will heal you and will banish untold suffering.</p>
   <p>Next consider another means of escape and protection from death, and take <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">helxine</name> and grind it in a round mortar <pb n="590"/> and pour in a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">cotyle</name> of <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">barley</name>  gruel , adding two <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">cyathi</name> of <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">wine</name> of ancient vintage, adding also an equal portion of gleaming <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">olive oil</name>; mix them by pounding and you will keep at bay the poison that bites like <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">gall</name>.</p>
</div>
<div type="book" n="31">
   <div type="section" n="90">
      <p>Take also to the sixth of a <name type="measure">cotyle</name> fragrant <name type="substance">pitch</name> and cut out the central pith from the green <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">giant fennel</name>; or grate the full-grown root of <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">horse-fennel</name> into <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">juniper berries</name>, also the seeds of the marsh-bred <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">celery</name>.</p>
      <p>The full depth of an <foreign xml:lang="grc">ἄλλα</foreign> cut off the seeds of <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">alexanders</name> <name type="measure">600</name> and two <name type="measure">drachmas</name>' weight of pungent <name type="substance">myrrh</name>: cut too the fruit of <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">cummin</name> that grows in summer and weigh them, or pour in at random and shake up unweighed.</p>
      <p>Then draw thrice a <name type="measure">cyathus</name> of wine and mix with them before drinking.</p>
      <p>Take to yourself a <name type="measure">drachma</name>'s weight of fruitful <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">spikenard</name> and with it crumble into fresh-drawn milk an eight-footed <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">crab</name> ravished from the river; some <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">iris</name> too which <persName>Drilon</persName> has fostered and the banks of <placeName>Naron</placeName>, the abode of <name type="deity">Sidonian</name> <persName>Cadmus</persName> and <persName>Harmonia</persName>, where as two fearsome snakes they move about the pastures.</p>
      <p>Take next the thick-growing <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">heath</name> when in flower, round which the thronging bees crawl and feed; take too a young frond of the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">tamarisk</name> that bears no fruit, an honoured prophet among mortals, which <persName>Apollo</persName> of <placeName>Corope</placeName> endued with prophetic properties and authority over men; with these green <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">fleabane</name>, also wind-blown stems of <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">elder</name>, also <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">marjoram</name> leaves and blossom in plenty, and <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">tree-medick</name> and the milky <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">spurge</name>.</p>
      <p>Bray all these in a mortar, and in the containing vessels medicate wine with them and take in one-tenth of a <name type="measure">chous</name>.</p>
      <p>But of a truth the tadpoles' all too noisy parents,</p>
   </div>
</div>
<div type="section" n="32">
   <p>frogs <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">frogs</name>, are excellent when boiled with vinegar in a pot; often the  liver  of the biting  <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">snake</name>  itself if drunk in common wine, or the poisonous head administered sometimes in water, at other times in a small quantity of wine, will help you.</p>
   <p>You must not neglect the blossom of the sweet  <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">gold-flower</name> , nor the   <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">blue pimpernel</name>   with its closed eye, nor the all-healing   <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">marjoram</name>  , which men honour as  <name type="deity">Heracles</name>'s  Organy; and with the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">Marjoram</name> you should rub small a leaf of   <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">pot marjoram</name>  , and dry pellets of the   <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">savory</name>   that muzzle evil disease.</p>
   <p>Be sure and take the well-watered  <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">rhamnus</name> , like to the little <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">Wild Lettuce</name>; it ever clothes itself in blossom of white. The name whereby men call it is Good Companion, the men who dwell about the tomb of  <placeName>Tmolus</placeName>  and of  <placeName>Gyges</placeName>  on the steep of <placeName>Parthenius</placeName>, where horses that toil not pasture upon <placeName>Cilbis</placeName>, and where the  <placeName>Caÿster</placeName>  rises.</p>
</div>
<div type="book" n="33">
   <div type="section" n="90">
      <p>Attend now and I will tell you of roots that are a help against <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Serpents</name>. First, learn the two kinds of <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">viper's bugloss</name> : of one the prickly leaf is somewhat like <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">alkanet</name>, since it is small, and the root which it extends is short and on the ground. <pb n="640"/> The other kind has robust leaves and stalks, is tall, grows purple with small blossoms all over, and puts out a head like that of a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">viper</name> but rough on top.</p>
      <p>Of these two kinds cut off an equal portion and use as a remedy after shredding them on a block of wood or in a mortar or a hollow stone. Also you should make a paste of the roots of the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">eryngo</name> and the flowering <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">bearsfoot</name>, and to these two add an equal weight of the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">campanula</name> that flourishes about the hedgerows. Take too the heavy foliage of the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">field-basil</name> upon the mountain and seed of the evergreen <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">celery</name> from <placeName>Nemea</placeName> ; <pb n="650"/> with them let the double burden of <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">anise</name> raise the scale that sinks with the weight of roots.</p>
      <p>These should you knead, and having mixed them in a single vessel you may cure one time the deadly bane of Male <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Vipers</name>, at another the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">scorpion</name>'s wound, at another the bite of the poisonous <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">spider</name>, if you will crumble three <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">obols</name> ' weight in wine.</p>
   </div>
</div>
<div type="book" n="34">
   <div type="section" n="1">
      <p>Consider too the white <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">pine-thistle</name> and the dark kind also. The two are distinct: the dusky is like golden thistle in appearance; it puts forth a circle of leaves, its root is strong and dark, and it grows beneath shady mountain spurs <pb n="660"/> or in glades, shunning the sun. But the other you will find ever in the pride of its leaves, while the head lies low and bloated in the middle of them, and its root is whitish and honey-sweet to the taste. Reject the dark root of these plants, but of other stir a piece of a <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">drachma</name>'s weight in river water and drink.</p>
      <p>Take herbage of another kind that also bears the name of <persName>Alcibius</persName>, fill your hand full, and drink in a little wine. it was that when hunting beneath <placeName>Phalacra</placeName>'s cliff, on <placeName>Crymna</placeName>'s plain and about <placeName>Grasus</placeName>, and where lie the meadows of the horse, <pb n="670"/> as he hallooed to his <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Amyclaean</name> whelps, he discovered through the anguished whimpering of his lion-hearted hound; for as it followed up a goat's trail along some woodland path it had received the female <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">viper</name>'s stab in the watering corner of its eye. And with a howl it flung her off and readily ate the leaves of this herb and escaped deadly destruction.</p>
   </div>
</div>
<div type="section" n="35">
   <p>Administer plenty of the sappy, oily bark of the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">castor oil tree</name>, together with the leaves of the thick <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">balm</name>, or else the plant whose name is that of the sun's turnings, and which, like the glaucous leaves of the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">olive</name>, <pb n="680"/> marks the path of the retreating scion of <name type="deity">Hyperion</name>. Take likewise the root of the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">navelwort</name>, which in frosty weather draws out the painful chilblains on the feet of those with broken skin. Sometimes you may take the green leaves of the tall <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">bindweed</name>, or of <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">hart's tongue</name>, shearing off the stalk. Take too the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">Phlegyan all-heal</name>, even that which the God of Healing was the first to pluck by the brim of the river <placeName>Melas</placeName>, when ministering to the wound of <persName>Iphicles</persName> <persName>Amphitryon's</persName> son, what time with <persName>Heracles</persName> he was burning the evil <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Hydra</name>.</p>
   <p>Now lay sudden hold on the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">marten's</name> young or their mischievous mother, <pb n="690"/> and strip their fur over the flame of a fiercely blazing fire, and after rejecting all the inwards and the stomach's excrements, dress with holy <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">salt</name>, and then dry away from the light of the sun, so that its swift shafts do not shrivel the fresh carcase. But, when necessity comes upon you in anguish, rub the desiccated beast thoroughly with a rasp as though it were frail <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">silphium</name> or a round cake of dried milk, grating it into wine. That will be a most excellent protection, for you will stave off death in all forms alike.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="36">
   <p>Learn also that the powerful aid of the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">sea-turtle</name> is a defence against the bite of all the long, crawling creatures that injure distressful mortals; and may you find it a strong protection.</p>
   <p>Thus, when fishermen draw the murderous <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Turtle</name> up out of the sea on to the dry beach, do you, having turned it on its back, strike the life from its head with a bronze knife and let the coarse blood pour forth into an earthen jar newly baked in the furnace; but draw of the livid, thin serum with a well-made colander and on this dry and break up the dots of blood, taking for your mixture four <foreign xml:lang="en">drachmas</foreign> by weight.</p>
   <p>And add two <foreign xml:lang="en">drachmas</foreign> of <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">wild cummin</name>, and to each two <foreign xml:lang="en">drachmas</foreign> a quarter by weight of the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">curd</name> in a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Hare</name>'s stomach.</p>
   <p>From this cut off one <foreign xml:lang="en">drachma</foreign> and drink in wine.</p>
   <p>Against <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Snakes</name> these remedies, you will find, will protect you.</p>
   <p>Consider now the operations of the dangerous <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">spider</name> and the symptoms that attend its bite.</p>
   <p>The one which is the colour of pitchy smoke is named the <foreign xml:lang="en">grape</foreign>; it moves its feet in succession, and in the centre of its stomach it has hard and deadly teeth.</p>
   <p>But even when it has fastened on a man, his skin nevertheless remains as though unwounded; yet the eyes above turn reddish and a shivering settles on his limbs, and straightway his skin and his genitals below grow taut, and his member projects, dripping with foul ooze, and at the same time numbness descending upon him overcomes his hips and the support of his knees.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="37">
   <p>Learn of one different from these - the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">starlet</name>, on whose back striped bands gleam radiant on the skin. When it has bitten, a shivering comes unexpectedly upon the victim, a torpor is in his head and breaks the bonds of his knees beneath him.</p>
   <p>Another kind is the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">blue spider</name>: it darts about off the ground and is covered with hair.</p>
   <p>Even on his flesh the victim of this <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">spider</name> carries a terrible wound: his heart is heavy within him and night is about his temples, while from his throat he discharges a deadly vomit like a spider's web; and he thinks that death is near to him.</p>
   <p>Yet another is the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">huntsman</name>, and he is like the Wolf-Spider in form, the destroyer of blue-bottles; he lies in wait for bees, gall-insects, gadflies, and whatsoever comes into his toils. But the bite he inflicts upon man is painless and without consequence.</p>
   <p>But another kind is an aggressive foe, the one men call the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">wasp-spider</name>, reddish and like the ravenous Wasp, which resembles the horse in its high spirit, for horses are the origin of wasps and bulls of bees [which are engendered in their rotting carcases]. When this creature has inflicted a wound, sever swelling ensues and various forms of sickness, and in some cases a quivering, in others powerlessness in the knees; and the wasting man is overcome by an evil sleep that brings the final alleviation.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="38">
   <p>The <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">antlet</name> — now mark — which in truth resembles the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">ant</name>, has a fiery neck, though its body is dust-coloured; its broad and spangled back is all speckled, <pb n="750"/> and its dusky head is raised but little on its neck, yet it inflicts as much pain as the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">spiders</name> aforenamed.</p>
   <p>Where men go plucking with their hands, not using sickles, gathering <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">pulse</name> and other <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">legumes</name> amid the fields while still green, there in swarms, wrapped in fiery colour and like to <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">blister-beetles</name>, dart small <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">spiders</name>. But for all their size around the troublesome bite of one <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">blisters</name> always rise, and the mind wanders and is crazed; the tongue shrieks disordered words and the eyes squint.</p>
   <p>Consider now monsters which the grim land of <placeName>Egypt</placeName> fosters, <pb n="760"/> like the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">moth</name> which the evening meal-time brings in to flutter round the lamps. All the wings are dense and are covered with down, even as a man appears who may chance to touch <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">dust</name> or <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">ashes</name>. Such in appearance, it is reared among the leaves of <persName>Perseus</persName>'s tree { <foreign xml:lang="la">Persea</foreign> }. Its terrible head nods ever in grim fashion and is hard, and its belly is heavy; its sting it plants in the top of a man's neck or on his head, and it may easily and on the spot bring the doom of death.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="39">
   <p>Come now, and I will speak of the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">scorpion</name>, armed with an agonising sting, <pb n="770"/> and of its disgusting brood. The white kind is harmless and does no hurt. But the red inflicts a swift and burning fever on men's mouths, and the victims struggle convulsively beneath the wound as though caught by fire, and there rises a mighty thirst. The black kind on the other hand, when it has struck, causes a fearful agitation in a man: victims go out of their wits and laugh without reason.</p>
   <p>But another kind is greenish, and when it strikes a limb it inflicts shivering fits, and after them a horrid eruption appears, even though the <name type="deity">Dog-Star</name> burn scorching hot. <pb n="780"/> Such in effect is the sharp edge of its sting, and behind such a sting nine-jointed vertebrae extend above its head.</p>
   <p>Another is livid; it carries beneath it a broad and hungry belly, for in truth it is ever an insatiable eater of grass and of earth; and it deals a stroke incurable upon the groin, so ravenous the hunger in its hard jaws. But another kind you will find like the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">crab</name> on the sea-shore, which feeds in the delicate seaweed and the noisy surf. Others again, like the bandy-legged common <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">crab</name> to look at, are heavy-limbed and their weighty claws are hard, <pb n="790"/> and serrated as in the rock-haunting <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">crabs</name>. It is from them that they have their allotted being, whenever they quit the rocks and the delicate wrack of the pebble-strewn sea. The fishermen with their baits draw them from the salt water; but directly they are caug</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="40">
   <p>ht they slip into mouse-holes, and there the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">scorpions</name>, the deadly offspring of these dead <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">crabs</name>, are born, to work ruin from wall and fence. Learn too of the  honey-coloured <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">scorpion</name> : its end joint is black at the tip, and it dispenses doom unassuageable and most deadly. But the worst enemy of man is the one whose crooked legs are like fire:  800  to children it instantly brings death. Upon its back white wings unfold themselves like those of the corn-devouring <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">locusts</name>, which flitting over the tops of the corn feed on husked grain, and haunt  <placeName>Pedasa</placeName>  and the vales of <placeName>Cissus</placeName>.</p>
</div>
<div type="book" n="41">
   <div type="section" n="90">
      <p>I can tell you however of remedies against the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">scorpion</name>'s strokes, just as for those of the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">buzzer</name> from the hills, or of the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">bee</name>, whose death follows from its very sting when it has stabbed a man as he labours around the hive or in the fields; as it implants its sting, it leaves it in the wound, <pb n="810"/> and to the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Bee</name> the sting is both life and death. Yes, and I know too the devices of the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">woodlouse</name>, and of the deadly <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">wasp</name>, and of the tiny <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">tree-wasp</name>, and of the two-headed <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">centipede</name>, which from both ends can bestow death upon a man, and as the creature moves there speed beneath it as it were the winged oars of a ship; also of the blind and fearsome <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">shrew-mouse</name>, which brings destruction upon men and meets its death in the wheel-tracks of carts.</p>
      <p>You should certainly avoid the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">seps</name>, which resembles the squat <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">lizards</name>; and that treacherous and ever detestable beast the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">salamander</name>, which makes its way through unquenchable fire [<foreign xml:lang="la">unharmed</foreign>] and without pain; <pb n="820"/> nor does the unquenchable flame injure its tattered skin or its extremities.</p>
      <p>Furthermore I have knowledge of all the creatures that the sea whirls amid its briny surges, and the horror of the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">murry</name>, since many a time has it sprung up from the fish-box and striking them with panic has hurled toiling fishermen from their boat to seek refuge in the sea . . . if it be true that this creature couples with deadly-biting <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">vipers</name> on the land, forsaking its salt pasturage. Again, from the death-dealing <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">sting-ray</name></p>
   </div>
</div>
<div type="section" n="42">
   <p>and the ravening <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">sea-snake</name> I can protect you. The <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">sting-ray</name> causes trouble when it strikes with its sting <pb n="830"/> the toiler labouring at his hauled drag-nets; or if the sting is fixed in the trunk of some tree which is flourishing in pride, then, as though the tree were stricken by the fierce beams of the sun, its roots and with them its leafage wither; on a man his flesh rots and wastes away. Indeed the story tells how <persName>Odysseus</persName> of yore perished from the baneful sting of this monster from the sea.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="43">
   <p>Now will I rehearse the several remedies for these afflictions. You should take at one time the leaves, like <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">wild-lettuce</name>, of <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">alkanet</name>, at another <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">potentilla</name>, or the crimson flowers of the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">bramble</name>; <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">bearwort</name>, <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">sorrel</name>, and the long-stemmed <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">viper's herb</name>, <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">cicamum</name>, the luxuriant <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">hartwort</name>, and you may well include <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">ground-pine</name> and thick bark which you have broken off from the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">oak tree</name>; with them too <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">hedge-parsley</name>, and seeds gathered from the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">carrot</name>, and the fresh and variegated berries from the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">terebinth</name>.</p>
   <p>Moreover you should store up the purple <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">orchella-weed</name> from the sea, and the unspotted <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">maiden-hair</name>, on whose leaves the fine moisture falling from the bursting rainstorm does not settle. Note too, you should cut the everblooming <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">cretan alexanders</name> or the tufted root of the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">dead-nettle</name> and of the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">eryngo</name>, together with the fruit-bearing <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">rosemary frankincense</name>.</p>
   <p>Let there be present also <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">cleavers</name> and <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">helxine</name> and the heavy-headed <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">poppy</name>, <foreign xml:lang="la">capsuled</foreign> or <foreign xml:lang="la">horned</foreign>, to protect you. Cut off also a budding shoot of the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">fig-tree</name> or the actual fruit of the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">wild fig</name> which appears orbed and swelling before other fruit. Take too the <foreign xml:lang="la">fiery</foreign> <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">thorn</name> and the blossoms of the bright <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">mullein</name>, and with them leaves of <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">havergrass</name>, and <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">celandine</name>, <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">wild carrot</name>, and the root of <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">bryony</name>, which wipes away freckles and the rash abhorrent to women's skin.</p>
   <p>Powder also the leaves of <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">vervain</name>, or pluck the twig</p>
</div>
<div type="book" n="44">
   <div type="section" n="90">
      <p>s of a the protective <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">rhamnus</name>, for by itself it is efficacious to ward off death from a man. Again, gather freshly plucked branches of <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">feverfew</name>, <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">blue pimpernel</name>, or <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">hart's tongue</name>, or take a portion of <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">Lemnian</name> <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">ruddle</name>, which is soothing in all afflictions. Sometimes too you may cut the bitter root of the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">squirting cucumber</name>; to a stomach even sore oppressed with anguish also fruit of the prickly <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">paliurus</name> affords relief; so too its spiky leaves, and the young fruits of the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">pomegranate</name> <foreign xml:lang="grc">870</foreign> with scarlet on its neck-like, closing sepals where it reddens about the slender flowers; at another time <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">hyssop</name> and the many-branched <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">rest-harrow</name> and the leaves of <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">love-in-absence</name> and the fresh tendril on the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">grape</name> cluster, <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">cloves of garlic</name>, and the seed of the mountain-born <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">coriander</name>, or even the downy leaves of the delicate <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">fleabane</name>. Often too you may cut of some fresh <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">pepper</name> or <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">Persian</name> <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">garden-cress</name> and administer it in a drink; and the flowering <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">pennyroyal</name> and <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">deadly nightshade</name> and <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">mustard</name> too may save one in evil plight. Take also the green <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">leak</name> from the garden-plot, or else the hurtful seed of the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">nettle</name> itself <foreign xml:lang="grc">880</foreign> with which boys play tricks. With these too perhaps the snow-white head of a <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">squill</name> and the dried coats of <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">purse-tassels</name> and the stalk of the dragon's namesake { <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">dracunculus</name> }, and the shoots of the shrubby <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">rhamnus</name>, and what the wildwood <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">pines</name> in the valleys nourish at the heart of their con</p>
   </div>
</div>
<div type="section" n="45">
   <p>Look you, you should lop the green root of the feeble herb <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">scorpius</name> that men liken to the poisonous sting of the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">beast</name>, or <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">waterlilies</name> from <persName>Psamathe</persName>, and those which <placeName>Traphea</placeName> and <placeName>Copae</placeName> foster by the waters of their lake, wherein discharge the streams of <persName>Schoeneus</persName> and <persName>Cnopus</persName>, <pb n="890"/></p>
   <p>and the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">pistachio nuts</name> which look like almonds upon the boughs by the Indian flood of the roaring <placeName>Choaspes</placeName>. Collect <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">hedge-parsley</name> and the red-brown, astringent <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">myrtle berries</name> and slips of <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">sage</name> and of the flourishing <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">fennel</name>; collect also <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">hedge-mustard</name> and the seeds of the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">wild chick-pea</name>, including with its green shoots the heavy-smelling leaves. Again, <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">water-cress</name> alleviates sickness; so too a fresh garland of <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">melilot</name>; also the white blossoms of the spongy <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">dropwort</name> which shepherds pound in a mortar, and those seeds which the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">corn-cockle</name> and the red <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">plantain</name> and the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">rose</name> foster within them, <pb n="900"/></p>
   <p>and the tiny seed of the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">gilliflower</name>. Or cut some <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">knot-grass</name> from the tangled watermeadows, <foreign xml:lang="la">depilatory</foreign>, and the seed of the mournful <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">hyacinth</name>, over whom <name type="deity">Phoebus</name> wept, since without willing it, hard by the river of <placeName>Amyclae</placeName> he slew with a blow the boy <persName>Hyacinthus</persName> in the bloom of youth; for the iron mass rebounding from a rock smote upon his temple and crushed the sheath beneath it. Mix too some <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">trefoil</name> and gum of <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">silphium</name> equal in scale to the weight of three <foreign xml:lang="grc">obols</foreign>; or else pluck the horn-shaped <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">tufted thyme</name>, often too</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="46">
   <p>samphire <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">or</name> <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">lavendar-cotton</name>, <pb n="910"/> and along with them grate into some drink <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">anise</name> and <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">libyan roots</name>. Having shredded them into a bowl, sometimes together sometimes separately, drink them mixed with <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">vinegar</name> or else with <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">wine</name> or <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">water</name>; these help too when shredded into <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">milk</name>.</p>
   <p>If however some bite should call for haste as you are on your journey and among waterless glades, the moment you are overcome chew with your jaws some roots or leaves or seeds growing by the way, and sucking out the sap, lay the half-eaten remains of the food upon the wounds <pb n="920"/> in order that you may avoid suffering and imminent death.</p>
   <p>Again, by applying to some deadly wound a brazen cupping vessel you will drain the poison and the blood together; or by pouring on the milky juice of the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">fig</name>, or by using an iron heated in the heart of a hot furnace. Sometimes the skin of a grazing <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">goat</name> filled with <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">wine</name> will be of service at a time when the wound is in ankle or hand. You will fix the sufferer in the wineskin to the mid forearm or ankle and wind the fastening cord about the groin or armpit until the strength of the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">wine</name> has drawn out the pain from the flesh. <pb n="930"/></p>
   <p>At times moreover let <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">leeches</name> feed on wounds and drink their fill. Or drip <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">onion juice</name>, or else pour lees of <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">wine</name> or of <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">vinegar</name>, upon <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">sheep</name>'s droppings, make a paste, and plaster the wound with the fresh dung.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="47">
   <p>But that you may with instruction compound a general panacea,— it will be very serviceable after you have mixed all the simples together — let there be <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">birthwort</name>, root of <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">iris</name> and of <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">spikenard</name>, of <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">all-heal</name> too with dried <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">pellitory</name>, of all-curing <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">wild carrot</name>, and of <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">black bryony</name>, <pb n="940"/> and with them the spongy roots of a freshly dug <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">peony</name>, sprigs of the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">black hellebore</name>, and mingled with them <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">native sodium carbonate</name>. Pour in too <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">cummin</name> and a sprig of <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">fleabane</name> mixed with the husks of <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">stavesacre</name>; and grate down an equal quantity of the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">bay's berries</name> and <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">tree-medick</name> and the lowly <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">horse-moss</name>, and gather in some <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">cyclamen</name>. Cast in also the juice of the gleaming <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">poppy</name>, and over all the seeds of the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">agnus castus</name>, <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">balsam</name> too and some <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">cassia</name>, and with them <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">cow-parsnip</name> and a bowlful of <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">salt</name>, mingling them with <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">curd</name> and a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">crab</name>; but the former should come from a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">hare</name>, <pb n="950"/> the latter should be a dweller in pebbly streams. Now all these you should throw into the belly of a capacious mortar, kneading them with the blows of stone pestles. And on the dry ingredients pour at once the juice of <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">cleavers</name> and mix well together; then prepare round cakes of a <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">drachma</name> each, limiting the weight precisely with a balance; then shake them up in two <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">cotylae</name> of wine and drink.</p>
   <p>So now you will treasure ever the memory of the <name type="deity">Homeric</name> <persName>Nicander</persName>, whom the snow-white town of <placeName>Clarus</placeName> nurtured.</p>
</div>
<div type="book" n="48">
  <p>So now you will treasure ever the memory of the <persName>Homeric</persName> <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Nicander</name>, whom the snow-white town of <placeName>Clarus</placeName> nurtured.</p>
  <p><name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Nicander</name>: <foreign xml:lang="en">Alexipharmaca</foreign> and <foreign xml:lang="en">Georgica</foreign></p>
  <p><name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Nicander</name> of <placeName>Colophon</placeName>  was a Greek poet, who probably lived in the middle of the 2nd century B.C.  He was the author of two surviving poems, <quote>' <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Theriaca</name> '</quote> and <quote>'<foreign xml:lang="en">Alexipharmaca</foreign>'</quote>, and also of several other poems that are now lost.  Some excerpts from his <foreign xml:lang="en">Georgica</foreign> have been preserved by  <persName>Athenaeus</persName> ; it is likely that this poem influenced <persName>Vergil</persName> when he wrote his  <foreign xml:lang="en">Georgics</foreign>  ( see <quote><persName>Quintilian</persName>,  10.1.56  </quote> ), but to what extent is unknown.</p>
  <p>This translation is by  <persName>A.S.F.Gow</persName>  <persName>A.F.Scholfield</persName> (1953). Because all of <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Nicander</name>'s poems contain a bewildering number of <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">plant</name> names, wherever possible links have been provided to the relevant <placeName>wikipedia</placeName> articles, in line with the translators' notes in their <quote>Index of Fauna, Flora etc.</quote></p>
  <p>However, in many cases, the identification of the modern <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">plant</name> name is far from certain. As the translators say: <quote>"The interpretations of Ancient Greek <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">plant</name>-names put forward by those who have given much time and thought to the study differ widely; many are tentative and uncertain, while some <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">plants</name> have far defied identification . . . and in <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Nicander</name> the difficulties of identification, already formidable in themselves, are enhanced by the doubt whether the poet knew what he (or his authority) was talking about."</quote></p>
  <p><name type="animal" xml:lang="en">NICANDER</name> ,   '<foreign xml:lang="en">ALEXIPHARMACA</foreign>'</p>
</div>
<div type="book" n="49">
   <p>The Greek text of the <quote>'Alexipharmaca'</quote> can be found on the  <placeName>Poesia Latina</placeName> website.</p>
   <p>Even though the peoples from whom you and I, <persName>Protagoras</persName>, have derived our births did not set up the walls of their strong towers side by side in  <placeName xml:lang="la">Asia</placeName>, and a great space separates us, yet I can easily instruct you in the remedies for those draughts of poison which attack men and bring them low.</p>
   <p>You indeed have made your home by the tempestuous sea beneath bossy <foreign xml:lang="grc">Arctus</foreign>, where are the caverns of <name type="deity">Lobrinian Rhea</name> and the place of the secret rites of <name type="deity">Attes</name>; while I dwell where the sons of the far-famed <persName>Creusa</persName> divided among themselves the richest portion of the mainland, settling by the tripods of <name type="deity">Apollo</name> in <placeName>Clarus</placeName>.</p>
   <p>You must, to be sure, learn of the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">aconite</name>, bitter as gall, deadly in the mouth, which the banks of <placeName>Acheron</placeName> put forth. There is the abyss of the Wise Counsellor { <name type="deity">Hades</name> } whence few escape, and there the towns of <placeName>Priolas</placeName> fell crashing in ruins.</p>
</div>
<div type="book" n="50">
   <p>All the drinker's jaws and the roof of his mouth and his gums are constricted by the bitter draught, as it wraps itself about the top of the chest, crushing with evil choking the man in the throes of heartburn. The top of the belly is gripped with pain - <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">20</name> the swelling, open mouth of the lower stomach, which some call the 'heart' of the digestive vessel, others the 'receiver' of the stomach - and the gate is closed immediately upon the beginning of the intestines where a man's food in all its abundance is carried in. And all the while from his streaming eyes drips the moisture; and his belly sore shaken vainly throws up wind, and much of it settles below about his mid-navel; and in his head is a grievous weight, and there ensues a rapid throbbing beneath his temples, and with his eyes he sees things double, like a man at night overcome with unmixed wine.</p>
   <p><name type="animal" xml:lang="en">30</name> And as when the <name type="deity">Silens</name>, the nurses of the horned <name type="deity">Dionysus</name>, crushed the wild grapes, and having for the first time fortified their spirits with the foaming drink, were confused in their sight and on reeling feet rushed madly about the hill of <placeName>Nysa</placeName>, even so is the sight of these men darkened beneath the weight of evil doom.</p>
   <p>This <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">plant</name> men call also Mouse-bane, for it utterly destroys troublesome, nibbling <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">mice</name>; but some call it Leopard's-choke, since cowherds and goatherds with it contrive the death of those great <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">beasts</name> amid the glades of <placeName>Ida</placeName> in the vale of <placeName>Phalacra</placeName>. Again they name it Woman-killer and Cr</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="51">
   <p>ayfish. And the deadly <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">aconite</name> flourishes amid the <placeName>Aconaean</placeName> mountains.</p>
</div>
<div type="book" n="52">
  <div type="section" n="90">
    <p>For one so poisoned <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">gypsum</name> to the weight of a handful will perhaps be a protection, if you draw thereto tawny wine in due measure with the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">gypsum</name> reduced to fine powder - let it be a full <foreign xml:lang="grc">cotyle</foreign> of wine - and add stalks of <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">wormwood</name>, cutting them from the shrub, or of bright green <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">horehound</name> which they call <foreign xml:lang="en">Honeyleaf</foreign>; administer also a shoot of the herbaceous, evergreen <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">spurge-olive</name> and <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">rue</name>, quenching in vinegar and honey <pb n="50"/> a red-hot lump of metal between the jaws of the fire-tongs, or <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">dross of iron</name> which the flame of the fire has separated within the melting-pot in the furnace; or sometimes just after warming in the fire a lump of gold or silver you should plunge it in the turbid draught. Or again you should take leaves, half a handful's weight, of the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">ground pine</name>; or a dry sprig of <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">pot marjoram</name> from the hills, or cut a fresh spray of <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">field basil</name>, and cover them in four <foreign xml:lang="grc">cyathi</foreign> of honey-sweet wine. Or you may take some broth, still meaty and undiluted, made from a domestic <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">fowl</name> <pb n="60"/> when the forcible glow of the fire beneath the pot reduces the body to pieces. Also you should render down the fresh meat of an <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">ox</name> abounding in fat and satisfy the stomach to its full capacity with the soup. Again, sometimes you should pour the juice of <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">balsam</name> into some drops of milk from a young girl, or else into water, until the patient discharges from his throat the undigested food. Sometimes too you should cut out the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">curd</name> from the stomach of the</p>
  </div>
</div>
<div type="section" n="53">
   <p>nimble beast that sleeps open-eyed <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">hare</name>, or of a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">fawn</name>, and give it mixed in wine; at other times cast the roots of the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">purple mulberry</name> into the hollow of a mortar, <pb n="70"/> bray them mingled with wine, and give them boiled in the labours of the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">bee</name>. Thus may you ward off loathsome sickness though it threaten to master a man, and he may once again walk on unfaltering feet.</p>
   <p>In the second place consider the hateful brew compounded with gleaming, deadly <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">white lead</name> whose fresh colour is like milk which foams all over when you milk it rich in the springtime into the deep pails. Over the victim's jaws and in the grooves of the gums is plastered an astringent froth, and the furrow of the tongue turns rough on either side, <pb n="80"/> and the depth of the throat grows somewhat dry, and from the pernicious venom follows a dry retching and hawking, for this is severe; meanwhile his spirit sickens and he is worn out with mortal suffering. His body too grows chill, while sometimes his eyes behold strange illusions or else he drowses; nor can he bestir his limbs as heretofore, and he succumbs to the overmastering fatigue.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="54">
   <p>Give the patient at once a cupful of oil of the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">Premadia</name>- or <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">Orchis</name>- or <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">Myrtle</name>- olive, so that the stomach being lubricated may void the evil drug; <pb n="90"/> or else you may readily milk the udder's swelling teat and give it him; but skim the oily surface from the draught.</p>
   <p>And you may infuse sprigs or leaves of the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">mallow</name> in fresh sap and dose the sufferer with as much as he can take.</p>
   <p>Or again pound <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">sesame</name> seeds and administer them also in wine; or else heat and cleanse in water the ashes of <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">vine</name> twigs, and strain the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">lye</name> through the interstices of a newly woven basket, for this will retain the sediment.</p>
   <p>Moreover if you rub down the hard stones of the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">persea</name> in gleaming olive oil, they will ward off injury - <pb n="100"/> the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">persea</name> which once on a time <persName>Perseus</persName>, when his feet bore him from the land of <placeName>Cepheus</placeName> and he had cut off the teeming head of <name type="deity">Medusa</name> with his <name type="weapon">falchion</name>, readily made to grow in the fields of <placeName>Mycenae</placeName> (it was a recent gift of <persName>Cepheus</persName>) on the spot where the scabbard-chape of his falchion fell, beneath the topmost summit of <placeName>Melanthis</placeName>, where a <name type="deity">Nymph</name> revealed to the son of <persName>Zeus</persName> the famed spring of <placeName>Langeia</placeName>.</p>
   <p>Or else you should break up in roasted barley the sap which congeals upon the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">frankincense</name> bushes of <placeName>Gerrha</placeName>; also as helpful you should dissolve in warm water the tears from the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">walnut-tree</name> or from the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">plum</name> or those which ever drip in plenty on the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">elm-twigs</name>, <pb n="110"/> and drops of <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">gum</name>, so that he may vomit up part of the poison,</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="55">
   <p>and part render wholesome as he yields to the hot water when the sweat moistens his body. And again he might sate himself with a meal which he has taken or with strong wine and so escape an inglorious death.</p>
   <p>When a liquid smells of the corn-eating <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">blister-beetle</name>, that is to say, like liquid pitch, refuse it, for on the nostrils it weighs like pitch and in the mouth like freshly eaten berries of the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">juniper</name>.</p>
   <p>Sometimes in a weak infusion these creatures produce a biting sensation upon the lips, or again deep down about the mouth of the stomach; at other times the middle of the belly or the bladder is gnawed and seized with griping pains, while discomfort attacks men where the cartilage of the chest rests over the hollow of the stomach.</p>
   <p>And the victims are distressed in themselves: swooning delusions hold in bondage what is human in them, and the victim is brought down unexpectedly by pain, like the freshly scattered thistledown which roams the air and is fluttered by every breeze.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="56">
   <p>At times administer to the patient doses of <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">pennyroyal</name> mixed with river water, making a  <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">posset</name>  of them in a mug.  <pb n="130"/>  This was the rich draught of the fasting <name type="deity">Deo</name>; once with this did <name type="deity">Deo</name> moisten her throat in the city of <placeName>Hippothoōn</placeName> by reason of the unchecked speech of  <persName>Thracian Iambe</persName>.</p>
   <p>At other times take from your pot and mix with the round seeds of  <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">flax</name>  a rich draught brewed from the head of a  <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">hog</name>  or of a  <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">lamb</name>  or from the horned head of a  <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">goat</name>  which you have but lately cut off, or even, maybe, from a  <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">goose</name> , and give it until the man is sick; and let him by tickling his throat stir up in the gullet below the entire mass of polluted food still undigested.</p>
   <p>At times you should draw the fresh milk of a  <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">sheep</name>  in a clyster-pipe,  <pb n="140"/>  administer a  <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">clyster</name>  and so empty the useless faeces from the bowel. At another time a draught of creamy  <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">milk</name>  will help the sufferer; or you should lop the green tendrils of the  <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">vine</name>  when they are fresh-burdened with leaves and chop them up in  <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">grape-syrup</name> ; or take from crumbling soil the ever sting-shaped roots of   <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">scorpius</name>   and steep in the bees' produce. The plant grows high like  <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">asphodel</name>  but sheds its stalks when withered.</p>
   <p>Also you should take four  <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">drachmas</name>  ' weight of <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">Parthenian earth</name>  which <persName>Phyllis</persName> brings forth under her mountain-spurs,  <pb n="150"/>  the snow-white earth of the <placeName>Imbrasus</placeName> which a horned <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">lamb</name>  first revealed to the <name type="deity">Chesiad Nymphs</name> beneath the rush-grown river-banks of snowcapped <placeName>Cercetes</placeName>. Or brew a drink</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="57">
   <p>of boiled-down <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">must</name> of twice that quantity, and into it shred some sprigs of <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">rue</name>, kneading the herbs with <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">rose-oil</name>, or sometimes soak it in <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">iris-oil</name>, which has often cured an illness.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="58">
   <p>If however a man thoughtlessly taste from loathsome cups a draught, deadly and hard to remedy, of <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">coriander</name>, the victims are struck with madness <pb n="160"/> and utter wild and vulgar words like lunatics, and like crazy <name type="deity">Bacchanals</name> bawl shrill songs in frenzy of the mind unabashed.</p>
   <p>To such a case you should administer a cupful of <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">hedanian</name> wine, <foreign xml:lang="la">'Pramnian'</foreign>, unmixed, just as it gushed from the vat. Or cast a cupful of <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">salt</name> into water and let it dissolve. Or else you should empty the fragile <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">egg</name> of a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">chicken</name> and mix with it the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">sea-foam</name> upon which the swift <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">petrel</name> feeds. It is with this that it sustains life, and also meets its doom, when the fishermen's destructive children assail with their tricks the swimming fowl; and it falls into the boys' hands as it chases the fresh and whitening surge of foam. <pb n="170"/></p>
   <p>Do you also draw from the bitter, violet-hued sea - the sea, which, with fire too, the <name type="deity">Earth-Shaker</name> has enslaved to the winds. For fire is vanquished by hostile blasts: the undying fire and the expanse of waters tremble before the north-west winds; though the unruly sea, swift to anger, lords it over ships and over the men who perish in it, while to the rule of the abhorred fire the forest is obedient. Again, common <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">oil</name> mingled with wine or a drink of <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">grape-syrup</name> mixed with snow will stay the pain, <pb n="180"/> what time the reapers with their pruning-hooks lop the heavy, wrinkled vintage of the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">hedanian</name> and the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">psithian</name> vine and crush it, while with a humming sound</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="59">
   <p>bees and the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">tree-wasp</name>, <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">wasps</name> and <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">buzzers</name> from the hills fall upon the grapes and feast their fill of sweetness, and the mischievous <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">fox</name> ravages the richer clusters.</p>
   <p>Take note too of the noxious draught which is <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">hemlock</name>, for this drink assuredly looses disaster upon the head bringing the darkness of night: the eyes roll, and men roam the streets with tottering steps and crawling upon their hands; 190 a terrible choking blocks the lower throat and the narrow passage of the windpipe; the extremities grow cold; and in the limbs the stout arteries are contracted; for a short while the victim draws breath like one swooning, and his spirit beholds <name type="deity">Hades</name>.</p>
   <p>Give the patient his fill of <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">oil</name> or of unmixed <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">wine</name> until he vomit up the evil, painful poison; or prepare and insert a <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">clyster</name>; or else give him draughts of unmixed <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">wine</name>, or cut and bring him twigs of <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">sweet bay</name> or <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">bay of Tempe</name> 200 (this was the first plant to crown the <placeName>Delphian</placeName> locks of <persName>Phoebus</persName>); or else pound some <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">pepper</name> with <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">nettle seeds</name> and administer them, or again infuse <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">wine</name> with the bitter juice of <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">silphium</name>. Sometimes you may offer him a measure of scented <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">iris-oil</name> and <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">silphium</name> shredded in with gleaming <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">oil</name>. Also give him a draught of honey-sweet <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">grape-syrup</name>, and a foaming vessel of <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">milk</name> which you have slightly warmed over the fire.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="60">
   <p>There are even means of promptly averting the oppression caused by deadly <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">arrow-poison</name>, when a man is overcome with anguish from drinking it. First, his tongue begins to thicken from the root <pb n="210"/> and weighs upon the lips which are heavy and swollen about the mouth; he suffers from a dry expectoration, and his gums break open from the base. Often too his heart is smitten with palpitations, and it is his fate that all his wits are stunned and overthrown by the evil poison; and he makes bleating noises, babbling endlessly in his frenzy; often too in his distress he cries aloud even as one whose head, the body's master, has just been cut off with the sword; or as the acolyte with her tray of offerings, <persName>Rhea</persName>'s priestess, appearing in the public highways on the ninth day of the month, raises a great shout with her voice, while the people tremble <pb n="220"/> as they hearken to the horrible yelling of the votary of <placeName>Ida</placeName>.</p>
   <p>Even so the man in his frenzy of mind bellows and howls incoherently, and as he glances sidelong like a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">bull</name>, he whets his white teeth and foams at the jaws.</p>
</div>
<div type="book" n="61">
   <div type="section" n="90">
      <p>You must even bind him fast with twisted ropes and make him drunk with wine, with gentle force filling him to satiety even against his will; then force his gnashing teeth apart in order that under your mastering hand he may vomit up the deadly stuff.</p>
      <p>Or divide up and boil till soft over a bright fire the young <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">gosling</name> of a free-feeding <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">goose</name>; <pb n="230"/> you should also give him the wild fruit of the rough-barked <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">apple-tree</name> grown upon the hills after cutting off the inedible parts; or even those kinds that pertain to the fields, such as the spring seasons bring forth for girls to sport with; or again <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">pear-quinces</name>, or else the famed fruit of the grim <name type="placeName">Cydon</name>, which <name type="placeName">Cretan</name> torrents have fostered.</p>
      <p>Or sometimes, after sufficiently pounding all these with a mallet, you should soak them in water and then throw in some fresh and fragrant <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">pennyroyal</name> and stir in together with <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">apple-pips</name>.</p>
      <p>Also you may soak up some fragrant <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">rose-oil</name> or <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">iris-oil</name> into wool <pb n="240"/> and let it drip into his parted lips.</p>
      <p>Yet hardly may a man after countless sufferings at the end of many days launch with safety his unsteady steps, while his startled gaze roams this way and that.</p>
      <p>This is the poison with which the nomads of <name type="placeName">Gerrha</name> and they who plough their fields by the river <name type="placeName">Euphrates</name> smear their brazen arrow-heads.</p>
      <p>And the wounds, quite past healing, blacken the flesh, for the stinging poison of the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Hydra</name> eats its way in, while the skin, turning putrid with the infection, breaks into open so</p>
   </div>
</div>
<div type="section" n="62">
   <p>But if a man taste the loathsome fire of <name type="deity">Colchian Medea</name>, the notorious <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">meadow-saffron</name>, an incurable itching assails: his lips all over as he moistens them, such as comes upon those whose skin is defiled with the snow-white juice of the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">fig-tree</name> or by the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">stinging nettle</name> or by the many-coated head of the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">squill</name>, which fearfully inflames the flesh of children.</p>
   <p>But if he retain the poison, there settles in his gullet a pain which at first eats into it and presently lacerates it from below with desperate retching as he disgorges the poison from his throat; and at the same time the belly also voids the polluted scourings, even as a carver pours off the turbid water in which the meat was washed.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="63">
   <p>Now sometimes you should cut and administer the crinkled leaves of the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">oak</name>, or else those of the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">Valonia oak</name> together with the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">acorns</name>; or you should draw fresh <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">milk</name> in a pail and then let the man swallow his fill of the milk after retaining it in his mouth. At times to be sure shoots of <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">knot-grass</name> will help, or else the roots boiled in <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">milk</name>. You should also infuse <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">vine-tendrils</name> in water, or equally well shoots of <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">bramble</name> which you have chopped.</p>
   <p>Further, you should strip the green hulls of a well-grown <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">chestnut-tree</name> that cover the thin-skinned nut where the dry husk encloses the inner flesh of the nut so hard to peel which the land of <placeName>Castanea</placeName> brings forth. You may suitably extract the inmost pith of the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">giant fennel</name> which received the spoils of <name type="deity">Prometheus</name>'s thieving, and at the same time throw in a quantity of leaves of the evergreen <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">tufted thyme</name> and of the berries of the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">styptic</name> <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">myrtle</name>; or you might perhaps soak the rind of the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">pomegranate</name>, and steep it with <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">apples</name> in a mixture until there is added to the draught something astringent, and you will dispel the sickness.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="64">
   <p>Beware lest by craft there pass undetected on the lips a deadly drink brewed with the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">chamaeleon-thistle</name>, <pb n="280"/> which has a smell like that of <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">basil</name>. The furrow of the victim's tongue grows rough at the base and inflamed from below, and his heart wanders within him. In his frenzy he gnaws his tongue with his <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">dog-teeth</name>, for at times his madness overmasters his wits, while the stomach blinds with wanton obstruction the two channels of liquid and solid food, and rumbles with the wind it has penned within, which circulating in a confined track often seems like the thunder of stormy <name type="deity">Olympus</name>, or again like the wicked roaring of the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">sea</name> <pb n="290"/> as it booms beneath rocky cliffs. Distressed though he is, despite his efforts scarce can the wind escape upward; yet medicinal draughts can at once make him void egg-shaped stools, like the shell-less lumps which the free-feeding <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">fowl</name>, when brooding her warlike <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">chicks</name>, sometimes under stress of recent blows drops from her belly in their membranes; sometimes under stress of sickness she will cast out her ill-fated offspring upon the earth.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="65">
   <p>The familiar astringent draught of <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">wormwood</name> steeped in freshly pressed <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">grape-syrup</name> will check his pain; <pb n="300"/> sometimes too you may cut up the resin of the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">terebinth-tree</name>, or else the tears of the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">Corsican pine</name>, or again of the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">Aleppo pine</name> which makes moan on the spot where <name type="deity">Phoebus</name> stripped the skin from the limbs of <persName>Marsyas</persName>; and the tree, lamenting in the glens his far-famed fate, alone utters her passionate plaint unceasingly. Give him also plenty of the flowers of the bright <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">hulwort</name>, fatal to <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">mice</name>, or strip the low-growing shoots of <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">rue</name>, and <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">spikenard</name>, and take also the testicle of the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">beaver</name> that dwells in the lake; or rub down an <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">obol</name> of <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">silphium</name> with a toothed scraper, or else cut off the same quantity of its gum.</p>
   <p><pb n="310"/> Sometimes too he may be given his fill of the wild <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">goat's marjoram</name>, or of <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">milk</name> just curdling in the pail after milking.</p>
   <p>But if a man in his folly taste the fresh blood of a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">bull</name> he falls heavily to the ground in distress, overmastered by pain, when, as it reaches the chest, the blood congeals easily, and, in the hollow of his stomach, clots; the passages are stopped, the breath is straitened within his clogged throat, while, often struggling in convulsions on the ground, he gasps bespattered with foam.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="66">
   <p>You should cut off for him some juicy <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">wild figs</name>, <pb n="320"/> soak in <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">vinegar</name>, and then mingle the whole with water, stirring together the water and the astringent draught of <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">vinegar</name>; or drain away the burden of his surcharged belly.</p>
   <p>Also you should strain through a porous bag of fine linen some stirred <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">curd</name> either from a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">fawn</name> of <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">roe</name> or <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">red deer</name> or from a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">kid</name>; or again if you take some from the nimble <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">hare</name> you will bring healing and help to the sufferer.</p>
   <p>Or give him three <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">obols</name>' weight of well-powdered <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">soda</name>, and mix it in a sweet draught of <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">wine</name>; mix too a pound weight with equal parts of <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">silphium</name> and of its gum, <pb n="330"/> and seed of <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">cabbage</name> soaked thoroughly in <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">vinegar</name>.</p>
   <p>And give him a sprig of <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">flea-bane</name> with its ill-coloured leaves. Or you should bruise some <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">pepper</name> and buds of the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">bramble-bush</name>; then you will easily dissipate a mass of congealing blood, or break it up if it has lodged in the vessels.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="67">
   <p>Do not let the agonising drink of the hateful <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">buprestis</name> escape your knowledge; and you should recognise a man overcome by it. In truth, when bitten, its contact with the jaws seems that of <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">soda</name>; it has an evil smell; and all about the mouths of the stomach arise shifting pains; <pb n="340"/> the urine is stopped and the lowest part of the bladder throbs, while the whole belly is inflated, as when a tympanitic <name type="disease">dropsy</name> settles in abundance about the mid navel, and all over the man's limbs the skin is visibly taut. This creature too, I fancy, causes swelling in plump-bellied heifers or calves, whenever they bite it as they graze. For this reason herdsmen name it <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">buprestis</name> {"cow-inflater"}.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="68">
   <p>Mix for the patient a draught of well-dried <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">navel-figs</name> from a flourishing tree in wine three years old; or you might also crush them together with a mallet, <pb n="350"/> dissolve them over a fire, and give as an antidote to his sickness.</p>
   <p>And when he recovers his appetite give him again his fill of this honey-sweet drink, sometimes adding <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">milk</name> to the mixture; or else cast in and mix with wine the dry fruit of the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">date-palm</name> or <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">wild pears</name> that have long been dried, or the fruit of the common <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">pear</name>, or of the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">cordate pear</name>, or sometimes <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">myrtle-berries</name>; or let him even, like a new-born child, put his lips to the nipple, and <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">calf</name>-like draw a draught from the breast, even as a new-born <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">calf</name> fresh from the womb, butting the udder, forces out the quickening flow from the teat.</p>
   <p><pb n="360"/> Or else you may give him his fill of some warm and greasy drink and compel him to vomit unwilling though he be, forcing him with your fingers or with a feather; or cut and twist from <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">papyrus</name> a curved throat-tickler.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="69">
   <p>But if fresh <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">milk</name> turn cheesy in the hollow of a man's stomach, then, as it collects, suffocation overcomes him. Give him three draughts, one of <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">vinegar</name> between two of <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">grape-syrup</name>, and purge his <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">costive</name> bowels. Or further, grate into a draught the root of <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">silphium</name> from <placeName>Libya</placeName>, or else some of its gum, and administer it dissolved in <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">vinegar</name>. <pb n="370"/></p>
   <p>Or again, you may add to the mixture dispersive <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">lye</name> or a fresh-blooming sprig of <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">Cretan thyme</name>. Sometimes the clustered fruit of the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">eucnemus</name> well-steeped in <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">wine</name> is a help. Also a drink of <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">curd</name>, they say, disperses the clots; so too the green leaves of <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">mint</name> mixed either with a draught of <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">honey</name> or with an astringent one of <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">vinegar</name>.</p>
   <p>Consider now the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">thorn-apple</name>, whose aspect and whose taste upon the lips are like <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">milk</name>. At once unwonted retchings agitate the throat of the drinker, and by reason of the pain at the mouth of his stomach <pb n="380"/> he either vomits up his food stained with blood, or else he voids it, foul and fill of mucus, from his bowels, like one suffering from the spasms of dysentery. Sometimes worn out with the parching struggle his limbs give way and he falls to the ground, yet has no wish to moisten his dry mouth.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="70">
   <p>You must either administer draughts of milk, or else perhaps grape-syrup, slightly warmed and mixed with it in his cup. Moreover the flesh from the plump breast of a sleek <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">fowl</name>, softened on the fire and eaten, can be a help; so too is gruel if swallowed by the bowlful; <pb n="390"/> also the creatures which beneath the roaring of the rocky sea ever feed about the weed-clad crags: some of these he should devour raw, others boiled, many of them after broiling over a fire; but dishes of <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">sea-snails</name> or of the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">purple</name> <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">limpet</name>, of <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">crayfish</name> and <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">pinna</name> and of the brown <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">sea-urchin</name> will be far more helpful, and <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">scallops</name>; neither . . . the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">trumpet-shell</name> or <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">sea-squirts</name> that revel in the seaweed.</p>
   <p>Let not the hateful draught of <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">pharicum</name> escape your memory - for you are not ignorant of it: it causes grievous suffering in the jaws. Know that to the taste it is like <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">spikenard</name>; but it sends men reeling <pb n="400"/> or sometimes out of their senses, and in a single day it can easily kill a strong man.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="71">
   <p>Now you may either weigh out and administer some of the purse-like root of the fair-flowering <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">mountain nard</name> which the headlands of <placeName>Cilicia</placeName> nourish by the brimming <foreign xml:lang="la">Cestrus</foreign>, or else well-ground <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">Cretan alexanders</name>. Take also the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">iris</name> itself and the head of the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">lily</name>, abhorred of <name type="deity">Aphrodite</name>, seeing that it was her rival for colour; wherefore in the midst of its petals she attached a thing of shame to vex it, making to grow there the shocking yard of an ass.</p>
   <p>Or else you may shave his head, and having cut the hair from the roots with a keen-edged razor, take it, and after heating along with it fresh <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">barley-meal</name> and the dry leaves of <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">rue</name>, which in its feeding the caterpillar is quickest to spoil, soak in vinegar and plaster thickly about his temples.</p>
   <p>Let no man in ignorance fill his belly with <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">henbane</name>, as men often do in error, or as children who, having lately put aside their swaddling-clothes and head-bindings, and their perilous crawling on all fours, and walking now upright with no anxious nurse at hand, chew its sprays of baleful flowers through witlessness, since they are just bringing to light the incisor teeth in their jaws, at which time itching assails their swollen gums.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="72">
   <p>Give the patient either pure <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">milk</name> to drink as a remedy or else <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">fenugreek</name>, which is grown for fodder and puts forth curving horns amid its windswept leaves - a great boon when it floats in common <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">oil</name>. Or else you should give him dried <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">nettle</name> seed, or even the raw leaves of the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">nettle</name> itself in plenty to suck, or <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">chicory</name> and <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">garden-cress</name> and what they call <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">perseum</name>, <pb n="430"/> and besides these, <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">mustard</name> and <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">radishes</name> in plenty, and mingled with them slender <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">spring onions</name>. A head of <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">garlic</name> with well-grown cloves just taken in a drink also averts disaster.</p>
   <p>Learn further that when men drink the tears of the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">poppy</name>, whose seeds are in a head, they fall fast asleep; for their extremities are chilled; their eyes do not open but are bound quite motionless by their eyelids. With the exhaustion an odorous sweat bathes all the body, turns the cheeks pale, and causes the lips to swell; the bonds of the jaw are relaxed, <pb n="440"/> and through the throat the laboured breath passes faint and chill. And often either the livid nail or wrinkled nostril is a harbinger of death; sometimes too the sunken eyes.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="73">
   <p>Of all these symptoms you must not be afraid, but devote yourself entirely to succour, filling the failing man with boiling-hot <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">wine</name> and <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">grape-syrup</name> . Or else make haste to break in pieces the labour of the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">bee</name> of <placeName>Hymettus</placeName> . (<name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Bees</name> were born from the carcase of a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">calf</name> that had fallen dead in the glades, and there in some hollow <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">oak</name> they first, maybe, united to build their nest, and then, bethinking themselves of work,  450  wrought round it in <name type="deity">Demeter</name> 's honour their many-celled combs, as with their feet they gathered <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">thyme</name> and flowering <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">heath</name>.) There are times when, prizing open his <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">dog-teeth</name>, or into his drooping <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">jaws</name>, you should squeeze with a tuft of fleecy <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">wool</name> some fresh, fragrant <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">rose-oil</name> or <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">iris-oil</name> or again <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">oil</name> of the sleek <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">olive</name> ; and let him drain a thick flock saturated with it. And forthwith rouse him with slaps on either cheek, or else by shouting, or again by shaking him as he sleeps, in order that the swooning man may dispel the fatal drowsiness and may then vomit, ridding himself of the grievous affliction.  460  And dip cloths first in <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">wine</name> and then in warm <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">oil</name> , and rub and chafe his chilled limbs with the liquid; or again, mix them in a bath-tub and dip his body in it, and at once immerse him in the hot bath and so thaw his blood and soften his taut, dry skin.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="74">
   <p>Also you should learn to know the dire and fateful drink of the deadly <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">sea-hare</name>, offspring of the waves of the pebbly sea. Its odour is that of fishes' scales and of the water in which they have been scoured; its taste is fishy like that of rotten fish, or of unwashed when scales taint the dish.</p>
   <p>A sordid creature with its slim tentacles, it resembles the new-born young of the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">calamary</name> or of the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">octopus</name> or the fugitive <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">cuttlefish</name>, which stains the sea black with its gall directly it perceives the fisherman's crafty assault. Over the limbs of the poisoned spreads the dusky pallor of jaundice, and piecemeal their flesh melts away and dwindles, and food is utterly loathsome.</p>
   <p>At times the surface of the flesh swells and grows puffy about the ankles; the eyes are swollen, and as it were luxuriant blossoms settle upon the cheeks. For there follows a scantier flow of urine, which is sometimes red, at others still more bloody in colour.</p>
   <p>Then the sight of every fish is hateful to his eyes and in his disgust he loathes food from the sea.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="75">
   <p>Give the patient a sufficient draught of <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">Phocian hellebore</name> or the gum of new-grown <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">scammony</name> in order that he may void both the draught and the filth of the evil <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">fish</name>; or else he should milk a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">she-ass</name> and drink the milk, or he should dissolve smooth-skinned sprigs of the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">mallow</name> in a pot. Then again he is given an <name type="deity">obol</name>'s weight of <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">cedar pitch</name>; or else let him eat his fill of the scarlet fruit of the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">pomegranate</name>, the <placeName>Cretan</placeName> kind, the wine-red, and the sort they call <foreign xml:lang="en">Promenean</foreign>, also that from <placeName>Aegina</placeName>, and all those which partition hard, red grains into sections by a covering like a spider's web. Or else you should squeeze the flesh of <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">grapes</name> through a strainer, like olives oozing beneath the presses.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="76">
   <p>But if a man whose throat is constrained by parching thirst fall on his knees and draw water from a stream like a bull, parting with his hand the delicate, moss-like <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">plants</name>, then, approaching eagerly along with the water there rushes upon him in its desire for food the blood-loving <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">leech</name>, <foreign xml:lang="la">long flaccid and yearning for gore</foreign>.</p>
   <p>Or when a man's eyes are shrouded beneath dark night, and without thinking he drinks from a pitcher, tipping it up and pressing his lips to its, the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">creature</name> floating on the surface of the water passes down his throat. At the point to which first the stream drives and collects them, the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">leeches</name> fasten on in numbers and suck the body's blood, settling now at the entrance where the breath always gathers to pour through the narrow pharynx, and sometimes one clings about the mouths of the stomach inflicting pain, <foreign xml:lang="la">and swallows a fresh repast</foreign>.</p>
   <p>You should administer to the patient a draught of <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">vinegar</name> mixed in his cup, and sometimes with it <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">snow</name> to eat, or <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">ice</name> fresh frozen by the north winds. Or you should dig up some moist, brackish <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">soil</name> and brew therewith a turbid potion to give him strength; or draw actual <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">salt water</name>, and either warm it at once beneath the late summer sun or heat it steadily over a fire. Or else you should give him <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">rock salt</name> in plenty or the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">salt flakes</name> which a salter ever gathers as they settle at the bottom when he mingles water with water.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="77">
   <p>Let not the evil ferment of the soil injure a man; it will often swell up in his chest, at other times it will choke him, when it is fostered over the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">viper</name>'s coil deep in its lair, sucking up the monster's venom and the noxious breath from its mouth. This is the evil ferment which they call <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">Fungi</name> in general, for to different kinds different names have been assigned.</p>
   <p>Now do you cut off either the head of a <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">cabbage</name> with its coats of leaves or the green fronds of <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">rue</name>, and administer them. Or else crumble the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">bloom of copper</name> that has had long use, or ashes of the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">vine</name> in <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">vinegar</name>. Sometimes grate the root of <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">bindweed</name> or some <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">soda</name> into an infusion of vinegar, or a leaf of the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">cress</name> which grows in garden-plots; and <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">citron</name> too, and the biting <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">mustard</name>. You should also reduce to ashes in the fire the lees of <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">wine</name> or the droppings of the domestic <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">fowl</name>, and then let the man thrust his hand hard down his throat and vomit up the deadly poison.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="78">
   <p>But if hurt come from a draught, hard to cure, of the sorcerer's <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">lizard</name>, slippery-skinned and utterly reckless, which they call the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">salamander</name>, and which not even a fierce flame can harm, <pb n="540"/> then on a sudden the base of the tongue is inflamed and then the victims are overcome with chill, and a fearful trembling burdens and loosens their joints. They stagger and crawl upon all fours like an <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">infant</name>, for the faculties of the mind are utterly blunted, and livid weals spreading thick over the skin blotch the extremities as the poison is diffused.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="79">
   <p>Give the sufferer frequent doses of the tears stripped from the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">pine-tree</name> mingled with the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">bee</name>'s rich produce; or boil down the leaves of the budding <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">ground-pine</name> together with the cones which the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">pine</name> puts forth. <pb n="550"/> And sometimes mix the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">nettle</name>'s seed with the finely ground meal of <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">bitter vetch</name>, and dry them. Sometimes too you should sprinkle cooked <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">nettles</name> with crumbling <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">barley-groats</name>, dress well in <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">oil</name>, and force the patient to eat in plenty even against his will.</p>
   <p>Again, <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">pine-resin</name> and the sacred produce of the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">bee</name> and the root of <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">all-heal</name> and the delicate eggs of the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">tortoise</name> are curative when you mix them on a hot fire; curative too the flesh of a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">hog</name> abounding in fat when boiled down together with the limbs of the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">sea-turtle</name> which swims at large with weak flippers; or else with those of the mountain <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">tortoise</name> that feeds on <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">tree-medick</name>, the creature <pb n="560"/> that <persName>Hermes</persName> the Gracious endowed with a voice though voiceless, for he separated the chequered shell from the flesh and extended two arms from its edges.</p>
   <p>Further, either you should bend to your service the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">tadpoles</name>' impudent parents and <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">eryngo</name> roots with them, or you should throw into a pot a sufficient quantity of <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">scammony</name> and cook it. With these feed the sick man to satiety, and though he be near to death, you will save him.</p>
</div>
<div type="book" n="80">
   <p>If a man imbibe a draught from the sun-loving <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">toad</name> or from the dumb and green-hued <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">toad</name> which in the springtime cling to the bushes, sleek, and licking up the dew, <pb n="570"/> one of them, the sun-lover, induces a pallor like <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">fustic</name> and causes swellings in the limbs while the breath issues continually in long gasps and forced, and smells foul at the mouth.</p>
   <p>Whereas the voiceless one that frequents the reeds sometimes diffuses the yellowness of <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">boxwood</name> over the limbs, <pb n="580"/> and sometimes bedews the mouth with a flow of bile. Sometimes too a man suffers from heart-burn, and persistent hiccups convulse him. And it causes the seed, now of man now of woman, to drip on, and often scattering it over their limbs it renders it infertile.</p>
   <p>But you should give the patient the flesh of a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">frog</name> boiled or roasted; sometimes <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">pitch</name> which you have mixed with sweet <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">wine</name>. And the spleen of the deadly <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">toad</name> averts the grievous oppression - the vocal toad of the fen, which cries on the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">sedge</name>, the first harbinger of delightful spring.</p>
   <p>Further, for such patients you should sometimes pour out <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">wine</name> in abundance, cup after cup, and induce the man to vomit, reluctant though he be; or else heat over a fire a big-bellied vessel and keep the sick man always warm, and let him sweat profusely.</p>
   <p>Also you should clip and mix with <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">wine</name> the roots of tall-growing <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">reeds</name> which are nourished by the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">toads</name>' native marsh, <pb n="590"/> where as tiny creatures they swim about with their feet, or roots of the life</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="81">
   <p>loving <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">galingale</name>, female and male; and dry the man's body by ceaseless exercise, keeping him from all food and drink, and exhaust his limbs.</p>
   <p>Also do not neglect <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">litharge</name>, which brings suffering when its hateful burden sinks into the stomach and wind circulates and rumbles about the mid navel, as in a violent colic which overpowers men, smiting them with sudden pains. The victim's flow of urine fails; then the limbs swell <pb n="600"/> and the skin has the appearance of lead.</p>
   <p>Give the patient either a double <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">obol</name>'s weight of <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">myrrh</name> or a fresh infusion of <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">sage</name>, or else cut him <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">hypericum</name> from the hills, or sprigs of <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">hyssop</name>, or again a spray of the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">wild</name> <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">fig</name> and seed of <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">celery</name> from the <placeName>Isthmus</placeName>, beneath which the sons of <persName>Sisyphus</persName> buried the youthful <name type="deity">Melicertes</name>, slain by the sea, and established games. Or else you should roast <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">pepper</name> along with <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">rue</name> and grate them into <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">wine</name>, and so rescue him from deadly sickness. You should also give him fresh buds of <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">henna</name>, or the firstling fruit of the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">pomegranate</name> <pb n="610"/> with the flower still upon it.</p>
   <p>[See that you do not pluck the dangerous, pine-like <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">yew</name> of <placeName>Oeta</placeName>: it is the giver of lamentable death, and only a copious draught of unmixed <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">wine</name> can bring instant help when it chokes the pharynx and the narrow passage of a man's throat.]</p>
</div>
<div type="book" n="1">
   <div type="section" n="82">
      <p>Some remedies medicinal for a man against noxious fungi <persName>Nicander</persName> in fact set down in his book, but in addition to these the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">myrtle</name> whose twigs <persName>Dictynna</persName> abhors, and which <name type="deity">Hera</name> of the <placeName>Imbrasus</placeName> alone receives not for her garland, seeing that it adorned the <name type="deity">Cyprian</name> queen on mount <placeName>Ida</placeName>, when the goddesses were roused to compete in beauty with one another - from this in some watered glade take as a healing boon the scarlet fruit that waxes and is warmed with the wintry rays of the sun, and pounding them with a pestle strain the juice over fine linen or with a rush sieve and administer a cup containing a <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">cyathus</name> - or more, for a larger dose is serviceable since this draught is not harmful to men - for that is in fact sufficient cure if you drink it.</p>
   </div>
   <div type="section" n="83">
      <p>And now hereafter you will treasure the memory of <persName>Nicander</persName> the singer, and observe the command of <name type="deity">Zeus</name>, Protector of Friendships.</p>
   </div>
   <div type="section" n="84">
      <p><persName>Nicander</persName>, <quote><foreign xml:lang="la">'GEORGICA'</foreign></quote></p>
      <p><persName>Nicander</persName> in the first book of his two <foreign xml:lang="la">Georgica</foreign> showing the use of groats also mentions the word <foreign xml:lang="grc">mystron</foreign> [spoon hollowed out of bread] in the following words :</p>
   </div>
</div>
<div type="book" n="2">
   <div type="section" n="1">
      <p>But when you prepare for eating a freshly-killed <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">kid</name> or <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">lamb</name> or even a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">chicken</name>, sprinkle the bottom of hollow vessels with unripe wheaten groats and pound them down; then stir up together with fragrant oil. And when the broth seethes, pour it over them . . . but smother by clapping on the lid, for as it stews the coarse meal swells. And when it simmers gently, eat it with hollow scoops of bread.</p>
   </div>
   <div type="section" n="2">
      <p><foreign xml:lang="la">Oaks</foreign>, the delight of  <name type="deity">Pan</name>,</p>
      <p>says <persName>Nicander</persName> in the second book of the <foreign xml:lang="la">Georgica</foreign>.</p>
      <p><placeName>Athen</placeName>. 9.369 B  4.133 D-E</p>
      <p>(a) <persName>Nicander</persName> in his <foreign xml:lang="la">Georgica</foreign> mentions the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">French turnip</name>. (b) And that to whet the appetite they also ate turnips treated with vinegar and mustard <persName>Nicander</persName> makes plain in the second book of his <foreign xml:lang="la">Georgica</foreign>, saying . . . (c) <persName>Nicander</persName> of  <placeName>Colophon</placeName>  mentioned mustard {in <foreign xml:lang="la">Th</foreign>. 921} and in his <foreign xml:lang="la">Georgica</foreign>.</p>
   </div>
</div>
<div type="section" n="84">
   <p>But sow turnips on a threshing-floor levelled with a roller, so that they may grow to the shape of low kneading-tables. The <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">turnip</name> . . . for two stocks, <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">turnip</name> and <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">French turnip</name>, both of them long and solid, are to be seen in our garden-plots. <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">French turnips</name> you should wash and dry in the north winds; they are welcome in winter to those who stay idle indoors, and if soaked in hot water they revive. But the roots of the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">turnip</name> you should cut into fine slices after gently washing the dry outer skin, and then let them parch for a little while in the sun; or else dip a number of them in boiling water, and then plunge them into bitter brine; or again pour <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">white must</name> and <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">vinegar</name> into the same vessel in equal quantities, and then immerse them in it and cover with <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">salt</name>. Again, you may pound <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">raisins</name> and the mordant seed of <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">mustard</name> with a pestle and pour them in. And at the same time moist lees of <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">vinegar</name> . . .</p>
   <p><quote>Nicander in the second book of his <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">Georgica</name> says:</quote></p>
   <p>And along with them a tall stem of <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">fennel</name>, along with them too roots of <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">stone sperage</name>, and even the slatternly <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">carrot</name> as well, <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">Cretan alexanders</name>, and <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">sow-thistle</name>, and <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">hound's tongue</name>, and <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">endive</name>; with them pound also the bitter leaves of <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">cuckoo-pint</name> and the plant which is called <foreign xml:lang="grc">'bird's milk'</foreign> .</p>
   <p><quote>Nicander of <placeName>Colophon</placeName> in the second book of <name type="work">his Georgica</name> makes mention of this practice, calling <foreign xml:lang="grc">kolokyntae</foreign> {<name type="plant" xml:lang="en">gourds</name>} <foreign xml:lang="grc">sikyae</foreign>, for, as we have said before, that was what they used to be called. And this is what he says:</quote></p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="85">
   <p>But as to the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">gourds</name> themselves, when you cut them, put cords through them and dry them in the open air. Then hang them up in the smoke so that in winter your servants may fill a sufficiently ample pot and may gobble them up with no need to work . . . the woman who grinds corn pours in pulse of all kinds. Into it men cast strings of <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">gourds</name> after a thorough cleansing, and <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">mushrooms</name> too, and ropes long since plaited of dried vegetables . . .</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="86">
   <p><persName>Nicander</persName> in the second book of his <name type="work">Georgica</name> speaking of <placeName>Sicilian</placeName> <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">doves</name> says</p>
   <p>And you should rear in your home <foreign xml:lang="la">Dracontian</foreign> <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">doves</name> which lay two eggs at a time, or <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">doves</name> of <placeName>Sicily</placeName> ; for it is said that neither <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">kites</name> harm them, nor (?) <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">snakes</name> their eggs.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="87">
   <p><quote><persName>Nicander</persName> in the second book of his <name type="work">Georgica</name>, likewise enumerating flowers which are suitable for wreaths, speaks of the <name type="deity">Ioniad Nymphs</name> and of <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">roses</name> as follows :</quote></p>
   <p>But the flowers of <placeName>Ionia</placeName> you should sow, and all such as come to full growth you should transplant. Of <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">gilliflowers</name> there are two kinds, <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">one</name> is yellow and like gold to look upon; the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">others</name> , those which the <name type="deity">Ioniad Nymphs</name> proffered in their yearning as a pure chaplet to <persName>Ion</persName> in the lands of <placeName>Pisa</placeName> ; for, pursuing a wild <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">boar</name> with his hounds, he had overtaken it, and in <persName>Alpheius</persName> 's stream he washed the bloodstains from his limbs at eve before passing the night with the <name type="deity">Ioniad Nymphs</name>.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="86">
   <p>But from the thorny <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">rose</name> you should cut shoots and plant them in trenches making them two full palms in length. First, those which <persName>Midas</persName> of <placeName>Odonia</placeName>, when he forsook his kingdom in <placeName>Asia</placeName>, raised in the lands of <placeName>Emathia</placeName>, ever crowned with full sixty petals in a ring.</p>
   <p>Second, the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">roses</name> of <placeName>Nisaea</placeName> by <placeName>Megara</placeName>; neither is <placeName>Phaselis</placeName> nor the city which reveres the <name type="deity">White-browed Goddess</name> to be spurned, the flourishing city by the waters of <placeName>Magnesian</placeName> <placeName>Lethaeus</placeName>.</p>
   <p>Sometimes plant shoots of the strong-rooted <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">ivy</name> in trenches, sometimes even a spray of the white-berried <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">ivy</name> from <placeName>Thrace</placeName> or else the white kind or that with wandering tendrils. They should be plucked as young shoots, and you should strengthen and make them to grow into a single head, fastening the twisted ends deep in freshly plaited baskets in order that two golden clusters may unite and be linked right up to the flaunting crown, the green foliage sheltering them on either side.</p>
   <p>From seed no doubt spring the cupped <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">flowers</name> {<name type="plant" xml:lang="en">lilies</name>} that put forth heads, whose petals are white, whose centres saffron-stained. These some poets style <foreign xml:lang="grc">krina</foreign>, and others <foreign xml:lang="grc">leiria</foreign>, others again <foreign xml:lang="grc">ambrosia</foreign>, and many <name type="deity">Aphrodite</name>'s Joy, for the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">lily</name> rivalled the hue of her skin. But the thing of shame uprising in its midst has been named the yard of a braying <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">ass</name>.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="87">
   <p>The <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">iris</name> however is grown from roots - the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">dwarf iris</name> and that which is like the mourning <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">hyacinth</name> but grows with blossoms <foreign xml:lang="en">swallow-hued</foreign>, keeping pace with the swallows' coming; and both kinds put forth in folds their ruthless leaves, and the new-born flower-cups seem ever to have drooping lips.</p>
   <p>So too grow the flowers of dazzling hue, <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">corn-cockle</name> and <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">plantain</name>; nor shall the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">camomile</name> in bloom be counted nought, nor the well-known <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">ox-eyes</name> which uplift their head so high, nor the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">wallflower</name> that vies with the rising beams of the Sun god.</p>
   <p>But <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">tufted thyme</name> you will plant on . . . in order that, as its long sprays creep forward, the wind may blow through them or that it may hang downwards in its desire for draughts of water.</p>
   <p>But of the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">poppy</name> itself . . . cast away the petals, in order that you may preserve its capsule undevoured by <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">caterpillars</name>, for in truth all creeping things settle upon the petals as they open and feed upon the capsule which is like dewdrops, full as it is of honey-sweet fruit.</p>
   <p>But when the petals are gone, the heat or else the buffeting winds easily harden the flesh, and the creatures get no firm foothold when they hope to find food, and often their footsteps slip when they essay the solid heads . . .</p>
   <p>A good depth of manure in the pot brings on the shoots of <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">marjoram</name> and the young sprigs of the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">frankincense-tree</name>, and all other plants which gardens furnish to make chaplets for toiling men . . .</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="88">
   <p>Yes, and delicate <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">ferns</name> and the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">acanthus</name> which resembles the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">white poplar</name>, and the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">crocus</name> which closes in the spring, <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">henna</name> too and scented <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">bergamot-mint</name> and all other lovelinesses that unsown a meadow rears in hollow, watered spots, <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">ox-eye</name> and fragrant <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">flower-of-Zeus</name>, <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">chrysanthemums</name> and also <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">hyacinth</name> and low-growing <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">violets</name>, dark, and abhorred of <name type="deity">Persephone</name> among flowers.</p>
   <p>And of their company are the towering <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">all-scent</name> and the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">cornflags</name> which encircle the graves of virgins lately dead, and sparkling <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">anemones</name> which with their dazzling colours lure living maidens from afar.</p>
   <p>And everybody plucks <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">elecampane</name> or gleaming <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">blue-daisy</name> and sets it down by the roadside shrines of gods or upon the statues themselves, as soon as he sees them, gathering sometimes, too, fair <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">lupins</name>, or else the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">gold-flower</name> and <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">lilies</name> that fade upon the tombstones of the dead, and <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">salsify</name> with its grey beard, and modest <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">cyclamens</name> and <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">garden-cress</name>, which men call the garland of the Netherworld Captain.</p>
   <p>And <persName>Nicander</persName> besides in his <quote>Georgica</quote> explains also that it (the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">mulberry</name>) appears earlier than other fruits, and he always calls the tree <foreign xml:lang="grc">morea</foreign>, as do the <name type="placeName">Alexandrian</name> writers too.</p>
   <p>And of the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">mulberry</name>, which is the delight of little boys and is the harbinger to man of the pleasant season of fruit.</p>
   <p>The <name type="placeName">Euboeans</name> named it {i.e. the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">sweet chestnut</name>} <foreign xml:lang="grc">lopimon</foreign> and <foreign xml:lang="grc">karyon</foreign>, but others <foreign xml:lang="grc">balanos</foreign>,</p>
   <p>says <persName>Nicander</persName> of <placeName>Colophon</placeName> in his <quote>Georgica</quote>.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="89">
   <p>And <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">fungi</name> are generated from the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">soil</name>, and only a few of them are edible, for the majority choke the eater . . . And <persName>Nicander</persName> in his <foreign xml:lang="la">Georgica</foreign> states also which are the deadly ones, and says</p>
   <p><quote>Horrid pains are in store from the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">olive</name> and from the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">pomegranate</name> and the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">holm-oak</name> and the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">oak</name> . . . the choking weight of puffy <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">fungi</name> that cling to . . .</quote></p>
   <p>When you bury the foot of a <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">fig-tree</name> deep in <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">dung</name> and moisten it with a constant flow of <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">water</name>, there will grow on the roots <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">fungi</name> of the harmless kind. You may gather any of these cultivated on the root, but not those which grow on the ground.</p>
   <p>(The remainder could not be read.)</p>
   <p>And then you will cook some <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">champignons</name> with them,</p>
   <p>says <persName>Nicander</persName> in the same passage.</p>
   <p><persName>Nicander</persName> in his <foreign xml:lang="la">Georgica</foreign> says</p>
   <p>At the same time they lop off the side-growths of the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">date-palm</name> and bear away the 'cabbage', which <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">children</name> delight to eat.</p>
   <p><persName>Nicander</persName> in his <foreign xml:lang="la">Georgica</foreign> says</p>
   <p>Of <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">beans</name> sow the <foreign xml:lang="en">Egyptian</foreign>, so that in summer you may contrive garlands with its flowers, and that, when the pods of ripe fruit have fallen off, you may hand them to <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">youths</name> who have long craved for them as they feast. But the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">tubers</name> I boil down and serve at banquets.</p>
   <p>What <persName>Nicander</persName> calls '<name type="plant" xml:lang="en">tubers</name>' <persName>Alexandrian</persName> writers call <foreign xml:lang="en">colocasia</foreign>; as the same writer has it</p>
   <p>Having stripped the <foreign xml:lang="en">colocasium</foreign> from its <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">bean</name> and shredded it into . . .</p>
   <p>And <persName>Nicander</persName> of <placeName>Colophon</placeName> in his <foreign xml:lang="la">Georgica</foreign> enumerates the following kinds of <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">shell-fish</name> :</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="90">
   <p>Or all such <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">shell-fish</name> also as feed in the depths of the brine - <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">sea-snails</name> and <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">whelks</name> and <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">clams</name> and <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">mussels</name>, the clinging children of the <name type="deity">sea-goddess</name>, and the den of the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">pinna</name> itself.</p>
   <p><persName>Nicander</persName> of <placeName>Colophon</placeName> mentions <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">mustard</name> and in his <foreign xml:lang="la">Georgica</foreign> says,</p>
   <quote>
      <p>And the mordant seeds of <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">mustard</name>.</p>
   </quote>
   <p><name type="plant" xml:lang="en">Garden-cress</name> and <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">pepper-grass</name> and the dark-leaved <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">mustard</name>.</p>
   <p><persName>Nicander</persName> in his <foreign xml:lang="la">Georgica</foreign> says :</p>
   <quote>
      <p>The <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">cabbage</name> is smooth, but at times the wild form may intrude into sown gardens and flourish with an abundance of leaves, either the curled kind. . . with leaves, or the green, which turns red and looks parched, and the ill-coloured <foreign xml:lang="en">Cumaean</foreign> which is like the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">soles</name> wherewith men cobble second-hand sandals. This men of an older generation style a prophet for vegetables.</p>
   </quote>
   <p><persName>Nicander</persName> of <placeName>Colophon</placeName> says that <foreign xml:lang="grc">oinos</foreign> was so called after <persName>Oineus</persName> :</p>
   <quote>
      <p>And <persName>Oeneus</persName> squeezed it out into hollow cups and called it <foreign xml:lang="grc">oinos</foreign>.</p>
   </quote>
   <p>The fruit they call the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">cuckoo's</name>.</p>
   <p>The word <foreign xml:lang="grc">ἀμορβεύειν</foreign> signifies 'to attend' and 'to minister to'. <persName>Nicander</persName> in another work writes:</p>
   <quote>
      <p><name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Oxherds</name> attend to the teams of <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">mules</name>.</p>
   </quote>
   <p>For he habitually calls bitter, pungent things 'astringent'. For example, he describes unripe <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">grapes</name> as 'drawing up', 'astringent'.</p>
   <quote>
      <p>When a draught of unripe <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">grapes</name> draws up the lip.</p>
   </quote>
</div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
