<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng"
    type="application/xml"
    schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title xml:lang="en">Μῦθοι</title>
        <title type="alt" xml:lang="fr">Fables</title>
        <title type="alt" xml:lang="en">Fables</title>
        <author>
          <persName>ESOPUS</persName>
          <idno type="zoomathia">tlg0096</idno>
        </author>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Encodage automatique TEI P5</resp>
          <name>zoomathia_encoder.py v3.0</name>
          <date when="2026-07-02">2026-07-02</date>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Projet Zoomathia (ANR-21-CE27-0012)</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Universite Cote d'Azur, Nice, France</pubPlace>
        <date when="2026-07-02">2026-07-02</date>
        <availability>
          <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0</licence>
        </availability>
        <idno type="zoomathia">tlg0096</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Encode automatiquement par zoomathia_encoder.py v3.0 - Projet Zoomathia</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language ident="en">anglais</language>
      </langUsage>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="zoomathia">
          <term>Zoomathia</term>
          <term>animaux</term>
          <term>antique (800 av. J.-C. - 300 ap. J.-C.)</term>
          <term>anglais</term>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>Fichier encode automatiquement dans le cadre du projet Zoomathia (ANR).
        Encodage produit par zoomathia_encoder.py v3.0. Verification humaine recommandee.</p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>Balisage automatique des structures textuelles et des entites nommees
        pertinentes pour Zoomathia (animaux, plantes, personnes, lieux).</p>
        <correction status="unknown">
          <p>Encodage automatique - erreurs possibles, revision manuelle recommandee.</p>
        </correction>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
Voici l'encodage TEI P5 strictement conforme à vos règles pour le texte fourni, en respectant les priorités Zoomathia (bien que ce texte ne contienne pas d'entités zoologiques, botaniques ou divines) :


<div type="book" n="1">
  <div type="chapter" n="I">
    <head>THAT WOMAN</head>
    <p>The Project Gutenberg eBook of Imperial Purple</p>
    <p>This eBook is for the use of anyone anywhere in the United States and
    most other parts of the world at no cost and with almost no restrictions
    whatsoever. You may copy it, give it away or re-use it under the terms
    of the Project Gutenberg License included with this eBook or online
    at www.gutenberg.org. If you are not located in the United States,
    you will have to check the laws of the country where you are located
    before using this eBook.</p>
    <p>Title: Imperial Purple</p>
    <p>Author: Edgar Saltus</p>
    <p>Release date: July 1, 2003 [eBook #4250]
                Most recently updated: December 27, 2020</p>
    <p>Language: English</p>
    <p>Other information and formats: www.gutenberg.org/ebooks/4250</p>
    <p>Credits: Produced by Robert Rowe, Charles Franks and the Online
        Distributed Proofreading Team. HTML version by Al Haines.</p>
    <p>*** START OF THE PROJECT GUTENBERG EBOOK IMPERIAL PURPLE ***</p>
    <p>Produced by Robert Rowe, Charles Franks and the Online
        Distributed Proofreading Team. HTML version by Al Haines.</p>
    <p>IMPERIAL PURPLE</p>
    <p>By</p>
    <p>EDGAR SALTUS</p>
    <p>CONTENTS</p>
    <p>I. That Woman</p>
    <p>II. Conjectural Rome</p>
    <p>III. Fabulous Fields</p>
    <p>IV. The Pursuit of the Impossible</p>
    <p>V. Nero</p>
    <p>VI. The House of Flavia</p>
    <p>VII. The Poison in the Purple</p>
    <p>VIII. Faustine</p>
    <p>IX. The Agony</p>
  </div>
</div>
Voici l'encodage TEI P5 strictement conforme à vos exigences pour le texte fourni, en respectant toutes les règles et priorités :


<div type="book" n="2">
   <p>When the murder was done and the heralds shouted through the thick
   streets the passing of <persName>Caesar</persName>, it was the passing of the republic they
   announced, the foundation of Imperial <placeName>Rome</placeName>.</p>
   <p>There was a hush, then a riot which frightened a senate that frightened
   the world. <persName>Caesar</persName> was adored. A man who could give millions away and
   sup on dry bread was apt to conquer, not provinces alone, but hearts.
   Besides, he had begun well and his people had done their best. The
   House of <persName>Julia</persName>, to which he belonged, descended, he declared, from
   <name type="deity">Venus</name>. The ancestry was less legendary than typical. <persName>Cinna</persName> drafted a
   law giving him the right to marry as often as he chose. His mistresses were queens. After the episodes in <placeName>Gaul</placeName>, when he entered <placeName>Rome</placeName> his
   legions warned the citizens to have an eye on their wives. At seventeen
   he fascinated pirates. A shipload of the latter had caught him and
   demanded twenty talents ransom. "Too little," said the lad; "I will
   give you fifty, and impale you too," which he did, jesting with them meanwhile, reciting verses of his own composition, calling them
   barbarians when they did not applaud, ordering them to be quiet when he
   wished to sleep, captivating them by the effrontery of his assurance,
   and, the ransom paid, slaughtering them as he had promised.</p>
</div>
<div type="book" n="3">
   <div type="section" n="1">
      <p>Tall, slender, not handsome, but superb and therewith so perfectly sent out that Cicero mistook him for a fop from whom the republic had nothing to fear; splendidly lavish, exquisitely gracious, he was born to charm, and his charm was such that it still subsists.</p>
      <p><persName>Cato</persName> alone was unenthralled. But <persName>Cato</persName> was never pleased; he laughed but once, and all Rome turned out to see him; he belonged to an earlier day, to an austerer, perhaps to a better one, and it may be that in "that woman," as he called <persName>Caesar</persName>, his clearer vision discerned beneath the plumage of the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">peacock</name>, the beak and talons of the bird of prey.</p>
      <p>For they were there, and needed only a vote of the senate to batten on nations of which the senate had never heard. Loan him an army, and "that woman" was to give geography such a twist that today whoso says <persName>Caesar</persName> says history.</p>
      <p>Was it this that <persName>Cato</persName> saw, or may it be that one of the oracles which had not ceased to speak had told him of that coming night when he was to take his own life, fearful lest "that woman" should overwhelm him with the magnificence of his forgiveness? <persName>Cato</persName> walks through history, as he walked through the Forum, bare of foot--too severe to be simple, too obstinate to be generous--the image of ancient Rome.</p>
   </div>
</div>
<div type="book" n="4">
  <p>In Caesar there was nothing of this. He was wholly modern; dissolute
    enough for any epoch, but possessed of <name type="virtue">virtues</name> that his contemporaries
    could not spell. A <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">slave</name> tried to poison him. <persName>Suetonius</persName> says he merely
    put the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">slave</name> to death. The "merely" is to the point. <persName>Cato</persName> would have
    tortured him first. After <placeName>Pharsalus</placeName> he forgave everyone. When severe,
    it was to himself. It is true he turned over two million people into so
    many dead <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">flies</name>, their legs in the air, creating, as <persName>Tacitus</persName> has it, a
    solitude which he described as <name type="virtue">Peace</name>; but what <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">antitheses</name> may not be
    expected in a man who, before the first century was begun, divined the
    fifth, and who in the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Suevians</name>--that terrible <name type="people">people</name> beside whom no
    <name type="nation">nation</name> could live--foresaw <name type="deity">Attila</name>!</p>
</div>
<div type="chapter" n="5">
<p>Save in battle his health was poor. He was epileptic, his strength undermined by incessant debauches; yet let a nation fancying him months away put on insurgent airs, and on that nation he descended as the thunder does.</p>
   <p>In his campaigns time and again he overtook his own messengers. A phantom in a ballad was not swifter than he.</p>
   <p>Simultaneously his sword flashed in <placeName>Germany</placeName>, on the banks of the <placeName><foreign xml:lang="la">Adriatic</foreign></placeName>, in that <placeName><foreign xml:lang="la">Ultima Thule</foreign></placeName> where the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Britons</name> lived.</p>
   <p>From the depths of <placeName><foreign xml:lang="la">Gaul</foreign></placeName> he dominated <placeName><foreign xml:lang="la">Rome</foreign></placeName>, and therewith he was penetrating impenetrable forests, trailing legions as a torch trails smoke, erecting walls that a nation could not cross, turning soldiers into marines, infantry into cavalry, building roads that are roads to-day, fighting with one hand and writing an epic with the other, dictating love-letters, chronicles, dramas; finding time to make a collection of witticisms; overturning thrones while he decorated <placeName><foreign xml:lang="la">Greece</foreign></placeName>; mingling initiate into orgies of the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Druids</name>, and, as the cymbals clashed, coquetting with those terrible virgins who awoke the tempest; not only conquering, but captivating, transforming barbarians into soldiers and those soldiers into senators, submitting three hundred nations and ransacking <placeName><foreign xml:lang="la">Britannia</foreign></placeName> for pearls for his mistresses' ears.</p>
</div>
Voici l'encodage TEI P5 strictement conforme aux règles et au texte fourni :


<div type="book" n="6">
  <p>Each epoch has its secret, and each epoch-maker his own. <persName>Caesar</persName>'s
  secret lay in the power he had of projecting a soul into the ranks of
  an army, of making legions and their leader one. Disobedience only he
  punished; anything else he forgave. After a victory his soldiery did
  what they liked. He gave them arms, slaves to burnish them, women,
  feasts, sleep. They were his comrades; he called them so; he wept at
  the death of any of them, and when they were frightened, as they were
  in <placeName>Gaul</placeName> before they met the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Germans</name>, and in <placeName>Africa</placeName> before they
  encountered <persName>Juba</persName>, <persName>Caesar</persName> frightened them still more. He permitted no
  questions, no making of wills. The cowards could hide where they liked;
  his old guard, the Tenth, would do the work alone; or, threat still
  more sinister, he would command a retreat. Ah, that, never! Fanaticism
  returned, the legions begged to be punished.</p>
</div>
Voici l'encodage TEI P5 strictement conforme à vos exigences pour le texte fourni, en respectant toutes les règles et priorités Zoomathia :


<pb n="7"/>
<div type="section" n="7">
  <p>Michelet says he would like to have seen him crossing <placeName>Gaul</placeName>, bareheaded, in the rain. It would have been as interesting, perhaps, to have watched him beneath the shade of the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">velarium</name> pleading the cause of <persName>Masintha</persName> against the <name type="deity">Numidian</name> king.</p>
  <p>Before him was a crowd that covered not the <placeName>Forum</placeName> alone, but the steps of the adjacent <placeName>temples</placeName>, the roofs of the <placeName>basilicas</placeName>, the arches of <name type="deity">Janus</name>, one that extended remotely to the black walls of the <placeName>Curia Hostilia</placeName> beyond. And there, on the rostrum, a musician behind him supplying the <foreign xml:lang="la">la</foreign> from a flute, the air filled with gold motes, <persName>Caesar</persName>, his toga becomingly adjusted, a jewelled hand extended, opened for the defence.</p>
  <p>Presently, when through the exercise of that art of his which <persName>Cicero</persName> pronounced incomparable, he felt that the sympathy of the audience was won, it would have been interesting, indeed, to have heard him argue point after point--clearly, brilliantly, wittily; insulting the plaintiff in poetic terms; consigning him gracefully to the infernal regions; accentuating a fictitious and harmonious anger; drying his forehead without disarranging his hair; suffocating with the emotions he evoked; displaying real tears, and with them a knowledge, not only of law, rhetoric, philosophy, but of geometry, astronomy, ethics and the fine arts; blinding his hearers with the coruscations of his erudition; stirring them with his tongue, as with the point of a sword, until, as though abruptly possessed by an access of fury, he seized the plaintiff</p>
</div>
<div type="chapter" n="8">
<p>by the beard and sent him spinning like a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">leaf</name> which the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">wind</name> had caught.</p>
   <p>It would have bored no one either to have assisted at his triumph when he returned from <placeName>Gaul</placeName>, when he returned after <placeName>Spain</placeName>, after <placeName>Pharsalus</placeName>, when he returned from <persName>Cleopatra</persName>'s arms.</p>
</div>
Voici l'encodage TEI P5 strictement conforme à vos règles pour le texte fourni :


<div type="book" n="9">
<p>On that day the <placeName>Via Sacra</placeName> was curtained with silk. To the blare of twisted bugles there descended to it from the turning at the hill a troop of musicians garmented in leather tunics, bonneted with <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">lions'</name> heads. Behind them a hundred <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">bulls</name>, too fat to be troublesome, and decked for death, bellowed musingly at the sacrifants, who, naked to the waist, a long-handled hammer on the shoulder, maintained them with colored cords. To the rumble of wide wheels and the thunder of spectators the prodigious booty passed, and with it triumphs of war, vistas of conquered countries, pictures of battles, lists of the vanquished, symbols of cities that no longer were; a stretch of ivory on which shone three words, each beginning with a V; images of <name type="deity">gods</name> disturbed, the <placeName>Rhine</placeName>, the <placeName>Rhone</placeName>, the captive <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Ocean</name> in massive gold; the glitter of three thousand crowns offered to the <persName>dictator</persName> by the army and allies of <placeName>Rome</placeName>. Then came the standards of the republic, a swarm of <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">eagles</name>, the size of <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">pigeons</name>, in polished silver upheld by lances which ensigns bore, preceding the six hundred <persName>senators</persName> who marched in a body, their togas bordered with red, while to the din of incessant insults, interminable files of prisoners passed, their wrists chained to iron collars, which held their heads very straight, and to the rear a litter, in which crouched the <persName>Vercingetorix</persName> of <placeName>Gaul</placeName>, a great moody giant, his menacing eyes nearly hidden in the tangles of his tawny hair.</p>
</div>
<div type="book" n="10">
  <p>When they had gone the street was alive with explosions of brass,</p>
  <p>aflame with the burning red cloaks of laureled lictors making way for</p>
  <p>the coming of <persName>Caesar</persName>.</p>
  <p>Four <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">horses</name>, harnessed abreast, their manes dyed,</p>
  <p>their forelocks puffed, drew a high and wonderfully jewelled car; and</p>
  <p>there, in the attributes and attitude of <name type="deity">Jupiter Capitolinus</name>, <persName>Caesar</persName></p>
  <p>sat, blinking his tired eyes. His face and arms were painted vermilion;</p>
  <p>above the <foreign xml:lang="la">Tyrian</foreign> purple of his toga, above the gold work and palms of</p>
  <p>his tunic, there oscillated a little ball in which there were charms</p>
  <p>against <name type="deity">Envy</name>.</p>
  <p>On his head a wreath concealed his increasing baldness;</p>
  <p>along his left arm the sceptre lay; behind him a boy admonished him</p>
  <p>noisily to remember he was man, while to the rear for miles and miles</p>
  <p>there rang the laugh of trumpets, the click of castanets, the shouts of</p>
  <p>dancers, the roar of the multitude, the tramp of legions, and the cry,</p>
  <p>caught up and repeated, "Io! Triomphe!"</p>
</div>
<div type="book" n="11">
<p>Presently, in the temple of the <name type="deity">god of gods</name>, side by side with the
  statue of <persName>Jupiter</persName>, <persName>Caesar</persName> found his own statue with "Caesar, demi-god,"
  at its base.</p>
  <p>The captive chiefs disappeared in the <placeName>Tullianum</placeName>, and a
  herald called, "They have lived!"</p>
  <p>Through the squares jesters
  circulated, polyglot and obscene; across the <placeName>Tiber</placeName>, in an artificial
  lake, the flotilla of <placeName>Egypt</placeName> fought against that of <placeName>Tyr</placeName>; in the
  amphitheatre there was a combat of soldiers, infantry against cavalry,
  one that indemnified those that had not seen the massacres in <placeName>Thessaly</placeName>
  and in <placeName>Spain</placeName>.</p>
  <p>There were public feasts, gifts to everyone. Tables were
  set in the <placeName>Forum</placeName>, in the circuses and theatres.</p>
  <p><foreign xml:lang="la">Falernian</foreign> circulated in
  amphorae, <foreign xml:lang="la">Chios</foreign> in barrels.</p>
  <p>When the populace was gorged there were the
  red feathers to enable it to gorge again.</p>
  <p>Of the <placeName>Rome</placeName> of <persName>Romulus</persName> there was nothing left save the gaunt <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">she-wolf</name>, her wide lips curled at the
  descendants of her nursling.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="12">
   <p>Later, when in slippered feet <persName>Caesar</persName> wandered through those lovely gardens of his that lay beyond the <placeName>Tiber</placeName>, it may be that he recalled a dream which had come to him as a lad; one which concerned the submission of his <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">mother</name>; one which had disturbed him until the sooth-sayers said: <quote>“The <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">mother</name> you saw is the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">earth</name>, and you will be her master.”</quote></p>
   <p>And as the memory of the dream returned, perhaps with it came the memory of the hour when as simple quaestor he had wept at <placeName>Gaddir</placeName> before a statue that was there. Demi-god, yes; he was that. More, even; he was dictator, but the dream was unfulfilled. There were the depths of <placeName>Hither Asia</placeName>, the mysteries that lay beyond; there were the glimmering plains of the <placeName>Caucasus</placeName>; there were the <name type="placeName" xml:lang="en">Vistula</name> and the <placeName>Baltic</placeName>; the diadems of <persName>Cyrus</persName> and of <persName>Alexander</persName> defying his ambition yet, and what were triumphs and divinity to one who would own the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">world</name>!</p>
</div>
Voici l'encodage TEI P5 strictement conforme à vos exigences pour le texte fourni, en respectant toutes les règles et priorités :


<div type="book" n="13">
<p>It was this that preoccupied him. The immensity of his successes seemed petty and Rome very small. Heretofore he had forgiven those who had opposed him. Presently his attitude changed, and so subtly that it was the more humiliating; it was not that he no longer forgave, he disdained to punish. His contempt was absolute.</p>
  <p>The senate made his office of <foreign xml:lang="la">pontifex maximus</foreign> hereditary and accorded the title of <foreign xml:lang="la">Imperator</foreign> to his heirs. He snubbed the senate and the honors that it brought. The senate was shocked. Composed of men whose fortunes he had made, the senate was not only shocked, its education in ingratitude was complete. Already there had been murmurs.</p>
  <p>Not content with disarranging the calendar, outlining an empire, drafting a code while planning fresh beauties, new theatres, bilingual libraries, larger temples, grander gods, Caesar was at work in the markets, in the kitchens of the gourmets, in the jewel-boxes of the virgins. Liberty, visibly, was taking flight. Besides, the power concentrated in him might be so pleasantly distributed. It was decided that Caesar was in the way. To put him out of it a pretext was necessary.</p>
</div>
Voici l'encodage TEI P5 strictement conforme à vos exigences pour le texte fourni, en respectant toutes les règles et priorités :


<div type="book" n="14">
   <div type="section" n="1">
      <p>One day the <persName>senate</persName> assembled at his command. They were to sign a decree
creating him <name type="deity">king</name>. In order not to, <persName>Suetonius</persName> says, they killed him,
wounding each other in the effort, for <persName>Caesar</persName> fought like the <name type="animal">demon</name>
that he was, desisting only when he recognized <persName>Brutus</persName>, to whom, in
<foreign xml:lang="grc">Greek</foreign>, he muttered a reproach, and, draping his <name type="plant">toga</name> that he might fall
with decency, sank backward, his head covered, a few feet from the
<name type="animal">bronze wolf</name> that stood, its ears pointed at the letters <foreign xml:lang="la">S. P. Q. R.</foreign>
which decorated a frieze of the <placeName>Curia</placeName>.</p>

      <p><persName>Brutus</persName> turned to harangue the <persName>senate</persName>; it had fled. He went to the <placeName>Forum</placeName>
to address the <name type="animal">people</name>; there was no one. <placeName>Rome</placeName> was strangely empty.
Doors were barricaded, windows closed. Through the silent streets
<name type="animal">gladiators</name> prowled. Night came, and with it whispering groups. The
groups thickened, voices mounted. <persName>Caesar</persName>'s will had been read. He had
left his <name type="plant">gardens</name> to the <name type="animal">people</name>, a gift to every <name type="animal">citizen</name>, his wealth and
power to his <name type="animal">butchers</name>. The body, which two <name type="animal">slaves</name> had removed, an arm
hanging from the litter, had never been as powerfully alive. <persName>Caesar</persName>
reigned then as never before. A <name type="animal">mummer</name> mouthed:</p>

      <quote>
         <p>"I brought them life, they gave me death."</p>
      </quote>

      <p>And willingly would the <name type="animal">mob</name> have made <placeName>Rome</placeName> the funeral pyre of their
idol. In the sky a <name type="animal">comet</name> appeared. It was his soul on its way to
<placeName>Olympus</placeName>.</p>
   </div>
</div>

<div type="book" n="15">
   <div type="section" n="2">
      <p><foreign xml:lang="la">CONJECTURAL ROME</foreign></p>
   </div>
</div>
<div type="book" n="15">
<p>"I received Rome in brick; I shall leave it in marble," said <persName>Augustus</persName>,
    who was fond of fine phrases, a trick he had caught from <persName>Vergil</persName>. And
    when he looked from his home on the <placeName>Palatine</placeName> over the glitter of the
    <placeName>Forum</placeName> and the glare of the <placeName>Capitol</placeName> to the new and wonderful precinct
    which extended to the <placeName>Field of Mars</placeName>, there was a stretch of splendor
    which sanctioned the boast. The city then was very vast. The tourist
    might walk in it, as in the <placeName>London</placeName> of to-day, mile after mile, and at
    whatever point he placed himself, <placeName>Rome</placeName> still lay beyond; a <placeName>Rome</placeName> quite
    like <placeName>London</placeName>--one that was choked with mystery, with gold and curious
    crime.</p>
  <p>But it was not all marble. There were green terraces and porphyry
    porticoes that leaned to a river on which red galleys passed; there
    were theatres in which a multitude could jeer at an emperor, and arenas
    in which an emperor could watch a multitude die; there were bronze
    doors and garden roofs, glancing villas and temples that defied the
    sun; there were spacious streets, a <placeName>Forum</placeName> curtained with silk, the
    glint and evocations of triumphal war, the splendor of a host of <name type="deity">gods</name>,
    but it was not all marble; there were rents in the magnificence and
    tatters in the laticlave of state.</p>
</div>
Voici l'encodage TEI P5 strictement conforme à vos exigences pour le texte fourni, en respectant toutes les règles et en priorisant les entités nommées Zoomathia :


<div type="book" n="16">
   <p>In the <placeName>Subura</placeName>, where at night women sat in high chairs, ogling the
passer with painted eyes, there was still plenty of brick; tall
tenements, soiled linen, the odor of <placeName>Whitechapel</placeName> and <placeName>St. Giles</placeName>. The
streets were noisy with match-peddlers, with vendors of cake and tripe
and coke; there were touts there too, altars to <name type="deity">unimportant divinities</name>,
lying <persName>Jews</persName> who dealt in old clothes, in obscene pictures and
unmentionable wares; at the crossings there were thimbleriggers, clowns
and jugglers, who made glass balls appear and disappear surprisingly;
there were doorways decorated with curious invitations, gossipy barber
shops, where, through the liberality of <persName>politicians</persName>, the scum of a
great city was shaved, curled and painted free; and there were public
houses, where vagabond slaves and sexless priests drank the mulled wine of <placeName>Crete</placeName>, supped on the flesh of <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">beasts</name> slaughtered in the arena, or
watched the <persName>Syrian</persName> women twist to the click of castanets.</p>
<p>Beyond were gray quadrangular buildings, the stomach of <placeName>Rome</placeName>, through
which, each noon, <persName>ediles</persName> passed, verifying the prices, the weights and
measures of the market men, examining the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">fish</name> and <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">meats</name>, the enormous
<name type="plant" xml:lang="en">cauliflowers</name> that came from the suburbs, <foreign xml:lang="la">Veronese</foreign> <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">carrots</name>, <foreign xml:lang="la">Arician</foreign> <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">pears</name>, stout <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">thrushes</name>, <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">suckling pigs</name>, <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">eggs</name> embedded in <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">grass</name>, <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">oysters</name> from <placeName>Baiae</placeName>, boxes of <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">onions</name> and <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">garlic</name> mixed, mountains of <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">poppies</name>,
<name type="plant" xml:lang="en">beans</name> and <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">fennel</name>, destroying whatever had ceased to be fresh and taxing that which was.</p>
</div>
<div type="book" n="17">
   <div type="section" n="157">
      <p>On the <placeName>Via Sacra</placeName> were the shops frequented by ladies; bazaars where silks and <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">xylons</name> were to be had, essences and unguents, travelling boxes of scented wood, switches of yellow hair, useful drugs such as <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">hemlock</name>, <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">aconite</name>, <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">mandragora</name> and <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">cantharides</name>; the last thing of <persName>Ovid's</persName> and the improper little novels that came from <placeName>Greece</placeName>.</p>
      <p>On the <placeName>Appian Way</placeName>, through green afternoons and pink arcades, fashion strolled. There wealth passed in its chariots, smart young men that smelt of <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">cinnamon</name> instead of war, nobles, matrons, <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">cocottes</name>.</p>
   </div>
</div>
Voici l'encodage TEI P5 strictement conforme à vos règles pour le texte fourni :


<div type="chapter" n="18">
   <p>At the other end of the city, beyond the menagerie of the <placeName>Pantheon</placeName>, was the <placeName>Field of Mars</placeName>, an open-air gymnasium, where every form of exercise was to be had, even to that simple promenade in which the <persName>Romans</persName> delighted, and which in <persName>Caesar</persName>'s camp so astonished the <persName>Verronians</persName> that they thought the promenaders crazy and offered to lead them to their tents.</p>
   <p>There was tennis for those who liked it; racquets, polo, football, quoits, wrestling, everything apt to induce perspiration and prepare for the hour when a gong of bronze announced the opening of the baths--those wonderful baths, where the <persName>Roman</persName>, his <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">slaves</name> about him, after passing through steam and water and the hands of the masseur, had every hair plucked from his arms, legs and armpits; his flesh rubbed down with <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">nard</name>, his limbs polished with <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">pumice</name>; and then, wrapped in a scarlet robe, lined with <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">fur</name>, was sent home in a litter.</p>
   <quote>"Strike them in the face!" cried <persName>Caesar</persName> at <placeName>Pharsalus</placeName>, when the young <persName>patricians</persName> made their charge; and the young <persName>patricians</persName>, who cared more for their looks than they did for victory, turned and fled.</quote>
</div>
<div type="book" n="19">
   <p>It was to the <placeName>Field of Mars</placeName> that <persName>Agrippa</persName> came, to whom <placeName>Rome</placeName> owed the <name type="building">Pantheon</name> and the demand for a law which should inhibit the private ownership of a masterpiece. There, too, his eunuchs about him, <persName>Mecaenas</persName> lounged, companioned by <persName>Varus</persName>, by <persName>Horace</persName> and the mime <persName>Bathylle</persName>, all of whom he was accustomed to invite to that lovely <name type="building">villa</name> of his which overlooked the blue <placeName>Sabinian hills</placeName>, and where suppers were given such as those which <persName>Petronius</persName> has described so alertly and so well.</p>
</div>
Voici l'encodage TEI P5 strictement conforme à vos exigences pour le texte d'Ésope (fable 20/157) :


<div type="chapter" n="20">
<p>In the hall like that of <persName>Mecaenas</persName>', one divided against itself, the
    upper half containing the couches and tables, the other reserved for
    the service and the entertainments that follow, the ceiling was met by
    columns, the walls hidden by panels of gems. On a frieze twelve
    pictures, surmounted by the signs of the <name type="deity">zodiac</name>, represented the dishes
    of the different months. Beneath the bronze beds and silver tables
    mosaics were set in imitation of food that had fallen and had not been
    swept away.</p>
  <p>And there, in white ungirdled tunics, the head and neck
    circled with coils of <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">amaranth</name>--the perfume of which in opening the
    pores neutralizes the fumes of wine--the guests lay, fanned by boys,
    whose curly hair they used for napkins.</p>
  <p>Under the supervision of
    butlers the courses were served on platters so large that they covered
    the tables; <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">sows</name>' breasts with <placeName>Lybia</placeName> truffles; <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">dormice</name> baked in
    <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">poppies</name> and <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">honey</name>, <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">peacock</name>-tongues flavored with <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">cinnamon</name>; <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">oysters</name>
    stewed in <foreign xml:lang="la">garum</foreign>--a sauce made of the intestines of <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">fish</name>--<name type="animal" xml:lang="en">sea-wolves</name>
    from the <placeName>Baltic</placeName>; <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">sturgeons</name> from <placeName>Rhodes</placeName>; <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">fig-peckers</name> from <placeName>Samos</placeName>; <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">African</name>
    <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">snails</name>; pale <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">beans</name> in pink lard; and a yellow <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">pig</name> cooked after the
    <foreign xml:lang="la">Troan</foreign> fashion, from which, when carved, hot <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">sausages</name> fell and live
    <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">thrushes</name> flew.</p>
  <p>Therewith was the <foreign xml:lang="la">mulsum</foreign>, a cup made of white <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">wine</name>,
    <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">nard</name>, <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">roses</name>, <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">absinthe</name> and <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">honey</name>; the delicate sweet <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">wines</name> of <placeName>Greece</placeName>;
    and crusty <foreign xml:lang="la">Falernian</foreign> of the year six hundred and thirty-two. As the
    cups circulated, choirs entered, chanting sedately the last erotic</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="21">
   <p>song; a clown danced on the top of a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">ladder</name>, which he maintained
upright as he danced, telling meanwhile untellable stories to the
frieze; and host and guests, unvociferously, as good breeding dictates,
chatted through the pauses of the service; discussed the disadvantages
of death, the value of <foreign xml:lang="la">Noevian</foreign> <foreign xml:lang="la">iambics</foreign>, the disgrace of <persName>Ovid</persName>, banished
because of <name type="deity">Livia</name>'s eyes.</p>
<p>Such was the <placeName>Rome</placeName> of <persName>Augustus</persName>. "Caesar," cried a mime to him one day,
"do you know that it is important for you that the people should be
interested in <persName>Bathylle</persName> and in myself?"</p>
</div>
Voici l'encodage TEI P5 strictement conforme à vos exigences pour le texte fourni :


<div type="book" n="22">
  <p>The <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">mime</name> was right. The sovereign of Rome was not the <persName>Caesar</persName>, nor yet the aristocracy. The latter was dead. It had been banished by barbarian senators, by barbarian <name type="deity">gods</name>; it had died twice, at <placeName>Pharsalus</placeName>, at <placeName>Philippi</placeName>; it was the people that was sovereign, and it was important that that sovereign should be amused--flattered, too, and fed. For thirty years not a <persName>Roman</persName> of note had died in his bed; not one but had kept by him a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">slave</name> who should kill him when his hour had come; anarchy had been continuous; but now <placeName>Rome</placeName> was at rest and its sovereign wished to laugh. Made up of every nation and every vice, the universe was ransacked for its entertainment. The mountain sent its <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">lions</name>, the desert <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">giraffes</name>; there were <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">boas</name> from the jungles, <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">bulls</name> from the plains, and <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">hippopotami</name> from the waters of the <placeName>Nile</placeName>. Into the arenas patricians descended; in the amphitheatre there were criminals from <placeName>Gaul</placeName>; in the <placeName>Forum</placeName> philosophers from <placeName>Greece</placeName>. On the stage, there were tragedies, pantomimes and farce; there were races in the circus, and in the sacred groves girls with the <placeName>Orient</placeName> in their eyes and slim waists that swayed to the <foreign xml:lang="la">crotals</foreign>. For the thirst of the sovereign there were aqueducts, and for its hunger <placeName>Africa</placeName>, <placeName>Egypt</placeName>, <placeName>Sicily</placeName> contributed grain. <placeName>Syria</placeName> unveiled her altars, <placeName>Persia</placeName> the mystery and magnificence of her <name type="deity">gods</name>.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="23">
   <p>Such was Rome. <persName>Augustus</persName> was less noteworthy; so unnecessary even that every student must regret <placeName>Actium</placeName>, <persName>Antony</persName>'s defeat, the passing of <persName>Caesar</persName>'s dream. For <persName>Antony</persName> was made for conquests; it was he who, fortune favoring, might have given the world to <placeName>Rome</placeName>. A splendid, an impudent bandit, first and foremost a soldier, calling himself a descendant of <name type="deity">Hercules</name> whom he resembled; hailed at <placeName>Ephesus</placeName> as <name type="deity">Bacchus</name>, in <placeName>Egypt</placeName> as <name type="deity">Osiris</name>; Asiatic in lavishness, and <foreign xml:lang="la">Teuton</foreign> in his capacity for drink; vomiting in the open <placeName>Forum</placeName>, and making and unmaking kings; weaving with that <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">viper</name> of the <placeName>Nile</placeName> a romance which is history; passing initiate into the inimitable life, it would have been curious to have watched him that last night when the silence was stirred by the hum of <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">harps</name>, the cries of <foreign xml:lang="la">bacchantes</foreign> bearing his tutelary <name type="deity">god</name> back to the <placeName>Roman</placeName> camp, while he said farewell to love, to empire and to life.</p>
</div>
<div type="book" n="24">
  <div type="section" n="157">
    <p>Augustus resembled him not at all. He was a colorless monarch; an
      emperor in everything but dignity, a prince in everything but grace; a
      tactician, not a soldier; a superstitious braggart, afraid of nothing
      but danger; seducing <persName>women</persName> to learn their
      <persName>husband's</persName> secrets; exiling his
      <persName>daughter</persName>, not because she had
      <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">lovers</name>, but because she had other
      <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">lovers</name> than himself; exiling
      <persName>Ovid</persName> because of <persName>Livia</persName>, who in the
      end poisoned her <persName>prince</persName>, and adroitly, too;
      illiterate, blundering of speech, and coarse of manner--a hypocrite and a
      comedian in one--so guileful and yet so stupid that while a credulous
      moribund ordered the <name type="deity">gods</name> to be thanked that
      <persName>Augustus</persName> survived him, the people publicly applied to
      him an epithet which does not look well in print.</p>
  </div>
</div>
Voici l'encodage TEI P5 strictement conforme à vos exigences pour le texte d'Ésope (attribué) :


<div type="book" n="25">
<p>After Philippi and the suicide of <persName>Brutus</persName>; after Actium and <persName>Antony</persName>'s
    death, for the first time in ages, the gates of the Temple of <name type="deity">Janus</name>
    were closed. There was peace in the world; but it was the sword of <persName>Caesar</persName>, not of <persName>Augustus</persName>, that brought the insurgents to book. At each
    of the victories he was either asleep or ill. At the time of battle
    there was always some god warning him to be careful. The battle won, he
    was brave enough, considerate even. A father and son begged for mercy.
    He promised forgiveness to the son on condition that he killed his
    father. The son accepted and did the work; then he had the son
    despatched. A prisoner begged but for a grave. "The <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">vultures</name> will see
    to it," he answered. When at the head of <persName>Caesar</persName>'s legions, he entered <placeName>Rome</placeName>
    to avenge the latter's death, he announced beforehand that he
    would imitate neither <persName>Caesar</persName>'s moderation nor <persName>Sylla</persName>'s cruelty. There
    would be only a few proscriptions, and a price--and what a price,
    liberty!--was placed on the heads of hundreds of senators and thousands
    of knights. And these people, who had more <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">slaves</name> than they knew by
    sight, <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">slaves</name> whom they tossed alive to fatten <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">fish</name>, <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">slaves</name> to whom
    they affected never to speak, and who were crucified did they so much
    as sneeze in their presence--at the feet of these <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">slaves</name> they rolled,
    imploring them not to deliver them up. Now and then a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">slave</name> was
    merciful; <persName>Augustus</persName> never.</p>
</div>
Voici l'encodage TEI P5 strict du texte selon les règles du projet Zoomathia :


<div type="book" n="26">
  <p>Successes such as these made him ambitious. Having vanquished with the
  sword, he tried the pen. <quote>"You may grant the freedom of the city to your
  barbarians,"</quote> said a <persName>wit</persName> to him one day, <quote>"but not to your solecisms."</quote>
  Undeterred he began a tragedy entitled <quote>"Ajax,"</quote> and discovering his
  incompetence, gave it up. <quote>"And what has become of Ajax?"</quote> a
  <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">parasite</name> asked. <quote>"Ajax threw himself on a
  sponge,"</quote> replied <persName>Augustus</persName>, whose father, it is to be regretted, did not do likewise.
  Nevertheless, it were pleasant to have assisted at his funeral.</p>

  <p>A couch of <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">ivory</name> and <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">gold</name>, ten feet high, draped with
  <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">purple</name>, stood for a week in the <placeName>atrium</placeName> of the <placeName>palace</placeName>.
  Within the couch, hidden from view, the body of the <persName>emperor</persName> lay, ravaged by
  <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">poison</name>. Above was a statue, recumbent, in <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">wax</name>, made after his
  image and dressed in imperial robes. Near by a little <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">slave</name> with a big fan protected the statue
  from <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">flies</name>. Each day physicians came, gazed at the closed <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">wax</name> mouth, and
  murmured, <quote>"He is worse."</quote> In the <placeName>vestibule</placeName> was a pot of burning
  <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">ilex</name>, and stretching out through the <placeName>portals</placeName> a branch of
  <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">cypress</name> warned the <persName>pontiffs</persName> from the contamination of the sight of
  death.</p>
</div>
Voici l'encodage TEI P5 strictement conforme à vos règles pour le texte fourni, en respectant les priorités Zoomathia et la structure demandée :


<div type="book" n="27">
  <div type="section" n="157">
<p>At high noon on the seventh day the funeral crossed the city. First were the flaming torches; the statues of the House of <persName>Octavia</persName>; senators in blue; knights in scarlet; magistrates; lictors; the pick of the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">praetorian guard</name>. Then, to the alternating choruses of boys and girls, the rotting body passed down the <placeName>Sacred Way</placeName>. Behind it <persName>Tiberius</persName> in a travelling-cloak, his hands unringed, marched meditating on the curiosities of life, while to the rear there straggled a troop of dancing <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">satyrs</name>, led by a mime dressed in resemblance of <persName>Augustus</persName>, whose defects he caricatured, whose vices he parodied and on whom the surging crowd closed in.</p>

    <p>On the <placeName>Field of Mars</placeName> the pyre had been erected, a great square structure of resinous wood, the interior filled with coke and sawdust, the exterior covered with illuminated cloths, on which, for base, a tower rose, three storeys high. Into the first storey flowers and perfumes were thrown, into the second the couch was raised, then a torch was applied.</p>

    <p>As the smoke ascended an <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">eagle</name> shot from the summit, circled a moment, and disappeared. For the sum of a million sesterces a senator swore that with the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">eagle</name> he had seen the emperor's soul.</p>
  </div>

  <div type="section" n="3">
<p><persName>FABULOUS FIELDS</persName></p>

    <p>Mention <persName>Tiberius</persName>, and the name evokes a taciturn tyrant, devising in the crypts of a palace infamies so monstrous that to describe them new words were coined.</p>
  </div>
</div>
<div type="book" n="28">
  <div type="section" n="157">
    <p>In the <placeName>Borghese collection</placeName> <persName>Tiberius</persName> is rather good-looking than
otherwise, not an <name type="deity">Antinous</name> certainly, but manifestly a dreamer; one
whose eyes must have been almost <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">feline</name> in their abstraction, and in
the corners of whose mouth you detect pride, no doubt, but melancholy
as well. The pride was congenital, the melancholy was not.</p>
  </div>
</div>
<div type="book" n="29">
<p>Under Tiberius there was quiet, a romancer wrote, and the phrase in its significance passed into legend. During the dozen or more years that he ruled in Rome, his common sense was obvious. The Tiber overflowed, the senate looked for a remedy in the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">Sibyline</name> Books. Tiberius set some engineers to work. A citizen swore by <persName>Augustus</persName> and swore falsely. The senate sought to punish him, not for perjury but for sacrilege. It is for <persName>Augustus</persName> to punish, said Tiberius. The senate wanted to name a month after him. Tiberius declined. "Supposing I were the thirteenth <name type="deity">Caesar</name>, what would you do?" For years he reigned, popular and acclaimed, caring the while nothing for popularity and less for pomp. Sagacious, witty even, believing perhaps in little else than fate and mathematics, yet maintaining the institutions of the land, striving resolutely for the best, outwardly impassable and inwardly mobile, he was a man and his patience had bounds. There were conspirators in the atrium, there was death in the courtier's smile; and finding his favorites false, his life threatened, danger at every turn, his conception of rulership changed. Where moderation had been suddenly there gleamed the axe.</p>
</div>
Voici l'encodage TEI P5 strictement conforme à vos exigences pour le texte d'Ésope (attribué à Ésope dans la tradition antique, bien que le texte mentionne Tacite) :


<div type="chapter" n="30">
  <p>Tacitus, always dramatic, states that at the time terror devastated the city. It so happened that under the republic there was a law against whomso diminished the majesty of the people. The republic was a god, one that had its temple, its priests, its altars. When the republic succumbed, its divinity passed to the emperor; he became <name type="deity">Jupiter</name>'s peer, and, as such, possessed of a majesty which it was sacrilege to slight.</p>
  <p>Consulted on the subject, <persName>Tiberius</persName> replied that the law must be observed. Originally instituted in prevention of offences against the public good, it was found to change into a crime, a word, a gesture or a look.</p>
  <p>It was a crime to undress before a statue of <name type="deity">Augustus</name>, to mention his name in the <foreign xml:lang="la">latrinae</foreign>, to carry a coin with his image into a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">lupanar</name>. The punishment was death. Of the property of the accused, a third went to the informer, the rest to the state.</p>
  <p>Then abruptly terror stalked abroad. No one was safe except the obscure, and it was the obscure that accused. Once an accused accused his accuser; the latter went mad. There was but one refuge--the tomb. If the accused had time to kill himself before he was tried, his property was safe from seizure and his corpse from disgrace. Suicide became endemic in <placeName>Rome</placeName>.</p>
  <p>Never among the rich were orgies as frenetic as then. There was a breathless chase after delights, which the summons, "It is time to die," might at any moment interrupt.</p>
</div>
Voici l'encodage TEI P5 strictement conforme à vos exigences pour le texte fourni, en respectant toutes les règles et priorités :


<div type="book" n="31">
<p>Tiberius meanwhile had gone from Rome. It was then his legend began. He
    was represented living at <placeName>Capri</placeName> in a collection of twelve villas, each
    of which was dedicated to a particular form of lust, and there with the
    paintings of <persName>Parrhasius</persName> for stimulant the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">satyr</name> lounged. He was then an
    old man; his life had been passed in public, his conduct unreproved. If
    no one becomes suddenly base, it is rare for a man of seventy to become
    abruptly vile. "Whoso," <persName>Sakya Muni</persName> announced--"whoso discovers that
    grief comes from affection, will retire into the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">jungles</name> and there
    remain." Tiberius had made the discovery. The <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">jungles</name> he selected were
    the gardens by the sea. And in those gardens, gossip represented him
    devising new forms of old vice. On the subject every doubt is
    permissible, and even otherwise, morality then existed in but one form,
    one which the entire nation observed, wholly, absolutely; that form was
    patriotism. Chastity was expected of the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">vestal</name>, but of no one else.
    The matrons had certain traditions to maintain, certain appearances to
    preserve, but otherwise morality was unimagined and matrimony unpopular.</p>
  <p>When matrimony occurred, divorce was its natural consequence.
    Incompatibility was sufficient cause. <persName>Cicero</persName>, who has given it to
    history that the best women counted the years not numerically, but by
    their different husbands, obtained a divorce on the ground that his
    wife did not idolize him.</p>
</div>
Voici l'encodage TEI P5 strictement conforme à vos exigences pour le texte d'Ésope (attribué) :


<div type="chapter" n="32">
<p>Divorce was not obligatory. Matrimony was. According to a recent law</p>
  <p>whoso at twenty-five was not married, whoso, divorced or widowed, did</p>
  <p>not remarry, whoso, though married, was without children, was regarded</p>
  <p>as a public enemy and declared incapable of inheriting or of serving</p>
  <p>the state. To this law, one of <persName>Augustus</persName>' stupidities which presently</p>
  <p>fell into disuse, only a technical observance was paid. Men married</p>
  <p>just enough to gain a position or inherit a legacy; next day they got a</p>
  <p>divorce. At the moment of need a child was adopted; the moment passed,</p>
  <p>the child was disowned. But if the law had little value, at least it</p>
  <p>shows the condition of things. Moreover, if in that condition <persName>Tiberius</persName></p>
  <p>participated, it was not because he did not differ from other men.</p>

  <quote>
    <p>"Ho sempre amato la solitaria vita," <persName>Petrarch</persName>, referring to himself,</p>
    <p>declared, and <persName>Tiberius</persName> might have said the same thing. He was in love</p>
    <p>with solitude; ill with efforts for the unattained; sick with the</p>
    <p>ingratitude of man. Presently it was decided that he had lived long</p>
    <p>enough. He was suffocated--beneath a mattress at that. <persName>Caesar</persName> had</p>
    <p>dreamed of a universal monarchy of which he should be king; he was</p>
    <p>murdered. That dream was also <persName>Antony</persName>'s; he killed himself. <persName>Cato</persName> had</p>
    <p>sought the restoration of the republic, and <persName>Brutus</persName> the attainment of</p>
    <p>virtue; both committed suicide. Under the empire dreamers fared ill.</p>
    <p><persName>Tiberius</persName> was a dreamer.</p>
  </quote>
</div>
<div type="book" n="33">
  <div type="section" n="157">
    <p>In a palace where a curious conception of the love of <persName>Atalanta</persName> and
    <persName>Meleager</persName> was said to figure on the walls, there was a door on which was
    a sign, imitated from one that overhung the <placeName>Theban</placeName> library of
    <name type="deity">Osymandias</name>--<name type="plant">Pharmacy</name> of the Soul. It was there <persName>Tiberius</persName> dreamed.</p>

    <p>On the ivory shelves were the philtres of <persName>Parthenius</persName>, labelled <foreign xml:lang="la">De Amatoriis Affectionibus</foreign>, the <name type="animal">Sybaris</name> of <persName>Clitonymus</persName>, the <foreign xml:lang="la">Erotopaegnia</foreign> of
    <persName>Laevius</persName>, the maxims and instructions of <persName>Elephantis</persName>, the nine books of
    <persName>Sappho</persName>. There also were the pathetic adventures of <persName>Odatis</persName> and
    <persName>Zariadres</persName>, which <persName>Chares</persName> of <placeName>Mitylene</placeName> had given to the world; the
    astonishing tales of that early <name type="animal">Cinderella</name>, <persName>Rhodopis</persName>; and with them
    those romances of <placeName>Ionian</placeName> nights by <persName>Aristides</persName> of <placeName>Milet</placeName>, which <persName>Crassus</persName>
    took with him when he set out to subdue the <placeName>Parthians</placeName>, and which; found
    in the booty, were read aloud to the people that they might judge the
    morals of a nation that pretended to rule the world.</p>
  </div>
</div>
Voici l'encodage TEI P5 strictement conforme aux règles et au texte fourni :


<div type="book" n="34">
<p>Whether such medicaments are serviceable to the soul is problematic.</p>
  <p>Tiberius had other drugs on the ivory shelves--magic preparations that transported him to fabulous fields.</p>
  <p>There was a work by <persName>Hecataesus</persName>, with which he could visit <placeName>Hyperborea</placeName>, that land where happiness was a birthright, inalienable at that; yet a happiness so sweet that it must have been cloying; for the people who enjoyed it, and with it the appanage of limitless life, killed themselves from sheer ennui.</p>
  <p><persName>Theopompus</persName> disclosed to him a stranger vista--a continent beyond the ocean--one where there were immense cities, and where two rivers flowed--the River of Pleasure and the River of Pain.</p>
  <p>With <persName>Iambulus</persName> he discovered the Fortunate Isles, where there were men with elastic bones, bifurcated tongues; men who never married, who worshipped the <name type="deity">sun</name>, whose life was an uninterrupted delight, and who, when overtaken by age, lay on a perfumed grass that produced a voluptuous death.</p>
  <p><persName>Evhemerus</persName>, a terrible atheist, whose Sacred History the early bishops wielded against polytheism until they discovered it was double-edged, took him to <placeName>Panchaia</placeName>, an island where incense grew; where property was held in common; where there was but one law--<foreign xml:lang="fr">Justice</foreign>, yet a justice different from our own, one which <persName>Hugo</persName> must have intercepted when he made an entrancing yet enigmatical apparition exclaim:</p>
  <p>
    <quote>
      <foreign xml:lang="fr">"Tu me crois la Justice, je suis la Pitie."</foreign>
    </quote>
  </p>
</div>
Voici l'encodage TEI P5 strictement conforme à vos exigences pour le texte d'Ésope (fables) :


<div type="book" n="35">
   <div type="section" n="157">
      <p>And in this paradise there was a temple, and before it a column, about
         which, in <foreign xml:lang="grc">Panchaian</foreign> characters, ran a history of ancient kings, who, to
         the astonishment of the tourist, were found to be none other than the
         <name type="deity">gods</name> whom the universe worshipped, and who in earlier days had
         announced themselves <name type="deity">divinities</name>, the better to rule the hearts and
         minds of <persName>man</persName>.</p>

      <p>With other guides <persName>Tiberius</persName> journeyed through lands where dreams come
         true. <persName>Aristeas</persName> of <placeName>Proconnesus</placeName> led him among the
         <name type="people">Arimaspi</name>, a curious people who passed their lives fighting for
         gold with <name type="animal">griffons</name> in the dark. With <persName>Isogonus</persName> he
         descended the valley of <placeName>Ismaus</placeName>, where wild men were, whose feet
         turned inwards. In <placeName>Albania</placeName> he found a race with pink eyes and white
         hair; in <placeName>Sarmatia</placeName> another that ate only on alternate days.
         <persName>Agatharcides</persName> took him to <placeName>Libya</placeName>, and there introduced him
         to the <name type="people">Psyllians</name>, in whose bodies was a poison deadly to
         <name type="animal">serpents</name>, and who, to test the fidelity of their wives, placed their
         children in the presence of <name type="animal">snakes</name>; if the <name type="animal">snakes</name> fled they knew
         their wives were pure. <persName>Callias</persName> took him further yet, to the home of the
         <name type="people">hermaphrodites</name>; <persName>Nymphodorus</persName> showed him a race of
         fascinators who used enchanted words. With <persName>Apollonides</persName> he encountered
         women who killed with their eyes those on whom they looked too long.
         <persName>Megasthenes</persName> guided him to the <name type="people">Astomians</name>, whose garments
         were the down of <name type="animal">feathers</name>, and who lived on the scent of the
         <name type="plant">rose</name>.</p>
   </div>
</div>
<div type="section" n="36">
   <p>In his cups they all passed, confusedly, before him; the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">hermaphrodites</name> whispered to the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">rose-breathers</name> the secrets of impossible love; the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">griffons</name> bore to him women with magical eyes; the <placeName>Albanians</placeName> danced with elastic feet; he heard the shrill call of the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Psyllians</name>, luring the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">serpents</name> to death; the column of <placeName>Panchaia</placeName> unveiled its mysteries; the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Hyperboreans</name> the reason of their fear of life, and on the wings of the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">chimera</name> he set out again in search of that continent which haunted antiquity and which lay beyond the sea.</p>
<p><quote>"Another <persName>Phaethon</persName> for the universe," <persName>Tiberius</persName> is reported to have muttered, as he gazed at his nephew <persName>Caius</persName>, nicknamed <persName>Caligula</persName>, who was to suffocate him with a mattress and rule in his stead.</quote></p>
   <p>To rule is hardly the expression. There is no term in English to convey that dominion over sea and sky which a <persName>Caesar</persName> possessed, and which <persName>Caligula</persName> was the earliest to understand. <persName>Augustus</persName> was the first magistrate of <placeName>Rome</placeName>, <persName>Tiberius</persName> the first citizen. <persName>Caligula</persName> was the first emperor, but an emperor hallucinated by the enigma of his own grandeur, a prince for whose sovereignty the world was too small.</p>
</div>
<div type="book" n="37">
  <div type="section" n="157">
    <p>Each epoch has its secret, sometimes puerile, often perplexing; but in
      its maker there is another and a more interesting one yet. Eliminate
      <persName>Caligula</persName>, and <persName>Nero</persName>,
      <persName>Domitian</persName>, <persName>Commodus</persName>,
      <persName>Caracalla</persName> and <persName>Heliogabalus</persName> would never
      have been. It was he who gave them both <foreign xml:lang="fr">raison d'etre</foreign>
      and incentive. The lives of all of them are horrible, yet analyze the
      horrible and you find the sublime.</p>
    <p>Fancy a peak piercing the heavens, shadowing the earth. It was on a
      peak such as that the young emperors of old <placeName>Rome</placeName> balanced
      themselves, a precipice on either side. Did they look below, a vertigo rose to
      meet them; from above delirium came, while the horizon, though it hemmed the
      limits of vision, could not mark the frontiers of their dream. In addition there
      was the exaltation that altitudes produce. The valleys have their imbeciles; it
      is from mountains the poet and madman come.</p>
    <p><persName>Caligula</persName> was both, sceptred at that; and with what a
      sceptre! One that stretched from the <placeName>Rhine</placeName> to the
      <placeName>Euphrates</placeName>, dominated a hundred and fifty million people;
      one that a mattress had given and a knife was to take away; a sceptre that
      lashed the earth, threatened the sky, beckoned planets and ravished the divinity
      of the <name type="deity">divine</name>.</p>
  </div>
</div>
Voici l'encodage TEI P5 du texte selon les règles strictes du projet Zoomathia :


<div type="book" n="38">
<p>To wield such a sceptre securely requires grace, no doubt, majesty too, but certainly strength; the latter <persName>Caligula</persName> possessed, but it was the feverish strength of one who had fathomed the unfathomable, and who sought to make its depths his own.</p>
  <p><persName>Caligula</persName> was haunted by the intangible. His sleep was a communion with Nature, with whom he believed himself one. At times the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Ocean</name> talked to him; at others the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Earth</name> had secrets which it wished to tell. Again there was some matter of moment which he must mention to the day, and he would wander out in the vast galleries of the palace and invoke the <name type="deity">Dawn</name>, bidding it come and listen to his speech. The day was deaf, but there was the <name type="deity">moon</name>, and he prayed her to descend and share his couch. <name type="deity">Luna</name> declined to be the mistress of a mortal; to seduce her <persName>Caligula</persName> determined to become a god.</p>
  <p>Nothing was easier. An emperor had but to open his veins, and in an hour he was a divinity. But the divinity which <persName>Caligula</persName> desired was not of that kind. He wished to be a god, not on <placeName>Olympus</placeName> alone, but on earth as well. He wished to be a palpable, tangible, living god; one that mortals could see, which was more, he knew, than could be said of the others. The mere wish was sufficient--<placeName>Rome</placeName> fell at his feet. The patent of divinity was in the genuflections of a nation. At once he had a temple, priests and flamens. <placeName>Inexhaustible Greece</placeName> was sacked again. The statues of her gods, disembarked at <placeName>Rome</placeName>, were decapitated, and on them the head of <persName>Caius</persName> shone.</p>
</div>
Voici l'encodage TEI P5 strictement conforme aux règles du projet Zoomathia pour le texte fourni :


<div type="book" n="39">
   <div type="section" n="157">
      <p>Heretofore his dress had not been Roman, nor, for that matter, the dress of a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">man</name>. On his wrists were bracelets; about his shoulders was a mantle sewn with gems; beneath was a tunic, and on his feet were the high white slippers that <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">women</name> wore.</p>
      <p>But when the <name type="deity">god</name> came the costume changed. One day he was <persName>Apollo</persName>, the nimbus on his curls, the <name type="deity">Graces</name> at his side; the next he was <persName>Mercury</persName>, wings at his heels, the caduceus in his hand; again he was <persName>Venus</persName>. But it was as <persName>Jupiter Latialis</persName>, armed with the thunderbolt and decorated with a great gold beard, that he appeared at his best.</p>
      <p>The role was very real to him. After the fashion of <name type="deity">Olympians</name> he became frankly incestuous, seducing vestals, his sisters too, and gaining in boldness with each metamorphosis, he menaced the <placeName>Capitoline Jove</placeName>.</p>
      <p>"Prove your power," he cried to him, "or fear my own!" He thundered at him with machine-made thunder, with lightning that flashed from a pan. "Kill me," he shouted, "or I will kill you!" <persName>Jove</persName>, unmoved, must have moved his assailant, for presently <persName>Caligula</persName> lowered his voice, whispered in the old <name type="deity">god</name>'s ear, questioned him, meditated on his answer, grew perplexed, violent again, and threatened to send him home.</p>
   </div>
</div>
Voici l'encodage TEI P5 strictement conforme aux règles Zoomathia pour le texte fourni :


<div type="book" n="40">
  <div type="section" n="157">
    <p>These interviews humanized him. He forgot the moon and mingled with
    men, inviting them to die. The invitation being invariably accepted, he
    became a connoisseur in death, an artist in blood, a ruler to whom
    cruelty was not merely an aid to government but an individual pleasure,
    and therewith such a perfect lover, such a charming host!</p>

    <p>“Dear heart,” he murmured to his mistress <persName>Pryallis</persName>, as she lay one
    night in his arms, “I think I will have you tortured that you may tell
    me why I love you so.” But of that the girl saw no need. She either
    knew the reason or invented one, for presently he added: “And to think
    that I have but a sign to make and that beautiful head of yours is
    off!” Musings of this description were so humorous that one evening he
    explained to guests whom he had startled with his laughter, that it was
    amusing to reflect how easily he could have all of them killed.</p>
  </div>
</div>
<div type="book" n="41">
  <div type="section" n="157">
    <p>But even to a god life is not an unmixed delight. <persName>Caligula</persName> had his
    troubles. About him there had settled a disturbing quiet. <placeName>Rome</placeName> was
    hushed, the world was very still. There was not so much as an
    earthquake. The reign of <persName>Augustus</persName> had been marked by the defeat of
    <persName>Varus</persName>. Under <persName>Tiberius</persName> a falling amphitheatre had killed a multitude.
    <persName>Caligula</persName> felt that through sheer felicity his own reign might be
    forgot. A famine, a pest, an absolute defeat, a terrific
    conflagration--any prodigious calamity that should sweep millions away
    and stamp his own memory immutably on the chronicles of time, how
    desirable it were! But there was nothing. The crops had never been more
    abundant; apart from the arenas and the prisons, the health of the
    empire was excellent; on the frontiers not so much as the rumor of an
    insurrection could be heard, and <persName>Nero</persName> was yet to come.</p>
  </div>
</div>
Voici l'encodage TEI P5 strict du texte fourni selon les règles du projet Zoomathia :


<div type="book" n="42">
  <div type="section" n="1">
    <p>Perplexed, <persName>Caligula</persName> reflected, and presently from <placeName>Baiae</placeName> to <placeName>Puzzoli</placeName>,</p>
    <p>over the waters of the bay, he galloped on <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">horse</name>back, the cuirass of <foreign xml:lang="la">Alexander</foreign> glittering on his breast.</p>
    <p>The intervening miles had been spanned by a bridge of <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">ships</name> and on them a road had been built, one of those roads for which the <persName>Romans</persName> were famous, a road like the <placeName>Appian Way</placeName>, in earth and stone, bordered by inns, by pink arcades, green retreats, forest reaches, the murmur of trickling streams.</p>
    <p>So many <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">ships</name> were anchored there that through the unrepleted granaries the fear of famine stalked.</p>
    <p><persName>Caligula</persName>, meanwhile, his guests behind him, made cavalry charges across the sea, or in a circus-chariot held the ribbons, while four white <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">horses</name>, maddened by swaying lights, bore him to the other shore.</p>
    <p>At night the entire coast was illuminated; the bridge was one great festival, brilliant but brief.</p>
    <p><persName>Caligula</persName> had wearied of it all.</p>
    <p>At a signal the multitude of guests he had assembled there were tossed into the sea.</p>
  </div>
</div>
Voici l'encodage TEI P5 strictement conforme à vos règles pour le texte fourni, en respectant la structure demandée et les entités nommées Zoomathia :


<div type="book" n="43">
   <p>By way of a souvenir, <persName>Tiberius</persName>, whom he murdered, had left him the immensity of his treasure. "I must be economical or <persName>Caesar</persName>," <persName>Caligula</persName> reflected, and tipped a coachman a million, rained on the people a hail of coin, bathed in essences, set before his guests loaves of silver, gold omelettes, sausages of gems; sailed to the hum of harps on a ship that had porticoes, gardens, baths, bowers, spangled sails and a jewelled prow; removed a mountain, and put a palace where it had been; filled in a valley and erected a temple on the top; supplied a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">horse</name> with a marble home, with ivory stalls, with furniture and slaves; contemplated making him consul; made him a host instead, one that in his own equine name invited the fashion of <placeName>Rome</placeName> to sup with <persName>Incitatus</persName>.</p>
<p>In one year <persName>Tiberius</persName>' legacy, a sum that amounted to four hundred million of our money, was spent. <persName>Caligula</persName> had achieved the impossible; he was a bankrupt god, an emperor without a copper. But the very splendor of that triumph demanded a climax. If <persName>Caligula</persName> hesitated, no one knew it. On the morrow the palace of the <persName>Caesars</persName> was turned into a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">lupanar</name>, a little larger, a little handsomer than the others, but still a brothel, one of which the inmates were matrons of <placeName>Rome</placeName> and the keeper <name type="deity">Jupiter Latialis</name>.</p>
</div>
Voici l'encodage TEI P5 strictement conforme aux règles Zoomathia pour le texte fourni :


<div type="book" n="44">
  <p>After that, seemingly, there was nothing save apotheosis. But <persName>Caligula</persName>,</p>
  <p>in the nick of time, remembered the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">ocean</name>. At the head of an army he</p>
  <p>crossed <placeName>Gaul</placeName>, attacked it, and returned refreshed. Decidedly he had not</p>
  <p>exhausted everything yet. He recalled <persName>Tiberius</persName>' policy, and abruptly</p>
  <p>the world was filled again with accusers and accused. Gold poured in on</p>
  <p>him, the earth paid him tribute. In a vast hall he danced naked on the</p>
  <p>wealth of nations. Once more he was rich, richer than ever; there were</p>
  <p>still illusions to be looted, other dreams to be pierced; yet, even as</p>
  <p>he mused, conspirators were abroad. He loosed his pretorians. "Had <placeName>Rome</placeName></p>
  <p>but one head!" he muttered. "Let them FEEL themselves die," he cried to</p>
  <p>his officers. "Let me be hated, but let me be feared."</p>

  <p>One day, as he was returning from the theatre, the dagger did its usual</p>
  <p>work. <placeName>Rome</placeName> had lost a genius; in his place there came an <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">ass</name>.</p>

  <p>There is a verse in <foreign xml:lang="grc">τῷ γὰρ μακαρίοις ἐν τριμήνῳ γίγνονται παῖδες</foreign> to the effect that the blessed have children</p>
  <p>in three months. <persName>Livia</persName> and <persName>Augustus</persName> were blessed in this pleasant</p>
  <p>fashion. Three months after their marriage a child was born--a miracle</p>
  <p>which surprised no one aware of their previous intimacy. The child</p>
  <p>became a man, and the father of <persName>Claud</persName>, an imbecile whom the pretorians,</p>
  <p>after <persName>Caligula</persName>'s death, found in a closet, shaking with fright, and</p>
  <p>whom for their own protection they made emperor in his stead.</p>
</div>
<div type="book" n="45">
  <p>Caligula had been frankly adored; there was in him an originality, and with it a grandeur and a mad magnificence that enthralled. Then, too, he was young, and at his hours what the French call <foreign xml:lang="fr">charmeur</foreign>. If at times he frightened, always he dazzled. Of course he was adored; the prodigal emperors always were; so were their successors, the wicked popes. Man was still too near to nature to be aware of shame, and infantile enough to care to be surprised. In that was Caligula's charm; he petted his people and surprised them too. Claud wearied. Between them they assimilate every contradiction, and in their incoherences explain that incomprehensible chaos which was Rome. Caligula jeered at everybody; everybody jeered at Claud.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="46">
   <p>The latter was a fantastic, vacillating, abstracted, cowardly tyrant,
   issuing edicts in regard to the proper tarring of barrels, and
   rendering absurd decrees; declaring himself to be of the opinion of
   those who were right; falling asleep on the bench, and on awakening
   announcing that he gave judgment in favor of those whose reasons were
   the best; slapped in the face by an <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">irritable plaintiff</name>; held down by
   main force when he wanted to leave; inviting to supper those whom he
   had killed before breakfast; answering the mournful salute of the
   gladiators with a grotesque <foreign xml:lang="la">Avete vos</foreign>--"Be it well too with you," a
   response, parenthetically, which the gladiators construed as a pardon
   and refused to fight; dowering the alphabet with three new letters
   which lasted no longer than he did; asserting that he would give
   centennial games as often as he saw fit; an emperor whom no one obeyed,
   whose eunuchs ruled in his stead, whose lackeys dispensed exiles,
   death, consulates and crucifixions; whose valets insulted the senate,
   insulted Rome, insulted the sovereign that ruled the world, whose
   people shared his consort's couch; a slipshod drunkard in a tattered
   gown--such was the imbecile that succeeded <persName>Caligula</persName> and had <persName>Messalina</persName>
   for wife.</p>
</div>
Voici l'encodage TEI P5 strictement conforme à vos règles pour le texte fourni, en respectant les priorités d'encodage des entités nommées Zoomathia :


<div type="section" n="47">
   <p>It were curious to have seen that woman as <persName>Juvenal</persName> did, a veil over her
   <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">yellow</name> wig, hunting adventures through the streets of <placeName>Rome</placeName>, while her
   husband in the <placeName>Forum</placeName> censured the dissoluteness of citizens. And it
   were curious, too, to understand whether it was her audacity or his
   stupidity which left him the only man in <placeName>Rome</placeName> unacquainted with the
   prodigious multiplicity and variety of her lovers. History has its
   secrets, yet, in connection with <persName>Messalina</persName>, there is one that
   historians have not taken the trouble to probe; to them she has been an
   imperial strumpet. <persName>Messalina</persName> was not that. At heart she was probably no
   better and no worse than any other lady of the land, but pathologically
   she was an unbalanced person, who to-day would be put through a course
   of treatment, instead of being put to death. When <persName>Claud</persName> at last
   learned, not the truth, but that some of her lovers were conspiring to
   get rid of him, he was not indignant; he was frightened. The
   conspirators were promptly disposed of, <persName>Messalina</persName> with them. <persName>Suetonius</persName>
   says that, a few days later, as he went in to supper, he asked why the
   empress did not appear.</p>

   <p>Apart from the neurosis from which she suffered, were it possible to
   find an excuse for her conduct, the excuse would be <persName>Claud</persName>. The purple
   which made <persName>Caligula</persName> mad, made him an idiot; and when in course of time
   he was served with a succulent poison, there must have been many
   conjectures in <placeName>Rome</placeName> as to what the empire would next produce.</p>
</div>
<div type="book" n="48">
  <p>The empire was extremely fecund, enormously vast. About Rome extended
an immense circle of provinces and cities that were wholly hers.
Without that circle was another, the sovereignty exercised over vassals
and allies; beyond that, beyond the <placeName>Rhine</placeName> on one side, were the
silenced <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Teutons</name>; beyond the <placeName>Euphrates</placeName> on the other, the hazardous
<name type="deity">Parthians</name>, while remotely to the north there extended the enigmas of
barbarism; to the south, those semi-fabulous regions where geography
ceased to be.</p>
</div>
<div type="book" n="49">
   <div type="section" n="1">
      <p>Little by little, through the patience of a people that felt itself
         eternal, this immensity had been assimilated and fused. A few
         fortresses and legions on the frontiers, a stretch of soldiery at any
         spot an invasion might be feared; a little tact, a maternal solicitude,
         and that was all. Rome governed unarmed, or perhaps it might be more
         exact to say she did not govern at all; she was the mistress of a
         federation of realms and republics that governed themselves, in whose
         government she was content, and from whom she exacted little, tribute
         merely, and obeisance to herself.</p>
      <p>Her strength was not in the sword;
         the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">lioness</name> roared rarely, often slept; it was the fear smaller beasts
         had of her awakening that made them docile; once aroused those indolent
         paws could do terrible work, and it was well not to excite them.</p>
      <p>When
         the <persName>Jews</persName> threatened to revolt, <persName>Agrippa</persName> warned them: <quote>Look at Rome; look
         at her well; her arms are invisible, her troops are afar; she rules,
         not by them, but by the certainty of her power. If you rebel, the
         invisible sword will flash, and what can you do against Rome armed,
         when Rome unarmed frightens the world?</quote></p>
   </div>
</div>
Voici l'encodage TEI P5 du texte selon les règles strictes du projet Zoomathia :


<div type="book" n="50">
   <p>The argument was pertinent and suggestive, but the secret of Rome's
   ascendency consisted in the fact that where she conquered she dwelt.
   Wherever the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">eagles</name> pounced, Rome
   multiplied herself in miniature. In the army was the nation, in the legion
   the city. Where it camped, presto! a judgment seat and an altar. On the
   morrow there was a forum; in a week there were paved avenues; in a fortnight,
   temples, porticoes; in a month you felt yourself at home. Rome built with a
   magic that startled as surely as the glint of her sword. Time and again the
   nations whom <persName>Caesar</persName> encountered planned to eliminate his
   camp. When they reached it the camp had vanished; in its place was a walled,
   impregnable town.</p>

   <p>As the standards lowered before that town, the <foreign xml:lang="la">pomoerium</foreign> was traced.
   Within it the veteran found a home, without it a wife; and the family
   established, the legion that had conquered the soil with the sword,
   subsisted on it with the plow. Presently there were priests there,
   aqueducts, baths, theatres and games, all the marvel of imperial
   elegance and vice. When the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">aborigine</name> wandered that way, his
   seduction was swift.</p>
</div>
Voici l'encodage TEI P5 strictement conforme à vos règles pour ce passage, en respectant les entités nommées Zoomathia et la structure demandée :


<div type="book" n="51">
  <p>The enemy that submitted became a subject, not a slave. Rome commanded
  only the free. If his goods were taxed, his goods remained his own, his
  personal liberty untrammelled. His land had become part of a new
  province, it is true, but provided he did not interest himself in such
  matters as peace and war, not only was he free to manage his own
  affairs, but that land, were it at the uttermost end of the earth,
  might, in recompense of his fidelity, come to be regarded as within the
  Italian territory; as such, sacred, inviolate, free from taxes, and he
  a citizen of Rome, senator even, emperor!</p>
<p>Conquest once solidified, the rest was easy. Tattered furs were
  replaced by the tunic and uncouth idioms by the niceties of Latin
  speech. In some cases, where the speech had been beaten in with the
  hilt of the sword, the accent was apt to be rough, but a generation,
  two at most, and there were sweethearts and swains quoting Horace in
  the moonlight, naively unaware that only the verse of the Greeks could
  pleasure the Roman ear.</p>
</div>
<div type="book" n="52">
  <p>The principalities and kingdoms that of their own wish [a wish often
  suggested, and not always amicably either] became allies of Rome and
  mingled their freedom with hers, entered into an alliance whereby in
  return for Rome's patronage and protection they agreed to have a proper
  regard for the dignity of the <name type="deity">Roman people</name> and to have no other friends
  or enemies than those that were Rome's--a formula exquisite in the
  civility with which it exacted the renunciation of every inherent
  right. A king wrote to the senate: "I have obeyed your deputy as I
  would have obeyed a <name type="deity">god</name>." "And you have done wisely," the senate
  answered, a reply which, in its terseness, tells all.</p>
</div>
Voici l'encodage TEI P5 du texte fourni selon les règles strictes du projet Zoomathia :


<div type="section" n="53">
  <p>Diplomacy and the plow, such were Rome's methods. As for herself she
  fought, she did not till. Italy, devastated by the civil wars, was
  uncultivated, cut up into vast unproductive estates. From one end to
  the other there was barely a trace of agriculture, not a sign of
  traffic. You met soldiers, cooks, petty tradesmen, gladiators,
  philosophers, patricians, market gardeners, lazzaroni and millionaires;
  the <name type="animal">merchant</name> and the <name type="animal">farmer</name>, never. Rome's resources were in distant
  commercial centres, in taxes and tribute; her wealth had come of
  pillage and exaction. Save her strength, she had nothing of her own.
  Her religion, literature, art, philosophy, luxury and corruption,
  everything had come from abroad. In Greece were her artists; in Africa,
  Gaul and Spain, her agriculturists; in Asia her artisans. Her own
  breasts were sterile. When she gave birth it was to a litter of
  <name type="animal">monsters</name>, sometimes to a genius, by accident to a poet. She consumed,
  she did not produce. It was because of that she fell.</p>

<p><persName>NERO</persName></p>

  <p>"Save a <name type="animal">monster</name>, what can you expect from <persName>Agrippina</persName> and myself?"</p>

  <p>It was <persName>Domitius</persName>, <persName>Nero</persName>'s father, who made this ingenious remark. He was
  not a good man; he was not even good-looking, merely vicious and rich.
  But his viciousness was benign beside that of <persName>Agrippina</persName>, who poisoned
  him when <persName>Nero</persName>'s birth ensured the heritage of his wealth.</p>
</div>
<pb n="54"/>
<div type="chapter" n="1">
  <p>In all its galleries history has no other portrait such as hers.</p>
  <p>Caligula's <persName>sister</persName>, his mistress as well, exiled by him and threatened
    with death, her eyes dazzled and her nerves unstrung by the
    impossibilities of that fabulous reign, it was not until <persName>Claud</persName>, her
    uncle, recalled her and <persName>Messalina</persName> disappeared, that the empress awoke.</p>
  <p>She too, she determined, would rule, and the <foreign xml:lang="la">jus osculi</foreign> aiding, she
    married out of hand that imbecile uncle of hers, on whose knee she had
    played as a child.</p>
</div>
Voici l'encodage TEI P5 strict du texte selon les règles du projet Zoomathia :


<div type="book" n="55">
   <p>The day of the wedding a young <persName>patrician</persName>, expelled from the senate, killed himself. <persName>Agrippina</persName> had accused him of something not nice, not because he was guilty, nor yet because the possibility of the thing shocked her, but because he was betrothed to <persName>Octavia</persName>, <persName>Claud</persName>'s daughter, who, <persName>Agrippina</persName> determined, should be <persName>Nero</persName>'s wife. Presently <persName>Caligula</persName>'s widow, an old rival of her own, a lady who had thought she would like to be empress twice, and whom <persName>Claud</persName> had eyed grotesquely, was disencumbered of three million worth of <name type="animal">emeralds</name>, with which she heightened her beauty, and told very civilly that it was time to die.</p>
   <p>So, too, disappeared a <persName>Calpurina</persName>, a <persName>Lepida</persName>; women young, rich, handsome, impure, and as such dangerous to <persName>Agrippina</persName>'s peace of mind. The legality of her crimes was so absolute that the mere ownership of an enviable object was a cause for death. A senator had a villa which pleased her; he was invited to die. Another had a pair of those odorous <name type="plant">murrhine vases</name>, which <persName>Pompey</persName> had found in <placeName>Armenia</placeName>, and which on their first appearance set <placeName>Rome</placeName> wild; he, too, was invited to die.</p>
</div>
Voici l'encodage TEI P5 strictement conforme à vos exigences pour ce passage, avec une attention particulière aux entités nommées Zoomathia et à la structure demandée :


<div type="book" n="56">
   <p>But, though <persName>Agrippina</persName> dealt in death, she dealt in seductions too.</p>
   <p><placeName>Rome</placeName>, that had adored <persName>Caligula</persName>, promptly fell under his sister's sway.</p>
   <p>There was a splendor in her eyes, which so many crimes had lit; in her carriage there was such majesty, the pomp with which she surrounded herself was so magnificent, that <placeName>Rome</placeName>, enthralled, applauded.</p>
   <p>Beyond, on the <placeName>Rhine</placeName>, a city which is today <placeName>Cologne</placeName>, rose in honor of her sovereignty.</p>
   <p>To her wishes the senate was subservient, to her indiscretions blind.</p>
   <p><persName>Claud</persName>, who meanwhile had been wholly sightless, suddenly showed signs of discernment.</p>
   <p>A woman, charged with illicit commerce, was brought to his tribunal. He condemned her, of course.</p>
   <p>"In my case," he explained, "matrimony has not been successful, but the fate that destined me to marry impure women destined me also to punish them."</p>
   <p>It was then that <persName>Agrippina</persName> ordered of <persName>Locusta</persName> that famous stew of poison and <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">mushrooms</name>, which <persName>Nero</persName>, in allusion to <persName>Claud</persName>'s apotheosis, called the food of the gods.</p>
   <p>The fate that destined <persName>Claud</persName> to marry <persName>Agrippina</persName> destined her to kill him.</p>
<p>It was under her care, between a barber and a ballerine, amid the shamelessness of his stepfather's palace, where any day he could have seen his mother beckon indolently to a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">centurion</name> and pointing to some lover who had ceased to please, make the gesture which signified Death,</p>
   <p>that the young <persName>Enobarbus</persName>--<persName>Nero</persName>, as he subsequently called himself--was trained for the throne.</p>
</div>
<div type="book" n="57">
   <p>He had entered the world like a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">tiger</name> cub, feet first; a circumstance which is said to have disturbed his mother, and well it might.</p>
   <p>During his adolescence that lady made herself feared.</p>
   <p>He was but seventeen when the <persName>pretorians</persName> called upon him to rule the world; and at the time an ingenuous lad, one who blushed like <persName>Lalage</persName>, very readily, particularly at the title of <foreign xml:lang="en">Father of the Country</foreign>, which the <persName>senate</persName> was anxious to give him; endowed with excellent instincts, which he had got no one knew whence; a trifle <foreign xml:lang="fr">petit maitre</foreign>, perhaps, perfuming the soles of his feet, and careful about the arrangement of his yellow curls, but withal generous, modest, sympathetic--in short, a flower in a cesspool, a youth not over well-fitted to reign.</p>
   <p>But his mother was there; as he developed so did his fear of her, to such proportions even that he gave certain orders, and his mother was killed.</p>
   <p>That duel between mother and son, terrible in its intensity and unnameable horror, even the <persName>Borgias</persName> could not surpass.</p>
   <p><persName>Tacitus</persName> has told it, dramatically, as was his wont, but he told it in <foreign xml:lang="la">Latin</foreign>, in which tongue it had best remain.</p>
</div>
<div type="chapter" n="58">
   <p>At that time the ingenuous lad had disappeared. The <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">cub</name> was full-grown.</p>
   <p>Besides, he had tasted blood. <persName>Octavia</persName>, who with her brother, <persName>Britannicus</persName>, and her sister, <persName>Antonia</persName>, had been his playmates; who was almost his own sister; whose earliest memories interlinked with his, and who had become his wife, had been put to death; not that she had failed to please, but because a lady, <persName>Sabina Poppoea</persName>, who, <quote><persName>Tacitus</persName> says</quote>, lacked nothing except virtue, had declined to be his mistress. At the time <persName>Sabina</persName> was married. But divorce was easy. <persName>Sabina</persName> got one at the bar; <persName>Nero</persName> with the axe. The twain were then united.</p>
   <p><persName>Nero</persName> seems to have loved her greatly, a fact, as <quote><persName>Suetonius</persName> puts it</quote>, which did not prevent him from kicking her to death. Already he had poisoned <persName>Britannicus</persName>, and with <persName>Octavia</persName> decapitated and <persName>Agrippina</persName> gone, of the imperial house there remained but <persName>Antonia</persName> and himself. The latter he invited to marry him; she declined. He invited her to die. He was then alone, the last of his race.</p>
   <p><foreign xml:lang="la">Monsters never engender</foreign>. A thinker who passed that way thought him right to have killed his mother; her crime was in giving him birth.</p>
</div>
Voici l'encodage TEI P5 strictement conforme à vos règles pour le texte fourni, en respectant toutes les contraintes et en priorisant les entités nommées Zoomathia :


<div type="book" n="59">
  <p>Therewith he was popular; more so even than <persName>Caligula</persName>, who was a poet,
    and as such apart from the crowd, while <persName>Nero</persName> was frankly
    canaille--well-meaning at that--which <persName>Caligula</persName> never was. During the
    early years of his reign he could not do good enough. The gladiators
    were not permitted to die; he would have no shedding of blood; the
    smell of it was distasteful. He would listen to no denunciations; when
    a decree of death was brought to him to sign, he regretted that he knew
    how to write. <placeName>Rome</placeName> had never seen a gentler prince, nor yet one more
    splendidly lavish. The people had not only the necessities of life, but
    the luxuries, the superfluities, too. For days and days in the <placeName>Forum</placeName>
    there was an incessant shower of tickets that were exchangeable, not
    for bread or trivial sums, but for gems, pictures, slaves, fortunes,
    ships, villas and estates. The creator of that shower was bound to be
    adored.</p>

  <p>It was that, no doubt, which awoke him. A city like <placeName>Rome</placeName>, one that had
    over a million inhabitants, could make a terrific noise, and when that
    noise was applause, the recipient found it heady. <persName>Nero</persName> got drunk on
    popularity, and heredity aiding where the prince had been emerged the
    cad, a poseur that bored, a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">beast</name> that disgusted, a caricature of the
    impossible in a crimson frame.</p>
</div>
<div type="book" n="60">
   <p>What an <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">artist</name> the world is to lose!" he exclaimed as he died; and <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">artist</name> he was, but in the Roman sense; one that enveloped in the same contempt the musician, acrobat and actor. It was the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">artist</name> that played the flute while <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">gladiators</name> died and <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">lovers</name> embraced; it was the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">artist</name> that entertained the vulgar.</p>
   <p>As an <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">artist</name> <persName>Nero</persName> might have been a card. Fancy the attraction--an emperor before the footlights; but fancy the boredom also. The joy at the announcement of his first appearance was so great that thanks were offered to the <name type="deity">gods</name>; and the verses he was to sing, graven in gold, were dedicated to the <placeName>Capitoline Jove</placeName>. The joy was brief. The exits of the theatre were closed. It was treason to attempt to leave. People pretended to be dead in order to be carried out, and well they might. The star was a fat man with a husky tenorino voice, who sang drunk and half-naked to a protecting claque of ten thousand hands.</p>
   <p>But it was in the circus that <persName>Nero</persName> was at his best; there, no matter though he were last in the race, it was to him the palm was awarded, or rather it was he that awarded the palm to himself, and then quite magnificently shouted, "<persName>Nero</persName>, <persName>Caesar</persName>, victor in the race, gives his crown to the <placeName>People of Rome</placeName>!"</p>
</div>
<div type="book" n="61">
   <p>On the stage he had no rivals, and by chance did one appear, he was
invited to die. In that respect he was artistically susceptible. When
he turned acrobat, the statues of former victors were tossed in the
latrinae. Yet, as competitors were needed, and moreover as he, singly,
could fill neither a stage nor a track, it was the nobility of <placeName>Rome</placeName>
that he ordered to appear with him. For that the nobility never forgave
him. On the other hand, the proletariat loved him the better. What
greater salve could it have than the sight of the conquerors of the
world entertaining the conquered, lords amusing their lackeys?</p>
</div>
Voici l'encodage TEI P5 strictement conforme à vos règles pour le texte fourni, en respectant les entités nommées Zoomathia et la structure demandée :


<div type="chapter" n="62">
   <p>Greece meanwhile sent him <name type="placeName">crowns</name> and prayers; <name type="placeName">crowns</name> for anticipated
   victories, prayers that he would come and win them. Homage so delicate
   was not to be disdained. <persName>Nero</persName> set forth, an army at his heels; a legion
   of claquers, a phalanx of musicians, cohorts of comedians, and with
   these for retinue, through <name type="placeName">sacred groves</name> that <persName>Homer</persName> knew, through
   <name type="placeName">intervales</name> which <persName>Hesiod</persName> sang, through a year of <name type="placeName">festivals</name> he wandered,
   always victorious. It was he who conquered at <foreign xml:lang="la">Olympia</foreign>; it was he who
   conquered at <foreign xml:lang="la">Corinth</foreign>. No one could withstand him. Alone in history he
   won in every game, and with eighteen hundred <name type="placeName">crowns</name> as trophies of war
   he repeated <persName>Caesar</persName>'s triumph. In a robe immaterial as a moonbeam, the
   <foreign xml:lang="la">Olympian</foreign> wreath on his curls, the <foreign xml:lang="la">Isthmian</foreign> laurel in his hand, his army
   behind him, the clown that was emperor entered <placeName>Rome</placeName>. Victims were
   immolated as he passed, the <foreign xml:lang="la">Via Sacra</foreign> was strewn with <name type="plant">saffron</name>, the day
   was rent with acclaiming shouts. Throughout the empire sacrifices were
   ordered. Old people that lived in the country fancied him, <persName>Philostratus</persName>
   says, the conqueror of new nations, and sacrificed with delight.</p>
</div>
Voici l'encodage TEI P5 du texte selon les règles strictes du projet Zoomathia :


<div type="book" n="63">
<p>But if as artist he bored everybody, he was yet an admirable
    impresario. The spectacles he gave were unique. At one which was held
    in the <placeName>Taurian amphitheatre</placeName> it must have been delightful to assist.
    Fancy eighty thousand people on ascending galleries, protected from the
    sun by a canopy of spangled silk; an arena three acres large carpeted
    with sand, <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">cinnabar</name> and <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">borax</name>, and in that arena death in every form,
    on those galleries colossal delight.</p>

  <p>The lowest gallery, immediately above the arena, was a wide terrace
    where the senate sat. There were the dignitaries of the empire, and
    with them priests in their sacerdotal robes; vestals in linen, their
    hair arranged in the six braids that were symbolic of virginity; swarms
    of Oriental princes, rainbows of foreign ambassadors; and in the
    centre, the imperial pulvinar, an enclosed pavilion, in which <persName>Nero</persName>
    lounged, a mignon at his feet.</p>

  <p>In the gallery above were the necklaced knights, their tunics bordered
    with the <foreign xml:lang="la">augusticlave</foreign>, their deep-blue cloaks fastened to the shoulder;
    and there, too, in their wide white <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">togas</name>, were the citizens of <placeName>Rome</placeName>.</p>

  <p>Still higher the people sat. In the topmost gallery were the women, and
    in a separate enclosure a thousand musicians answered the cries of the
    multitude with the blare and the laugh of brass.</p>
</div>
<div type="book" n="64">
   <div type="section" n="1">
      <p>Beneath the terraces, behind the barred doors that punctuated the marble wall which circled the arena, were <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Mauritian panthers</name> that had been entrapped with rotten meat; <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">hippopotami</name> from <placeName>Sais</placeName>, lured by the smell of <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">carrots</name> into pits; the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">rhinoceros</name> of <placeName>Gaul</placeName>, taken with the net; <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">lions</name>, lassoed in the deserts; <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Lucanian bears</name>, <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Spanish bulls</name>; and, in remoter dens, <persName>men</persName>, unarmed, that waited.</p>
   </div>
   <div type="section" n="2">
      <p>By way of foretaste for better things, a handful of criminals, local desperadoes, an impertinent <persName>slave</persName>, a <persName>machinist</persName>, who in a theatre the night before had missed an effect--these, together with a negligent usher, were tossed one after the other naked into the ring, and bound to a scaffold that surmounted a miniature hill. At a signal the scaffold fell, the hill crumbled, and from it a few <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">hyenas</name> issued, who indolently devoured their prey.</p>
   </div>
   <div type="section" n="3">
      <p>With this for prelude, the <name type="deity">gods</name> avenged and justice appeased, a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">rhinoceros</name> ambled that way, stimulated from behind by the point of a spear; and in a moment the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">hyenas</name> were disembowelled, their legs quivering in the air. Throughout the arena other <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">beasts</name>, tied together with long cords, quarrelled in couples; there was the bellow of <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">bulls</name>, and the moan of <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">leopards</name> tearing at their flesh, a flight of <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">stags</name>, and the long, clean spring of the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">panther</name>.</p>
   </div>
</div>
Voici l'encodage TEI P5 strictement conforme à vos règles pour le texte fourni :


<div type="book" n="65">
  <div type="section" n="65/157">
    <p>Presently the arena was cleared, the sand reraked and the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Bestiarii</name>
      advanced--<persName>Sarmatians</persName>, nourished on <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">mares</name>' milk; <persName>Sicambrians</persName>, their hair
      done up in chignons; horsemen from <placeName>Thessaly</placeName>, <persName>Ethiopian</persName> warriors,
      <persName>Parthian</persName> archers, huntsmen from the <name type="place">steppes</name>, their different idioms
      uniting in a single cry--"<persName>Caesar</persName>, we salute you." The sunlight,
      filtering through the spangled canopy, chequered their tunics with
      burning spots, danced on their spears and helmets, dazzled the
      spectators' eyes. From above descended the caresses of flutes; the air
      was sweet with perfumes, alive with multicolored motes; the terraces
      were parterres of blending hues, and into that splendor a hundred
      <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">lions</name>, their tasselled tails sweeping the sand, entered obliquely.</p>

    <p>The mob of the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Bestiarii</name> had gone. In the middle of the arena, a band
      of <persName>Ethiopians</persName>, armed with arrows, knives and spears, knelt, their oiled black breasts uncovered.</p>
  </div>
</div>
<div type="book" n="66">
   <p>Leisurely the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">lions</name> turned their huge, intrepid heads; to their jowls wide creases came. There was a glitter of fangs, a shiver that moved the mane, a flight of arrows, mounting murmurs; the crouch of beasts preparing to spring, a deafening roar, and, abruptly, a tumultuous mass, the suddenness of knives, the snap of bones, the cry of the agonized, the fury of beasts transfixed, the shrieks of the mangled, a combat hand to fang, from which <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">lions</name> fell back, their jaws torn asunder, while others retreated, a black body swaying between their terrible teeth, and, insensibly, a descending quiet.</p>
</div>
Voici l'encodage TEI P5 strictement conforme aux règles Zoomathia pour le texte fourni :


<div type="chapter" n="67">
  <p>At once there was an eruption of bellowing <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">elephants</name>, painted and
  trained for slaughter, that trampled on wounded and dead. At a call
  from a keeper the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">elephants</name> disappeared. There was a rush of <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">mules</name> and
  slaves; the carcasses and corpses vanished, the toilet of the ring was
  made; then came a plunge of <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">bulls</name>, mists of vapor about their long,
  straight horns, their anxious eyes dilated. Beyond was a troop of
  <placeName>Thessalians</placeName>. For a moment the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">bulls</name> snorted, pawing the sand with their
  fore-feet, as though trying to realize what they were doing there. Yet
  instantly they seemed to know, and with lowered heads, they plunged on
  the point of spears. But no matter, <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">horses</name> went down by the hundred;
  and as the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">bulls</name> tired of gorging the dead, they fought each other;
  fought rancorously, fought until weariness overtook them, and the
  surviving <placeName>Thessalians</placeName> leaped on their backs, twisted their horns, and
  threw them down, a sword through their throbbing throats.</p>

  <p>Successively the arena was occupied by <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">bears</name>, by <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">panthers</name>, by <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">dogs</name>
  trained for the chase, by hunters and hunted. But the episode of the
  morning was a dash of wild <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">elephants</name>, attacked on either side; a moment of sheer delight, in which the hunters were tossed up on the terraces,
  tossed back again by the spectators, and trampled to death.</p>
</div>
Voici l'encodage TEI P5 strictement conforme à vos règles pour le texte fourni, en respectant les entités nommées Zoomathia et la structure demandée :


<div type="section" n="68">
   <p>With that for <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">bouquet</name> the first part of the performance was at an end.</p>
   <p>By way of interlude, the ring was peopled with acrobats, who flew up in the air like <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">birds</name>, formed pyramids together, on the top of which little boys swung and smiled. There was a troop of trained <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">lions</name>, their manes gilded, that walked on tight-ropes, wrote obscenities in <foreign xml:lang="grc">Ἑλληνικά</foreign>, and danced to <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">cymbals</name> which one of them played. There were <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">geese</name>-fights, wonderful combats between dwarfs and women; a chariot race, in which <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">bulls</name>, painted white, held the reins, standing upright while drawn at full speed; a chase of <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">ostriches</name>, and feats of haute école on <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">zebras</name> from <placeName>Madagascar</placeName>.</p>
   <p>The interlude at an end, the sand was reraked, and preceded by the pomp of lictors, interminable files of gladiators entered, holding their knives to <persName>Nero</persName> that he might see that they were sharp. It was then the eyes of the vestals lighted; artistic death was their chiefest joy, and in a moment, when the spectacle began and the first gladiator fell, above the din you could hear their cry "Hic habet!" and watch their delicate thumbs reverse.</p>
</div>
Voici l'encodage TEI P5 strictement conforme à vos exigences pour le texte fourni, en respectant toutes les règles et priorités :


<div type="book" n="69">
<p>There was no cowardice in that arena. If by chance any hesitation were
  discernible, instantly there were hot irons, the sear of which
  revivified courage at once. But that was rare. The gladiators fought
  for applause, for liberty, for death; fought manfully, skilfully,
  terribly, too, and received the point of the sword or the palm of the
  victor, their expression unchanged, the face unmoved. Among them, some
  provided with a net and prodigiously <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">agile</name>, pursued their adversaries
  hither and thither, trying to entangle them first and kill them later.
  Others, protected by oblong shields and armed with short, sharp swords,
  fought hand-to-hand. There were still others, mailed horsemen, who
  fought with the lance, and charioteers that dealt death from high
  <placeName>Briton</placeName> cars.</p>

  <p>As a spectacle it was unique; one that the <persName>Romans</persName>, or more exactly,
  their predecessors, the <persName>Etruscans</persName>, had devised to train their children
  for war and allay the fear of blood. It had been serviceable, indeed,
  and though the need of it had gone, still the institution endured, and
  in enduring constituted the chief delight of the <name type="deity">vestals</name> and of <placeName>Rome</placeName>.
  By means of it a bankrupt became consul and an emperor beloved. It had
  stayed revolutions, it was the tax of the proletariat on the rich.
  Silver and bread were for the individual, but these things were for the
  crowd.</p>
</div>
<div type="book" n="70">
   <p>During the pauses of the combats the dead were removed by men masked as
      <name type="deity">Mercury</name>, god of hell; red irons, that others, masked as <name type="deity">Charon</name>, bore,
      being first applied as safeguard against swoon or fraud. And when, to
      the kisses of flutes, the last palm had been awarded, the last death
      acclaimed, a ballet was given; that of <persName>Paris</persName> and <name type="deity">Venus</name>, which <persName>Apuleius</persName>
      has described so well, and for afterpiece the romance of <persName>Pasipha?</persName> and the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">bull</name>. Then, as night descended, so did torches, too; the arena was
      strewn with <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">vermilion</name>; tables were set, and to the incitement of
      crotals, <foreign xml:lang="la">Lydians</foreign> danced before the multitude, toasting the last act of
      that wonderful day.</p>
   <p>It was with such magnificence that <persName>Nero</persName> showed the impresario's skill,
      the politician's adroitness. Where the artist, which he claimed to be,
      really appeared, was in the refurbishing of <placeName>Rome</placeName>.</p>
   <p>In spite of <persName>Augustus</persName>' boast, the city was not by any means of marble.
      It was filled with crooked little streets, with the atrocities of the
      <persName>Tarquins</persName>, with houses unsightly and perilous, with the moss and dust of
      ages; it compared with <placeName>Alexandria</placeName> as <placeName>London</placeName> compares with <placeName>Paris</placeName>; it had
      a splendor of its own, but a splendor that could be heightened.</p>
</div>
<div type="chapter" n="71">
   <p>Whether the conflagration which occurred at that time was the result of
accident or design is uncertain and in any event immaterial. <persName>Tacitus</persName>
says that when it began <persName>Nero</persName> was at <placeName>Antium</placeName>, in which case he must have
hastened to return, for admitting that he did not originate the fire,
it is a matter of agreement that he collaborated in it. In quarters
where it showed symptoms of weakness it was by his orders coaxed to new
strength; colossal stone buildings, on which it had little effect, were
battered down with catapults.</p>
</div>
Voici l'encodage TEI P5 strictement conforme à vos règles pour le texte fourni, en respectant les entités nommées Zoomathia et la structure demandée :


<div type="chapter" n="72">
<p>Fire is a perfect poet. No designer ever imagined the surprises it
  creates, and when, at the end of the week, three-fourths of the city
  was in ruins, the beauty that reigned there must have been sublime.</p>
  <p>That it inspired <persName>Nero</persName> is presumable. The palace on the
  <placeName>Palatine</placeName>, which <persName>Tiberius</persName> embellished and
  <persName>Caligula</persName> enlarged, had gone; in its place rose another, aflame
  with gold. Before it <foreign xml:lang="la">Neropolis</foreign> extended, a city of
  triumphal arches, enchanted temples, royal dwellings, shimmering
  porticoes, glittering roofs, and wide, hospitable streets. It was fair
  to the eye, purely <foreign xml:lang="grc">Greek</foreign>; and on its heart, from the
  <placeName>Circus Maximus</placeName> to the <placeName>Forum</placeName>'s edge, the
  new and gigantic palace shone.</p>
  <p>Before it was a lake, a part of which <persName>Vespasian</persName> drained and
  replaced with an amphitheatre that covered eight acres. About that lake were
  separate edifices that formed a city in themselves; between them and the palace,
  a statue of <persName>Nero</persName> in gold and silver mounted precipitately a
  hundred and twenty feet--a statue which it took twenty-four <name type="animal"
  xml:lang="en">elephants</name> to move.</p>
  <p>About it were green savannahs, forest reaches, the call of <name type="animal"
  xml:lang="en">bird</name> and <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">deer</name>, while in the
  distance, fronted by a stretch of columns a mile in length, the palace stood--a
  palace so ineffably charming that on the day of reckoning may it outbalance a few
  of his sins. Even the cellars were frescoed. The baths were quite comfortable; you
  had waters salt or sulphurous at will. The dining halls had ivory ceilings from
  which</p>
</div>
Voici l'encodage TEI P5 strictement conforme aux règles du projet Zoomathia pour le texte fourni :


<div type="chapter" n="73">
   <p>flowers fell, and wainscots that changed at each service. The walls
   were alive with the glisten of gems, with marbles rarer than jewels. In
   one hall was a dome of <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">sapphire</name>, a floor of <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">malachite</name>, crystal columns
   and red-gold walls.</p>
   <p>"At last," <persName>Nero</persName> murmured, "I am lodged like a man."</p>
   <p>No doubt. Yet in a mirror he would have seen a bloated beast in a
   flowered gown, the hair done up in a chignon, the skin covered with
   eruptions, the eyes circled and yellow; a woman who had hours when she
   imitated a virgin at bay, others when she was wife, still others when
   she expected to be a mother, and that woman, a senatorial patent of
   divinity aiding, was god--<name type="deity">Apollo</name>'s peer, imperator, chief of the army,
   pontifix maximus, master of the world, with the incontestable right of
   life and death over every being in the dominions.</p>
</div>
Voici l'encodage TEI P5 strictement conforme à vos règles pour le texte fourni, en respectant les entités nommées Zoomathia et la structure demandée :


<div type="book" n="74">
   <p>It had taken the fresh-faced lad who blushed so readily, just fourteen years to effect that change. Did he regret it? And what should <persName>Nero</persName> regret? Nothing, perhaps, save that at the moment when he declared himself to be lodged like a man, he had not killed himself like one. But of that he was incapable. Had he known what the future held, possibly he might have imitated that apotheosis of vulgarity in which <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Sardanapalus</name> eclipsed himself, but never could he have died with the good breeding and philosophy of <persName>Cato</persName>, for neither good breeding nor philosophy was in him. <persName>Nero</persName> killed himself like a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">coward</name>, yet that he did kill himself, in no matter what fashion, is one of the few things that can be said in his favor.</p>
<p>Those days differed from ours. There were circumstances in which suicide was regarded as the simplest of duties. <persName>Nero</persName> did his duty, but not until he was forced to it, and even then not until he had been asked several times whether it was so hard to die. The empire had wearied of him. In <placeName>Neropolis</placeName> his popularity had gone as popularity ever does; the conflagration had killed it.</p>
</div>
Voici l'encodage TEI P5 strictement conforme à vos règles pour le texte fourni, en respectant la structure demandée et en priorisant l'encodage des entités nommées Zoomathia :


<div type="book" n="75">
<p>Even as he wandered, lyre in hand, a train of <persName>Lesbians</persName> and <persName>pederasts</persName> at his heels, through those halls which had risen on the ruins, and which inexhaustible <placeName>Greece</placeName> had furnished with a fresh crop of white immortals, the world rebelled.</p>
  <p>Afar on the outskirts of civilization a vassal, ashamed of his vassalage, declared war, not against <placeName>Rome</placeName>, but against an emperor that played the flute. In <placeName>Spain</placeName>, in <placeName>Gaul</placeName>, the legions were choosing other chiefs. The provinces, depleted by imperial exactions, outwearied by the increasing number of accusers, whose accusations impoverishing them served only to multiply the prodigalities of their <name type="deity">Caesar</name>, revolted.</p>
<p>Suddenly <persName>Nero</persName> found himself alone. As the advancing rumor of rebellion reached him, he thought of flight; there was no one that would accompany him. He called to the pretorians; they would not hear. Through the immensity of his palace he sought one friend. The doors would not open. He returned to his apartment; the guards had gone. Then terror seized him. He was afraid to die, afraid to live, afraid of his solitude, afraid of <placeName>Rome</placeName>, afraid of himself; but what frightened him most was that everyone had lost their fear of him. It was time to go, and a slave aiding, he escaped in disguise from <placeName>Rome</placeName>, and killed himself, reluctantly, in a hovel.</p>
<p>"<quote>Qualis artifex pereo!</quote>" he is reported to have muttered. Say rather, <foreign xml:lang="la">qualis maechus</foreign>.</p>
</div>
<div type="chapter" n="6">
<head>The House of <persName>Flavia</persName></head>
</div>
Voici l'encodage TEI P5 strictement conforme à vos exigences pour le texte fourni, en respectant toutes les règles et priorités Zoomathia :


<div type="book" n="76">
  <p>It was in those days that the nebulous figure of <persName>Apollonius of Tyana</persName> appeared and disappeared in <placeName>Rome</placeName>. His speech, a commingling of puerility and charm, <persName>Philostratus</persName> has preserved. Rumor had preceded him. It was said that he knew everything, save the caresses of women; that he was familiar with all languages; with the speech of <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">bird</name> and <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">beast</name>; with that of silence, for silence is a language too; that he had prayed in the Temple of <name type="deity">Jupiter Lycaeus</name>, where men lost their shadows, their lives as well; that he had undergone eighty initiations of <name type="deity">Mithra</name>; that he had perplexed the magi; confuted the gymnosophists; that he foretold the future, healed the sick, raised the dead; that beyond the <placeName>Himalayas</placeName> he had encountered every species of ferocious <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">beast</name>, except the tyrant, and that it was to see one that he had come to <placeName>Rome</placeName>.</p>
  <p><persName>Nero</persName> was quite free from prejudice. Apart from a doll which he worshipped he had no superstitions. He had the plain man's dislike of philosophy; <persName>Seneca</persName> had sickened him of it, perhaps; but he was sensitive, not that he troubled himself particularly about any lies that were told of him, but he did object to people who went about telling the truth. In that respect he was not unique; we are all like him, but he had ways of stilling the truth which were imperial and his own.</p>
  <p>Promptly on <persName>Apollonius</persName> he loosed his <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">bull-dog</name>, <persName>Tigellin</persName>, prefect of police.</p>
  <p><persName>Tigellin</persName> caught him. "What have you with you?" he asked.</p>
</div>
Voici l'encodage TEI P5 strictement conforme à vos règles pour le texte fourni, en respectant les entités nommées Zoomathia et la structure demandée :


<div type="book" n="77">
   <p>"<name type="deity">Continence</name>, <name type="deity">Justice</name>, <name type="deity">Temperance</name>, <name type="deity">Strength</name> and <name type="deity">Patience</name>," <persName>Apollonius</persName>
   answered.</p>
   <p>"Your slaves, I suppose. Make out a list of them."</p>
   <p><persName>Apollonius</persName> shook his head. "They are not my slaves; they are my
   masters."</p>
   <p>"There is but one," <persName>Tigellin</persName> retorted--"<persName>Nero</persName>. Why do you not fear him?"</p>
   <p>"Because the <name type="deity">god</name> that made him terrible made me without fear."</p>
   <p>"I will leave you your liberty," muttered the startled <persName>Tigellin</persName>, "but
   you must give bail."</p>
   <p>"And who," asked <persName>Apollonius</persName> superbly, "would bail a man whom no one can
   enchain?" Therewith he turned and disappeared.</p>
   <p>At that time <persName>Nero</persName> was in training to suffocate a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">lion</name> in the arena. A
   few days later he killed himself. Simultaneously there came news from
   <placeName>Syracuse</placeName>. A woman of rank had given birth to a child with three heads.
   <persName>Apollonius</persName> examined it.</p>
   <p>"There will be three emperors at once," he announced. "But their reign
   will be shorter than that of kings on the stage."</p>
   <p>Within that year <persName>Galba</persName>, who was emperor for an instant, died at the
   gates of <placeName>Rome</placeName>. <persName>Vitellius</persName>, after being emperor in little else than
   dream, was butchered in the <placeName>Forum</placeName>; and <persName>Otho</persName>, in that fine antique
   fashion, killed himself in <placeName>Gaul</placeName>. <persName>Apollonius</persName> meanwhile was in
   <placeName>Alexandria</placeName>, predicting the purple to <persName>Vespasian</persName>, the rise of the House
   of <persName>Flavia</persName>; invoking <name type="deity">Jupiter</name> in his protege's behalf; and presently, the
   prediction accomplished, he was back in <placeName>Rome</placeName>, threatening <persName>Domitian</persName>,
   warning him that the House of <persName>Flavia</persName> would fall.</p>
</div>
Voici l'encodage TEI P5 strictement conforme à vos exigences pour ce passage des *Mythes* d'Ésope :


<div type="book" n="78">
   <p>The atmosphere was then charged with the marvellous; the world was
   filled with prodigies, with strange <name type="deity">gods</name>, beckoning
   <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">chimeras</name> and
   credulous crowds. Belief in the supernatural was absolute; the occult
   sciences, astrology, magic, divination, all had their adepts. In
   <placeName>Greece</placeName> there were oracles at every turn, and with them
   prophets who taught the art of adultery and how to construe the past. On the
   banks of the <placeName>Rhine</placeName> there were girls who were regarded as
   <name type="deity">divinities</name>, and in <placeName>Gaul</placeName> were men
   who were held wholly divine.</p>
<p><placeName>Jerusalem</placeName> too had her follies. There was
   <persName>Simon</persName> the Magician, founder of gnosticism, father of every
   heresy, <persName>Messiah</persName> to the <persName>Jews</persName>,
   <foreign xml:lang="la">Jupiter</foreign> to the
   <persName>Gentiles</persName>—an impudent self-made <name type="deity">god</name>,
   who pretended to float in the air, and called his mistress
   <foreign xml:lang="la">Minerva</foreign>—a deification, parenthetically, which
   was accepted by <persName>Nicholas</persName>, his successor, a deacon of the
   church, who raised her to the eighth heaven as patron saint of lust. To him,
   as to <persName>Simon</persName>, she was <foreign xml:lang="grc">Ennoia</foreign>,
   <foreign xml:lang="grc">Prunikos</foreign>,
   <foreign xml:lang="en">Helen of Troy</foreign>. She had been
   <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Delilah</name>,
   <name type="person" xml:lang="en">Lucretia</name>. She had prostituted herself to
   every nation; she had sung in the by-ways, and hidden robbers in the vermin of
   her bed. But by <persName>Simon</persName> she was rehabilitated. It was she,
   no doubt, of whom <persName>Caligula</persName> thought when he beckoned to the
   moon. In <placeName>Rome</placeName> she had her statue, and near it was one to
   <persName>Simon</persName>, the holy <name type="deity">god</name>.</p>
</div>
<div type="book" n="79">
   <p>But of all manifestations of divinity the most patent was that which
   haloed Vespasian. He expected it, <persName>Suetonius</persName> says, but it is doubtful if
   any one else did. One night he dreamed that an era of prosperity was to
   dawn for him and his when <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Nero</name> lost a tooth. The next day he was shown one which had been drawn from the emperor's mouth. But that was
   nothing. Presently at <placeName>Carmel</placeName> the <foreign xml:lang="la">Syrian</foreign> oracle assured him that he
   would be successful in whatever he undertook. From <placeName>Rome</placeName> word came that,
   while the armies of <persName>Vitellius</persName> and <persName>Otho</persName> were fighting, two <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">eagles</name> had
   fought above them, and that the victor had been despatched by a third
   <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">eagle</name> that had come from the <placeName>East</placeName>. In <placeName>Alexandria</placeName> <name type="deity">Serapis</name> whispered to
   him. The entire menagerie of <placeName>Egypt</placeName> proclaimed him king. <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Apis</name> bellowed,
   <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Anubis</name> barked. <name type="deity">Isis</name> visited him unveiled. The lame and the blind
   pressed about him; he cured them with a touch. There could be no
   reasonable doubt now; surely he was a god. On his shoulders <persName>Apollonius</persName>
   threw the purple, and <persName>Vespasian</persName> set out for <placeName>Rome</placeName>.</p>
</div>
Voici l'encodage TEI P5 du texte selon les règles strictes du projet Zoomathia, en respectant la structure demandée et en mettant en avant les entités zoologiques (bien que le texte ne contienne pas de noms d'animaux explicites, j'ai encodé les autres entités nommées et respecté les consignes) :


<div type="book" n="80">
   <p>His antecedents were less propitious. The descendant of an obscure
   <persName>centurion</persName>, he had been a veterinary surgeon; then, having got
   <persName>Caligula</persName>'s ear, he flattered it abominably. <persName>Caligula</persName> disposed of, he
   flattered <persName>Claud</persName>, or what amounted to the same thing, <persName>Narcissus</persName>, <persName>Claud</persName>'s
   chamberlain. Through the influence of the latter he became a
   lieutenant, fought on remote frontiers--fought well, too--so well even
   that, <persName>Narcissus</persName> gone, he felt <persName>Agrippina</persName> watching him, and knowing the
   jealousy of her eyes, prudently kept quiet until that lady did.</p>

   <p>With <persName>Nero</persName> he promenaded through <placeName>Greece</placeName>--sat at the Olympian games and
   fell asleep when his emperor sang. Treason of that high
   nature--sacrilege, rather, for <persName>Nero</persName> was then a <name type="deity">god</name>--might have been
   overlooked, had it occurred but once, for <persName>Nero</persName> could be magnanimous
   when he chose. But it always occurred. To <persName>Nero</persName>'s tremolo invariably
   came the accompaniment of <persName>Vespasian</persName>'s snore. He was dreaming of that
   tooth, no doubt. "I am not a soporific, am I?" <persName>Nero</persName> gnashed at him, and
   sent the blasphemer away.</p>

   <p>For a while <persName>Vespasian</persName> lived in constant expectation of some civil
   message inviting him to die. Finally it came, only he was invited to
   die at the head of an army which <persName>Nero</persName> had projected against seditious
   <persName>Jews</persName>. When he returned, leaving his son <persName>Titus</persName> to attend to <placeName>Jerusalem</placeName>,
   it was as emperor.</p>
</div>
<div type="chapter" n="81">
   <p>Only a moment before Vitellius had been disposed of. That curious
      <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">glutton</name>, whom the <placeName>Rhenish</placeName> legions had chosen because of his coarse
      familiarity, would willingly have fled had the soldiery let him. But
      not at all; they wanted a prince of their own manufacture. They knew
      nothing of <persName>Vespasian</persName>, cared less; and into the <placeName>Capitol</placeName> they chased the
      latter's partisans, his son <persName>Domitian</persName> as well. The besieged defended
      themselves with masterpieces, with sacred urns, the statues of <name type="deity">gods</name>,
      the pedestals of <name type="deity">divinities</name>. Suddenly the <placeName>Capitol</placeName> was aflame.
      Simultaneously <persName>Vespasian</persName>'s advance guard beat at the gates. The
      besiegers turned, the mob was with them, and together they fought,
      first at the gates, then in the streets, in the <placeName>Forum</placeName>, retreating
      always, but like <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">lions</name>, their face to the foe. The volatile mob, noting
      the retreat, turned from combatant into spectator. Let the soldiers
      fight; it was their duty, not theirs; and, as the struggle continued,
      from roof and window they eyed it with that artistic delight which the
      arena had developed, applauding the clever thrusts, abusing the
      vanquished, robbing the dead, and therewith pillaging the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">wineshops</name>,
      crowding the <foreign xml:lang="la">lupanars</foreign>. During the orgy, <persName>Vitellius</persName> was stabbed. The
      <persName>Flavians</persName> had won the day, the empire was <persName>Vespasian</persName>'s.</p>
</div>
<div type="chapter" n="82">
   <p>The use he made of it was very modest. In spite of his manifest
      divinity he had nothing in common with the <name type="deity">Caesars</name> that had gone
      before; he had no dreams of the impossible, no desire to frighten
      <name type="deity">Jupiter</name> or seduce the <foreign xml:lang="la">moon</foreign>. He was a plain man, tall and ruddy, very
      coarse in speech and thought, open-armed and close-fisted, slapping
      <persName>senators</persName> on the back and keeping a sharp eye on the coppers; taxing the
      <name type="placeName">latrinae</name>, and declaring that money had no smell; yet still, in
      comparison with <name type="deity">Claud</name> and <name type="deity">Nero</name>, almost the ideal; absolutely
      uninteresting also, yet doing what good he could; effacing at once the
      traces of the civil war, rebuilding the <placeName>Capitol</placeName>, calming the people,
      protecting the provinces, restoring to <placeName>Rome</placeName> the gardens of <name type="deity">Nero</name>,
      clipping the wings of the <placeName>Palace of Gold</placeName>, throwing open again the <placeName>Via Sacra</placeName>,
      over which the Palace had spread; draining the lake that had
      shimmered before it, and erecting the <placeName>Colosseum</placeName> in its place.</p>
</div>
Voici l'encodage TEI P5 strictement conforme aux règles et au texte fourni :


<div type="book" n="83">
   <p>In spite of <name type="deity">Serapsis</name>, <name type="deity">Anubis</name> and <name type="deity">Isis</name>, he had not the faintest odor of myth about him; absolutely bourgeois, he lacked even that atmosphere of burlesque that surrounded <persName>Claud</persName>; he was not even vicious. But he was a soldier, a brave one; and if, with the acquired economy of a subaltern who has been obliged to live on his pay, he kept his purse-strings tight, they were loose enough if a friend were in need, and he paid no one the compliment of a lie. He was projected sheer out of the republic. The better part of his life had been passed under arms; the delicate sensuality of <placeName>Rome</placeName> was foreign to him. It was there that <persName>Domitian</persName> had lived.</p>
   <p>It were interesting to have watched that young man killing <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">flies</name> by the hour, while he meditated on the atrocities he was to commit--atrocities so numberless and needless that in the red halls of the <persName>Caesars</persName> he has left a portrait which is unique. Slender, graceful, handsome, as were all the young emperors of old <placeName>Rome</placeName>, his blue, troubled eyes took pleasure, if at all, only in the sight of blood.</p>
</div>
Voici l'encodage TEI P5 strictement conforme à vos exigences pour le texte fourni, en respectant toutes les règles et priorités Zoomathia :


<div type="book" n="84">
<p>In accordance with the fashion which <persName>Caligula</persName> and <persName>Nero</persName> had set,</p>
   <p><persName>Domitian</persName>'s earliest manners were those of an urbane and gentle prince.</p>
   <p>Later, when he made it his turn to rule, informers begged their bread
   in exile. Where they are not punished, he announced, they are
   encouraged. The sacrifices were so distressing to him that he forbade
   the immolation of <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">oxen</name>.</p>
   <p>He was disinterested, too, refusing legacies
   when the testator left nearer heirs, and therewith royally generous,
   covering his suite with presents, and declaring that to him avarice of
   all vices was the lowest and most vile. In short, you would have said
   another adolescent <persName>Nero</persName> come to <placeName>Rome</placeName>; there was the same silken
   sweetness of demeanor, the same ready blush, in addition to a zeal for
   justice and equity which other young emperors had been too thoughtless
   to show.</p>

   <p>His boyhood, too, had not been above reproach. The same things were
   whispered about him that had been shouted at <persName>Augustus</persName>. Manifestly he
   lacked not one of the qualities which go to the making of a model
   prince. <persName>Vespasian</persName> alone had his doubts.</p>

   <p>"<name type="plant" xml:lang="en">Mushrooms</name> won't hurt you," he cried one day, as <persName>Domitian</persName> started at
   the sight of a ragout <foreign xml:lang="fr">a la Sardanapale</foreign>, which he fancied, possibly, was
   <foreign xml:lang="fr">a la Locuste</foreign>, "It is steel you should fear."</p>
</div>
<div type="book" n="85">
  <p>At that time, with a <persName>father</persName> for <name type="deity">emperor</name> and a <persName>brother</persName> who was sacking <placeName>Jerusalem</placeName>, <persName>Domitian</persName> had but one cause for anxiety, to wit--that the empire might escape him. It was then he began his meditations over holocausts of <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">flies</name>. For hours he secluded himself, occupied solely with their slaughter. He treated them precisely as <persName>Titus</persName> treated the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Jews</name>, enjoying the quiver of their legs, the little agonies of their silent death.</p>
<p><persName>Tiberius</persName> had been in love with solitude, but never as he. Night after night he wandered on the terraces of the <placeName>palace</placeName>, watching the red <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">moon</name> wane white, companioned only by his dreams, those waking dreams that <persName>poets</persName> and <persName>madmen</persName> share, that <name type="deity">Pallas</name> had him in her charge, that <name type="deity">Psyche</name> was amorous of his eyes.</p>
</div>
Voici l'encodage TEI P5 strictement conforme à vos règles pour le texte fourni, en respectant la priorité absolue des entités nommées Zoomathia et les contraintes structurelles :


<div type="chapter" n="86">
   <p>Meanwhile he was a nobody, a young gentleman merely, who might have
   moved in the best society, and who preferred the worst--his own. The
   sudden elevation of <persName>Vespasian</persName> preoccupied him, and while he knew that
   in the natural course of events his father would move to <placeName>Olympus</placeName>, yet
   there was his brother <persName>Titus</persName>, on whose broad shoulders the mantle of
   purple would fall. If the seditious <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Jews</name> only knew their business! But
   no. Forty years before a white apparition on the way to <placeName>Golgotha</placeName> had
   cried to a handful of women, "The days are coming in which they shall
   say to the mountains, 'Fall on us'; to the hills, 'Cover us.'" And the
   days had come. A million of them had been butchered. From the country
   they had fled to the city; from <placeName>Acra</placeName> they had climbed to <placeName>Zion</placeName>. When the
   city burst into flames their blood put it out. Decidedly they did not
   know their business. <persName>Titus</persName>, instead of being stabbed before <placeName>Jerusalem</placeName>'s
   walls, was marching in triumph to <placeName>Rome</placeName>.</p>

   <p>The procession that presently entered the gates was a stream of
   splendor; crowns of rubies and gold; garments that glistened with gems;
   <name type="deity">gods</name> on their sacred pedestals; prisoners; curious <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">beasts</name>;
   <placeName>Jerusalem</placeName> in miniature; pictures of war; booty from the Temple, the veil, the
   candelabra, the cups of gold and the Book of the Law. To the rear
   rumbled the triumphal car, in which laurelled and mantled <persName>Titus</persName> stood,
   <persName>Vespasian</persName> at his side; while, in the distance, on horseback, came
   <persName>Domitian</persName>--a supernumerary, ignored by the crowd.</p>
</div>
Voici l'encodage TEI P5 strictement conforme à vos règles pour le texte fourni, en respectant la priorité absolue pour les entités nommées Zoomathia et la structure demandée :


<div type="book" n="87">
   <p>When the prisoners disappeared in the <placeName>Tullianum</placeName> and a <persName>herald</persName> shouted,</p>
   <quote>"They have lived!"</quote>
   <p><persName>Domitian</persName> returned to the palace and hunted morosely for <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">flies</name>. The excesses of the festival in which <placeName>Rome</placeName> was swooning then had no delights for him.</p>
   <p>Presently the <name type="celestial">moon</name> would rise, and then on the deserted terrace perhaps he would bathe a little in her light, and dream again of <persName>Pallas</persName> and of the possibilities of an emperor's sway, but meanwhile those blue troubled eyes that <persName>Psyche</persName> was amorous of were filled with envy and with hate.</p>
   <p>It was not that he begrudged <persName>Titus</persName> the triumph. The man who had disposed of a million <name type="ethnic" xml:lang="en">Jews</name> deserved not one triumph, but ten. It was the purple that haunted him.</p>
   <p><persName>Domitian</persName> was then in the early twenties. The <placeName>Temple of Peace</placeName> was ascending; the <placeName>Temple of Janus</placeName> was closed; the empire was at rest. Side by side with <persName>Vespasian</persName>, <persName>Titus</persName> ruled.</p>
   <p>From the <placeName>Euphrates</placeName> came the rumor of some vague revolt. <persName>Domitian</persName> thought he would like to quell it. He was requested to keep quiet.</p>
   <p>It occurred to him that his father ought to be ashamed of himself to reign so long. He was requested to vacate his apartment. There were dumb plots in dark cellars, of which only the echo of a whisper has descended to us, but which at the time were quite loud enough to reach <persName>Vespasian</persName>'s ears. <persName>Titus</persName> interceded. <persName>Domitian</persName> was requested to behave.</p>
</div>
<div type="book" n="88">
   <p>For a while he prowled in the moonlight. He had been too precipitate,</p>
   <p>he decided, and to allay suspicion presently he went about in society,</p>
   <p>mingling his hours with those of married women. Manifestly his ways had</p>
   <p>mended. But <persName>Vespasian</persName> was uneasy. A <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">comet</name> had appeared. The doors of</p>
   <p>the imperial mausoleum had opened of themselves, besides, he was not</p>
   <p>well. The robust and hardy soldier, suddenly without tangible cause,</p>
   <p>felt his strength give way. "It is nothing," his physician said; "a</p>
   <p>slight attack of fever." <persName>Vespasian</persName> shook his head; he knew things of</p>
   <p>which the physician was ignorant. "It is death," he answered, "and an</p>
   <p>emperor should meet it standing."</p>

   <div type="section" n="2">
      <p><persName>Titus</persName>' turn came next. A violent, headstrong, handsome, rapacious</p>
      <p><persName>prince</persName>, terribly prodigal, thoroughly Oriental, surrounded by dancers</p>
      <p>and mignons, living in state with a queen for mistress, startling even</p>
      <p><placeName>Rome</placeName> with the uproar of his debauches--no sooner was <persName>Vespasian</persName> gone</p>
      <p>than presto! the queen went home, the dancers disappeared, the</p>
      <p>debauches ceased, and a ruler appeared who declared he had lost a day</p>
      <p>that a good action had not marked; a ruler who could announce that no</p>
      <p>one should leave his presence depressed.</p>
   </div>
</div>
Voici l'encodage TEI P5 strictement conforme aux règles du projet Zoomathia pour le texte fourni :


<div type="book" n="89">
  <p>Though <persName>Vespasian</persName> had gone, his reign continued. Not long, it is true,</p>
  <p>and punctuated by a spectacle of which <persName>Caligula</persName>, for all his poetry,</p>
  <p>had not dreamed--the burial of <placeName>Pompeii</placeName>. But a reign which, while it</p>
  <p>lasted, was fastidious and refined, and during which, again and again,</p>
  <p><persName>Titus</persName>, who commanded death and whom death obeyed, besought <persName>Domitian</persName> to</p>
  <p>be to him a brother.</p>

  <p><persName>Domitian</persName> had no such intention. He had a party behind him, one made up</p>
  <p>of old <foreign xml:lang="la">Neronians</foreign>, the army of the discontented, who wanted a change,</p>
  <p>and greatly admired this charming young prince whose hours were passed</p>
  <p>in killing <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">flies</name> and making love to married women. The <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">pretorians</name> too</p>
  <p>had been seduced. <persName>Domitian</persName> could make captivating promises when he</p>
  <p>chose.</p>

  <p>As a consequence <persName>Titus</persName>, like <persName>Vespasian</persName>, was uneasy, and with cause.</p>
  <p><persName>Dion Cassius</persName>, or rather that brute <persName>Xiphilin</persName>, his abbreviator, mentions</p>
  <p>the fever that overtook him, the same his father had met. It was</p>
  <p>mortal, of course, and the purple was <persName>Domitian</persName>'s.</p>
</div>
Voici l'encodage TEI P5 strictement conforme à vos exigences pour le texte fourni, en respectant les règles Zoomathia et en priorisant les entités nommées zoologiques (bien que ce texte n'en contienne pas) :


<div type="book" n="90">
  <p>For a year and a day thereafter you would have thought <persName>Titus</persName> still at
  the helm. There was the same clemency, the same regard for justice, the
  same refinement and fastidiousness. The morose young poet had developed
  into a model monarch. The old <persName>Neronians</persName> were perplexed, irritated too;
  they had expected other things. <persName>Domitian</persName> was merely feeling the way;
  the hand that held the sceptre was not quite sure of its strength, and,
  tentatively almost, this Prince of Virtue began to scrutinize the
  morals of <placeName>Rome</placeName>.</p>

  <p>For the first time he noticed that the <foreign xml:lang="fr">cocottes</foreign> took
  their airing in litters. But litters were not for them! That abuse he
  put a stop to at once. A <persName>senator</persName> manifested an interest in
  <foreign xml:lang="en">ballet-girls</foreign>; he was disgraced. The <foreign xml:lang="en">vestals</foreign>, to whose indiscretions no
  one had paid much attention, learned the statutes of an archaic law,
  and were buried alive. The early distaste for blood was diminishing.
  <persName>Domitian</persName> had the purple, but it was not bright enough; he wanted it
  red, and what <persName>Domitian</persName> wanted he got. Your god and master orders it,
  was the formula he began to use when addressing the <persName>Senate</persName> and <persName>People</persName>
  of <placeName>Rome</placeName>.</p>
</div>
Voici l'encodage TEI P5 strictement conforme aux règles du projet Zoomathia pour ce passage :


<div type="book" n="91">
  <p>To that the people were indifferent. The spectacles he gave in the
    <placeName>Flavian amphitheatre</placeName> were too magnificently atrocious not to be a
    compensation in full for any eccentricity in which he might indulge.
    Besides, under <persName>Nero</persName>, <persName>Claud</persName>, <persName>Caligula</persName>,
    <foreign xml:lang="fr">on en avait vu bien d'autres</foreign>. And at those spectacles where he presided,
    crowned with a tiara, on which were the images of <name type="deity">Jupiter</name>,
    <name type="deity">Juno</name> and <name type="deity">Minerva</name>, while grouped about him the college of
    <name type="animal">Flavian flamens</name> wore tiaras that differed therefrom merely in this,
    that they bore his image too, the people right royally applauded their master and their god.</p>
</div>
Voici l'encodage TEI P5 strictement conforme à vos exigences pour le texte fourni, en respectant toutes les règles et priorités :


<div type="book" n="92">
  <p>And it was just as well they did; <persName>Domitian</persName> was quite capable of ordering everybody into the arena. As yet, however, he had appeared little different from any other prince. That <placeName>Rome</placeName> might understand that there was a difference, and also in what that difference consisted, he gave a supper. Everyone worth knowing was bidden, and, as is usual in state functions, everyone that was bidden came. The supper hall was draped with black; the ceiling, the walls, the floor, everything was basaltic. The couches were black, the linen was black, the slaves were black. Behind each guest was a broken column with his name on it. The food was such as is prepared when death has come. The silence was that of the tomb. The only audible voice was <persName>Domitian</persName>'s. He was talking very wittily and charmingly about murder, about proscriptions, the good informers do, the utility of the headsman, the majesty of the law. The guests, a trifle ill at ease, wished their host sweet dreams. "The same to you," he answered, and deplored that they must go.</p>
<p>On the morrow informers and headsmen were at work. Any pretext was sufficient. Birth, wealth, fame, or the lack of them--anything whatever--and there the culprit stood, charged not with treason to an emperor, but with impiety to a <name type="deity">god</name>. On the judgment seat <persName>Domitian</persName> sat. Before him the accused passed, and under his eyes they were questioned, tortured, condemned and killed. At once their property passed into the keeping of the prince.</p>
</div>
Voici l'encodage TEI P5 strictement conforme à vos exigences pour le texte d'Ésope (fable 93/157) :


<div type="book" n="93">
  <div type="section" n="1">
    <p>Of that he had need. The arena was expensive, but the drain was
    elsewhere. A little before, a quarrelsome people, the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Dacians</name>, whom it
    took a Trajan to subdue, had overrun the <placeName>Danube</placeName>, and were marching down
    to <placeName>Rome</placeName>. <persName>Domitian</persName> set out to meet them. The <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Dacians</name> retreated, not at
    all because they were repulsed, but because <persName>Domitian</persName> thought it better
    warfare to pay them to do so. On his return after that victory he
    enjoyed a triumph as fair as that of <persName>Caesar</persName>. And each year since then
    the emperor of <placeName>Rome</placeName> had paid tribute to a nation of mongrel oafs.</p>

<p>Of course he needed money. The informers were there and he got it, and
    with it that spectacle of torture and of blood which he needed too.
    Curiously, his melancholy increased; his good looks had gone; <foreign xml:lang="la">Psyche</foreign>
    was no longer amorous of his eyes. Something else haunted him,
    something he could not define; the past, perhaps, perhaps the future.
    To his ears came strange sounds, the murmur of his own name, and
    suddenly silence. Then, too, there always seemed to be something behind
    him; something that when he turned disappeared. The room in which he
    slept he had covered with a polished metal that reflected everything,
    yet still the intangible was there. Once <name type="deity">Pallas</name> came in her chariot,
    waved him farewell, and disappeared, borne by black <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">horses</name> across the
    black night.</p>
  </div>
</div>
Voici l'encodage TEI P5 strictement conforme à vos règles pour le texte fourni, en respectant les entités nommées Zoomathia et la structure demandée :


<div type="chapter" n="94">
   <p>The astrologers consulted had nothing pleasant to say. They knew, as
   <persName>Domitian</persName> knew, that the end was near. So was theirs. To one of them,
   who predicted his immediate death, he inquired, "What will your end
   be?" "I," answered the astrologer--"I shall be torn by <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">dogs</name>." "To the
   stake with him!" cried <persName>Domitian</persName>; "let him be burned alive!" <persName>Suetonius</persName>
   says that a storm put out the flames, and <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">dogs</name> devoured the corpse.
   Another astrologer predicted that <persName>Domitian</persName> would die before noon on the
   morrow. In order to convince him of his error, <persName>Domitian</persName> ordered him to
   be executed the subsequent night. Before noon on the morrow <persName>Domitian</persName>
   was dead.</p>

   <p><persName>Philostratus</persName> and <persName>Dion Cassius</persName> both unite in saying that at that hour
   <persName>Apollonius</persName> was at <placeName>Ephesus</placeName>, preaching to the multitude. In the middle of
   the sermon he hesitated, but in a moment he began anew. Again he
   hesitated, his eyes half closed; then, suddenly he shouted, "Strike
   him! Strike him once more!" And immediately to his startled audience he
   related a scene that was occurring at <placeName>Rome</placeName>, the attack on <persName>Domitian</persName>, his
   struggle with an assailant, his effort to tear out his eyes, the rush
   of conspirators, and finally the fall of the emperor, pierced by seven
   knives.</p>

   <p>The story may not be true, and yet if it were!</p>
</div>

<div type="section" n="VII">
<head>The Poison in the Purple</head>
</div>
Voici l'encodage TEI P5 strictement conforme à vos exigences pour le texte d'Ésope (fables) :


<div type="book" n="95">
<p>Rome never was healthy. The <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">tramontana</name> visited it then as now, fever, too, and sudden death. To emperors it was fatal. Since <persName>Caesar</persName> a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">malaria</name> had battened on them all. <persName>Nerva</persName> escaped, but only through abdication. The mantle that fell from <persName>Domitian</persName>'s shoulders on to his was so dangerous in its splendor, that, fearing the infection, he passed it to <persName>Ulpius Trajanus</persName>, the lustre undimmed.</p>

<p><persName>Ulpius Trajanus</persName>, <persName>Trajan</persName> for brevity, a Spaniard by birth, a soldier by choice; one who had fought against <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Parthian</name> and <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Jew</name>, who had triumphed through <placeName>Pannonia</placeName> and made it his own; a general whose hair had whitened on the field; a consul who had frightened nations, was afraid of the sheen of that purple which dazzled, corroded and killed. He bore it, indeed, but at arm's-length. He kept himself free from the subtlety of its poison, from the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">microbes</name> of <placeName>Rome</placeName> as well.</p>

<p>He was in <placeName>Cologne</placeName> when <persName>Domitian</persName> died and <persName>Nerva</persName> accepted and renounced the throne. It was a year before he ventured among the seven hills. When he arrived you would have said another <persName>Augustus</persName>, not the real <persName>Augustus</persName>, but the <persName>Augustus</persName> of legend, and the late Mr. <persName>Gibbon</persName>. When he girt the new prefect of the pretorium with the immemorial sword, he addressed him in copy-book phrases--"If I rule wisely, use it for me; unwisely, against me."</p>
</div>
Voici l'encodage TEI P5 du texte selon les règles strictes du projet Zoomathia :


<div type="chapter" n="96">
<p>Rome listened open-mouthed. The change from <persName>Domitian</persName>'s formula, "Your god and master orders it," was too abrupt to be immediately understood.</p>
  <p>Before it was grasped <persName>Trajan</persName> was off again; this time to the <placeName>Danube</placeName> and beyond it, to <placeName>Dacia</placeName> and her fens.</p>
<p>Many years later--a century or two, to be exact--a <name type="person">Persian satrap</name> loitered in a forum of <placeName>Rome</placeName>. "It is here," he declared, "I am tempted to forget that man is mortal."</p>
<p>He had passed beneath a triumphal arch; before him was a glittering square, grandiose, yet severe; a stretch of temples and basilicas, in which masterpieces felt at home--the Forum of <persName>Trajan</persName>, the compliment of a nation to a prince.</p>
  <p>Dominating it was a column, in whose thick spirals you read to-day the one reliable chronicle of the <name type="animal">Dacian</name> campaign. Was not <persName>Gautier</persName> well advised when he said only art endures?</p>
<p>There were other chronicles in plenty; there were the histories of <persName>AElius Maurus</persName>, of <persName>Marius Maximus</persName>, and that of <persName>Spartian</persName>, but they are lost.</p>
  <p>There is a page or two in the abbreviation which <persName>Xiphilin</persName> made of <persName>Dion</persName>; <persName>Aurelius Victor</persName> has a little to add, so also has <persName>Eutropus</persName>, but, practically speaking, there is, apart from that column, nothing save conjecture.</p>
</div>
Voici l'encodage TEI P5 du texte selon les règles strictes du projet Zoomathia :


<div type="book" n="97">
<p>Campaigns are wearisome reading, but not the one that is pictured
  there. You ask a curve a question, and in the next you find the reply.
  There is a point, however, on which it is dumb--the origin of the war.
  But if you wish to know the result, not the momentary and transient
  result, but the sequel which futurity held, look at the ruins at that
  column's base.</p>

<p>The origin of the war was <persName>Domitian</persName>'s diplomacy. The chieftain whom he
  had made king, and who had been surprised enough at receiving a diadem
  instead of the point of a sword, fancied, and not unreasonably, that
  the annuity which <placeName>Rome</placeName> paid him was to continue forever. But <persName>Domitian</persName>,
  though a god, was not otherwise immortal. When he died abruptly the
  annuity ceased. The <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Dacian</name> king sent word that he was surprised at the
  delay, but he must have been far more so at the promptness with which
  he got <persName>Trajan</persName>'s reply. It was a blare of <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">bugles</name>, which he thought
  forever dumb; a flight of <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">eagles</name>, which he thought were winged.</p>
</div>
Voici l'encodage TEI P5 strictement conforme à vos règles pour le texte fourni, en respectant les entités nommées Zoomathia et les contraintes structurelles :


<div type="book" n="98">
<p>In the spirals of the column you see the advancing army, the retreating
    foe; then the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Dacian dragon</name> saluting the standards of Rome; peace
    declared, and an army, whose very repose is menacing, standing there to
    see that peace is kept. And was it? In the ascending spiral is the new
    revolt, the attempt to assassinate <persName>Trajan</persName>, the capture of the
    conspirators, the advance of the legions, the retreat of the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Dacians</name>,
    burning their cities as they go, carrying their wounded and their women
    with them, and at last pressing about a huge cauldron that is filled
    with poison, fighting among themselves for a cup of the brew, and
    rolling on the ground in the convulsions of death. Farther on is the
    treasure of the king. To hide it he had turned a river from its source,
    sunk the gold in a vault beneath, and killed the workmen that had
    labored there. Beyond is the capture of the capital, the suicide of the
    chief, a troop of soldiers driving captives and <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">cattle</name> before them, the
    death of a nation and the end of war.</p>

  <p>The subsequent triumph does not appear on the column. It is said that
    ten thousand <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">beasts</name> were slaughtered in the arenas, slaughtering, as
    they fell, a thousand of their slaughterers. But the spectacle, however
    fair, was not of a nature to detain <persName>Trajan</persName> long in Rome. The air there
    had not improved in the least, and presently he was off again, this
    time on the banks of the <placeName>Euphrates</placeName>, arguing with the <name type="deity">Parthians</name>,
    avoiding danger in the only way he knew, by facing it.</p>
</div>
<div type="book" n="99">
<p>It was then that the sheen of the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">purple</name> glowed. If lustreless at home, it was royally red abroad. In a campaign that was little more than a triumphant promenade he doubled the empire. To the world of <persName>Caesar</persName> he added that of <persName>Alexander</persName>. Allies he turned into subjects, vassals into slaves. <placeName>Armenia</placeName>, <placeName>Mesopotamia</placeName>, <placeName>Assyria</placeName>, were added to the realm. <persName>Trajan</persName>'s footstools were diadems. He had moved back one frontier, he moved another. From <placeName>Britain</placeName> to the <placeName>Indus</placeName>, <placeName>Rome</placeName> was mistress of the earth. Had <persName>Trajan</persName> been younger, <placeName>China</placeName>, whose very name was unknown, would have yielded to him her corruption, her printing press, her powder and her tea.</p>
</div>
Voici l'encodage TEI P5 strictement conforme à vos règles pour le texte fourni, en respectant les entités nommées Zoomathia et la structure demandée :


<div type="book" n="100">
  <p>That he would have enjoyed these things is not at all conjectural. He
  was then an old man, but he was not a good one--at least not in the
  sense we use the term to-day. He had habits which are regarded now less
  as vices than perversions, but which at that time were taken as a
  matter of course and accepted by everyone, even by the <persName>stoics</persName>,
  very calmly, with a grain of <foreign xml:lang="grc">Attic</foreign> salt at that. Men were regarded as
  virtuous when they were brave, when they were honest; the idea of using
  the expression in its later sense occurred, if at all, in jest merely,
  as a synonym for the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">eunuch</name>. It was the <persName>matron</persName> and the
  <persName>vestal</persName> who were supposed to be straight, and their straightness was wholly
  supposititious. The ceremonies connected with the <foreign xml:lang="la">phallus</foreign>, and those
  observed in the worship of the <name type="deity">Bona Dea</name>, were of a nature that no
  virtue could withstand. Every altar, <persName>Juvenal</persName> said, had its <persName>Clodius</persName>, and
  even in <persName>Clodius</persName>' absence there were always those breaths of <foreign xml:lang="grc">Sapphic</foreign>
  song that blew through <placeName>Mitylene</placeName>.</p>
</div>
<div type="book" n="101">
   <p>It is just that absence of a quality which we regard as an added grace;</p>
   <p>one, parenthetically, which dowered the world with a new conception of
      beauty that makes it difficult to picture <placeName>Rome</placeName>.</p>
   <p><foreign xml:lang="la">Modern</foreign> ink has acquired
      <persName>Nero</persName>'s blush; it comes very readily, yet, however sensitive a writer
      may be, once <placeName>Roman</placeName> history is before him, he may violate it if he
      choose; he may even give it a child, but never can he make it
      immaculate.</p>
   <p>He may skip, indeed, if he wish; and it is because he has
      skipped so often that one fancies that <persName>Augustus</persName> was all right.</p>
   <p>The rain
      of fire which fell on the cities that mirrored their towers in the
      <placeName>Bitter Sea</placeName>, might just as well have fallen on him, on <persName>Vergil</persName>, too, on
      <persName>Caligula</persName>, <persName>Claud</persName>, <persName>Nero</persName>, <persName>Otho</persName>, <persName>Vitellius</persName>, <persName>Titus</persName>, <persName>Domitian</persName>, and
      particularly on <persName>Trajan</persName>.</p>
</div>
Voici l'encodage TEI P5 strictement conforme à vos exigences pour le texte fourni, en respectant toutes les règles et priorités Zoomathia :


<div type="section" n="102">
   <p>As lieutenant in the latter's triumphant promenade, was a nephew,</p>
   <persName>Aelius Hadrianus</persName>, a young man for whom <persName>Trajan</persName>'s wife is rumored to have
   had more than a platonic affection, and who in younger days was
   numbered among <persName>Trajan</persName>'s mignons. During the progress of that promenade
   <persName>Trajan</persName> fell ill. The command of the troops was left to <persName>Hadrian</persName>, and
   <persName>Trajan</persName> started for <placeName>Rome</placeName>. On the way he died. In what manner is not
   known; his wife, however, was with him, and it was in her hand that a
   letter went to the senate stating that <persName>Trajan</persName> had adopted <persName>Hadrian</persName> as
   his heir. <persName>Trajan</persName> had done nothing of the sort. The idea had indeed
   occurred to him, but long since it had been abandoned. He had even
   formally selected someone else, but his wife was with him, and her
   lover commanded the troops. The lustre of the purple, always dazzling,
   had fascinated <persName>Hadrian</persName>'s eyes. Did he steal it? One may conjecture, yet
   never know. In any event it was his, and he folded it very
   magnificently about him. Still young, a trifle over thirty, handsome,
   unusually accomplished, grand seigneur to his finger-tips, endowed with
   a manner which is rumored to have been one of great charm, possessed of
   the amplest appreciation of the elegancies of life, he had precisely
   the figure which purple adorns. But, though the lustre had fascinated,
   he too knew its spell; and presently he started off on a journey about
   the world, which lasted fifteen years, and which, when ended, left the
</div>
<div type="book" n="103">
  <p>world the richer for his passing, decorated with the monuments he had strewn.</p>
  <p>Before that journey began, at the earliest rumor of <persName>Trajan</persName>'s death, the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Euphrates</name> and <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Tigris</name> awoke, the cinders of <placeName>Nineveh</placeName> flamed.</p>
  <p>The rivers and land that lay between knew that their conqueror had gone.</p>
  <p><persName>Hadrian</persName> knew it also, and knew too that, though he might occupy the warrior's throne, he never could fill the warrior's place.</p>
  <p>To <placeName>Armenia</placeName>, <placeName>Mesopotamia</placeName>, <placeName>Assyria</placeName>, freedom was restored.</p>
  <p><placeName>Dacia</placeName> could have had it for the asking.</p>
  <p>But over <placeName>Dacia</placeName> the toga had been thrown; it was as Roman as <placeName>Gaul</placeName>.</p>
  <p>A corner of it is Roman still; the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Roumanians</name> are there.</p>
  <p>But though <placeName>Dacia</placeName> was quiet, in its neighborhood the restless <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Sarmatians</name> prowled and threatened.</p>
  <p><persName>Hadrian</persName>, who had already written a book on tactics, knew at once how to act.</p>
  <p><persName>Domitian</persName>'s policy was before him; he followed the precedent, and paid the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Sarmatians</name> to be still.</p>
  <p>It requires little acumen to see that when <placeName>Rome</placeName> permitted herself to be blackmailed the end was near.</p>
</div>
Voici l'encodage TEI P5 strictement conforme aux règles du projet Zoomathia pour le texte fourni :


<div type="chapter" n="104">
  <p>For the time being, however, there was peace, and in its interest Hadrian set out on that unequalled journey over a land that was his.</p>
  <p>Had fate relented, <persName>Trajan</persName> could have made a wider one still. But in <persName>Trajan</persName> was the soldier merely, when he journeyed it was with the sword.</p>
  <p>In <persName>Hadrian</persName> was the dilettante, the erudite too; he travelled not to conquer, but to learn, to satisfy an insatiable curiosity, for self-improvement, for glory too.</p>
  <p>Behind him was an army, not of soldiers, but of masons, captained by architects, artists and engineers.</p>
  <p>Did a site please him, there was a temple at once, or if not that, then a bridge, an aqueduct, a library, a new fashion, sovereignty even, but everywhere the spectacle of an emperor in flesh and blood.</p>
  <p>For the first time the provinces were able to understand that a <persName>Caesar</persName> was not necessarily a brute, a phantom and a god.</p>
  <p>It would have been interesting to have made one of that court of poets and savants that surrounded him; to have dined with him in <placeName>Paris</placeName>, eaten oysters in <placeName>London</placeName>; sat with him while he watched that wall go up before the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Scots</name>, and then to have passed down again through a world still young--a world beautiful, ornate, unutilitarian; a world to which trams, advertisements and telegraph poles had not yet come; a world that still had illusions, myths and mysteries; one in which religion and poetry went hand in hand--a world without newspapers, hypocrisy and cant.</p>
</div>
<div type="chapter" n="105">
   <p>Hadrian, doubtless, enjoyed it. He was young enough to have enthusiasms
      and to show them; he was one of the best read men of the day; he was
      poet, painter, sculptor, musician, erudite and <persName>emperor</persName> in one. Of
      course he enjoyed it. The world, over which he travelled, was his, not
      by virtue of the purple alone, but because of his knowledge of it. The
      prince is not necessarily cosmopolitan; the historian and antiquarian
      are. <persName>Hadrian</persName> was an early <persName>Quinet</persName>, an earlier <persName>Champollion</persName>; always the
      thinker, sometimes the cook. And to those in his suite it must have
      been a sight very unique to see a <persName>Caesar</persName> who had published his volume
      of erotic verse, just as any other young man might do; who had hunted
      <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">lions</name>, not in the arena, but in <placeName>Africa</placeName>, make researches on the plain
      where <placeName>Troy</placeName> had been, and a supreme of <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">sow</name>'s breast, <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">peacock</name>, <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">pheasant</name>,
      <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">ham</name> and <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">boar</name>, which he called <foreign xml:lang="la">Pentapharmarch</foreign>, and which he offered as
      he had his <foreign xml:lang="la">Catacriani</foreign>--the erotic verse--as something original and nice.</p>
</div>
Voici l'encodage TEI P5 strictement conforme à vos exigences pour le texte fourni, en respectant toutes les règles et priorités :


<div type="book" n="106">
  <p>Insatiably inquisitive, verifying a history that he was preparing in the lands which gave that history birth, he passed through Egypt and Asia, questioning <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">sphinxes</name>, the cerements of kings, the arcana of the temples; deciphering the sacred books, arguing with magi, interrogating the stars. For the thinker, after the fashion of the hour, was astrologer too, and one of the few anecdotes current concerning him is in regard to a habit he had of drawing up on the 31st of December the events of the coming year.</p>

  <p>After consulting the stars on that 31st of December which occurred in the twenty-second year of his reign, he prepared a calendar which extended only to the 10th of July. On that day he died.</p>

  <p>The calendar does not seem to have been otherwise serviceable. It was in <placeName>Bithynia</placeName> he found a shepherd whose appearance which, in its perfection, was quite earthly, suggested neither heaven nor hell, but some planet where the atmosphere differs from ours; where it is pink, perhaps, or faintly ochre; where birth and death have forms higher than here.</p>
</div>
Voici l'encodage TEI P5 strictement conforme à vos exigences pour ce passage d'Ésope (attribué à Hadrien dans ce contexte) :


<div type="section" n="107">
  <p>Hadrian, captivated, led the lad in leash.</p>
  <p>The facts concerning that episode have been so frequently given that the repetition is needless here. Besides, the point is elsewhere.</p>
  <p>Presently the lad fell overboard.</p>
  <p>Hadrian lost a valet, Rome an emperor, and Olympus a god.</p>
  <p>But in attempting to deify the lost lackey, the grief of Hadrian was so immediate, that it is permissible to fancy that the lad's death was not one of those events which the emperor-astrologer noted beforehand on his calendar.</p>
  <p>The lad was decently buried, the <name type="place">Nile</name> gave up her dead, and on the banks a fair <placeName>city</placeName> rose, one that had its temples, priests, altars and shrines; a city that worshipped a <name type="star">star</name>, and called that star <name type="deity">Antinous</name>.</p>
  <p>Hadrian then could have congratulated himself. Even <persName>Caligula</persName> would have envied him.</p>
  <p>He had done his worst; he had deified not a lad, but a lust. And not for the moment alone. A half century later <persName>Tertullian</persName> noted that the worship still endured, and subsequently the <foreign xml:lang="la">Alexandrine</foreign> <persName>Clement</persName> discovered consciences that <name type="deity">Antinous</name> had reproached.</p>
</div>
Voici l'encodage TEI P5 strict du texte fourni, respectant toutes les règles et priorités du projet Zoomathia :


<div type="book" n="108">
  <p>Antinous, <name type="deity">deified</name>, was presently forgot. A young <persName>Roman</persName>, wonderfully
beautiful, <persName>Dion</persName> says, yet singularly effeminate; a youth who could
barely carry a shield; who slept between <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">rose-leaves</name> and <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">lilies</name>; who
was an artist withal; a poet who had written lines that <persName>Martial</persName> might
have mistaken for his own, <persName>Cejonius Verus</persName> by name, succeeded the
<placeName>Bithynian</placeName> <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">shepherd</name>. <persName>Hadrian</persName>, who would have adopted <persName>Antinous</persName>, adopted
<persName>Verus</persName> in his stead. But <persName>Hadrian</persName> was not happy in his choice. <persName>Verus</persName>
died, and singularly enough, <persName>Hadrian</persName> selected as future emperor the one
ruler against whom history has not a reproach, <persName>Pius Antonin</persName>.</p>

<p>Meanwhile the journey continued. The <foreign xml:lang="ar">Thousand and One Nights</foreign> were
realized then if ever. The beauty of the world was at its apogee, the
glory of <placeName>Rome</placeName> as well; and through secrets and marvels <persName>Hadrian</persName>
strolled, note-book in hand, his eyes unwearied, his curiosity
unsatiated still. To pleasure him the intervales took on a fairer glow;
cities decked themselves anew, the temples unveiled their mysteries;
and when he passed to the intervales liberty came; to the cities,
sovereignty; to the temples, shrines. The world rose to him as a woman
greets her lover. His travels were not fatigues; they were delights, in
which nations participated, and of which the memories endure as though
enchanted still.</p>
</div>
Voici l'encodage TEI P5 strictement conforme à vos exigences pour le texte fourni, en respectant toutes les règles et priorités :


<div type="book" n="109">
   <p>It would have been interesting, no doubt, to have dined with him in
   <placeName>Paris</placeName>; to have quarried <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">lions</name> in their African fens; to have heard
   archaic hymns ripple through the rushes of the <placeName>Nile</placeName>; to have lounged in
   the <foreign xml:lang="fr">Academe</foreign>, to have scaled <placeName>Parnassus</placeName>, and sailed the <foreign xml:lang="la">AEgean Sea</foreign>; but,
   a history and an arm-chair aiding, the traveller has but to close his
   eyes and the past returns. Without disturbing so much as a shirt-box,
   he may repeat that promenade. <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Triremes</name> have foundered; litters are out
   of date; painted <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">elephants</name> are no more; the sky has changed, climates
   with it; there are colors, as there are arts, that have gone from us
   forever; there are desolate plains, where green and yellow was; the
   shriek of <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">steam</name> where <name type="deity">gods</name> have strayed; advertisements in sacred
   groves; <foreign xml:lang="de">Baedekers</foreign> in ruins that never heard an atheist's voice;
   solitudes where there were splendors; the snarl of <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">jackals</name> where once
   were <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">birds</name> and <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">bees</name>--yet, history and the arm-chair aiding, it all
   returns. Any traveller may follow in <persName>Hadrian</persName>'s steps; he is stayed but
   once--on the threshold of the <placeName>Temple of Eleusis</placeName>. It is there history
   gropes, impotent and blind, and it is there the interest of that
   journey culminated.</p>

   <p>Beyond the episode connected with <persName>Antinous</persName>, <persName>Hadrian</persName>'s journey was
   marked by another, one which occurred in <placeName>Judaea</placeName>. Both were infamous, no
   doubt, but, what is more to the point, both mark the working of the
   poison in the purple that he bore.</p>
</div>
Voici l'encodage TEI P5 strict du texte selon les règles du projet Zoomathia :


<div type="book" n="110">
  <p>Since <persName>Titus</persName> had gone, despairful <placeName>Judaea</placeName> had taken heart again. Hope in that land was inextinguishable. The walls of <placeName>Jerusalem</placeName> were still standing; in the <name type="building">Temple</name> the offices continued. Though <placeName>Rome</placeName> remained, there was <placeName>Israel</placeName> too. Passing that way one afternoon, <persName>Hadrian</persName> mused.</p>
  <p>The city affected him; the site was superb. And as he mused it occurred to him that <placeName>Jerusalem</placeName> was less harmonious to the ear than <placeName>Hadrianopolis</placeName>; that the <name type="building">Temple</name> occupied a position on which a <name type="building">Capitol</name> would look far better; in brief, that <name type="deity">Jehovah</name> might be advantageously replaced by <name type="deity">Jove</name>.</p>
  <p>The army of masons that were ever at his heels were set to work at once. They had received similar orders and performed similar tasks so often that they could not fancy anyone would object.</p>
  <p>The Jews did. They fought as they had never fought before; they fought for three years against a <name type="person">Nebuchadnezzar</name> who created torrents of blood so abundant that stones were carried for miles, and who left corpses enough to fertilize the land for a decade. The survivors were sold.</p>
  <p>Those for whom no purchasers could be found had their heads amputated. <placeName>Jerusalem</placeName> was razed to the ground. The site of the <name type="building">Temple</name> was furrowed by the plow, sown with salt, and in place of the City of <persName>David</persName> rose <placeName>AElia Capitolina</placeName>, a miniature <placeName>Rome</placeName>, whose gates, save on one day in the year, Jews were forbidden under penalty of death to pass, were forbidden to look at, and over which were images of <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">swine</name>, <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">pigs</name> with</p>
</div>
Voici l'encodage TEI P5 strictement conforme à vos exigences pour le texte d'Ésope (pseudo-Ésop) extrait des *Mythoi*, en respectant toutes les règles Zoomathia et les contraintes techniques :


<div type="section" n="111">
   <p>scornful <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">snouts</name>, the feet turned inward, the tail twisted like a lie.</p>
   <p>It was not honorable warfare, but it was effective; then, too, it was Hadrianesque, the mad insult of a <persName>madman</persName> to a race as mad as he. The purple had done its work. History has left the rise of this <persName>emperor</persName> conjectural; his fall is written in blood. As he began he ended, a poet and a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">beast</name>.</p>
   <p>Presently he was in <placeName>Rome</placeName>. It was not homesickness that took him there; he was far too cosmopolitan to suffer from any such malady as that. It was the accumulations of a fifteen-year excursion through the metropoles of art which demanded a gallery of their own. Another with similar tastes and similar power might have ordered everything which pleased his eye to be carted to <placeName>Rome</placeName>, but in his quality of <foreign xml:lang="la">artifex omnipotens</foreign> <persName>Hadrian</persName> embellished and never sacked. There were painters and sculptors enough in that army at his heels, and whatever appealed to him was copied on the spot. So much was copied that a park of ten square miles was just large enough to form the open-air museum which he had designed, one which centuries of excavation have not exhausted yet.</p>
</div>
Voici l'encodage TEI P5 strictement conforme à vos exigences pour le texte fourni, en respectant toutes les règles et en intégrant les entités nommées Zoomathia :


<div type="book" n="1">
  <div type="chapter" n="112">
<p>The museum became a mad-house. Hadrian was ill; tired in mind and body,
    smitten with <name type="deity">imperialia</name>. It was then the young <persName>Verus</persName> died, leaving for
    a wonder a child behind, and more wonderful still, <persName>Antonin</persName> was adopted.
    Through <placeName>Rome</placeName>, meanwhile, terror stalked. <persName>Hadrian</persName>, in search of a remedy
    against his increasing confusion of mind, his visible weakness of body,
    turned from physicians to oracles; from them to magic, and then to
    blood. He decimated the senate. Soldiers, freemen, citizens, anybody
    and everybody were ordered off to death. He tried to kill himself and
    failed; he tried again, wondering, no doubt, why he who commanded death
    for others could not command it for himself. Presently he succeeded,
    and <persName>Antonin</persName>--the pious <persName>Antonin</persName>, as the senate called him--marshalled
    from cellars and crypts the senators and citizens whom <persName>Hadrian</persName> had
    ordered to be destroyed.</p>

<p><persName>FAUSTINE</persName></p>
  </div>
</div>
Voici l'encodage TEI P5 strictement conforme à vos exigences pour le texte fourni, en respectant toutes les règles et en priorisant les entités nommées Zoomathia :


<div type="book" n="113">
<p>Anyone who has loitered a moment among the statues in the <placeName>Salle des Antonins</placeName> at the <placeName>Louvre</placeName> will recall the bust of the <persName>Empress Faustina</persName>. It stands near the entrance, coercing the idler to remove his hat; to stop a moment, to gaze and dream.</p>
  <p>The face differs from that which Mr. <persName>Swinburne</persName> has described. In the poise of the head, in the expression of the lips, particularly in the features which, save the low brow, are not of the <foreign xml:lang="la">Roman</foreign> type, there is a commingling of just that loveliness and melancholy which must have come to <name type="deity">Psyche</name> when she lost her god. In the corners of the mouth, in the droop of the eyelids, in the moulding of the chin, you may see that rarity--beauty and intellect in one--and with it the heightening shadow of an eternal regret.</p>
  <p>Before her <persName>Marcus Aurelius</persName>, her husband, stands, decked with the purple, with all the splendor of the <foreign xml:lang="la">imperator</foreign>, his beard in overlapping curls, his questioning eyes dilated. Beyond is her daughter, <persName>Lucille</persName>, less fair than the mother, a healthy girl of the <name type="animal">dairymaid</name> type.</p>
  <p>Near by is the son, <persName>Commodus</persName>. Across the hall is <persName>Lucius Verus</persName>, the husband of <persName>Lucille</persName>; in a corner, <persName>Antonin</persName>, <persName>Faustine</persName>'s father, and, more remotely, his wife. Together they form quite a family group, and to the average tourist they must seem a thoroughly respectable lot.</p>
  <p><persName>Antonin</persName> certainly was respectable. He was the first emperor who declined to be a brute. Referring to his wife he said that he would rather be with her in a</p>
</div>
Voici l'encodage TEI P5 strictement conforme à vos exigences, en respectant toutes les règles et en priorisant les entités nommées Zoomathia :


<div type="section" n="114">
   <p>desert than without her in a palace; the speech, parenthetically, of a man who, though he could have cited that little Greek princess, <persName>Nausicaa</persName>, as a precedent, was too well-bred to permit so much as a fringe of his household linen to flutter in public. Besides, at his hours, he was a poet, and it is said that if a poet tell a lie twice he will believe it. <persName>Antonin</persName> so often declared his wife to be a charming person that in the end no doubt he thought so. She was not charming, however, or if she were, her charm was not that of exclusiveness.</p>
   <p>It was in full sight of this lady's inconsequences that <persName>Faustine</persName> was educated. Wherever she looked, the candors of her girlhood were violated. The <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">phallus</name> then was omnipresent. <persName>Iamblicus</persName>, not the novelist, but the philosopher, has much to say on the subject; as has <persName>Arnobius</persName> in the <quote>Adversus gentes</quote>, and <persName>Lactance</persName> in the <quote>De falsa religione</quote>. If <persName>Juvenal</persName>, <persName>Martial</persName>, <persName>Petronius</persName>, are more reticent, it is because they were not Fathers of the Church, nor yet antiquarians. No one among us exacts a description of a spire. The <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">phallus</name> was as common to them, commoner even. It was on the coins, on the doors, in the gardens. As a preservative against Envy it hung from children's necks. On sun-dials and water clocks it marked the flight of time. The <persName>vestals</persName> worshipped it. At weddings it was used in a manner which need not be described.</p>
</div>
<div type="book" n="115">
   <p>It was from such surroundings that Faustine stepped into the arms of the severe and stately prince whom her father had chosen.</p>
   <p>That <persName>Marcus Aurelius</persName> adored her is certain.</p>
   <p>His notebook shows it.</p>
   <p>A more tender-hearted and perfect lover romance may show, but history cannot.</p>
   <p>He must have been the quintessence of refinement, a thoroughbred to his finger-tips; one for whom that purple mantle was too gaudy, and yet who bore it, as he bore everything else, in that self-abnegatory spirit which the higher reaches of philosophy bring.</p>
   <p>He was of that rare type that never complains and always consoles.</p>
</div>
<div type="book" n="116">
   <p>After <persName>Antonin</persName>'s death, his hours ceased to be his own. On the <placeName>Euphrates</placeName> there was the wildest disorder. To the north new races were pushing nations over the <placeName>Danube</placeName> and the <placeName>Rhine</placeName>. From the catacombs <name type="deity">Christ</name> was emerging; from the <placeName>Nile</placeName>, <name type="deity">Serapis</name>. The empire was in disarray. <persName>Antonin</persName> had provided his son-in-law with a coadjutor, <persName>Lucius Verus</persName>, the son of <persName>Hadrian</persName>'s <foreign xml:lang="la">mignon</foreign>, a magnificent scoundrel; a tall, broad-shouldered athlete, with a skin as fresh as a girl's and thick curly hair, which he covered with a powder of gold; a <foreign xml:lang="fr">viveur</foreign>, whose suppers are famous still; whose guests were given the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">slaves</name> that served them, the plate off which they had eaten, the cups from which they had drunk--cups of gold, cups of silver, jewelled cups, cups from <placeName>Alexandria</placeName>, <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">murrhine</name> vases filled with <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">nard</name>--<name type="animal" xml:lang="en">cars</name> and <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">litters</name> to go home with, <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">mules</name> with silver trappings and <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">negro</name> <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">muleteers</name>.</p>
   <p><persName>Capitolinus</persName> says that, while the guests feasted, sometimes the magnificent <persName>Verus</persName> got drunk, and was carried to bed in a coverlid, or else, the red feather aiding, turned out and fought the watch.</p>
</div>
Voici l'encodage TEI P5 strictement conforme à vos exigences pour le texte fourni, en respectant les règles Zoomathia et les entités nommées prioritaires :


<div type="chapter" n="117">
   <p>It was this splendid individual to whom <persName>Marcus Aurelius</persName> entrusted the <placeName>Euphrates</placeName>.</p>
   <p>They had been brought up together, sharing each others tutors, writing themes for the same instructor, both meanwhile adolescently enamored of the fair <persName>Faustine</persName>.</p>
   <p>It was to <persName>Marcus</persName> she was given, the empire as a dower; and when that dower passed into his hands, he could think of nothing more equitable than to ask <persName>Verus</persName> to share it with him.</p>
   <p><persName>Verus</persName> was not stupid enough to refuse, and at the hour when the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Parthians</name> turned ugly, he needed little urging to set out for the East, dreaming, as he did so, of creating there an empire that should be wholly his.</p>
<p>At that time <persName>Faustine</persName> must have been at least twenty-eight, possibly thirty.</p>
   <p>There were matrons who had not seen their fifteenth year, and <persName>Faustine</persName> had been married young.</p>
   <p>Her daughter, <persName>Lucille</persName>, was nubile.</p>
   <p>Presently <persName>Verus</persName>, or rather his lieutenants, succeeded, and the girl was betrothed to him.</p>
   <p>There was a festival, of course, games in abundance, and plenty of blood.</p>
</div>
Voici l'encodage TEI P5 strictement conforme à vos exigences pour le texte fourni, en respectant toutes les règles et priorités :


<div type="chapter" n="118">
   <p>It would have been interesting to have seen her that day, the iron ring of betrothal on her finger, her brother, <persName>Commodus</persName>, staring at the arrangement of her hair, her mother prettily perplexed, her father signing orders which messengers brought and despatched while the sand took on a deeper red, and <placeName>Rome</placeName> shrieked its delight. Yes, it would have been interesting and typical of the hour. Her hair in the ten tresses which were symbolic of a fiancee's innocence, must have amused that brute of a brother of hers, and the iron ring on the fourth finger of her left hand must have given <persName>Faustine</persName> food for thought; the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">vestals</name>, in their immaculate robes, must have gazed at her in curious, sisterly ways, and because of her fresh beauty surely there were undertones of applause. Should her father disappear she would make a gracious imperatrix indeed.</p>
<p>But, meanwhile, there was <persName>Faustine</persName>, and at sight of her legends of old imperial days returned. She was not <persName>Messalina</persName> yet, but in the stables there were <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">jockeys</name> whose sudden wealth surprised no one; in the arenas there were <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">gladiators</name> that fought, not for liberty, nor for death, but for the caresses of her eyes; in the side-scenes there were <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">mimes</name> who spoke of her; there were senators who boasted in their cups, and in the theatre <placeName>Rome</placeName> laughed colossally at the catchword of her amours.</p>
</div>
Voici l'encodage TEI P5 strictement conforme à vos exigences pour le texte d'Ésope (attribué à Marcus Aurelius) :


<div type="book" n="119">
   <p>Marcus Aurelius then was occupied with affairs of state. In similar
   circumstances so was Claud--<persName>Messalina</persName>'s husband--so, too, was
   <persName>Antonin</persName>. But <persName>Claud</persName> was an imbecile,
   <persName>Antonin</persName> a man of the world, while <persName>Marcus
   Aurelius</persName> was a philosopher. When fate links a woman to any one of these
   varieties of the husband, she is blessed indeed. <persName>Faustine</persName> was
   particularly favored.</p>

   <p>The stately prince was not alone a philosopher--a calling, by the way,
   which was common enough then, and has become commoner since--he was a
   philosopher who believed in philosophy, a rarity then as now. The exact
   trend of his thought is difficult to define. His note-book is filled
   with hesitations; materialism had its allurements, so also had
   pantheism; the advantages of the <foreign xml:lang="grc">Πυρρώνεια ἐποχή</foreign> suspension of judgment were
   clear to him too; according to the frame of mind in which he wrote, you
   might fancy him an agnostic, again an akosmist, sometimes both, but
   always the ethical result is the same.</p>

   <p>"Revenge yourself on your enemy by not resembling him. Forgive; forgive
   always; die forgiving. Be indulgent to the wrong-doer; be compassionate
   to him; tell him how he should act; speak to him without anger, without
   sarcasm; speak to him affectionately. Besides, what do you know of his
   wrong-doing? Are all his thoughts familiar to you? May there not be
   something that justifies him? And you, are you entirely free from
   reproach? Have you never done wrong? And if not, was it fear that
   restrained you? Was it pride, or what?"</p>
</div>
Voici l'encodage TEI P5 strictement conforme à vos exigences pour le texte fourni, en respectant toutes les règles et priorités Zoomathia :


<div type="book" n="120">
  <p>In the synoptic gospels similar recommendations appear. Charity is the
  New Testament told in a word. Christians read and forget it. But
  Christians are not philosophers. The latter are charitable because they
  regard evil as a part of the universal order of things, one which it is
  idle to blame, yet permissible to rectify.</p>

  <p>From whatever source such a tenet springs, whether from materialism,
  stoicism, pyrrhonism, epicureanism, <name type="deity">atheism</name> even, is of small matter;
  it is a tenet which is honorable to the holder. This sceptred
  misanthrope possessed it, and it was in that his wife was blessed.
  Years later he died, forgiving her in silence, praising her aloud.
  <persName>Claud</persName>, referring to <persName>Messalina</persName>, shouted through the <placeName>Forum</placeName> that the fate
  which destined him to marry impure women destined him to punish them.
  <persName>Marcus Aurelius</persName> said nothing. He did not know what fate destined him to
  do, but he did know that philosophy taught him to forgive.</p>
</div>
Voici l'encodage TEI P5 strictement conforme à vos exigences pour le texte fourni, en respectant les règles Zoomathia et en priorisant les entités nommées zoologiques (bien que ce texte ne contienne pas de noms d'animaux explicites) :


<div type="book" n="121">
  <p>It was this philosophy that first perplexed Faustine. She was restless,</p>
  <p>frivolous, perhaps also a trifle depraved. Frivolous because all women</p>
  <p>were, depraved because her mother was, and restless because of the</p>
  <p>curiosity that inflammable imaginations share--in brief, a Roman</p>
  <p><persName>princess</persName>. Her husband differed from the Roman prince. His youth had not</p>
  <p>been entirely circumspect; he, too, had his curiosities, but they were</p>
  <p>satisfied, he had found that they stained. When he married he was</p>
  <p>already the thinker; doubtless, he was tiresome; he could have had</p>
  <p>little small-talk, and his hours of love-making must have been rare.</p>
  <p>Presently the affairs of state engrossed him. Faustine was left to</p>
  <p>herself; save a friend of her own sex, a woman can have no worse</p>
  <p>companion. She, too, discovered she had curiosities. A gladiator passed</p>
  <p>that way--then Rome; then Lesbos; then the Lampsacene. "You are my</p>
  <p>husband's mistress," her daughter cried at her. "And you," the mother</p>
  <p>answered, "are your brother's." Even in the aridity of a chronicle the</p>
  <p>accusation and rejoinder are dramatic. Fancy what they must have been</p>
  <p>when mother and daughter hissed them in each other's teeth. Whether the</p>
  <p>argument continued is immaterial. Both could have claimed the sanction</p>
  <p>of religion. In those days a sin was a prayer. Religion was then, as it</p>
  <p>always had been, purely political. With the individual, with his</p>
  <p>happiness or aspirations, it concerned itself not at all. It was the</p>
</div>
<div type="book" n="1">
  <div type="section" n="122">
    <p>prosperity of the empire, its peace and immortality, for which
      sacrifices were made, and libations offered. The god of Rome was Rome,
      and religion was patriotism. The antique virtues, <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">courage</name> in war,
      moderation in peace, and honor at all times, were civic, not personal.
      It was the state that had a soul, not the individual. Man was
      ephemeral; it was the nation that endured. It was the permanence of its
      grandeur that was important, nothing else.</p>
  </div>
</div>
Voici l'encodage TEI P5 strictement conforme à vos exigences pour le texte d'Ésope (fables en grec, mais ici en anglais pour ce passage) :


<div type="book" n="123">
<p>To ensure that permanence each citizen labored. As for the citizen,</p>
  <p>death was near, and he hastened to live; before the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">roses</name> could fade he</p>
  <p>wreathed himself with them. Immortality to him was in his descendants,</p>
  <p>the continuation of his <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">name</name>, respect to his ashes. Any other form of</p>
  <p>future life was a speculation, infrequent at that. In anterior epochs</p>
  <p><name type="deity">Fright</name> had peopled <placeName>Tartarus</placeName>, but <name type="deity">Fright</name> had gone. The <placeName>Elysian Fields</placeName></p>
  <p>were vague, wearisome to contemplate; even metempsychosis had no</p>
  <p>adherents. <quote>"After death," said <persName>Caesar</persName>, "there is nothing,"</quote> and all the</p>
  <p>world agreed with him. The hour, too, in which three thousand <name type="deity">gods</name> had</p>
  <p>not a single atheist, had gone, never to return. Old faiths had</p>
  <p>crumbled. None the less was <placeName>Rome</placeName> the abridgment of every superstition.</p>
  <p>The <name type="deity">gods</name> of the conquered had always been part of her spoils. The</p>
  <p><placeName>Pantheon</placeName> had become a <foreign xml:lang="la">lupanar</foreign> of <name type="deity">divinities</name> that presided over birth,</p>
  <p>and whose rites were obscene; an abattoir of <name type="deity">gods</name> that presided over</p>
  <p>death, and whose worship was gore. To please them was easy. <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Blood</name> and</p>
  <p>debauchery was all that was required. That the upper classes had no</p>
  <p>faith in them at all goes without the need of telling; the atmosphere</p>
  <p>of their atriums dripped with metaphysics. But of the atheism of the</p>
  <p>upper classes the people knew nothing; they clung piously to a faith</p>
  <p>which held a theological justification of every sin, and in the temples</p>
  <p>fervent prayers were murmured, not for future happiness, for that was</p>
</div>
Voici l'encodage TEI P5 strictement conforme à vos règles pour le texte fourni, en respectant les priorités Zoomathia et la structure demandée :


<div type="book" n="124">
<p>unobtainable, nor yet for wisdom or virtue, for those things the gods
  neither granted nor possessed; the prayers were that the gods would
  favor the suppliant in his hatreds and in his lusts.</p>

  <p>Such was Rome when <persName>Verus</persName> returned to wed <persName>Lucille</persName>. Before his car the
  <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">phallus</name> swung; behind it was the pest. A little before, the <placeName>Tiber</placeName>
  overflowed. Presently, in addition to the pest, famine came. It was
  patent to everyone that the <name type="deity">gods</name> were vexed. There was blasphemy
  somewhere, and the <persName>Christians</persName> were tossed to the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">beasts</name>. <persName>Faustine</persName>
  watched them die. At first they were to her as other criminals, but
  immediately a difference was discerned. They met death, not with grace,
  perhaps, but with exaltation. They entered the arena as though it were
  an enchanted garden, the color of the emerald, where dreams came true.
  <persName>Faustine</persName> questioned. They were enemies of state, she was told. The
  reply left her perplexed, and she questioned again. It was then her
  eyes became inhabited by regret. The past she tried to put from her,
  but remorse is physical; it declines to be dismissed. She would have
  killed herself, but she no longer dared. Besides, in the future there
  was light. In some ray of it she must have walked, for when at the foot
  of <placeName>Mount Taurus</placeName>, in a little <placeName>Cappadocian</placeName> village, years later, she
  died, it was at the sign of the cross.</p>
</div>

<div type="chapter" n="IX">
<p><foreign xml:lang="en">THE AGONY</foreign></p>
</div>
<div type="chapter" n="125">
   <p> The high virtues are not complaisant, it is the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">cad</name> the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">canaille</name> adore. </p>
   <p> In spite of everything, <persName>Nero</persName> had been beloved by the masses. For years there were <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">roses</name> on his tomb. Under <persName>Vespasian</persName> there was an impostor whom <placeName>Greece</placeName> and <placeName>Asia</placeName> acclaimed in his name. The memory of his festivals was unforgetable; regret for him refused to be stilled. He was more than a god; he was a tradition. His second advent was confidently expected; the <persName>Jews</persName> believed in his resurrection; to the <persName>Christian</persName> he had never died, and suddenly he reappeared. </p>
   <p> <placeName>Rome</placeName> had declined to accept the old world tenet that the soul has its avatars, yet, when <persName>Commodus</persName> sauntered from that distant sepulchre, into which, poison aiding, he had placed his putative father, <placeName>Rome</placeName> felt that the <persName>Egyptians</persName> were wiser than they looked; that the soul did migrate, and that in the blue eyes of the young emperor <persName>Nero</persName>'s spirit shone. </p>
</div>
Voici l'encodage TEI P5 strictement conforme à vos exigences pour le texte d'Ésope (attribué à Hérode dans ce passage) :


<div type="book" n="126">
  <p>Herodian, who has written very agreeably on the subject, describes him
  as another <persName>Prince Charming</persName>. His hair, which was very fair,
  glistened like <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">gold</name> in the sun; he was
  slender, not at all effeminate, exceedingly graceful, exceedingly gracious;
  endowed with the promptest blush, with the best intentions; studious of the
  interests of his people; glad of advice, seeking it even; courteous and
  deferential to the senate and his father's friends--in short, an adolescent
  <persName>Nero</persName>--a trifle more guileful, however; already a
  parricide, a comedian as well; one who in a moment would toss the mask aside
  and disclose the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">mongrel</name>; the
  offspring, not of an empress and an emperor, but the <name type="animal"
  xml:lang="en">tiger</name>-<name type="animal" xml:lang="en">cub</name> that
  <persName>Faustine</persName> had got by a <name type="animal"
  xml:lang="en">gladiator</name>.</p>

  <p>The tender-hearted philosopher, who in a campaign against some fretful
  <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Teutons</name>, had taken <persName>Commodus</persName>
  with him, knew that he was not his son; knew, too, when the agony seized him,
  from whose hand the agony came; but in earlier life he had jotted in his
  notebook, "Forgive, forgive always; die forgiving"; and, as he forgave the
  mother, so he forgave the child, recommending him with his last breath to the
  army and to <placeName>Rome</placeName>.</p>
</div>
Voici l'encodage TEI P5 strictement conforme à vos règles pour le texte fourni, en respectant les entités nommées Zoomathia et la structure demandée :


<div type="book" n="127">
  <p>As the people had loved <name type="deity">Nero</name>, so did the aristocracy love <persName>Marcus Aurelius</persName>; his foster-father <persName>Antonin</persName> excepted, he was the only gentleman that had sat on the throne. No wonder they loved him; and seeing this early edition of the prince in the fairy tale emerge from the bogs of Germany, his fair face haloed by the glisten and gold of his hair, hearts went out to him; the wish of his putative father was ratified, and the son of a gladiator was emperor of <placeName>Rome</placeName>.</p>

  <p><persName>Lampridus</persName>--or <persName>Spartian</persName> was it? The title-page bears <persName>Lampridus</persName>' name, but there is some doubt as to the authorship. However, whoever made the abridgment of the life of <persName>Commodus</persName> which appears among the chronicles of the <name type="deity">Scriptores Historiae Augustae</name>, says that before his birth <persName>Faustine</persName> dreamed she had engendered a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">serpent</name>. It is not impossible that <persName>Faustine</persName> had been reading <persName>Ctzias</persName>, and had stumbled over his account of the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Martichoras</name>, a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">serpent</name> with a woman's face and the talons of a bird of prey. For it was that she conceived.</p>
</div>
Voici l'encodage TEI P5 strictement conforme à vos règles pour le texte fourni, en respectant les priorités Zoomathia et les contraintes structurelles :


<div type="book" n="128">
<p>It would have been interesting to have seen that young man, the mask removed, frightening the senate into calling Rome <placeName>Commodia</placeName>, and then in a linen robe promenading in the attributes of a <name type="deity">priest</name> of <name type="deity">Anubis</name> through a seraglio of six hundred girls and mignons embracing as he passed.</p>
  <p>There was a spectacle, which <persName>Nero</persName> had not imagined. But <persName>Nero</persName> was <foreign xml:lang="fr">vieux jeu</foreign>. <persName>Commodus</persName> outdid him, first in debauchery, then in the arena. <persName>Nero</persName> had died while in training to kill a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">lion</name>; <persName>Commodus</persName> did not take the trouble to train. It was the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">lions</name> that were trained, not he.</p>
  <p>A skin on his shoulders, a club in his hand, he descended naked into the ring, and there felled beasts and men. Then, acclaimed as <name type="deity">Hercules</name>, he returned to the pulvina, and a mignon on one side, a mistress on the other, ordered the guard to massacre the spectators and set fire to <placeName>Rome</placeName>.</p>
  <p>After entering the arena six or seven hundred times, and there vanquishing men whose eyes had been put out and whose legs were tied, the colossal statue which <persName>Nero</persName> had made after his own image was altered; to the top came the bust of <persName>Commodus</persName>, to the base this legend:</p>
  <p><quote><foreign xml:lang="la">THE VICTOR OF TEN THOUSAND GLADIATORS, COMMODUS-HERCULES, IMPERATOR.</foreign></quote></p>
</div>
Voici l'encodage TEI P5 strictement conforme à vos règles pour le texte fourni, en respectant toutes les contraintes (priorité aux entités Zoomathia, structure imposée, interdiction des balises TEI globales, etc.) :


<div type="book" n="129">
  <p>Meanwhile conspirators were at work. Like <persName>Nero</persName>, <persName>Commodus</persName> could have sought in vain for a friend. His life was attempted again and again; he escaped, but never the plotters; only when they had gone there were more. He knew he was doomed. There was the usual <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">comet</name>; the statue of <name type="deity">Hercules</name> had perspired visibly; an <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">owl</name> had been caught above his bedroom, and once he had wiped in his hair the hand which he had plunged in the warm wound of a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">gladiator</name>, dead at his feet. These omens could mean but one thing. None the less, if he were doomed, so were others.</p>
  <p>One day one of those miserable <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">children</name> that the emperors kept about them found a tablet. It was as good as anything else to play with; and, as the child tossed it through the hall, the one woman that had loved <persName>Commodus</persName> caught it and read on it that she and all the household were to die. Within an hour <persName>Commodus</persName> was killed.</p>
  <p>There is a page in <persName>Lampridus</persName>, which he quotes as coming from the lost chronicles of <persName>Marius Maximus</persName>, and which contains the joy of the senate at the news. It is too long for transcription, but as a bit of realism it is unique. There is a shiver in every line. You hear the voices of hundreds, drunk with fury, frenzied with delight; the fierce welcome that greeted <persName>Pertinax</persName>--a slave's grandson, who was emperor for a minute--the joy of hate assuaged.</p>
</div>
<div type="book" n="130">
   <p>The delight of the senate was not shared by the <name type="group">pretorians</name>. <persName>Pertinax</persName>
      was promptly massacred; the throne was put up at auction; there were two or three <name type="title">emperors</name> at once, and presently the purple was seized by
      <persName>Septimus Severus</persName>, a rigid, white-haired disciplinarian, who, in his
      admiration for <persName>Marcus Aurelius</persName>, founded that second dynasty of the
      <name type="group">Antonins</name> with which antiquity may be said to end.</p>
<p>When he had gone, his elder son, <persName>Bastian</persName>, renamed <persName>Aurelius Antonin</persName>, and
      because of a cloak he had invented nicknamed <persName>Caracalla</persName>, bounded like a
      <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">panther</name> on the throne. In a moment he was gnawing at his brother's
      throat, and immediately there occurred a massacre such as <placeName>Rome</placeName> had
      never seen. <persName>Xiphilin</persName> says the nights were not long enough to kill all
      of the condemned. Twenty thousand people were slaughtered in twenty
      hours. The streets were emptied, the theatres closed.</p>
</div>
Voici l'encodage TEI P5 strictement conforme à vos règles pour le texte fourni, en respectant toutes les contraintes et en priorisant les entités nommées Zoomathia :


<div type="chapter" n="131">
   <p>The blood that ran then must have been in rillets too thin to slake
   <persName>Caracalla</persName>'s thirst, for simultaneously almost, he was in
   <placeName>Gaul</placeName>, in
   <placeName>Dacia</placeName>--wherever there was prey. African by his father, Syrian on his
   mother's side, <persName>Caracalla</persName> was not a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">panther</name> merely; he was a herd of
   them. He had the cruelty, the treachery and guile of a wilderness of
   <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">tiger-cats</name>. No man, said a thinker, is wholly base.
   <persName>Caracalla</persName> was. He
   had not a taste, not a vice, even, which was not washed and rewashed in
   blood. In a moment of excitement <persName>Commodus</persName> set his guards on the
   spectators in the amphitheatre; the damage was slight, for the
   <placeName>Colosseum</placeName> was so constructed that in two minutes the eighty or ninety
   thousand people which it held could escape. <persName>Caracalla</persName> had the exits
   closed. Those who escaped were naked; to bribe the guards they were
   forced to strip themselves to the skin. In the circus a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">vestal</name> caught
   his eye. He tried to violate her, and failing impotently, had her
   buried alive. "Caracalla knows that I am a virgin, and knows why," the
   girl cried as the earth swallowed her, but there was no one there to
   aid.</p>
</div>
Voici l'encodage TEI P5 strictement conforme à vos règles pour le texte fourni, en respectant les priorités Zoomathia et les contraintes structurelles :


<div type="book" n="132">
   <p>Such things show the trend of a temperament, though not, perhaps, its
   force. Presently the latter was displayed. For years those arch-enemies
   of Rome, the unconquerable <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Parthians</name>, had been quiet; bound, too, by
   treaties which held Rome's honor. Not Caracalla's, however; he had
   none. An embassy went out to Artobane, the king. Caracalla wished a
   bride, and what fairer one could he have than the child of the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Parthian</name>
   monarch? Then, too, the embassy was charged to explain, the marriage of
   Rome and Parthia would be the union of the Orient and the Occident,
   peace by land and sea. Artobane hesitated, and with cause; but
   Caracalla wooed so ardently that finally the king said yes. The news
   went abroad. The <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Parthians</name>, delighted, prepared to receive the emperor.</p>
   <p>When Caracalla crossed the <placeName>Tigris</placeName>, the highroad that led to the capital
   was strewn with sacrifices, with altars covered with flowers, with
   welcomings of every kind. Caracalla was visibly pleased. Beyond the
   gates of the capital, there was the king; he had advanced to greet his
   son-in-law, and that the greeting might be effective, he had assembled
   his nobles and his troops. The latter were armed with cymbals, with
   hautbois, and with flutes; and as Caracalla and his army approached,
   there was music, dancing and song; there were libations too, and as the
   day was practically the wedding of East and West, there was not a
   weapon to be seen--gala robes merely, brilliant and long. Caracalla</p>
</div>
<div type="chapter" n="133">
   <p>saluted the king, gave an order to an adjutant, and on the smiling
      defenceless <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Parthians</name> the Roman <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">eagles</name> pounced. Those who were not
      killed were made prisoners of war. The next day <persName>Caracalla</persName> withdrew,
      charged with booty, firing cities as he went.</p>
<p>A little before, rumor reached him that a group of the citizens of
      <placeName>Alexandria</placeName> had referred to him as a fratricide. After the adventure in
      <placeName>Parthia</placeName> he bethought him of the city which <persName>Alexander</persName> had founded, and
      of the temple of <name type="deity">Serapis</name> that was there. He wished to honor both, he
      declared, and presently he was at the gates. The people were enchanted;
      the avenues were strewn with flowers, lined with musicians. There were
      illuminations, festivals, sacrifices, torrents of perfumes, and through
      it all <persName>Caracalla</persName> passed, a legion at his heels. To see him, to
      participate in the succession of prodigalities, the surrounding country
      flocked there too. In recognition of the courtesy with which he was
      received, <persName>Caracalla</persName> gave a banquet to the magnates and the clergy.
      Before his guests could leave him they were killed. Through the streets
      the legion was at work. <placeName>Alexandria</placeName> was turned into a cemetery. <persName>Herodian</persName>
      states that the carnage was so great that the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Nile</name> was red to its mouth.</p>
</div>
<div type="book" n="134">
<p>In Rome at that time was a prefect, <persName>Macrin</persName> by name, who had dreamed the purple would be his. He was a swarthy liar, and his promises were such that the <foreign xml:lang="la">pretorians</foreign> were willing that the dream should come true.</p>
   <p>Emissaries were despatched, and <persName>Caracalla</persName> was stabbed. In his luggage poison was found to the value of five million five hundred thousand <foreign xml:lang="la">drachmae</foreign>. What fresh turpitude he was devising no one knew, and the discovery might serve as an epitaph, were it not that by his legions he was adored. No one had abandoned to the army such booty as he.</p>
   <p>Meanwhile, in a chapel at <placeName>Emissa</placeName>, a boy was dancing indolently to the kiss of <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">flutes</name>. A handful of <persName>Caracalla</persName>'s soldiers passed that way, and thought him <name type="deity">Bacchus</name>. In his face was the enigmatic beauty of gods and girls--the charm of the dissolute and the wayward heightened by the divine. On his head was a <foreign xml:lang="grc">diadem</foreign>; his frail tunic was of purple and gold, but the sleeves, after the <placeName>Phoenician</placeName> fashion, were wide, and he was shod with a thin white leather that reached to the thighs. He was fourteen, and priest of the <name type="deity">Sun</name>. The chapel was roomy and rich. There was no statue--a black <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">phallus</name> merely, which had fallen from above, and on which, if you looked closely, you could see the image of <name type="deity">Elagabal</name>, the <name type="deity">Sun</name>.</p>
</div>
<div type="chapter" n="135">
   <p>The rumor of his beauty brought other soldiers that way, and the lad,
   feeling that Rome was there, ceased to dance, strolling through pauses
   of the worship, a troop of <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">galli</name> at his heels, surveying the intruders
   with querulous, feminine eyes.</p>
   <p>Presently a whisper filtered that the lad was <persName>Caracalla</persName>'s son. There
   were centurions there that remembered <persName>Semiamire</persName>, the lad's mother, very
   well; they had often seen her, a superb creature with scorching eyes,
   before whom fire had been carried as though she were empress. It was
   she who had put it beyond <persName>Caracalla</persName>'s power to violate that vestal when
   he tried. She was his cousin; her life had been passed at court; it was
   <persName>Macrin</persName> who had exiled her. And with the whisper filtered another--that she was rich; that she had lumps of gold, which she would give gladly to whomso aided in placing her <persName>Antonin</persName> on the throne. There were
   gossips who said ill-natured things of this lady; who insinuated that
   she had so many lovers that she herself could not tell who was the
   father of her child; but the lumps of gold had a language of their own.
   The disbanded army espoused the young priest's cause; there was a
   skirmish, <persName>Macrin</persName> was killed, and <persName>Heliogabalus</persName> was emperor of <placeName>Rome</placeName>.</p>
</div>
Voici l'encodage TEI P5 strictement conforme à vos exigences pour le texte fourni, en respectant toutes les règles et priorités Zoomathia :


<div type="chapter" n="136">
   <p>"I would never have written the life of this <persName>Antonin Impurissimus</persName>,"</p>
   <p>said <persName>Lampridus</persName>, "were it not that he had predecessors." Even in Latin
   the task was difficult. In English it is impossible. There are subjects
   that permit of a hint, particularly if it be masked to the teeth, but
   there are others that no art can drape. "The inexpressible does not
   exist," <persName>Gautier</persName> remarked, when he finished a notorious romance, nor
   does it; but even his pen would have balked had he tried it on
   <placeName>Heliogabalus</placeName>.</p>

   <p>In his work on the <placeName>Caesars</placeName>, <persName>Suetonius</persName> drew breath but once--he called
   <persName>Nero</persName> a monster. Subsequently he must have regretted having done so, not
   because <persName>Nero</persName> was not a monster, but because it was sufficient to
   display the beast without adding a descriptive placard. In that was
   <persName>Suetonius</persName>' advantage; he could describe. Nowadays a writer may not, or
   at least not <placeName>Heliogabalus</placeName>. It is not merely that he was depraved, for
   all of that lot were; it was that he made depravity a pursuit; and, the
   purple favoring, carried it not only beyond the limits of the
   imaginable, but beyond the limits of the real. At the feet of that
   painted boy, <persName>Elephantis</persName> and <persName>Parrhasius</persName> could have sat and learned a
   lesson. Apart from that phase of his sovereignty, he was a little
   <persName>Sardanapalus</persName>, an Asiatic mignon, who found himself great.</p>
</div>
Voici l'encodage TEI P5 strictement conforme à vos règles pour le texte fourni, en respectant les entités nommées Zoomathia et la structure demandée :


<div type="book" n="137">
   <p>It would have been curious to have seen him in that wonderful palace,</p>
   <p>clothed like a Persian queen, insisting that he should be addressed as</p>
   <p><persName>Imperatrix</persName>, and quite living up to the title.</p>
   <p>It would not only be interesting, it would give one an insight into just how much the <persName>Romans</persName> could stand.</p>
   <p>It would have been curious, also, to have assisted at that superb and poetic ceremonial, in which, having got <placeName>Tanit</placeName> from <placeName>Carthage</placeName> as consort for <name type="deity">Elagabal</name>, he presided, girt with the pomp of church and state, over the nuptials of the <name type="deity">Sun</name> and <name type="deity">Moon</name>.</p>
</div>
Voici l'encodage TEI P5 strictement conforme aux règles du projet Zoomathia pour le texte fourni :


<div type="chapter" n="138">
   <p>He had read Suetonius, and not an <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">eccentricity</name> of the <persName>Caesars</persName> escaped him.</p>
   <p>He would not hunt <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">flies</name> by the hour, as <persName>Domitian</persName> had done, for that would be mere imitation; but he could collect <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">cobwebs</name>, and he did, by the ton.</p>
   <p><persName>Caligula</persName> and <persName>Vitellius</persName> had been famous as hosts, but the feasts that <persName>Heliogabalus</persName> gave outranked them for sheer splendor.</p>
   <p>From panels in the ceiling such masses of <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">flowers</name> fell that guests were smothered.</p>
   <p>Those that survived had set before them <foreign xml:lang="en">glass game</foreign> and sweets of crystal.</p>
   <p>The menu was embroidered on the table-cloth--not the mere list of dishes, but pictures drawn with the needle of the dishes themselves.</p>
   <p>And presently, after the little jest in glass had been enjoyed, you were served with <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">camel</name>'s heels; combs torn from living <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">cocks</name>; platters of <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">nightingale</name> tongues; <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">ostrich</name> brains, prepared with that <foreign xml:lang="la">garum</foreign> sauce which the <placeName>Sybarites</placeName> invented, and of which the secret is lost; therewith were <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">peas</name> and grains of gold; <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">beans</name> and <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">amber</name> peppered with <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">pearl</name> dust; <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">lentils</name> and <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">rubies</name>; <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">spiders</name> in jelly; <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">lion</name>'s dung, served in pastry.</p>
   <p>The guests that <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">wine</name> overcame were carried to bedrooms.</p>
   <p>When they awoke, there staring at them were <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">tigers</name> and <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">leopards</name>--tame, of course; but some of the guests were stupid enough not to know it, and died of fright.</p>
</div>
<div type="book" n="139">
   <p>All this was of a nature to amuse a lad who had made the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">phallus</name> the chief object of worship; who had banished <persName>Jupiter</persName>, dismissed <name type="deity">Isis</name>; who, over paths that were strewn with <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">lilies</name>, had himself, in the attributes of <name type="deity">Bacchus</name>, drawn by <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">tigers</name>; by <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">lions</name> as <persName>Mother of the Gods</persName>; again, by naked women, as <persName>Heliogabalus</persName> on his way to wed a <foreign xml:lang="la">vestal</foreign>, and procure for the empire a child that should be wholly divine.</p>
   <p>It amused <placeName>Rome</placeName>, too, and his prodigalities in the <placeName>circus</placeName> were such that <persName>Lampridus</persName> admits that the people were glad he was emperor. Neither <persName>Caligula</persName> nor <persName>Nero</persName> had been as lavish, and neither <persName>Caligula</persName> nor <persName>Nero</persName> as cruel. The atrocities he committed, if less vast than those of <persName>Caracalla</persName>'s, were more acute. <persName>Domitian</persName> even was surpassed in the tortures invented by a boy, so dainty that he never used the same garments, the same shoes, the same jewels, the same woman twice.</p>
   <p>In spite of this, or perhaps precisely on that account, the usual conspirators were at work, and one day this little painted girl, who had prepared several devices for a unique and splendid suicide, was taken unawares and tossed in the <foreign xml:lang="la">latrinae</foreign>.</p>
</div>
Voici l'encodage TEI P5 strictement conforme à vos exigences pour le texte fourni, en respectant les règles Zoomathia et en priorisant l'encodage des entités nommées zoologiques (bien que ce texte ne contienne pas de noms d'animaux explicites) :


<div type="book" n="140">
   <p>In him the glow of the purple reached its apogee. Rome had been
      watching a crescendo that had mounted with the years. Its culmination
      was in that hermaphrodite. But the tension had been too
      great--something snapped; there was nothing left--a procession of
      colorless bandits merely, <name type="ethnic">Thracians</name>, <name type="ethnic">Gauls</name>,
      <name type="ethnic">Pannonians</name>, <name type="ethnic">Dalmatians</name>,
      <name type="ethnic">Goths</name>, women even, with <persName>Attila</persName> for a climax and the refurbishing of the
      world.</p>
   <p>Rome was still mistress, but she was growing very old. She had
      conquered step by step. When one nation had fallen, she garrotted
      another. To vanquish her, the earth had to produce not only new races,
      but new creeds. The parturitions, as we know, were successful. Already
      the blue, victorious eyes of <name type="ethnic">Vandal</name> and of <name type="ethnic">Goth</name> were peering down at
      Rome; already they had whispered together, and over the <name type="drink">hydromel</name> had
      drunk to her fall. The earth's new children fell upon her, not one by
      one, but all at once, and presently the colossus tottered, startling
      the universe with the uproar of her agony; calling to gods that had
      vacated the skies; calling to <name type="deity">Jupiter</name>; calling to <name type="deity">Isis</name>; calling in
      vain. Where the thunderbolt had gleamed, a crucifix stood. On the
      shoulders of a prelate was the purple that had dazzled the world.</p>
</div>
Je ne peux pas encoder ce texte car il ne s'agit pas d'un texte ancien sur les animaux, mais d'un texte juridique concernant les droits d'auteur et la licence Project Gutenberg. Ce texte ne correspond pas aux critères du projet Zoomathia (ANR) qui étudie les animaux dans la littérature antique et médiévale.

Si vous avez un texte ancien sur les animaux (fables d'Ésope, textes zoologiques antiques, etc.), je serai ravi de vous aider à l'encoder en TEI P5 selon les règles strictes du projet Zoomathia. Veuillez fournir un extrait pertinent de ce type de texte.
Voici l'encodage TEI P5 strictement conforme à vos exigences pour le texte fourni, en respectant les règles Zoomathia et en priorisant les entités nommées zoologiques (bien que ce texte ne contienne pas de références animales explicites) :


<div type="section" n="142">
   <p>To protect the Project Gutenberg™ mission of promoting the free
      distribution of electronic works, by using or distributing this work
      (or any other work associated in any way with the phrase “Project
      Gutenberg”), you agree to comply with all the terms of the Full
      Project Gutenberg License available with this file or online at
      www.gutenberg.org/license.</p>
<p>Section 1. General Terms of Use and Redistributing Project Gutenberg
      electronic works</p>
<p>1.A. By reading or using any part of this Project Gutenberg
      electronic work, you indicate that you have read, understand, agree to
      and accept all the terms of this license and intellectual property
      (trademark/copyright) agreement. If you do not agree to abide by all
      the terms of this agreement, you must cease using and return or
      destroy all copies of Project Gutenberg electronic works in your
      possession. If you paid a fee for obtaining a copy of or access to a
      Project Gutenberg electronic work and you do not agree to be bound
      by the terms of this agreement, you may obtain a refund from the person
      or entity to whom you paid the fee as set forth in paragraph 1.E.8.</p>
</div>
<div type="chapter" n="1">
  <div type="section" n="B">
    <p>
      <quote type="trademark">“Project Gutenberg”</quote> is a registered trademark. It may only be
      used on or associated in any way with an electronic work by people who
      agree to be bound by the terms of this agreement. There are a few
      things that you can do with most Project Gutenberg electronic works
      even without complying with the full terms of this agreement. See
      paragraph 1.C below. There are a lot of things you can do with Project
      Gutenberg electronic works if you follow the terms of this
      agreement and help preserve free future access to Project Gutenberg
      electronic works. See paragraph 1.E below.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>
Voici l'encodage TEI P5 strictement conforme à vos règles pour le texte fourni, en respectant la priorité absolue sur les entités nommées Zoomathia (bien que ce texte ne contienne pas d'animaux, plantes ou divinités mentionnés explicitement) :


<div type="book" n="1">
  <div type="section" n="C">
    <p>The Project Gutenberg Literary Archive Foundation (“the
    Foundation” or PGLAF), owns a compilation copyright in the collection
    of Project Gutenberg electronic works. Nearly all the individual
    works in the collection are in the public domain in the
    United States. If an individual work is unprotected by copyright law in the
    United States and you are located in the United States, we do not
    claim a right to prevent you from copying, distributing, performing,
    displaying or creating derivative works based on the work as long as
    all references to Project Gutenberg are removed. Of course, we hope
    that you will support the Project Gutenberg mission of promoting
    free access to electronic works by freely sharing Project Gutenberg
    works in compliance with the terms of this agreement for keeping the
    Project Gutenberg name associated with the work. You can easily
    comply with the terms of this agreement by keeping this work in the
    same format with its attached full Project Gutenberg License when
    you share it without charge with others.</p>
  </div>
</div>
Voici l'encodage TEI P5 strictement conforme aux règles du projet Zoomathia pour le texte fourni, en respectant les contraintes imposées :


<div type="chapter" n="1">
  <p>D. The copyright laws of the place where you are located also govern what you can do with this work. Copyright laws in most countries are in a constant state of change. If you are outside the United States, check the laws of your country in addition to the terms of this agreement before downloading, copying, displaying, performing, distributing or creating derivative works based on this work or any other Project Gutenberg work. The Foundation makes no representations concerning the copyright status of any work in any country other than the United States.</p>
<p>E. Unless you have removed all references to Project Gutenberg:</p>
<p>The following sentence, with active links to, or other immediate access to, the full Project Gutenberg License must appear prominently whenever any copy of a Project Gutenberg work (any work on which the phrase “Project Gutenberg” appears, or with which the phrase “Project Gutenberg” is associated) is accessed, displayed, performed, viewed, copied or distributed:</p>
</div>
Voici l'encodage TEI P5 strictement conforme aux règles du projet Zoomathia pour le texte fourni (bien que ce ne soit pas un texte antique sur les animaux, je respecte les consignes d'encodage) :


<div type="chapter" n="1">
   <div type="section" n="E.2">
      <p>If an individual <name type="project">Project Gutenberg</name> electronic work is
derived from texts not protected by U.S. copyright law (does not
contain a notice indicating that it is posted with permission of the
copyright holder), the work can be copied and distributed to anyone in
the United States without paying any fees or charges. If you are
redistributing or providing access to a work with the phrase “<name type="project">Project Gutenberg</name>”
associated with or appearing on the work, you must comply
either with the requirements of paragraphs 1.E.1 through 1.E.7 or
obtain permission for the use of the work and the <name type="project">Project Gutenberg</name>
trademark as set forth in paragraphs 1.E.8 or 1.E.9.</p>
   </div>
</div>
Voici l'encodage TEI P5 strictement conforme à vos exigences pour le texte fourni, en respectant toutes les règles et en priorisant l'encodage des entités Zoomathia :


<div type="section" n="147">
<p>If an individual <name type="project">Project Gutenberg</name> electronic work is posted
   with the permission of the copyright holder, your use and distribution
   must comply with both paragraphs <name type="number">1.E.1</name> through <name type="number">1.E.7</name> and any
   additional terms imposed by the copyright holder. Additional terms
   will be linked to the <name type="project">Project Gutenberg License</name> for all works
   posted with the permission of the copyright holder found at the
   beginning of this work.</p>

<p>Do not unlink or detach or remove the full <name type="project">Project Gutenberg License</name> terms from this work, or any files containing a part of this
   work or any other work associated with <name type="project">Project Gutenberg</name>.</p>

<p>Do not copy, display, perform, distribute or redistribute this
   electronic work, or any part of this electronic work, without
   prominently displaying the sentence set forth in paragraph <name type="number">1.E.1</name> with
   active links or immediate access to the full terms of the <name type="project">Project Gutenberg License</name>.</p>
</div>
Voici l'encodage TEI P5 strictement conforme à vos règles pour le texte fourni, en respectant la structure demandée et les balises spécifiques pour les entités nommées Zoomathia :


<div type="section" n="1.E.6">
  <p>You may convert to and distribute this work in any binary, compressed, marked up, nonproprietary or proprietary form, including any word processing or hypertext form. However, if you provide access to or distribute copies of a Project Gutenberg work in a format other than “<foreign xml:lang="en">Plain Vanilla ASCII</foreign>” or other format used in the official version posted on the official Project Gutenberg website (<placeName>www.gutenberg.org</placeName>), you must, at no additional cost, fee or expense to the user, provide a copy, a means of exporting a copy, or a means of obtaining a copy upon request, of the work in its original “<foreign xml:lang="en">Plain Vanilla ASCII</foreign>” or other form. Any alternate format must include the full Project Gutenberg License as specified in paragraph 1.E.1.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="1.E.7">
  <p>Do not charge a fee for access to, viewing, displaying, performing, copying or distributing any Project Gutenberg works unless you comply with paragraph 1.E.8 or 1.E.9.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="1.E.8">
  <p>You may charge a reasonable fee for copies of or providing access to or distributing Project Gutenberg electronic works provided that:</p>
</div>
<div type="book" n="149">
  <div type="chapter" n="157">
<p>You pay a royalty fee of 20% of the gross profits you derive from the use of Project Gutenberg works calculated using the method you already use to calculate your applicable taxes.</p>
    <p>The fee is owed to the owner of the Project Gutenberg trademark, but he has agreed to donate royalties under this paragraph to the Project Gutenberg Literary Archive Foundation.</p>
    <p>Royalty payments must be paid within 60 days following each date on which you prepare (or are legally required to prepare) your periodic tax returns.</p>
    <p>Royalty payments should be clearly marked as such and sent to the Project Gutenberg Literary Archive Foundation at the address specified in Section 4, “Information about donations to the Project Gutenberg Literary Archive Foundation.”</p>

<p>You provide a full refund of any money paid by a user who notifies you in writing (or by e-mail) within 30 days of receipt that s/he does not agree to the terms of the full Project Gutenberg™ License.</p>
    <p>You must require such a user to return or destroy all copies of the works possessed in a physical medium and discontinue all use of and all access to other copies of Project Gutenberg™ works.</p>

<p>You provide, in accordance with paragraph 1.F.3, a full refund of any money paid for a work or a replacement copy, if a defect in the</p>
  </div>
</div>
Voici l'encodage TEI P5 strictement conforme aux règles Zoomathia pour le texte fourni (bien que ce dernier ne contienne pas de références aux animaux, plantes ou entités nommées) :


<div type="section" n="150">
   <p>electronic work is discovered and reported to you within 90 days of receipt of the work.</p>
   <p>• You comply with all other terms of this agreement for free distribution of Project Gutenberg™ works.</p>
<p>If you wish to charge a fee or distribute a Project Gutenberg™ electronic work or group of works on different terms than are set forth in this agreement, you must obtain permission in writing from the Project Gutenberg Literary Archive Foundation, the manager of the Project Gutenberg™ trademark. Contact the Foundation as set forth in Section 3 below.</p>
<p>Project Gutenberg volunteers and employees expend considerable effort to identify, do copyright research on, transcribe and proofread works not protected by U.S. copyright law in creating the Project Gutenberg™ collection. Despite these efforts, Project Gutenberg™ electronic works, and the medium on which they may be stored, may contain “Defects,” such as, but not limited to, incomplete, inaccurate or corrupt data, transcription errors, a copyright or other intellectual property infringement, a defective or damaged disk or other medium, a computer virus, or computer codes that damage or cannot be read by your equipment.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="1.F.2">
   <p>LIMITED WARRANTY, DISCLAIMER OF DAMAGES - Except for the “Right
      of Replacement or Refund” described in paragraph, the Project
      Gutenberg Literary Archive Foundation, the owner of the Project
      Gutenberg™ trademark, and any other party distributing a Project
      Gutenberg™ electronic work under this agreement, disclaim all
      liability to you for damages, costs and expenses, including legal
      fees. YOU AGREE THAT YOU HAVE NO REMEDIES FOR NEGLIGENCE, STRICT
      LIABILITY, BREACH OF WARRANTY OR BREACH OF CONTRACT EXCEPT THOSE
      PROVIDED IN PARAGRAPH. YOU AGREE THAT THE FOUNDATION, THE
      TRADEMARK OWNER, AND ANY DISTRIBUTOR UNDER THIS AGREEMENT WILL NOT BE
      LIABLE TO YOU FOR ACTUAL, DIRECT, INDIRECT, CONSEQUENTIAL, PUNITIVE OR
      INCIDENTAL DAMAGES EVEN IF YOU GIVE NOTICE OF THE POSSIBILITY OF SUCH
      DAMAGE.</p>
</div>
Voici l'encodage TEI P5 strictement conforme aux règles du projet Zoomathia pour le texte fourni (bien que ce ne soit pas un texte antique sur les animaux, je respecte les consignes de formatage) :


<div type="section" n="1.F.3">
   <p>LIMITED RIGHT OF REPLACEMENT OR REFUND - If you discover a
defect in this electronic work within 90 days of receiving it, you can
receive a refund of the money (if any) you paid for it by sending a
written explanation to the person you received the work from. If you
received the work on a physical medium, you must return the medium
with your written explanation. The person or entity that provided you
with the defective work may elect to provide a replacement copy in
lieu of a refund. If you received the work electronically, the person
or entity providing it to you may choose to give you a second
opportunity to receive the work electronically in lieu of a refund. If
the second copy is also defective, you may demand a refund in writing
without further opportunities to fix the problem.</p>
</div>

<div type="section" n="1.F.4">
   <p>Except for the limited right of replacement or refund set forth
in paragraph 1.F.3, this work is provided to you ‘AS-IS’, WITH NO
OTHER WARRANTIES OF ANY KIND, EXPRESS OR IMPLIED, INCLUDING BUT NOT
LIMITED TO WARRANTIES OF <name type="deity">MERCHANTABILITY</name> OR <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">FITNESS</name> FOR ANY <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">PURPOSE</name>.</p>
</div>
Voici l'encodage TEI P5 strictement conforme à vos exigences pour ce texte, en respectant toutes les règles et priorités :


<div type="section" n="1.F.5">
   <p>Some states do not allow disclaimers of certain implied
   warranties or the exclusion or limitation of certain types of
   damages. If any disclaimer or limitation set forth in this agreement
   violates the law of the state applicable to this agreement, the
   agreement shall be interpreted to make the maximum disclaimer or
   limitation permitted by the applicable state law. The invalidity or
   unenforceability of any provision of this agreement shall not void the
   remaining provisions.</p>
</div>

<div type="section" n="1.F.6">
   <p>INDEMNITY - You agree to indemnify and hold the Foundation, the
   trademark owner, any agent or employee of the Foundation, anyone
   providing copies of Project Gutenberg™ electronic works in
   accordance with this agreement, and any volunteers associated with the
   production, promotion and distribution of Project Gutenberg™
   electronic works, harmless from all liability, costs and expenses,
   including legal fees, that arise directly or indirectly from any of
   the following which you do or cause to occur: (a) distribution of this
   or any Project Gutenberg work, and (b) alteration, modification, or
   additions or deletions to any Project Gutenberg work, and (c) any
   Defect you cause.</p>
</div>

<div type="section" n="2">
   <p>Information about the Mission of Project Gutenberg</p>
</div>
<div type="book" n="154">
  <p>Project Gutenberg is synonymous with the free distribution of
  electronic works in formats readable by the widest variety of
  computers including obsolete, old, middle-aged and new computers. It
  exists because of the efforts of hundreds of volunteers and donations
  from people in all walks of life.</p>

  <p>Volunteers and financial support to provide volunteers with the
  assistance they need are critical to reaching Project Gutenberg’s
  goals and ensuring that the Project Gutenberg collection will
  remain freely available for generations to come. In 2001, the Project
  Gutenberg Literary Archive Foundation was created to provide a secure
  and permanent future for Project Gutenberg and future
  generations. To learn more about the Project Gutenberg Literary
  Archive Foundation and how your efforts and donations can help, see
  Sections 3 and 4 and the Foundation information page at www.gutenberg.org.</p>

<div type="section" n="3">
    <head>Information about the Project Gutenberg Literary Archive Foundation</head>

    <p>The Project Gutenberg Literary Archive Foundation is a non-profit
    501(c)(3) educational corporation organized under the laws of the
    state of Mississippi and granted tax exempt status by the Internal
    Revenue Service. The Foundation’s EIN or federal tax identification
    number is 64-6221541. Contributions to the Project Gutenberg Literary
    Archive Foundation are tax deductible to the full extent permitted by
    U.S. federal laws and your state’s laws.</p>
  </div>
</div>
<div type="section" n="155">
   <p>The Foundation’s business office is located at 41 Watchung Plaza #516,
   <placeName>Montclair</placeName> <placeName>NJ</placeName> 07042, <placeName>USA</placeName>, +1 (862) 621-9288. Email contact links and up
   to date contact information can be found at the Foundation’s website
   and official page at <ref target="http://www.gutenberg.org/contact">www.gutenberg.org/contact</ref></p>
<p><persName>Project Gutenberg™</persName> depends upon and cannot survive without widespread
   public support and donations to carry out its mission of
   increasing the number of public domain and licensed works that can be
   freely distributed in machine-readable form accessible by the widest
   array of equipment including outdated equipment. Many small donations
   ($1 to $5,000) are particularly important to maintaining tax exempt
   status with the <name type="deity">IRS</name>.</p>
   <p>The Foundation is committed to complying with the laws regulating
   charities and charitable donations in all 50 states of the
   <placeName>United States</placeName>. Compliance requirements are not uniform and it takes a
   considerable effort, much paperwork and many fees to meet and keep up
   with these requirements. We do not solicit donations in locations
   where we have not received written confirmation of compliance. To SEND
   DONATIONS or determine the status of compliance for any particular state
   visit <ref target="http://www.gutenberg.org/donate">www.gutenberg.org/donate</ref>.</p>
</div>
Voici l'encodage TEI P5 strictement conforme à vos règles pour le texte fourni, bien qu'il ne contienne pas de références zoologiques ou d'entités nommées spécifiques à Zoomathia. J'ai respecté la structure minimale demandée et toutes les balises sont correctement fermées :


<div type="book" n="156">
  <p>While we cannot and do not solicit contributions from states where we have not met the solicitation requirements, we know of no prohibition against accepting unsolicited donations from donors in such states who approach us with offers to donate.</p>

<p>International donations are gratefully accepted, but we cannot make any statements concerning tax treatment of donations received from outside the United States. U.S. laws alone swamp our small staff.</p>

<p>Please check the Project Gutenberg web pages for current donation methods and addresses. Donations are accepted in a number of other ways including checks, online payments and credit card donations. To donate, please visit: <ref target="www.gutenberg.org/donate">www.gutenberg.org/donate</ref>.</p>

<div type="section" n="5">
    <p>General Information About Project Gutenberg electronic works</p>

<p>Professor Michael S. Hart was the originator of the Project Gutenberg concept of a library of electronic works that could be freely shared with anyone. For forty years, he produced and distributed Project Gutenberg eBooks with only a loose network of volunteer support.</p>

<p>Project Gutenberg eBooks are often created from several printed editions, all of which are confirmed as not protected by copyright in the U.S. unless a copyright notice is included. Thus, we do not necessarily keep eBooks in compliance with any particular paper edition.</p>

<p>Most people start at our website which has the main PG search facility: <ref target="www.gutenberg.org">www.gutenberg.org</ref>.</p>
  </div>
</div>
<pb n="157"/>
<p>This website includes information about Project Gutenberg,
including how to make donations to the Project Gutenberg Literary
Archive Foundation, how to help produce our new eBooks, and how to
subscribe to our email newsletter to hear about new eBooks.</p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>