<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
	<title>Elegy and Iambus, Volume II</title>
	<title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
	<editor role="editor" n="Loeb">J. M. Edmonds</editor>
	[responsibility]
	
      </titleStmt>
      <extent/>
	
      <sourceDesc>
	<listBibl>
	  <biblStruct>
	    <analytic/>
	    <monogr>
	      <author/>
	      <title>Elegy and Iambus</title>
	      <respStmt><resp>with an English Translation by</resp>
		<name>J. M. Edmonds</name>
	      <name/></respStmt>
	      <imprint>
		<pubPlace>Cambridge, MA</pubPlace>
		<publisher>Harvard University Press</publisher>
		<pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
		<publisher>William Heinemann Ltd.</publisher>
		<date>1931</date>
	      </imprint>
	      <biblScope type="volume">2</biblScope>
	    </monogr>
	  </biblStruct>
	</listBibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <correction status="high" method="silent">
               <p>optical character recognition</p>
            </correction>
         </editorialDecl>
     <refsDecl>
      <refState unit="volume" delim="."/>
      <refState unit="text" delim="."/>
      <refState unit="section"/>
     </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <langUsage> 
          <language ident="en">English</language> 
         <language ident="grc">Greek</language> 
        </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change when="2026-07-01">Section extraite automatiquement du fichier anthologie '2_eng_p5.xml' (xml:id d'origine : tlg-0260) par zoomathia_extraire_section_auteur.py.</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div2 type="text" xml:id="tlg-0260"><head>SEMONIDES</head>


<div3 type="section"><!--testimonia-->



<div4 type="biodata">
<cit xml:id="tlg-0260.cit.1"><quote>Semonides<note>the spelling with an <hi>e</hi> is vouched for by <hi>Vol. Herc.</hi> P. 1074. 105. col. 3, <hi>Coll. Alt.</hi> 4. 201, as well as by <hi>Et. Mag.</hi> s.v. [lpar]Choeroboscus[rpar]; though everywhere else we find <hi>Simonides</hi> , I have adopted the distinctive spelling throughout</note>: [mdash]Son of Crines, of Amorgos, writer of iambic verse; in origin he was of Samos, but was sent out by the Samians at the head of the colony they planted in Amorgos, founding three cities there, Minoa, Aegialus, and Arcesime. He flourished 390 years after the Trojan War.<note>cf. Syncell. p. 213</note> According to some authorities he was the first writer of iambics, and he wrote a <hi>History of Samos</hi> in two Books, in Elegiac verse, and other poetry of various kinds.</quote> <bibl>Suidas <title>Lexicon:</title></bibl></cit>
</div4>



<div4 type="biodata">
<cit xml:id="tlg-0260.cit.2"><quote>Amorgos is one of the Sporades and was the home of Semonides the iambic poet.</quote> <bibl>Strabo <title>Geography:</title></bibl></cit>
</div4>



<div4 type="biodata">
<cit xml:id="tlg-0260.cit.3"><quote>Semonides is made contemporary with Archilochus, and Callinus comes a little earlier, Archilochus speaking of Magnesia as destroyed and Callinus as still flourishing. Eumelus of Corinth is said to have belonged to an earlier date and been contemporary with Archias the founder of Syracuse. </quote> <bibl>Clement of Alexandria <title>Miscellanies</title></bibl></cit>
</div4>



<div4 type="biodata">
<cit xml:id="tlg-0260.cit.4"><quote>Amorgos [mdash]an island, one of the Cyclades, containing three cities, Arcesine, Minoa, and Aegiale ... Of Minoa was Semonides the iambic writer called of Amorgos.<note>cf. Tz. <hi>Chil.</hi> 12. 52, Phot. <hi>Bibl.</hi> 319 b. 28</note></quote> <bibl>Stephanus of Byzantium <title>Lexicon:</title></bibl></cit>
</div4>



<div4 type="biodata">
<cit xml:id="tlg-0260.cit.5"><quote>... I know too well that your life has been marked by innumerable deeds worthy of satire,<note>lit. iambic poems</note> deeds such that I believe Archilochus himself could not cope with even one of them, though he should call in the aid of Semonides and Hipponax. Why, <hi>their</hi> satires [mdash]Orodoecides, Lycambes, Bupalus [mdash]you have made mere child's play in every sort of beastliness.<note>cf. Censor. fr. 9</note></quote> <bibl>Lucian <title>The Liar:</title></bibl></cit>
</div4>



<div4 type="biodata">
<cit xml:id="tlg-0260.cit.6"><quote>Semonides is said to have been born [lsqb]or flourished[rsqb] in the 29th Olympiad [lpar]664-1 B.C.[rpar].</quote> <bibl>Cyril <title>Against Julian:</title></bibl></cit>
</div4>



<div4 type="biodata"><head><bibl>See also Eust. ad Dion. P. 525, Sch. Il. 2. 219.</bibl></head><p/></div4></div3>


<div3 type="section"><!--fragments--><head>Iambi</head>



<div4 type="book"><head>BOOKS I and II</head>


<div5 type="iambic" n="1">
<cit xml:id="tlg-0260.cit.7"><quote>[lsqb]that life is short, of little account, and full of care[rsqb]: Semonides: [mdash]
<cit xml:id="tlg-0260.cit.8"><quote><p>Thundering Zeus, lad, hath the ends of all things there be, and doeth with them what he will. There's no mind in us men, but we live each day as it cometh like grazing cattle, knowing no whit how God shall end it. Yet Hope and Trust keep us all a-pondering the impracticable; some abide till a day come, others for the turning of years. There 's none alive but thinketh he will come home winged with wealth and good things next year; yet one of us ere he reach his goal is taken with unenvied Age, another's mind is wasted by miserable Disease, or Death sendeth him below dark Earth whelmed by War. Some die at sea when they have laden a ship with their substance, confounded by storm and the many waves of the purple brine; others tie a noose about their miserable neck and leave the sunlight of their free choice. So true is it that nothing is without ills, nay, ten thousand the Dooms of men, and their woes and sorrows past reckoning. If they would be advised by me, we should not set our hearts on good things, nor yet do ourselves despite by letting our minds dwell upon evil troubles.</p></quote> <bibl>CURFRAG.tlg-0260.1</bibl></cit>
</quote> <bibl>Stobaeus <title>Anthology</title></bibl></cit>
</div5>

<div5 type="iambic" n="2">
<cit xml:id="tlg-0260.cit.9"><quote>[lsqb]consolations[rsqb]: Semonides: [mdash]
<cit xml:id="tlg-0260.cit.10"><quote><p>Were he to die we should not take it to heart, if we were wise, for more than a single day.<note>or now that he is dead we shall not ... if we are wise ... [lpar]cf. Theogn. <hi>passim</hi> [rpar]</note></p></quote> <bibl>CURFRAG.tlg-0260.2</bibl></cit>
</quote> <bibl>Stobaeus <title>Anthology</title></bibl></cit>
</div5>

<div5 type="iambic" n="3">
<cit xml:id="tlg-0260.cit.11"><quote>[lsqb]comparison of life and death[rsqb]: Semonides: [mdash]
<cit xml:id="tlg-0260.cit.12"><quote><p>There's much time for us to lie dead in, yet we live years few in number and live them ill.</p></quote> <bibl>CURFRAG.tlg-0260.3</bibl></cit>
</quote> <bibl>Stobaeus <title>Anthology</title></bibl></cit>
</div5>

<div5 type="iambic" n="4">
<cit xml:id="tlg-0260.cit.13"><quote><note>cf. Apost. 13. 86 b</note>[lsqb]that the prosperity of man is uncertain, because fortune easily changes[rsqb]: Semonides: [mdash]
<cit xml:id="tlg-0260.cit.14"><quote><p>No man is altogether without blame nor without harm.<note>meaning of <foreign xml:lang="greek">a)kh/rios</foreign> uncertain, but as <foreign xml:lang="greek">a)/mwmos</foreign> refers to what he does, it prob. refers to what happens to him; lit. unaffected by the <foreign xml:lang="greek">*kh=res</foreign> or Doom-Spirits [lpar]cf. i. 21[rpar]</note></p></quote> <bibl>CURFRAG.tlg-0260.4</bibl></cit>
</quote> <bibl>Stobaeus <title>Anthology</title></bibl></cit>
</div5>

<div5 type="iambic" n="5">
<cit xml:id="tlg-0260.cit.15"><quote><note>cf. Plut. <hi>An. Seni</hi> 12, <hi>Es. Carn.</hi> 2. 2, <hi>Virt. Mor.</hi> 7, <hi>Tuend. San.</hi> 22, Apost. 11. 98, Stob. <hi>Fl.</hi> 115. 18</note>But he who is making true progress, comparing himself rather with the deeds and actions of a good and perfect man than with his words, and at the same time being pricked with the knowledge of his deficiency and glad with hope and desire, full of an impulse that will not rest [mdash]he is able, in Semonides[rsquo] phrase,
<cit xml:id="tlg-0260.cit.16"><quote><p>to run like a sucking foal beside his mother</p></quote> <bibl>CURFRAG.tlg-0260.5</bibl></cit>
<p>craving almost to be one with his good friend.</p></quote> <bibl>Plutarch <title>How a Man knows he is progressing in Virtue:</title></bibl></cit>
</div5>

<div5 type="iambic" n="6">
<cit xml:id="tlg-0260.cit.17">
<quote><note>cf. Euseb.
 <hi>Praep. Ev.</hi> 10. 466 d [lpar] <foreign xml:lang="greek">*s. e)n e[lsqb]ndeka/tw</foreign> [rsqb], Apost. 5. 77 c, Boiss.
 <hi>An.</hi> i. 22 [lsqb] <foreign xml:lang="greek">*qe/ognis</foreign> [rsqb]</note>Hesiod says [lsquo]For a man wins himself nought better than a good wife nor worse than a bad,[rsquo] and Semonides after him:
<cit xml:id="tlg-0260.cit.18"><quote><p>A man wins himself nothing whatsoever that is better than a good wife nor worse than a bad.</p></quote> <bibl>CURFRAG.tlg-0260.6</bibl></cit>
</quote> <bibl>Clement of Alexandria <title>Miscellanies</title></bibl></cit>
</div5>

<div5 type="iambic" n="7">
<cit xml:id="tlg-0260.cit.19"><quote>[lsqb]censure of women, and concerning marriage[rsqb]: Semonides: [mdash]
<cit xml:id="tlg-0260.cit.20"><quote><p>In the beginning God made woman's mind apart from man's.<note>or made mind apart from woman</note>
</p>

<p>One made He of a bristly Sow; all that is in her house lies disorderly, defiled with dirt, and rolling upon the floor, and she groweth fat a-sitting among the middens in garments as unwashed as herself.
</p>

<p>Another did God make of a knavish Vixen, a woman knowing in all things, who taketh note of all, be it bad or good; for the bad often calleth she good and the good bad; and she hath now this mood and now that.
</p>

<p>Another of a Bitch, a busybody<note>the mss have <foreign xml:lang="greek">litorgo/n</foreign> , a form which occurs nowhere else and is prob. corrupt.; two ancient glosses prob. belong here; one, <foreign xml:lang="greek">li/targon</foreign> , explained by [lsquo]running fast,[rsquo] seems etymologically unsound, the other, <foreign xml:lang="greek">litourgo/n</foreign> [lsqb] <foreign xml:lang="greek">leitourgo/n</foreign> ?[rsqb], explained by [lsquo]scoundrelly,[rsquo] can hardly have that meaning; but the latter, besides its official use as [lsquo]doer of public works,[rsquo] may have had the meaning given above</note> like her mother, one that would fain hear all, know all, and peering and prying everywhere barketh e'en though she see nothing; a man cannot check her with threats, no, not if in anger he dash her teeth out with a stone, nor yet though he speak gently with her, even though she be sitting among strangers [mdash]she must needs keep up her idle baying.
</p>

<p>Another the Olympians fashioned of Earth, and gave to her husband all wanting in wits; such a woman knoweth neither evil nor good; her only art is to eat; and never though God give a bad winter draweth she her stool nigher the fire for the cold.
</p>

<p>Another of the Sea, whose thoughts are in two minds; one day she laughs and is gay [mdash]a stranger seeing her within will praise her, saying [lsquo]There's no better wife in all the world, nay, nor comelier[rsquo]; the next she is intolerable to behold or draw nigh to, for then she rageth unapproachably, like a bitch with young; implacable and nasty is she to all, alike foe and friend. Even as the sea in summertime often will stand calm and harmless, to the great joy of the mariners, yet often will rage and toss with roaring waves, most like unto it is such a woman in disposition, nor hath the ocean a nature of other sort than hers.<note> <hi>or keeping the Greek</hi> but the ocean hat a different nature</note>
</p>

<p>Another's made of a stubborn<note>reading doubtful</note> and belaboured She-Ass; everything she doeth is hardly done, of necessity and after threats, and then 'tis left unfinished; meanwhile eateth she day in day out, in bower and in hall, and all men alike are welcome to her bed.
</p>

<p>Another of a Cat, a woeful and miserable sort; for in her there's nought of fair or lovely or pleasant or desirable; she is wood<note>mad</note> for a love-mate, and yet when she hath him turneth his stomach; she doeth her neighbours much harm underhand, and often eateth up unaccepted offerings.<note>cf. Ath. 5. 179 d [lsqb] <foreign xml:lang="greek">p. th=s a)ko/smou gunako\s</foreign> [rsqb]</note>
</p>

<p>Another<note>11. 57-70 are also in Ael. <hi>H.A.</hi> 16. 24, cf. 11. 36</note> is the child of a dainty long-maned Mare; she refuseth menial tasks and toil; she'll neither set hand to mill nor take up sieve, nor cast forth the muck, nor, for that she shunneth the soot, will she sit beside the oven. She taketh a mate only of necessity. Every day will she wash herself twice, or even thrice, and anointeth her with unguents. She ever weareth her hair deep-combed and wreathed with flowers. Such a wife may be a fair sight for other men, but she's an ill to her husband if he be not a despot or a king, such as take pride in adornments like to her.
</p>

<p>Another cometh of an Ape; she is the greatest ill of all Zeus giveth man. Foul of face, such a woman maketh laughter for all men as she goeth through the town; short in neck, she moveth hardly, hipless, leanshanked [mdash]alas for the wretched man that claspeth such a mischief! Like an ape she knoweth all arts and wiles, nor recketh of men's laughter. Neither will she do a man any kindness; all her care, all her considering, is how she shall do the greatest ill she may.
</p>

<p>Another of a Bee; and happy he that getteth her. On her alone alighteth there no blame, and life doth flourish and increase because of her; loving and loved groweth she old with her husband, the mother of a fair and name-honoured progeny; she is pre-eminent among all the women, and a divine grace pervadeth her; neither taketh she delight in sitting among women where they tell tales of venery. Such wives are the best and wisest that Zeus bestoweth upon men; these other kinds, thanks unto Him, both are and will ever be a mischief in the world.
</p>

<p>For this is the greatest ill that Zeus hath made, women. Even though they may seem to advantage us, a wife is more than all else a mischief to him that possesseth her; for whoso dwelleth with a woman, he never passeth a whole day glad, nor quickly shall he thrust out of doors Hunger the hated housefellow and hostile deity. But when a man thinketh withindoors to be gladdest at heart by grace of God or favour of man, then of all times will she find cause for blame and gird herself for battle. For where a woman is, they e'en cannot receive a stranger heartily. And she that most seemeth to be discreet, she is all the time doing the greatest harm; her husband is all agape for her, but the neighbours rejoice that yet another is deceived. And no man but will praise his own wife when he speaketh of her,<note> <hi>not</hi> when he remembers her after her death [lpar]which would be put more explicitly[rpar]</note> and blame another's, yet we cannot see<note> <hi>or, emending the Gk.</hi> we know well</note> that we be all alike. Aye, this is the greatest ill that Zeus hath made, this hath he put about us as the bondage of a fetter irrefragable, ever since Death received them that went a-warring for a woman.<note>Helen, cf. Hes. <hi>Op.</hi> 165 ff</note></p></quote> <bibl>CURFRAG.tlg-0260.7</bibl></cit>
</quote> <bibl>Stobaeus <title>Anthology</title></bibl></cit>
</div5>

<div5 type="iambic" n="8, 9">
<cit xml:id="tlg-0260.cit.21"><quote><note>cf. Clem. Al. <hi>Paed.</hi> 2. 164</note>Semonides in the <hi>Iambi:</hi> [mdash]
<cit xml:id="tlg-0260.cit.22"><quote><p> like an eel in the sediment<note>the oily sediment of a public bath</note>
</p></quote> <bibl>CURFRAG.tlg-0260.8</bibl></cit>
<p>and the accusative:</p>
<cit xml:id="tlg-0260.cit.23"><quote><p>For a heron that hath found a hawk eating a Maeandrian eel hath taken it from him.<note>prob. metaphorical, but it might be the beginning of a Fable</note></p></quote> <bibl>CURFRAG.tlg-0260.9</bibl></cit>
</quote> <bibl>Athenaeus <title>Doctors at Dinner</title> ,</bibl></cit>
</div5>

<div5 type="iambic" n="10">
<cit xml:id="tlg-0260.cit.24"><quote>Some take <foreign xml:lang="greek">katena/sqhn</foreign> [lsquo]I took up my abode[rsquo] as equivalent to the future [lsquo]I shall take up my abode.[rsquo] Compare Semonides in the <hi>Iambi</hi> :
<cit xml:id="tlg-0260.cit.25"><quote><p>Why have I let my story run to a long tale?</p></quote> <bibl>CURFRAG.tlg-0260.10</bibl></cit>
<p>where <foreign xml:lang="greek">a)ne/dramon</foreign> stands for <foreign xml:lang="greek">a)nadramei=n me/llw.</foreign> </p></quote> <bibl>Scholiast on Euripides</bibl></cit>
</div5>

<div5 type="iambic" n="11">
<cit xml:id="tlg-0260.cit.26"><quote><note>cf. Eust. 1686. 51</note>[lsqb] <foreign xml:lang="greek">[lpar]w|)o/n</foreign> [lsquo]egg[rsquo] as a trisyllable[rsqb]: Semonides in the Second Book of the <hi>Iambi</hi> :
<cit xml:id="tlg-0260.cit.27"><quote><p> like to the egg of a Maeandrian goose </p></quote> <bibl>CURFRAG.tlg-0260.11</bibl></cit>
</quote> <bibl>Athenaeus <title>Doctors at Dinner</title></bibl></cit>
</div5>

<div5 type="iambic" n="12">
<cit xml:id="tlg-0260.cit.28">
<quote><note>cf. <hi>E. M. Vet.</hi> 167</note>The nominative is
 <foreign xml:lang="greek">i)/ktinos</foreign> ... the genitive of it being <foreign xml:lang="greek">i)kti/nou</foreign> as in Semonides:
<cit xml:id="tlg-0260.cit.29"><quote><p>forthwith plunging among<note> <hi>lit.</hi> putting on like a garment, but the reading may be wrong</note> the entrails like a kite</p></quote> <bibl>CURFRAG.tlg-0260.12</bibl></cit>
</quote><bibl>Herodian <title>Nouns</title> [lsqb]on nouns in -n[rsqb]</bibl></cit>
</div5>

<div5 type="iambic" n="13">
<cit xml:id="tlg-0260.cit.30"><quote><note>cf. Zon. 967</note> <foreign xml:lang="greek">zw/|dion</foreign> : [mdash][lsquo]carved or painted figure[rsquo]; it is written with the iota because it is found <hi>in diaeresi</hi> , as in Semonides for instance:
<cit xml:id="tlg-0260.cit.31"><quote><p>[lsquo]What a creature is this that hath flown to us! it hath the worst life of all living things[rsquo].<note>Fable of Zeus and the Crab? cf. Sch. <hi>Il.</hi> 18. 407 [lsquo]said the Crab[rsquo]</note></p></quote> <bibl>CURFRAG.tlg-0260.13</bibl></cit>
</quote> <bibl> <title>Etymolicum Magnum:</title></bibl></cit>
</div5>

<div5 type="iambic" n="14">
<cit xml:id="tlg-0260.cit.32"><quote><note>cf. Gal. 18. 1. 411 [lsqb] <foreign xml:lang="greek">ou)/pw tis ou)/tw</foreign> [rsqb]</note>... not knowing that the Ionians say <foreign xml:lang="greek">stenugro/n</foreign> for <foreign xml:lang="greek">steno/n</foreign> [lsquo]narrow[rsquo]; yet we have self-sufficient authority in what we find in the following lines of Semonides:
<cit xml:id="tlg-0260.cit.33"><quote><p>&lt;If so,&gt; no man would have so feared a lion in the shadowy hills nor yet a leopard if he met him alone in a narrow way.</p></quote> <bibl>CURFRAG.tlg-0260.14</bibl></cit>
</quote> <bibl>Galen <title>on Hippocrates</title></bibl></cit>
</div5>

<div5 type="iambic" n="15">
<cit xml:id="tlg-0260.cit.34">
<quote>Sophron uses the form
 <foreign xml:lang="greek">kouri/des</foreign> for <foreign xml:lang="greek">kari=des</foreign> [lsquo]prawns[rsquo] ... and so Epicharmus in
 <hi>Land and Sea,</hi> but in <hi>Logos and Logina</hi> he uses the form with
 <foreign xml:lang="greek">w</foreign> ... as does Semonides:
<cit xml:id="tlg-0260.cit.35"><quote><p>cuttlefish with tunnies, prawns with gudgeons<note>do not mate?</note></p></quote> <bibl>CURFRAG.tlg-0260.15</bibl></cit>
</quote> <bibl>Athenaeus <title>Doctors at Dinner</title></bibl></cit>
</div5>

<div5 type="iambic" n="16">
<cit xml:id="tlg-0260.cit.36"><quote><note>cf. Ath. 15. 699 c</note>Semonides in his <hi>Iambi</hi> has no compunction in saying:
<cit xml:id="tlg-0260.cit.37"><quote><p>and I anointed myself with unguents and spices and baccaris; for a merchant was there.</p></quote> <bibl>CURFRAG.tlg-0260.16</bibl></cit>
</quote> <bibl>Clement of Alexandria <title>Paedagogus:</title></bibl></cit>
</div5>

<div5 type="iambic" n="17">
<cit xml:id="tlg-0260.cit.38"><quote> <foreign xml:lang="greek">o)rsoqu/rh</foreign> : [mdash]a little door which gives access to<note>the Gk. suggests that the door is at the foot of the stairs</note> an upper chamber, from <foreign xml:lang="greek">o)/rw, o[rpar]/rsw,</foreign> and <foreign xml:lang="greek">qu/ra</foreign> ... so called because people move or rush [lsqb] <foreign xml:lang="greek">o)rou/ein</foreign> [rsqb] towards it;<note>improbable derivation; it is prob. for o)rqoqu/rh because it opened not on the level but upon the last step of a staircase or ladder, cf. Hesych. o)rsoqu/rh [lpar]cf. o)rso/qric[rsqb] occurs in Od. 22. 126, 132, 333</note> Semonides uses it in a [lsquo]lazy[rsquo] form [lpar]i.e. drops the middle syllable as in <foreign xml:lang="greek">a)mforeu/s</foreign> for <foreign xml:lang="greek">a)mfiforeu/s</foreign> [rsqb]:
<cit xml:id="tlg-0260.cit.39"><quote><p>and I let myself out by<note>lit. shut myself from</note> the back staircase-door.</p></quote> <bibl>CURFRAG.tlg-0260.17</bibl></cit>
</quote> <bibl> <title>Etymolicum Magnum:</title></bibl></cit>
</div5>

<div5 type="iambic" n="18">
<cit xml:id="tlg-0260.cit.40"><quote><note>cf. Zon. 539</note> <foreign xml:lang="greek">diasaulou/menos</foreign> [lsquo]strutting[rsquo]: [mdash]from <foreign xml:lang="greek">sau=los,</foreign> which means effeminate and disdainful; Semonides in the <hi>Iambi:</hi>
<cit xml:id="tlg-0260.cit.41"><quote><p>and with a swaggering gait like a horse with arching neck.</p></quote> <bibl>CURFRAG.tlg-0260.18</bibl></cit>
</quote> <bibl> <title>Etymolicum Magnum:</title></bibl></cit>
</div5>

<div5 type="iambic" n="19">
<cit xml:id="tlg-0260.cit.42"><quote> <foreign xml:lang="greek">sknipo/s</foreign> is used by Semonides the writer of iambics in the sense of one that does not see clearly:
<cit xml:id="tlg-0260.cit.43"><quote><p> either blind or blear-eyed or leering.<note>last word doubtful: if rightly emended it means [lsquo]with lewd looks[rsquo]</note>
</p></quote> <bibl>CURFRAG.tlg-0260.19</bibl></cit>
</quote> <bibl>Pollux <title>Onomasticon:</title></bibl></cit>
</div5>

<div5 type="iambic" n="20">
<cit xml:id="tlg-0260.cit.44"><quote><note>cf. Eust. 1766. 1</note>According to Semonides [lsquo]they [lpar]the shepherds[rpar] sacrifice,[rsquo] etc.
<cit xml:id="tlg-0260.cit.45"><quote><p>They sacrifice to the Nymphs and to the offspring of Maia;<note>Hermes</note> for these have honour<note>emendation doubtful</note> of shepherd folk.</p></quote> <bibl>CURFRAG.tlg-0260.20</bibl></cit>
</quote> <bibl>Scholiast on the <title>Odyssey</title></bibl></cit>
</div5>

<div5 type="iambic" n="21">
<cit xml:id="tlg-0260.cit.46"><quote>... and Semonides' phrase
<cit xml:id="tlg-0260.cit.47"><quote><p> cast forth with sodden clothes </p></quote> <bibl>CURFRAG.tlg-0260.21</bibl></cit>
<p>that is, wet through.</p></quote> <bibl>Strabo <title>Geography</title></bibl></cit>
</div5>

<div5 type="iambic" n="21A">
<cit xml:id="tlg-0260.cit.48"><quote> <foreign xml:lang="greek">pardako/s</foreign> means [lsquo]wet through,[rsquo] for so it is used by Archilochus, and by Semonides of Amorgos thus:
<cit xml:id="tlg-0260.cit.49"><quote><p> laden with sodden clothes </p></quote> <bibl>CURFRAG.tlg-0260.22</bibl></cit>
</quote> <bibl>Scholiast on Aristophanes <title>Peace:</title></bibl></cit>
</div5>

<div5 type="iambic" n="22, 23">
<cit xml:id="tlg-0260.cit.50"><quote>The Tromilean cheese is famous; of it Demetrius of Scepsis speaks in the 2nd Book of the <hi>Forces of the Trojans</hi> as follows: Tromileia is a city of Achaia in the district of which is made a very good goat's-milk cheese which has no rival, and is called Tromilean; it is mentioned by Semonides in the Iambic poem which begins:
<cit xml:id="tlg-0260.cit.51"><quote><p>Many the things thou dost finish, Telembrotus, ere ...</p></quote> <bibl>CURFRAG.tlg-0260.23</bibl></cit>
<p>and he says of it:</p>
<cit xml:id="tlg-0260.cit.52"><quote><p>But there [lpar]stood?[rpar] a wondrous Tromilean cheese from Achaia which they had brought down.</p></quote> <bibl>CURFRAG.tlg-0260.24</bibl></cit>
</quote> <bibl>Athenaeus <title>Doctors at Dinner</title></bibl></cit>
</div5>

<div5 type="iambic" n="24">
<cit xml:id="tlg-0260.cit.53"><quote>No wonder therefore that the cooks of old times were skilled <hi>haruspices</hi> [lpar]or diviners by entrails[rpar]; for they had the management both of weddings and sacrifices; ... and another says in Semonides:
<cit xml:id="tlg-0260.cit.54"><quote><p>And the pig, how I singed it and cut it up in ritual fashion; I'm no 'prentice.</p></quote> <bibl>CURFRAG.tlg-0260.25</bibl></cit>
</quote> <bibl>Athenaeus <title>Doctors at Dinner</title></bibl></cit>
</div5>

<div5 type="iambic" n="25">
<cit xml:id="tlg-0260.cit.55">
<quote>[lsqb]on cups[rsqb]: They are also called <foreign xml:lang="greek">a)rusth=res</foreign> and
 <foreign xml:lang="greek">a)ru/stixoi</foreign> [lpar]which generally mean [lsquo]ladles[rsquo][rpar]; compare Semonides:
<cit xml:id="tlg-0260.cit.56"><quote><p>No man gave [lpar]me[rpar] so much as a cup of wine-lees.</p></quote> <bibl>CURFRAG.tlg-0260.26</bibl></cit>
</quote> <bibl>Athenaeus <title>Doctors at Dinner</title></bibl></cit>
</div5>

<div5 type="iambic" n="26">
<cit xml:id="tlg-0260.cit.57"><quote>[lsqb]on cups[rsqb]: I know that the poet Semonides of Amorgos is the first to call them <foreign xml:lang="greek">poth/ria,</foreign> which he does in his <hi>Iambi</hi> thus:
<cit xml:id="tlg-0260.cit.58"><quote><p>He took away the table whither he had taken the cups.<note>lit. by the path by which, etc.; or to which the cups ..; the tops of Gk. tables were removable</note></p></quote> <bibl>CURFRAG.tlg-0260.27</bibl></cit>
</quote> <bibl>Athenaeus <title>Doctors at Dinner</title></bibl></cit>
</div5>

<div5 type="iambic" n="27">
<cit xml:id="tlg-0260.cit.59"><quote><note>cf. <hi>E.M.</hi> 798. 20, Zon. 1817, Apoll. Soph. 164. 21, <hi>E.G.</hi> 560. 22, Cram. <hi>A.P.</hi> 3. 279. 8, Matr. <hi>An.</hi> 467, Ath. 11. 480d</note> <foreign xml:lang="greek">foco/s</foreign> [lsqb]of Thersites' head[rsqb]: [mdash][lpar]a[rpar] This use comes from pottery tapered off at the kiln from the handle downwards;<note>reading and meaning doubtful</note> compare Semonides:
<cit xml:id="tlg-0260.cit.60"><quote><p>But this is a taper-footed Argive cup;</p></quote> <bibl>CURFRAG.tlg-0260.28</bibl></cit>
<p>but some writers explain it as one that has his head tapering [lsqb] <foreign xml:lang="greek">o[rpar]cu/s</foreign> [rsqb]towards his eyes [lsqb] <foreign xml:lang="greek">fa/h</foreign> [rsqb]. [lpar]b[rpar] <foreign xml:lang="greek">foco/s</foreign> is properly applied to fire-cracked pottery, being as it were <foreign xml:lang="greek">floco/s</foreign> or <hi>flamy.</hi> <note>a variant is <foreign xml:lang="greek">faoco/s</foreign> , which apparently comes from the first etymology</note></p></quote> <bibl>Scholiast on the <title>Iliad</title></bibl></cit>
</div5>

<div5 type="iambic" n="28">
<cit xml:id="tlg-0260.cit.61"><quote><note>cf. Suid. <foreign xml:lang="greek">o(plh/</foreign> </note>Aristophanes is not alone in using <foreign xml:lang="greek">o(plai/,</foreign> [lsquo]hoofs,[rsquo] of pigs; Semonides also does so, thus:
<cit xml:id="tlg-0260.cit.62"><quote><p> waggled the hoofs of his hind-legs<note>from a Fable?</note>
</p></quote> <bibl>CURFRAG.tlg-0260.29</bibl></cit>
</quote> <bibl>Scholiast on Aristophanes</bibl></cit>
</div5>

<div5 type="iambic" n="29">
<cit xml:id="tlg-0260.cit.63"><quote><note>cf. Eust. 1541. 31</note>The Dorians give the octopus an <foreign xml:lang="greek">w, pw/lupos,</foreign> for instance Epicharmus; and Semonides too:
<cit xml:id="tlg-0260.cit.64"><quote><p> looking for an octopus </p></quote> <bibl>CURFRAG.tlg-0260.30</bibl></cit>
</quote> <bibl>Athenaeus <title>Doctors at Dinner</title></bibl></cit>
</div5>

<div5 type="iambic" n="30">
<cit xml:id="tlg-0260.cit.65"><quote><note>cf. Cram. <hi>A.O.</hi> i. 106. 1</note> <foreign xml:lang="greek">dau/w:</foreign> [mdash][lsquo]to burn[rsquo] in Semonides:
<cit xml:id="tlg-0260.cit.66"><quote><p> burnt thigh-bones<note>these, wrapped in some of the fat, were the parts of the victim which the Greeks burnt at a sacrifice, the rest being eaten by the company</note>
</p></quote> <bibl>CURFRAG.tlg-0260.31</bibl></cit>
</quote> <bibl> <title>Etymolicum Magnum:</title></bibl></cit>
</div5>

<div5 type="iambic" n="31">
<cit xml:id="tlg-0260.cit.67">
<quote><note>cf. <hi>E.M.</hi> 36. 37</note> <foreign xml:lang="greek">e)/plhnt' a)llh/lh|si</foreign> [lsquo]they drew near to one another[rsquo]:<note>i.e. the opposing shields in a battle, Il. 4. 449</note> from <foreign xml:lang="greek">plw=</foreign> to approach; the perfect is
 <foreign xml:lang="greek">pe/plhka</foreign> and <foreign xml:lang="greek">pe/plaka,</foreign> the passive <foreign xml:lang="greek">pe/plhmai, pe/plhtai,</foreign> and in Semonides <foreign xml:lang="greek">peplh/atai:</foreign>
<cit xml:id="tlg-0260.cit.68"><quote><p> the other benches are full<note>the etymologist appears to have taken this to mean [lsquo]the other timbers have drawn nigh,[rsquo] but there must be some mistake</note>
</p></quote> <bibl>CURFRAG.tlg-0260.32</bibl></cit>
</quote><bibl> <title>Old Etymologicum Magnum:</title></bibl></cit>
</div5>

<div5 type="iambic" n="31A">
<cit xml:id="tlg-0260.cit.69"><quote><note>cf. Hesych. <foreign xml:lang="greek">si/sus</foreign> , Sch. Ar. Av. 122</note> <foreign xml:lang="greek">si/surna</foreign> is a thick mantle or leathern cloak, which Semonides calls <foreign xml:lang="greek">si/sus</foreign> for short, thus:
<cit xml:id="tlg-0260.cit.70"><quote><p> a thick plaidie </p></quote> <bibl>CURFRAG.tlg-0260.33</bibl></cit>
</quote> <bibl>Scholiast in Lycophron</bibl></cit>
</div5>

<div5 type="iambic" n="32">
<cit xml:id="tlg-0260.cit.71"><quote> <foreign xml:lang="greek">h)/i+a</foreign>
<cit xml:id="tlg-0260.cit.72"><quote><p> victuals </p></quote> <bibl>CURFRAG.tlg-0260.34</bibl></cit>
<p>not what you eat at home but what you eat on a journey, compare the <hi>Odyssey</hi> [lpar]2.410[rpar] and Semonides.<note>citation lost, but we at least know that S. used the word</note></p></quote> <bibl>Scholiast on the <title>Iliad</title></bibl></cit>
</div5>

<div5 type="iambic" n="33">
<cit xml:id="tlg-0260.cit.73"><quote>ka/rkara ...
<cit xml:id="tlg-0260.cit.74"><quote><p> bran </p></quote> <bibl>CURFRAG.tlg-0260.35</bibl></cit>
<p>in Semonides.</p></quote> <bibl>Hesychius <title>Glossary</title></bibl></cit>
</div5>

<div5 type="iambic" n="34">
<cit xml:id="tlg-0260.cit.75"><quote> <foreign xml:lang="greek">ke/rkwpes</foreign> : [mdash]scoundrels and cheats; and <foreign xml:lang="greek">kerkwpi/a</foreign>
<cit xml:id="tlg-0260.cit.76"><quote><p> deception </p></quote> <bibl>CURFRAG.tlg-0260.36</bibl></cit>
<p>in Semonides.</p></quote> <bibl>Suetonius</bibl></cit>
</div5>

<div5 type="iambic" n="35">
<cit xml:id="tlg-0260.cit.77"><quote> <foreign xml:lang="greek">kordu/lh</foreign> : a
<cit xml:id="tlg-0260.cit.78"><quote><p> tumour </p></quote> <bibl>CURFRAG.tlg-0260.37</bibl></cit>
<p>in Semonides' 2nd Book.</p></quote> <bibl>Anti-Atticist</bibl></cit>
</div5>

<div5 type="iambic" n="36">
<cit xml:id="tlg-0260.cit.79"><quote> <foreign xml:lang="greek">ku/bhbon</foreign> ... The Ionians use this to mean what is now called a
<cit xml:id="tlg-0260.cit.80"><quote><p> begging priest </p></quote> <bibl>CURFRAG.tlg-0260.38</bibl></cit>
<p>or <hi>Gallus</hi> ; thus Semonides.</p></quote> <bibl>Photius <title>Lexicon:</title></bibl></cit>
</div5>

<div5 type="iambic" n="37">
<cit xml:id="tlg-0260.cit.81"><quote>
<cit xml:id="tlg-0260.cit.82"><quote><p>booty of the Mysians </p></quote> <bibl>CURFRAG.tlg-0260.39</bibl></cit>
<p>Demosthenes in the speech <hi>On behalf of Ctesiphon;</hi> a proverb runs thus, which according to Demon in the 1st Book of his treatise <hi>On Proverbs</hi> takes its origin from the inroads of the border peoples and robbers into Mysia during the absence of King Telephus. Notable users of the proverb are Strattis in his <hi>Medea</hi> and Semonides in his <hi>Iambi.</hi> <note>the proverb was used of anything that may be plundered with impunity</note></p></quote><bibl>Harpocration <title>Lexicon to the Ten Orators:</title></bibl></cit>
</div5>

<div5 type="iambic" n="38">
<cit xml:id="tlg-0260.cit.83"><quote><note>cf. Orion <hi>App.</hi> 187. 29, <hi>E.G.</hi> 408. 40, Matro ap. Ath. 4. 134 f</note> <foreign xml:lang="greek">nh/sths</foreign>
<cit xml:id="tlg-0260.cit.84"><quote><p> starving </p></quote> <bibl>CURFRAG.tlg-0260.40</bibl></cit>
<p>or fasting; so Semonides ... according to Herodian in his Homophones.</p></quote> <bibl>Grammarian in Bekker's <title>Anecdota:</title></bibl></cit>
</div5>

<div5 type="iambic" n="39">
<cit xml:id="tlg-0260.cit.85"><quote><note>cf. Hesych. <foreign xml:lang="greek">parsih/n</foreign> , <hi>E.G.</hi> 256</note> <foreign xml:lang="greek">trasia/</foreign>
<cit xml:id="tlg-0260.cit.86"><quote><p> drying-crate </p></quote> <bibl>CURFRAG.tlg-0260.41</bibl></cit>
<p>for figs.... also in the form <foreign xml:lang="greek">tarsia/</foreign> [lpar]i.e. <foreign xml:lang="greek">tarsih/</foreign> [rsqb], which occurs in Semonides.</p></quote> <bibl> <title>Etymolicum Magnum:</title></bibl></cit>
</div5>

<div5 type="iambic" n="40">
<cit xml:id="tlg-0260.cit.87"><quote><note>cf. Orion 168. 9</note> <foreign xml:lang="greek">yhno/s</foreign>
<cit xml:id="tlg-0260.cit.88"><quote><p> baldhead </p></quote> <bibl>CURFRAG.tlg-0260.42</bibl></cit>
<p>in Semonides.</p></quote> <bibl> <title>Etymolicum Magnum:</title></bibl></cit>
</div5>

<div5 type="iambic" n="41">
<cit xml:id="tlg-0260.cit.89"><quote><note>for a possible ref. to S.'s Book ii see Xenophanes fr. 21 n</note>The Lesbian Prylis: this saying is adapted by Semonides:
<cit xml:id="tlg-0260.cit.90"><quote><p>... ye sleep in ... like Lesbian Prylis<note>cf. Sch. Lycophr. 219 and Milne <hi>Cat. Lit. Pap. Brit. Mus.</hi> 53 p. 40, a frag. too mutilated to be included here</note> ...</p></quote> <bibl>CURFRAG.tlg-0260.43</bibl></cit>
</quote> <bibl>Athens MS. in Crusius <title>Paroemiographica:</title></bibl></cit>
</div5></div4>
</div3>
</div2>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
