<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader type="text">
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     De sacrificiis
    </title>
    <title type="sub">
     Machine readable text
    </title>
    <author n="Plut.">
     Lucian
    </author>
    <editor n="Loeb" role="editor">
     A. M. Harmon
    </editor>
    <sponsor>
     Perseus Project, Tufts University
    </sponsor>
    <principal>
     Gregory Crane
    </principal>
    <respStmt>
     <resp>
      Prepared under the supervision of
     </resp>
     <name>
      Lisa Cerrato
     </name>
     <name>
      William Merrill
     </name>
     <name>
      Elli Mylonas
     </name>
     <name>
      David Smith
     </name>
    </respStmt>
    <funder n="org:NEH">
     The National Endowment for the Humanities
    </funder>
    <funder n="org:Google">
     Google Digital Humanities Awards Program
    </funder>
   </titleStmt>
   <extent/>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>
     Trustees of Tufts University
    </publisher>
    <pubPlace>
     Medford, MA
    </pubPlace>
    <authority>
     Perseus Project
    </authority>
   </publicationStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <listBibl>
     <biblStruct>
      <monogr>
       <author>
        Lucian
       </author>
       <title>
        Works
       </title>
       <respStmt>
        <resp>
         with an English Translation by
        </resp>
        <name>
         A. M. Harmon
        </name>
       </respStmt>
       <imprint>
        <pubPlace>
         Cambridge, MA
        </pubPlace>
        <publisher>
         Harvard University Press
        </publisher>
        <pubPlace>
         London
        </pubPlace>
        <publisher>
         William Heinemann Ltd.
        </publisher>
        <date>
         1921
        </date>
       </imprint>
       <biblScope type="volume">
        3
       </biblScope>
      </monogr>
     </biblStruct>
    </listBibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <refsDecl n="CTS">
    <cRefPattern matchPattern="(\\w+)" n="section" replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div/tei:div[@n=\'$1\'])">
     <p>
      This pointer pattern extracts section
     </p>
     <p lang="it">
      Questo modello di puntatore estrae la sezione
     </p>
     <p lang="en">
      This pointer pattern extracts section
     </p>
    </cRefPattern>
   </refsDecl>
   <editorialDecl>
    <correction method="silent">
     <p>
      optical character recognition
     </p>
     <p lang="it">
      riconoscimento ottico dei caratteri
     </p>
     <p lang="en">
      optical character recognition
     </p>
    </correction>
   </editorialDecl>
   <refsDecl>
    <refState unit="section"/>
   </refsDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <langUsage>
    <language ident="greek">
     Greek
    </language>
   </langUsage>
  </profileDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text xml:lang="grc">
  <body>
   <div n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg027.perseus-grc2" type="edition">
    <pb n="v.3.p.154"/>
    <div n="1" subtype="section" type="textpart">
     <p>
      ἃ μὲν γὰρ ἐν ταῖς θυσίαις οἱ μάταιοι πράττουσι καὶ ταῖς ἑορταῖς καὶ
                        προσόδοις τῶν θεῶν καὶ ἃ αἰτοῦσι καὶ ἃ εὔχονται καὶ ἃ γιγνώσκουσι περὶ
                        αὐτῶν, οὐκ οἶδα εἴ τις οὕτως κατηφής ἐστι καὶ λελυπημένος ὅστις οὐ γελάσεται
                        τὴν ἀβελτερίαν· ἐπιβλέψας τῶν δρωμένων. καὶ πολύ γε, οἶμαι, πρότερον τοῦ
                        γελᾶν πρὸς ἑαυτὸν ἐξετάσει πότερον εὐσεβεῖς αὐτοὺς χρὴ καλεῖν ἢ τοὐναντίον
                        θεοῖς ἐχθροὺς καὶ κακοδαίμονας, οἵ γε οὕτω ταπεινὸν καὶ ἀγεννὲς τὸ θεῖον
                        ὑπειλήφασιν ὥστε εἶναι ἀνθρώπων ἐνδεὲς καὶ κολακευόμενον ἥδεσθαι καὶ
                        ἀγανακτεῖν ἀμελούμενον. τὰ γοὺν Αἰτωλικὰ πάθη καὶ τὰς τῶν Καλυδωνίων
                        συμφορὰς καὶ τοὺς τοσούτους φόνους καὶ τὴν Μελεάγρου διάλυσιν, πάντα ταῦτα
                        ἔργα φασὶν εἶναι τῆς Ἀρτέμιδος μεμψιμοιρούσης ὅτι μὴ παρελήφθη πρὸς τὴν
                        θυσίαν ὑπὸ τοῦ Οἰνέως· οὕτως ἄρα βαθέως καθίκετο αὐτῆς ἡ τῶν ἱερείων διαφορά
                        καί μοι δοκῶ ὁρᾶν αὐτὴν ἐν τῷ οὐρανῷ τότε μόνην τῶν ἄλλων θεῶν εἰς Οἰνέως
                        πεπορευμένων, δεινὰ ποιοῦσαν καὶ σχετλιάζουσαν οἵας ἑορτῆς ἀπολειφθήσεται.
      <pb n="v.3.p.156"/>
     </p>
     <p lang="it">
      per ciò che non c'è nei sacrifici che fanno invano e nelle feste e
                        i doni degli dei e cosa chiedono, cosa desiderano e cosa sanno
                        di loro non li ho visti così tristi, anche chi non ride è triste
                        l'abelteriano; hai supervisionato le azioni. e molto prima
                        ridono tra loro esaminando chi li adora quando chiamano o il contrario
                        dei nemici e demone malvagio, che è quindi umile e non nato il dio
                        presumere che sia un essere umano e lusingato di venire e
                        negligente indignato. le antiche passioni etoliche e quelle dei Caledoni
                        calamità e simili omicidi e la dissoluzione di Meleagro, tutto questo
                        le opere di Phasin sono di Artemis mepsimourisus perché non fu portata al mondo
                        sacrificio sotto Oineos; come punizione la differenza dei preti
                        e cerco di vederla nel cielo allora sola tra gli altri dei di Eneo
                        di coloro che viaggiavano, soffrivano e bestemmiavano ogni volta che la festa veniva abolita.
     </p>
     <p lang="en">
      for what is not in the sacrifices they do in vain and in the feasts and
                        bounties of the gods and what they ask and what they wish and what they know about
                        of them, I have not seen them so sad, he who does not laugh is also sad
                        the abelterian; you oversaw the actions. and much earlier than that
                        they laugh to themselves examine who worships them when they call or the opposite
                        enemy gods and evil demon, who is thus humble and unborn the god
                        to assume that he is a human being and flattered to come and
                        indignant negligent. the old Aetolian passions and those of the Caledonians
                        calamity and such murders and the dissolution of Meleagro, all these
                        the works of Phasin are of Artemis mepsimourisus because she was not taken to the
                        sacrifice under Oineos; as her punishment the difference of the priests
                        and I try to see her in the sky then alone of the other gods in Oeneos
                        of those who traveled, they were suffering and blaspheming whenever the holiday was abolished.
     </p>
    </div>
    <div n="2" subtype="section" type="textpart">
     <p>
      τοὺς δʼ αὖ Αἰθίοπας καὶ μακαρίους καὶ τρισευδαίμονας εἴποι τις ἄν, εἴ γε
                        ἀπομνημονεύει τὴν χάριν αὐτοῖς ὁ Ζεὺς ἣν πρὸς αὐτὸν ἐπεδείξαντο δώδεκα ἑξῆς
                        ἡμέρας ἑστιάσαντες, καὶ ταῦτα ἐπαγόμενον καὶ τοὺς ἄλλους θεούς. οὕτως οὐδέν,
                        ὡς ἔοικεν, ἀμισθὶ ποιοῦσιν ὧν ποιοῦσιν, ἀλλὰ πωλοῦσιν τοῖς ἀνθρώποις τἀγαθά,
                        καὶ ἔνεστι πρίασθαι παρʼ αὐτῶν τὸ μὲν ὑγιαίνειν, εἰ τύχοι, βοϊδίου, τὸ δὲ
                        πλουτεῖν βοῶν τεττάρων, τὸ δὲ βασιλεύειν ἑκατόμβης, τὸ δὲ σῶον ἐπανελθεῖν ἐξ
                        Ἰλίου εἰς Πύλον ταύρων ἐννέα, καὶ τὸ ἐκ τῆς Αὐλίδος εἰς Ἴλιον διαπλεῦσαι
                        παρθένου βασιλικῆς. ἡ μὲν γὰρ Ἑκάβη τὸ μὴ ἁλῶναι τὴν πόλιν τότε ἐπρίατο παρὰ
                        τῆς Ἀθηνᾶς βοῶν δώδεκα καὶ πέπλου. εἰκάζειν δὲ χρὴ πολλὰ εἶναι ἀλεκτρυόνος
                        καὶ στεφάνου καὶ λιβανωτοῦ μόνου παρʼ αὐτοῖς ὤνια.
     </p>
     <p lang="it">
      Gli Etiopi, beati e benedetti, dissero loro se, sì,
                        Zeus ricorda la grazia mostratagli dai dodici
                        concentrandosi sul giorno, e questi e gli altri dei furono scacciati. quindi niente
                        come ἔiken, fanno quello che fanno senza essere pagati, ma vendono beni alle persone,
                        e c'era tra loro un prete che fu guarito, se per caso, da un toro, ma
                        essere ricco con la ricchezza di quattro, regnare su centomila ed essere salvato da
                        Ilio al Pilone nove tori, e dall'Aulis a Ilio navighi
                        basilico vergine. perché in quel tempo non disturbavo la città
                        di Atena con dodici voci e un velo. ma ipotizzano che sia un alectrione
                        e accanto a loro solo una ghirlanda e un turibolo.
     </p>
     <p lang="en">
      The Ethiopians, blessed and blessed, said to them if, yes,
                        Zeus remembers the grace shown to him by twelve
                        focusing on the day, and these and the other gods were driven away. so nothing
                        as ἔiken, they do what they do without pay, but they sell goods to people,
                        and there was a priest among them that they were healed, if by chance, of a bull, but
                        to be rich with the wealth of four, and to reign a hundred thousand, and to be saved from
                        Ilio to Pylon nine bulls, and from the Aulis to Ilio you sail
                        virgin basil. because I did not disturb the city at that time
                        of Athena with twelve voices and a veil. but they speculate that he is an alectryon
                        and a wreath and a censer alone beside them.
     </p>
    </div>
    <div n="3" subtype="section" type="textpart">
     <p>
      ταῦτά γε, οἶμαι, καὶ ὁ Χρύσης ἐπιστάμενος ἅτε ἱερεὺς ὢν καὶ γέρων καὶ τὰ
                        θεῖα σοφός, ἐπειδὴ ἄπρακτος ἀπῄει παρὰ τοῦ Ἀγαμέμνονος, ὡς ἂν καὶ
                        προδανείσας τῷ Ἀπόλλωνι τὴν χάριν δικαιολογεῖται καὶ ἀπαιτεῖ τὴν ἀμοιβὴν καὶ
                        μόνον οὐκ ὀνειδίζει λέγων,
      <q type="unspecified">
       ὦ βέλτιστε Ἄπολλον, ἐγὼ μέν
                            σου τὸν νεὼν τέως ἀστεφάνωτον ὄντα πολλάκις ἐστεφάνωσα, καὶ τοσαῦτά σοι
                            μηρία ταύρων τε καὶ αἰγῶν ἔκαυσα ἐπὶ τῶν βωμῶν, σὺ δὲ ἀμελεῖς μου
                            τοιαῦτα πεπονθότος καὶ παρʼ οὐδὲν τίθεσαι ʼτὸν εὐεργέτην.
      </q>
      τοιγαροῦν
                        οὕτω κατεδυσώπησεν αὐτὸν ἐκ τῶν λόγων, ὥστε ἁρπασάμενος τὰ τόξα
      <pb n="v.3.p.158"/>
      καὶ ἐπὶ τοῦ ναυστάθμου καθίσας ἑαυτὸν κατετόξευσε τῷ
                        λοιμῷ τοὺς Ἀχαιοὺς αὐταῖς ἡμιόνοις καὶ κυσίν.
     </p>
     <p lang="it">
      queste cose, io sono, e Crise, che si crede sacerdote, è anche lui un vecchio e il
                        zia saggia, perché morì senza azione davanti ad Agamennone, anche se
                        hai già prestato il favore ad Apollo, sei giustificato e chiedi la ricompensa e
                        solo che non esita a dire: "Apollo ottimale", ho detto
                            Molte volte ho incoronato il tuo essere giovane, prima senza corona, e questo per te
                            Ho bruciato sugli altari le cosce dei tori e dei capri, ma tu mi trascuri
                            Così triste e nonostante nulla, ti fidi del benefattore. loro litigano
                        tanto lo costernò dalle parole, tanto che, afferrati gli archi e seduto sul naustatmus, si lanciò al
                        una piaga sugli Achei questi halfling e Cisine.
     </p>
     <p lang="en">
      these things, I am, and Chrysis, who is believed to be a priest, is also an old man and the
                        wise aunt, because he died without action before Agamemnon, even though
                        you have already lent Apollo the favor, you are justified and demand the reward and
                        only he does not hesitate to say, ``Optimal Apollo,'' I said
                            I have crowned your young, previously uncrowned being many times, and this much to you
                            I burned the thighs of bulls and goats on the altars, but you neglect me
                            So sad and in spite of nothing, you trust the benefactor. they fight
                        so he dismayed him from the words, so that seizing the bows and sitting on the naustatmus, he launched himself at the
                        a plague on the Achaeans these halflings and Cysines.
     </p>
    </div>
    <div n="4" subtype="section" type="textpart">
     <p>
      ἐπεὶ δὲ ἅπαξ τοῦ Ἀπόλλωνος ἐμνήσθην, βούλομαι καὶ τὰ ἄλλα εἰπεῖν, ἃ περὶ
                        αὐτοῦ οἱ σοφοὶ τῶν ἀνθρώπων λέγουσιν, οὐχ ὅσα περὶ τοὺς ἔρωτας ἐδυστύχησεν
                        οὐδὲ τοῦ Ὑακίνθου τὸν φόνον οὐδὲ τῆς Δάφνης τὴν ὑπεροψίαν, ἀλλʼ ὅτι καὶ
                        καταγνωσθεὶς ἐπὶ τῷ τῶν Κυκλώπων θανάτῳ καὶ ἐξοστρακισθεὶς διὰ τοῦτο ἐκ τοῦ
                        οὐρανοῦ, ἐπέμφθη εἰς τὴν γῆν ἀνθρωπίνῃ χρησόμενος τῇ τύχῃ· ὅτε δὴ καὶ
                        ἐθήτευσεν ἐν Θετταλίᾳ παρὰ Ἀδμήτῳ καὶ ἐν Φρυγίᾳ παρὰ Λαομέδοντι, παρὰ τούτῳ
                        μέν γε οὐ μόνος ἀλλὰ μετὰ τοῦ Ποσειδῶνος, ἀμφότεροι πλινθεύοντες ὑπʼ ἀπορίας
                        καὶ ἐργαζόμενοι τὸ τεῖχος· καὶ οὐδὲ ἐντελῆ τὸν μισθὸν ἐκομίσαντο παρὰ τοῦ
                        Φρυγός, ἀλλὰ προσώφειλεν αὐτοῖς πλέον ἢ τριάκοντα, φασί, δραχμὰς Τρωϊκάς.
     </p>
     <p lang="it">
      ma dopo che si è parlato di Apollo, voglio che parlino anche gli altri, che ne dite?
                        a lui i saggi dicono non che hanno fallito nelle relazioni amorose
                        né l'omicidio di Giacinto né l'arroganza di Dafne, ma perché
                        condannato alla morte dei Ciclopi e quindi ostracizzato
                        del cielo, venne allora sulla terra un uomo che fu usato dalla fortuna;
                        tuttavia prestò servizio in Thetalia sotto Admeto e in Frigia sotto Laomedonte
                        Non vado da solo ma con Poseidone, entrambi tremanti per la meraviglia
                        e lavorando sul muro, e non ricevevano per questo il salario intero
                        Frigio, ma doveva loro più di trenta, fassi, dracme di Troia.
     </p>
     <p lang="en">
      but after Apollo has been mentioned, I want the others to speak as well, what about
                        to him the wise men say, not that they have failed in love affairs
                        neither the murder of Iacinthus nor the arrogance of Daphne, but because
                        condemned to the death of the Cyclops and thus ostracized from
                        of heaven, came to the earth a man who was used by fortune; then
                        served in Thetalia under Admetus and in Phrygia under Laomedon, nevertheless
                        I do not go alone but with Poseidon, both of them cringing in wonder
                        and working on the wall, and they did not receive a full wage for it
                        Phrygian, but he owed them more than thirty, fassi, drachmas of Troy.
     </p>
    </div>
    <div n="5" subtype="section" type="textpart">
     <p>
      ἢ γὰρ οὐ ταῦτα σεμνολογοῦσιν οἱ ποιηταὶ περὶ τῶν θεῶν καὶ πολὺ τούτων
                        ἱερώτερα περί τε Ἡφαίστου καὶ Προμηθέως καὶ Κρόνου καὶ Ῥέας καὶ σχεδὸν ὅλης
                        τῆς τοῦ Διὸς οἰκίας; καὶ ταῦτα παρακαλέσαντες τὰς Μούσας συνῳδοὺς ἐν ἀρχῇ
                        τῶν ἐπῶν, ὑφʼ ὧν δὴ ἔνθεοι γενόμενοι, ὡς τὸ εἰκός, ᾅδουσιν ὡς ὁ μὲν Κρόνος
                        ἐπειδὴ τάχιστα ἐξέτεμε τὸν πατέρα τὸν Οὐρανόν, ἐβασίλευσέν τε ἐν αὐτῷ καὶ τὰ
                        τέκνα κατήσθιεν ὥσπερ ὁ Ἀργεῖος Θυέστης ὕστερον· ὁ δὲ Ζεὺς ˘ κλαπεὶς ὑπὸ τῆς
                        Ῥέας ὑποβαλομένης τὸν λίθον εἰς τὴν Κρήτην ἐκτεθεὶς ὑπʼ αἰγὸς ἀνετράφη
                        καθάπερ ὁ Τήλεφος
      <pb n="v.3.p.160"/>
      ὑπὸ ἐλάφου καὶ ὁ Πέρσης Κῦρος ὁ
                        πρότερος ὑπὸ τῆς κυνός, εἶτʼ ἐξελάσας τὸν πατέρα καὶ εἰς τὸ δεσμωτήριον
                        καταβαλὼν αὐτὸς ἔσχε τὴν ἀρχὴν ἔγημε δὲ πολλὰς μὲν καὶ ἄλλας, ὑστάτην δὲ τὴν
                        ἀδελφὴν κατὰ τοὺς Περσῶν καὶ Ἀσσυρίων νόμους· ἐρωτικὸς δὲ ὢν καὶ εἰς τὰ
                        ἀφροδίσια ἐκκεχυμένος ˘ ῥᾳδίως ἐνέπλησε παίδων τὸν οὐρανόν, . τοὺς μὲν ἐξ
                        ὁμοτίμων ποιησάμενος, ἐνίους δὲ νόθους ἐκ τοῦ θνητοῦ καὶ ἐπιγείου γένους,
                        ἄρτι μὲν ὁ γεννάδας γενόμενος χρυσός, ἄρτι δὲ ταῦρος ἢ κύκνος ἢ ἀετός, καὶ
                        ὅλως ποικιλώτερος αὐτοῦ Πρωτέως· μόνην δὲ τὴν Ἀθηνᾶν ἔφυσεν ἐκ τῆς ἑαυτοῦ
                        κεφαλῆς ὑπʼ αὐτὸν ἀτεχνῶς τὸν ἐγκέφαλον συλλαβών τὸν μὲν γὰρ Διόνυσον
                        ἡμιτελῆ, φασίν, ἐκ τῆς μητρὸς ἔτι καιομένης ἁρπάσας ἐν τῷ μηρῷ φέρων
                        κατώρυξε κᾆτα ἐξέτεμεν τῆς ὠδῖνος ἐνστάσης.
     </p>
     <p lang="it">
      Oppure non è questo ciò che i poeti intendono degli dei e di molti di loro
                        più sacro su Efesto e Prometeo e Saturno e Rea e quasi tutti
                        della casa di Zeus? e questi in principio supplicavano le Muse
                        della terra, affinché coloro che non nascono come dei, come gli eikos, si vestiranno come Saturno
                        perché abbiamo scomunicato subito il padre del Cielo, ha regnato in lui e il
                        ai bambini piace sempre l'argivo Tieste in seguito; ma Zeus le ha rubato
                        Ῥῦῆ῔ῆῆῖῖῖῖ Ῥεῖα Ῥεῖα Ῥεας Ῥεας Ῥεας Ῥεας Ῥεας
                        e Telephos sotto un cervo e il persiano Kyros the
                        prima da sotto il segugio, se fai uscire il padre di prigione
                        quando ha pagato da principio, siamo diventati tanti, l'uno e l'altro, e hanno trovato il
                        fratello secondo i Persiani e gli Assiri n spalle; ma è anche erotico
                        emanando afrodisiacamente ˘ ῥᾳδως riempì il cielo di bambini, . quelli miei
                        dei poeti onorevoli, ma degli ingiusti della razza mortale e mortale,
                        quanto più dell'oro calvo, e quanto più un toro o un cigno o un'aquila, e
                        tutti più diversi del suo Proteo; ma solo Atena soffiò da se stesso
                        della testa sotto di lui ingenuamente le sillabe dell'encefalo il me perché Dioniso
                        Incompleto
                        Ha abbattuto gli ᾆta exetemen degli ḍdinos instasis.
     </p>
     <p lang="en">
      Or is this not what the poets mean about the gods and many of them
                        more sacred about Hephaestus and Prometheus and Saturn and Rhea and almost all
                        of the house of Zeus? and these, supplicating the Muses in the beginning
                        of the earth, so that those who are not born as gods, like the eikos, will dress like Saturn
                        because we quickly excommunicated the father Heaven, reigned in him and the
                        children always like the Argive Thyestes later; but Zeus ˘ stolen from her
                        Ῥῦῆ῔ῆῆῖῖῖῖ Ῥεῖα Ῥεῖα Ῥεας Ῥεας Ῥεας Ῥεας Ῥεας
                        and Telephos under a deer and the Persian Kyros the
                        first from under the hound, if you let the father out of prison
                        when he paid the beginning, we became many, one and another, and they found the
                        brother according to the Persians and Assyrians n shoulders; but he is also erotic
                        aphrodisiacally emanating ˘ ῥᾳδως filled the sky with children, . those of me
                        of the honorable poets, but of the unrighteous of the mortal and mortal race,
                        how much more than the bald born gold, and how much more a bull or a swan or an eagle, and
                        all more diverse than his Proteus; but Athena alone he blew from himself
                        of the head under him artlessly the encephalon syllables the me because Dionysus
                        Incomplete
                        He brought down the ᾆta exetemen of the ḍdinos instasis.
     </p>
    </div>
    <div n="6" subtype="section" type="textpart">
     <p>
      ὅμοια δὲ τούτοις καὶ περὶ τῆς Ἥρας ᾄδουσιν, ἄνευ τῆς πρὸς τὸν ἄνδρα ὁμιλίας
                        ὑπηνέμιον αὐτὴν παῖδα γεννῆσαι τὸν Ἥφαιστον, οὐ μάλα εὐτυχῆ τοῦτον, ἀλλὰ
                        βάναυσον καὶ χαλκέα καὶ πυρίτην, ἐν καπνῷ τὸ πᾶν βιοῦντα καὶ σπινθήρων
                        ἀνάπλεων οἷα δὴ καμινευτήν, καὶ οὐδὲ ἄρτιον τὼ πόδε· χωλευθῆναι γὰρ αὐτὸν
                        ἀπὸ τοῦ πτώματος, ὁπότε ἐρρίφη ὑπὸ τοῦ Διὸς ἐξ οὐρανοῦ, καὶ εἴ γε μὴ οἱ
                        Λήμνιοι καλῶς ποιοῦντες ἔτι φερόμενον αὐτὸν ὑπεδέξαντο, κἂν ἐτεθνήκει ἡμῖν ὁ
                        Ἥφαιστος ὥσπερ ὁ Ἀστυάναξ ἀπὸ τοῦ πύργου καταπεσών.
      <pb n="v.3.p.162"/>
      Καίτοι τὰ μὲν Ἡφαίστου μέτρια· τὸν δὲ Προμηθέα τίς οὐκ οἶδεν οἷα ἔπαθεν,
                        διότι καθʼ ὑπερβολὴν φιλάνθρωπος ἦν; καὶ γὰρ αὖ καὶ τοῦτον εἰς τὴν Σκυθίαν
                        ἀγαγὼν ὁ Ζεὺς ἀνεσταύρωσεν ἐπὶ τοῦ Καυκάσου, τὸν ἀετὸν αὐτῷ παρακαταστήσας
                        τὸ ἧπαρ ὁσημέραι κολάψοντα.
     </p>
     <p lang="it">
      E parimenti parlano della donna, senza parlare all'uomo.
                        lascia che questo bambino dia alla luce Efesto, non felice, ma
                        brutale e rame e pirite, in fumo tutti gli esseri viventi e scintille
                        Non indosso niente che non bruci, e non indosso nemmeno il piede, perché si sporca.
                        dal cadavere, quindi cadde da Zeus dal cielo, e lasciò che il
                        Limnios, che sono coloro che lo hanno accettato, anche se il
                        Fiero come Astianatte dalla torre dei tiranni. 
                        Dicono che Efesto sia moderato, ma Prometeo non vide ciò che soffrì,
                        perché era eccessivamente filantropico? E per questo anche in Scizia
                        quando Zeus crocifisse sul Caucaso, l'aquila che aveva
                        l'Ἣpar dorme durante il giorno.
     </p>
     <p lang="en">
      And likewise they speak of the woman, without speaking to the man.
                        let this child give birth to Hephaestus, not a happy one, but
                        brutal and copper and pyrite, in smoke all living things and sparks
                        I don't wear anything that doesn't burn, and I don't even wear the foot, because it makes it dirty.
                        from the corpse, therefore it fell from Zeus from heaven, and let the
                        Limnios, who are those who have accepted him, even if the
                        As fierce as Astyanax from the tower of tyrants. 
                        They say that Hephaestus is moderate, but Prometheus did not see what he suffered,
                        because he was excessively philanthropic? And because of this also in Scythia
                        when Zeus crucified on the Caucasus, the eagle that had
                        the Ἣpar is asleep during the day.
     </p>
    </div>
    <div n="7" subtype="section" type="textpart">
     <p>
      οὗτος μὲν οὖν ἐξετέλεσε τὴν καταδίκην. ἡ Ῥέα δὲ — χρὴ γὰρ ἴσως καὶ ταῦτα
                        εἰπεῖν — πῶς οὐκ ἀσχημονεῖ καὶ δεινὰ ποιεῖ, γραῦς μὲν ἤδη καὶ ἔξωρος οὖσα
                        καὶ τοσούτων μήτηρ θεῶν, παιδεραστοῦσα δὲ ἔτι καὶ ζηλοτυποῦσα καὶ τὸν Ἄττιν
                        ἐπὶ τῶν λεόντων περιφέρουσα, καὶ ταῦτα μηκέτι χρήσιμον εἶναι δυνάμενον; ὥστε
                        πῶς ἂν ἔτι μέμφοιτό τις ἢ τῇ Ἀφροδίτῃ ὅτι μοιχεύεται, ἢ τῇ Σελήνῃ πρὸς τὸν
                        Ἐνδυμίωνα κατιούσῃ πολλάκις ἐκ μέσης τῆς ὁδοῦ;
     </p>
     <p lang="it">
      Ha quindi eseguito la sentenza. Ma Rhea - perché forse anche questi
                        dicono: come non è brutto e doloroso, scrivimi adesso e all'estero allora
                        e tante divinità madri, ma io amavo i bambini e ero geloso di Attin
                        sui leoni che volteggiano, e questo modello utile è forte? in modo che
                        come se li accusassi o ad Afrodite per aver commesso adulterio, o a Selene per
                        Endimione è sceso molte volte dal centro della strada?
     </p>
     <p lang="en">
      He therefore carried out the sentence. But Rhea - because maybe even these
                        they say - how is it not ugly and painful, write me now and abroad then
                        and so many mother gods, but I was child-loving and jealous of Attin
                        on the lions circling, and is this useful model strong? in order that
                        how if I accuse them either to Aphrodite for committing adultery, or to Selene for
                        Did Endymion come down many times from the middle of the road?
     </p>
    </div>
    <div n="8" subtype="section" type="textpart">
     <p>
      φέρε δὲ ἤδη τούτων ἀφέμενοι τῶν λόγων εἰς αὐτὸν ἀνέλθωμεν τὸν οὐρανὸν
                        ποιητικῶς ἀναπτάμενοι κατὰ τὴν αὐτὴν Ὁμήρῳ καὶ Ἡσιόδῳ ὁδὸν καὶ θεασώμεθα
                        ὅπως διακεκόσμηται τὰ ἄνω. καὶ ὅτι μὲν χαλκοῦς ἐστιν τὰ ἔξω, καὶ πρὸ ἡμῶν
                        τοῦ, Ὁμήρου λέγοντος ἠκούσαμεν ὑπερβάντι δὲ καὶ ἀνακύψαντι μικρὸν εἰς τὸ ἄνω
                        καὶ ἀτεχνῶς ἐπὶ τοῦ νώτου γενομένῳ φῶς τε λαμπρότερον φαίνεται καὶ ἥλιος
                        καθαρώτερος καὶ ἄστρα διαυγέστερα καὶ τὸ πᾶν ἡμέρα καὶ χρυσοῦν τὸ δάπεδον.
                        εἰσιόντων δὲ πρῶτα μὲν οἰκοῦσιν αἱ Ὧραι· πυλωροῦσι γάρ· ἔπειτα δʼ ἡ Ἶρις καὶ
                        ὁ Ἑρμῆς ὄντες ὑπηρέται καὶ ἀγγελιαφόροι τοῦ Διός, ἑξῆς δὲ τοῦ Ἡφαίστου τὸ
                        χαλκεῖον ἀνάμεστον ἁπάσης τέχνης, μετὰ δὲ αἱ τῶν θεῶν
      <pb n="v.3.p.164"/>
      οἰκίαι καὶ τοῦ Διὸς τὰ βασίλεια, ταῦτα πάντα περικαλλῆ τοῦ Ἡφαίστου
                        κατασκευάσαντος.
     </p>
     <p lang="it">
      ma ora, lasciando queste parole, ascendiamo a quel cielo
                        svolgendosi poeticamente lungo lo stesso percorso di Omero ed Esiodo e vediamo
                        come sopra è decorato. e che l'esterno è come il rame, e per noi
                        abbiamo sentito Homer parlare, ma si è alzato un po' più in alto
                        e artificialmente sulla luce nata dal sud, anche il sole appare più luminoso
                        più pulite e le stelle più chiare e ogni giorno dorano il pavimento.
                        ma se prima gli dei abitano con me;
                        Hermes è il servitore e messaggero di Zeus, e accanto a Efesto il
                        il rame tra tutte le arti, ma poi quelle degli dei 
                        le case e i regni di Zeus, tutto intorno a Efesto
                        produttore.
     </p>
     <p lang="en">
      but now, leaving these words, let us ascend to that heaven
                        poetically unfolding along the same path of Homer and Hesiod and we see
                        as the above is decorated. and that the outside is like copper, and to us
                        we heard Homer speaking, but he rose up a little higher
                        and artificially on the south born light, the sun also appears brighter
                        cleaner and stars clearer and every day and they gild the floor.
                        but if first the gods dwell with me;
                        Hermes is the servant and messenger of Zeus, and next to Hephaestus the
                        copper among all art, but after that those of the gods 
                        the houses and kingdoms of Zeus, all these around Hephaestus
                        manufacturer.
     </p>
    </div>
    <div n="9" subtype="section" type="textpart">
     <p>
      <q type="unspecified">
       οἱ δὲ θεοὶ πὰρ Ζηνὶ καθήμενοι —
      </q>
      πρέπει γάρ, οἶμαι,
                        ἄνω· ὄντα μεγαληγορεῖν — ἀποσκοποῦσιν εἰς τὴν γῆν καὶ πάντῃ περιβλέπουσιν
                        ἐπικύπτοντες εἴ ποθεν ὄψονται πῦρ ἀναπτόμενον ἢ ἀναφερομένην κνῖσαν
      <q type="unspecified">
       ἑλισσομένην περὶ καπνῷ.
      </q>
      κἂν μὲν θύῃ τις,
                        εὐωχοῦνται πάντες ἐπικεχηνότες τῷ καπνῷ καὶ τὸ αἷμα πίνοντες τοῖς βωμοῖς
                        προσχεόμενον ˘ ὥσπερ αἱ μυῖαι· ἢν δὲ οἰκοσιτῶσιν, νέκταρ καὶ ἀμβροσία τὸ
                        δεῖπνον. πάλαι μὲν οὖν καὶ ἄνθρωποι συνειστιῶντο καὶ συνέπινον αὐτοῖς, ὁ
                        Ἰξίων καὶ ὁ Τάνταλος· ἐπεὶ δὲ ἦσαν ὑβρισταὶ καὶ λάλοι, ἐκεῖνοι μὲν ἔτι καὶ
                        νῦν κολάζονται, ἄβατος δὲ τῷ θνητῷ γένει καὶ ἀπόρρητος ὁ οὐρανός.
     </p>
     <p lang="it">
      Ma gli dei sono seduti - deve essere, lo sono,
                        in alto; esseri di grande statura: mirano alla terra e guardano sempre
                        che si verifica, dove si vede un incendio che brucia o viene segnalato un incendio che brucia attorno al fumo. anche se li odia,
                        benedici tutti coloro che supplicano al fumo e bevono il sangue sugli altari
                        offerti come i muscoli, ma se nutrono, nettare e ambrosia;
                        assonnato Una volta anche le persone vivevano insieme e vivevano insieme a loro, i
                        Issione e Tantalo; e c'erano insulti e pettegolezzi, quelli senza anni e
                        ora sono all'inferno, ma il paradiso è nascosto alla nascita mortale.
     </p>
     <p lang="en">
      But the gods are seated - must be, I am,
                        above; beings of great stature - they aim at the earth and always watch
                        occuring, where a fire is seen burning or a fire is reported burning around smoke. even if he hates them,
                        bless all those supplicating to the smoke and drinking the blood at the altars
                        offered as the muscles; but if they feed, nectar and ambrosia the
                        sleepy Once upon a time, people also lived together and lived together with them, the
                        Ixion and Tantalus; and there were insults and gossips, those without years and
                        now they are in hell, but heaven is hidden from mortal birth.
     </p>
    </div>
    <div n="10" subtype="section" type="textpart">
     <p>
      τοιοῦτος ὁ βίος τῶν θεῶν. τοιγαροῦν καὶ οἱ ἄνθρωποι συνῳδὰ τούτοις καὶ
                        ἀκόλουθα περὶ τὰς θρησκείας ἐπιτηδεύουσιν. καὶ πρῶτον μὲν ὕλας ἀπετέμοντο
                        καὶ ὄρη ἀνέθεσαν καὶ ὄρνεα καθιέρωσαν καὶ φυτὰ ἐπεφήμισαν ἑκάστῳ θεῷ. μετὰ
                        δὲ νειμάμενοι κατὰ ἔθνη σέβουσι καὶ πολίτας αὐτῶν ἀποφαίνουσιν, ὁ μὲν Δελφὸς
                        τὸν Ἀπόλλω καὶ ὁ Δήλιος, ὁ δὲ Ἀθηναῖος τὴν Ἀθηνᾶν — μαρτυρεῖται γοῦν τὴν
                        οἰκειότητα τῷ ὀνόματι — καὶ τὴν Ἥραν ὁ Ἀργεῖος καὶ ὁ Μυγδόνιος τὴν Ῥέαν καὶ
                        τὴν Ἀφροδίτην ὁ Πάφιος. οἱ δʼ αὖ Κρῆτες οὐ γενέσθαι παρʼ αὐτοῖς οὐδὲ
                        τραφῆναι μόνον τὸν Δία λέγουσιν, ἀλλὰ καὶ τάφον αὐτοῦ δεικνύουσιν· καὶ ἡμεῖς
                        ἄρα τοσοῦτον ἠπατήμεθα χρόνον οἰόμενοι
      <pb n="v.3.p.166"/>
      τὸν Δία βροντᾶν
                        τε καὶ ὕειν καὶ τὰ ἄλλα πάντα ἐπιτελεῖν, ὁ δὲ ἐλελήθει πάλαι τεθνεὼς παρὰ
                        Κρησὶ τεθαμμένος.
     </p>
     <p lang="it">
      tale è la vita degli dei. anche il popolo combatte insieme a loro
                        seguendo la religione fingono. e prima di tutto con una spalla mancante
                        E assegnarono montagne e stabilirono aquile e piante a ciascun dio. Dopo
                        ma divisi in nazioni, rispettano e dichiarano cittadino quello di Delfi
                        Apollo e Delios e Athenaios Atena - questo è testimoniato
                        familiarità con il nome - e Argeios e Mygdonius chiamavano Æran e Ærea e
                        Afrodite Paphios. I dʼaὖ Cretesi non nasceranno senza di loro
                        solo Zeus viene nutrito, dicono, ma indicano anche la sua tomba e noi;
                        così passiamo tanto tempo a sognare Zeus tuonante
                        questi e quelli e il resto avvengono sempre, ma colui che parla prima
                        La crisi è stata sepolta.
     </p>
     <p lang="en">
      such is the life of the gods. the people also fight together with them
                        following about religion they pretend. and first of all, with a cutaway
                        And they assigned mountains and established eagles and plants to each god. after
                        but divided into nations, they respect and declare their citizens, the one at Delphi
                        Apollo and Delios, and Athenaios Athena - it is witnessed that
                        familiarity with the name - and Argeios and Mygdonius called Æran and Ærea and
                        Aphrodite Paphios. The dʼ aὖ Cretans will not be born apart from them
                        only Zeus is fed, they say, but they also point to his tomb; and we
                        so we spend so much time dreaming of Zeus thundering
                        these and those and the rest always come to pass, but the one who speaks before
                        Crises was buried.
     </p>
    </div>
    <div n="11" subtype="section" type="textpart">
     <p>
      ἔπειτα δὲ ναοὺς ἐγείραντες ἵνα αὐτοῖς μὴ ἄοικοι μηδὲ ἀνέστιοι δῆθεν ὦσιν,
                        εἰκόνας αὐτοῖς ἀπεικάζουσιν παρακαλέσαντες ἢ Πραξιτέλην ἢ Πολύκλειτον ἢ
                        Φειδίαν, οἱ δὲ οὐκ οἶδʼ ὅπου ˘ ἰδόντες ἀναπλάττουσι γενειήτην μὲν τὸν Δία,
                        παῖδα δὲ εἰς ἀεὶ τὸν Ἀπόλλωνα καὶ τὸν. Ἑρμῆν ὑπηνήτην καὶ τὸν Ποσειδῶνα
                        κυανοχαίτην καὶ γλαυκῶπιν τὴν Ἀθηνᾶν. ὅμως δʼ οὖν οἱ παριόντες εἰς τὸν νεὼν
                        οὔτε τὸν ἐξ Ἰνδῶν ἐλέφαντα ἔτι οἴονται ὁρᾶν οὔτε τὸ ἐκ τῆς Θρᾴκης
                        μεταλλευθὲν χρυσίον ἀλλʼ αὐτὸν τὸν Κρόνου καὶ Ῥέας, εἰς τὴν γῆν ὑπὸ Φειδίου
                        μετῳκισμένον καὶ τὴν Πισαίων ἐρημίαν ἐπισκοπεῖν κεκελευσμένον, ἀγαπῶντα εἰ
                        διὰ πέντε ὅλων ἐτῶν θύσει τις αὐτῷ πάρεργον Ὀλυμπίων.
     </p>
     <p lang="it">
      ma disse a coloro che erigevano i templi, affinché davanti a loro non si vedessero né i disabitati né i malati,
                        immagine a loro fingendosi supplicanti o Prassitele o Policleto o
                        Fidia, ma coloro che non hanno visto dove vedono, riproducono la generazione con Zeus,
                        ma gioca nel sacro Apollo e nel. Hermes sostenne Poseidone
                        Atena aveva i capelli blu ed era glauca. ma guarda dunque quelli presenti nel nuovo
                        né l'elefante dell'India che si vede, né quello della Tracia
                        oro estratto tranne quello di Saturno e Rea, nella terra sotto Fidio
                        trasmigrato e a visitare il deserto di Pisa
                        per cinque anni interi gli sacrificò i modelli di Olimpia.
     </p>
     <p lang="en">
      but he said to those who were erecting temples, so that to them neither the uninhabited nor the sick should be seen,
                        image to them pretending to be supplicants or Praxiteles or Polycletos or
                        Phidias, but those who have not seen where they see, reproduce the generation with Zeus,
                        but play in the hallowed Apollo and the. Hermes supported Poseidon
                        Athena was blue-haired and glaucous. but see, then, those present in the new
                        nor the elephant from India that can be seen nor the one from Thrace
                        mined gold but that of Saturn and Rhea, in the earth under Pheidius
                        transmigrated and to visit the desert of Pisa
                        for five whole years he sacrificed to him the paragons of Olympia.
     </p>
    </div>
    <div n="12" subtype="section" type="textpart">
     <p>
      θέμενοι δὲ βωμοὺς καὶ προρρήσεις καὶ περιρραντήρια προσάγουσι τὰς θυσίας,
                        βοῦν μὲν ἀροτῆρα ὁ γεωργός, ἄρνα δὲ ὁ ποιμὴν καὶ αἶγα ὁ αἰπόλος, ὁ δέ τις
                        λιβανωτὸν ἢ πόπανον, ὁ δὲ πένης ἱλάσατο τὸν θεὸν κύσας μόνον τὴν ἑαυτοῦ
                        δεξιάν.˘ ἀλλʼ οἵ γε θύοντες — ἐπʼ ἐκείνους γὰρ ἐπάνειμι — στεφανώσαντες τὸ
                        ζῷον καὶ πολύ γε πρότερον ἐξετάσαντες εἰ ἐντελὲς εἴη, ἵνα μηδὲ τῶν ἀχρήστων
                        τι κατασφάττωσιν, προσάγουσι τῷ βωμῷ καὶ φονεύουσιν ἐν ὀφθαλμοῖς τοῦ θεοῦ
                        γοερόν τι μυκώμενον καὶ ὡς τὸ εἰκὸς εὐφημοῦν καὶ ἡμίφωνον ἤδη τῇ θυσίᾳ
                        ἐπαυλοῦν. τίς οὐκ
      <pb n="v.3.p.168"/>
      ἂν εἰκάσειεν ἥδεσθαι ταῦτα ὁρῶντας
                        τοὺς θεούς;
     </p>
     <p lang="it">
      ed avendo eretto altari, profezie e incensieri, offrono sacrifici,
                        il contadino ara, ma il pastore e la capra rifiutano, e il
                        incenso o incenso, ma la penna salvò al dio solo i suoi
                        a destra ˘ ἀλλʼ οἵ ge thyontes — su quelli per il vento — a coronamento del
                        vita e molto tempo fa esaminandola nella sua interezza, in modo che non ci fosse nulla di inutile
                        cosa realizzano, portano all'altare e uccidono agli occhi di Dio
                        belli e ammuffiti e come se esultassero e fossero già sommessi al sacrificio
                        ritardano. tis οὐκ Ἀκασιεν ἥεσται ταῶτα ἐρίντα
                        gli dei;
     </p>
     <p lang="en">
      and having set up altars, and prophecies, and censers, they offer the sacrifices,
                        the farmer plows, but the shepherd and the goat refuse, and the
                        frankincense or incense, but the pen saved the god only his own
                        on the right. ˘ ἀλλʼ οἵ ge thyontes — on those for the wind — crowning the
                        life and long ago examining it in its entirety, so that none of the useless
                        what do they accomplish, bring to the altar and kill in the eyes of God
                        beautiful and moldy and as if they were exulting and half-voiced already at the sacrifice
                        they delay. tis οὐκ Ἀκασιεν ἥεσται ταῶτα ἐρίντα
                        the gods;
     </p>
    </div>
    <div n="13" subtype="section" type="textpart">
     <p>
      καὶ τὸ μὲν πρόγραμμά φησι μὴ παριέναι εἰς τὸ εἴσω τῶν περιρραντηρίων ὅστις
                        μὴ καθαρός ἐστιν . τὰς χεῖρας· ὁ δὲ ἱερεὺς αὐτὸς ἕστηκεν ᾑμαγμένος καὶ ὥσπερ
                        ὁ Κύκλωψ ἐκεῖνος ἀνατέμνων καὶ τὰ ἔγκατα ἐξαιρῶν καὶ καρδιουλκῶν καὶ τὸ αἷμα
                        τῷ βωμῷ περιχέων καὶ τί γάρ οὐκ εὐσεβὲς ἐπιτελῶν; ἐπὶ πᾶσι δὲ πῦρ ἀνακαύσας
                        ἐπέθηκε φέρων αὐτῇ δορᾷ τὴν αἶγα καὶ αὐτοῖς ἐρίοις τὸ πρόβατον ἡ δὲ κνῖσα
                        θεσπέσιος καὶ ἱεροπρεπὴς χωρεῖ ἄνω καὶ εἰς αὐτὸν τὸν οὐρανὸν ἠρέμα
                        διασκίδναται. ὁ μέν γε Σκύθης πάσας τὰς θυσίας ἀφεὶς καὶ ἡγησάμενος ταπεινὰς
                        αὐτοὺς τοὺς ἀνθρώπους τῇ Ἀρτέμιδι παρίστησι καὶ οὕτως ποιῶν ἀρέσκει τὴν
                        θεόν.
     </p>
     <p lang="it">
      e il programma non entra negli allegati that
                        Non è pulito. mani; ma questo prete era stregato e come
                        Ciclope, quel dissettore, e il sangue
                        All'altare ti circondi e perché non lo compi devotamente? Ma non hai ascoltato nessun fuoco
                        Arrivò portando la pelle di capra su di lei e le pecore dall'altra parte, ma Knisa
                        atto solenne e sacro sopra e nello stesso cielo
                        è fatto a pezzi. il sovrano scita che ha rinunciato a tutti i sacrifici ed è un umile sovrano
                        presenta questi uomini ad Artemide e chi le piace
                        Dio
     </p>
     <p lang="en">
      and the program does not fit inside the enclosures that
                        He is not clean. hands; but this priest was bewitched and as
                        Cyclops, that dissector, and the blood
                        To the altar you surround yourself and why do you not perform devoutly? But you did not listen to any fire
                        He came, carrying the goat's skin on her, and the sheep on the other side, but Knisa
                        solemn and sacred fit above and in the same heaven
                        is torn apart. the Scythian ruler who has given up all sacrifices and is a humble ruler
                        present these men to Artemis, and so whom she pleases
                        god
     </p>
    </div>
    <div n="14" subtype="section" type="textpart">
     <p>
      ταῦτα μὲν δὴ ἴσως μέτρια καὶ τὰ ὑπʼ Ἀσσυρίων γιγνόμενα καὶ ὑπὸ Φρυγῶν καὶ
                        Λυδῶν, ʼ ἢν δʼ εἰς τὴν Αἴγυπτον ἔλθῃς, τότε δὴ τότε ὄψει πολλὰ τὰ σεμνὰ καὶ
                        ὡς ἀληθῶς ἄξια τοῦ οὐρανοῦ, κριοπρόσωπον μὲν τὸν Δία, κυνοπρόσωπον δὲ τὸν
                        βέλτιστον Ἑρμῆν καὶ τὸν Πᾶνα ὅλον τράγον καὶ ἶβίν τινα καὶ κροκόδειλον
                        ἕτερον καὶ πίθηκον. εἰ δʼ ἐθέλεις καὶ ταῦτα δαήμεναι, ὄφρʼ εὖ εἰδῇς, ἀκούσῃ
                        πολλῶν σοφιστῶν καὶ γραμματέων καὶ προφητῶν ἐξυρημένων διηγουμένων, —
                        πρότερον δέ, φησὶν ὁ λόγος,
      <q type="unspecified">
       θύρας δʼ ἐπίθεσθε
                            βέβηλοι
      </q>
      <pb n="v.3.p.170"/>
      — ὡς ἄρα ὑπὸ τὸν πόλεμον ˘ καὶ τῶν γιγάντων τὴν
                        ἐπανάστασιν οἱ θεοὶ φοβηθέντες ἧκον εἰς τὴν Αἴγυπτον ὡς δὴ ἐνταῦθα λησόμενοι
                        τοὺς πολεμίους· εἶθʼ ὁ μὲν αὐτῶν ὑπέδυ τράγον, ὁ δὲ κριὸν ὑπὸ τοῦ δέους, ὁ
                        δὲ θηρίον ἢ ὄρνεον διὸ δὴ εἰσέτι καὶ νῦν φυλάττεσθαι τὰς τότε μορφὰς τοῖς
                        θεοῖς. ταῦτα γὰρ ἀμέλει ἐν τοῖς ἀδύτοις ἀπόκειται γραφέντα πλεῖον ἢ πρὸ ἐτῶν
                        μυρίων.
     </p>
     <p lang="it">
      questi, forse non moderatamente, e quelli fatti sotto gli Assiri e sotto i Frigi e
                        Lidi, se venite in Egitto, non guardate molti modesti e
                        come veramente degno del paradiso, faccia d'uomo con Zeus, ma faccia di cane
                        Soprattutto, Hermes e Pana, tutti i draghi, le creature viventi e i coccodrilli
                        un altro e una scimmia. se non vuoi anche tu queste cose, se le sai, ascolta
                        di molti sofisti e scribi e profeti oratori scomunicati, —
                        per prima cosa, lascia che la parola venga pronunciata, attacca la porta
                            profano
 — come quindi sotto la guerra˘ e dei giganti
                        gli dei, terrorizzati, tornarono in Egitto come se non fossero stati dimenticati lì
                        i guerrieri; quello sotto di loro è un drago, e l'ariete sotto timore, il
                        Ma non essere una bestia o un uccello, e ora stai proteggendo il quando li guardi
                        di Dio. per queste cose trascura tra quelle che non appartengono a quelle scritte più o prima di lui
                        miriadi
     </p>
     <p lang="en">
      these, perhaps not moderately, and those made under the Assyrians and under the Phrygians and
                        Lydians, if you come to Egypt, then don't then look at many modest and
                        as truly worthy of heaven, man-faced with Zeus, but dog-faced
                        Best of all, Hermes and Pana, all the dragons and living creatures and crocodiles
                        another and a monkey. if you don't want these things too, if you know, listen
                        of many sophists and scribes and prophets excommunicated orators, —
                        first, let the word be spoken, attack the door
                            profane
 — as thus under the war ˘ and of the giants
                        the gods, terrified, returned to Egypt as if they had not been forgotten there
                        the warriors; the one under them is a dragon, and the ram under awe, the
                        But do not be a beast or a bird, and now you are guarding the when you look at them
                        gods. for these things he neglects among those who do not belong to those who were written more or before him
                        myriads
     </p>
    </div>
    <div n="15" subtype="section" type="textpart">
     <p>
      αἱ δὲ θυσίαι καὶ παρʼ ἐκείνοις αἱ αὐταί, πλὴν ὅτι πενθοῦσι τὸ ἱερεῖον καὶ
                        κόπτονται περιστάντες ἤδη πεφονευμένον. οἱ δὲ καὶ θάπτουσι μόνον
                        ἀποσφάξαντες. ὁ μὲν γὰρ Ἆπις, ὁ μέγιστος αὐτοῖς θεός, ἐὰν ἀποθάνῃ, τίς οὕτω
                        περὶ πολλοῦ ποιεῖται τὴν κόμην ὅστις οὐκ ἀπεξύρησε καὶ ψιλὸν ˘ ἐπὶ τῆς
                        κεφαλῆς τὸ πένθος ἐπεδείξατο, κἂν τὸν Νίσου ἔχῃ πλόκαμον τὸν πορφυροῦν; ἔστι
                        δὲ ὁ Ἆπις ἐξ ἀγέλης θεός, ἐπὶ τῷ προτέρῳ χειροτονούμενος ὡς πολὺ καλλίων καὶ
                        σεμνότερος τῶν ἰδιωτῶν Βοῶν. ταῦτα οὕτω γιγνόμενα καὶ ὑπὸ τῶν πολλῶν
                        πιστευόμενα δεῖσθαί μοι δοκεῖ τοῦ μὲν ἐπιτιμήσοντος οὐδενός, Ἡρακλείτου δέ
                        τινος ἢ Δημοκρίτου, τοῦ μὲν γελασομένου τὴν ἄγνοιαν αὐτῶν, τοῦ δὲ τὴν ἄνοιαν
                        ὀδυρουμένου.
     </p>
     <p lang="it">
      E i sacrifici sono gli stessi, tranne che il prete e
                        ci sono casi in cui sta già morendo. e si limitano a seppellire
                        macellai. poiché se muore, il dio più grande per loro,
                        si parla molto dell'uomo che non ha speso un solo centesimo per lei
                        del capo era mostrato il lutto, e Nisso ha un mantello purpureo? ἔστι
                        e il dio della mandria, Opis, essendo ordinato sul davanti come molto bello e
                        più modesto dei Boa privati. queste cose vengono fatte così e da molti
                        Le superstizioni in cui credo non mi mettono alla prova con nessuno che mi stima, Eraclito
                        di Democrito, che non rideva della loro ignoranza, ma della loro follia
                        di sofferenza
     </p>
     <p lang="en">
      And the sacrifices are the same, except that the priest and
                        there are instances of him already dying. and they only bury
                        butchers. for if he dies, the greatest god to them,
                        much is said of the man who has not spent a single penny on her
                        of the head the mourning was shown, and Nissus has a purple cloak? ἔστι
                        and the god of the herd, Opis, being ordained on the front as very beautiful and
                        more modest than the private Boas. these things being done like this and by the many
                        Believed superstitions test me of none who esteems me, Heraclitus
                        of Democritus, who did not laugh at their ignorance, but at their insanity
                        of suffering
     </p>
    </div>
   </div>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
