<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title xml:lang="en">Μυθίαμβοι Αἰσώπειοι</title>
        <author>
          <persName>BABRIUS</persName>
          
        </author>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Encodage automatique TEI P5</resp>
          <name>zoomathia_encoder.py v3.0</name>
          <date when="2026-07-11">2026-07-11</date>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Projet Zoomathia (ANR-21-CE27-0012)</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Universite Cote d'Azur, Nice, France</pubPlace>
        <date when="2026-07-11">2026-07-11</date>
        <availability>
          <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0</licence>
        </availability>
        <idno type="zoomathia"/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Encode automatiquement par zoomathia_encoder.py v3.0 - Projet Zoomathia</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language ident="en">anglais</language>
      </langUsage>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="zoomathia">
          <term>Zoomathia</term>
          <term>animaux</term>
          <term>inconnu</term>
          <term>anglais</term>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>Fichier encode automatiquement dans le cadre du projet Zoomathia (ANR).
        Encodage produit par zoomathia_encoder.py v3.0. Verification humaine recommandee.</p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>Balisage automatique des structures textuelles et des entites nommees
        pertinentes pour Zoomathia (animaux, plantes, personnes, lieux).</p>
        <correction status="unknown">
          <p>Encodage automatique - erreurs possibles, revision manuelle recommandee.</p>
        </correction>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
<div type="book" n="1">
  <div type="chapter" n="20">
    <p>Fab. <name type="number">XX</name>. — .</p>
    <p>From <name type="work">Fables of Babrius</name>, in Two Parts, translated into English Verse from the text of Sir <persName>G. C. Lewis</persName>, by the Rev. <persName>John Davies</persName>, M.A., <placeName>London</placeName>: <placeName>Lockwood &amp; Co.</placeName>,1860; pp. 3 to 39.</p>
    <p>___________________</p>
    <p><name type="work">THE FABLES OF BABRIUS</name>,</p>
    <p>IN TWO PARTS. Translated into English verse from the text of Sir <persName>G. C. Lewis</persName>. BY THE REV. <persName>JOHN DAVIES</persName>, M.A. ___________________</p>
    <p>The race of just men flourish’d first, of old; Its name, son <persName>Branchus</persName>, was the “age of gold.” * * * * * Third after these was born a brazen race, And next the <name type="deity">god-sprung heroes</name> found their place; Fifth came a stock depraved, an iron root. But ’twas the golden age, when every <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">brute</name> Had voice articulate, in speech was skill’d, And the mid-forests with its synods fill’d. The tongues of <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">rock</name> and <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">pine-leaf</name> then were free; To <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">ship</name> and <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">sailor</name> then would speak the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">sea</name>; <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Sparrows</name> with <persName>farmers</persName> would shrewd talk maintain; <name type="placeName">Earth</name> gave all <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">fruits</name>, nor ask’d for toil again. <persName>Mortals</persName> and <name type="deity">gods</name> were wont to mix as friends. To which conclusion all the teaching tends Of sage old <persName>Æsop</persName>; him, to whom belong <name type="work">Fables</name> set forth in free, outspoken song, These should a place in thy remembrance get; Therefore for thee this <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">honeycomb</name> I set, Desirous, as I hive it, to assuage The harsh <foreign xml:lang="en">Iambic</foreign>’s bitterness and rage.</p>
  </div>
</div>
<div type="book" n="2">
   <div type="section" n="1">
      <p>The <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">griffin</name>-like productions, over-wise;</p>
   </div>
   <div type="section" n="2">
      <p>Now I in simple speech my <foreign xml:lang="la">fables</foreign> set,</p>
      <p>Nor care the famed <foreign xml:lang="la">Iambic</foreign>’s teeth to whet.</p>
      <p>Rather to dull their edge, to soothe their stings,</p>
      <p>Aims he, who now this second volume sings.</p>
   </div>
   <div type="section" n="3">
      <p><persName>Cybisass</persName>, or <persName>Cybissus</persName>. <persName>Theon</persName> and <persName>Apthonius</persName>, later teachers of rhetoric, mention <persName>Cybissus</persName> the <placeName>Libyan</placeName>, and <persName>Connis</persName> the <placeName>Cilician</placeName>, as fabulists.</p>
      <p>Cf. <persName>Muller</persName> and <persName>Donaldson</persName>, <quote>Gr. Lit. i. 193</quote>. <foreign xml:lang="la">Fables</foreign> of the <placeName>Phrygians</placeName>, <placeName>Cilicians</placeName>, and <placeName>Cyprians</placeName>, are mentioned by Greek writers.</p>
      <p>See <persName>Bernhardy</persName>, Vol. I. p. 58.</p>
   </div>
</div>
<div type="book" n="3">
   <p>A <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">skilful archer</name> the hill country sought,</p>
   <p>Intent on sport. His coming quickly brought</p>
   <p>To every <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">wild beast</name> fear and headlong flight.</p>
   <p>The <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">lion</name> only tarried to invite</p>
   <p>The archer’s onslaught. “Haste not! Prythee stay,”</p>
   <p>The stranger said; “nor hope to win the day.</p>
   <p>“Learn from mine envoy, whom you soon shall meet,</p>
   <p>“Your wisest plan.” Forth sped his <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">arrow</name> fleet</p>
   <p>From no great distance; and was buried deep</p>
   <p>In the beast’s flank. Afraid his post to keep</p>
   <p>The wounded <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">lion</name> straight essay’d to fly</p>
   <p>To where the lonesome woodland thickets lie.</p>
   <p>But, lo! A <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">fox</name> was standing at his side,</p>
   <p>Who urg’d him still the archer’s shafts to bide.</p>
   <p>“Not so!” the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">lion</name> said; “beguile not me!</p>
   <p>“Yon envoy came but now so bitterly,</p>
   <p>“That doubly fierce his master needs must be.”</p>
</div>
<div type="chapter" n="123">
   <p>Trenching his <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">vineyard</name> once a <persName>husbandman</persName></p>
   <p>His <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">mattock</name> lost; and to inquire began,</p>
   <p>If it had gone by any workman’s theft.</p>
   <p>But each denied. When no resource was left,</p>
   <p>To put them on their oaths, he took them all</p>
   <p>Up to the <placeName>city</placeName>. ’Tis our wont to call</p>
   <p>The country <name type="deity">gods</name> poor folks: but those who dwell</p>
   <p>In walls, we deem, are true, and order well.</p>
   <p>Now in a <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">fountain</name> in the <placeName>foregate street</placeName></p>
   <p>The party stay’d to rest, and wash’d their feet.</p>
   <p>Just then the crier rich rewards was telling</p>
   <p>To him who’d show who robb’d the sacred dwelling.</p>
   <p>The <persName>farmer</persName> heard, and said, “My journey’s vain!</p>
   <p>“If the <name type="deity">god</name> knows not, who has robbed his fane,</p>
   <p>“And but from men, for bribes, the news receives,</p>
   <p>“How can he know, or find out, other thieves?”</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="4">
   <p>A <persName>Goatherd</persName> wish’d to gather home his flock; Some came; some tarried; on a cleft of rock The fragrant shoots of <name type="plant">mastich</name> and <name type="plant">goatsrue</name> One <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">she-goat</name> into disobedience drew. Quickly the hireling lifted up a stone, Which brake her horn, tho’ from a distance thrown. And now he sued her: “<name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Goat</name> and fellow-slave, “By <name type="deity">Pan</name>, the patron of these glens, I crave, “Do not thou to my lord this act proclaim, “I meant not that the stone should take good aim.” “Nay, how,” said she, “a plain fact can I hide? “My horn is telltale, tho’ my tongue be tied.”</p>
   <p>His late-cast net ashore a fisher drew, Enclosing <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">fish</name>, not all alike nor few; The smallest, taking flight, contrived to get Safe through the bottom of the meshy net, Whilst in the ship the greater emptied lay. ’Tis surely safe, and farthest from harm’s way, To be but small: for you shall seldom see The high in rank escape calamity.</p>
   <p>Two <placeName>Tanagræan</placeName> <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">cocks</name> a fight began; Their spirit is, ’tis said, as that of man; Of these the beaten bird, a mass of blows, For shame into a corner creeping goes; The other to the housetop quickly flew, And there in triumph flapped his wings, and crew. But him an <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">eagle</name> lifted from the roof, And bore away. His fellow gain’d a proof That oft the wages of defeat are best, None else remain’d the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">hens</name> to interest. Wherefore, O <persName>man</persName>, beware of boastfulness, Should fortune lift thee, others to depress, Many are saved by lack of her caress.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="5">
   <p>A <persName>fisherman</persName> , who all the <name type="place">seashore</name> drain’d,</p>
   <p>While he with slender rod sweet life maintain’d,</p>
   <p>Once caught with <name type="animal">horsehair</name> line a tiny <name type="animal">fish</name>,</p>
   <p>Ill-suited for the frying-pan or dish.</p>
   <p>The gasping <name type="animal">fish</name> its captor thus besought:</p>
   <p>“What am I worth? For what shall I be bought?</p>
   <p>10 “I’m not half-grown! whom on yon rocky <name type="place">shore</name></p>
   <p>“My mother in the <name type="plant">sea-weed</name> lately bore.</p>
   <p>“Now let me go; oh, kill me not in vain,</p>
   <p>“And you shall catch me when you come again,</p>
   <p>“On <name type="plant">sea-weed</name> food ere then grown large and fine,</p>
   <p>“And meet to grace a board, where rich men dine.”</p>
   <p>As thus she prayed, she raised a piteous moan</p>
   <p>And panted much; but the old man was stone.</p>
   <p>Vain was her hope with winning words to plead;</p>
   <p>He said, while piercing her with ruthless reed:</p>
   <p>“Who holds not fast a small but certain prize,</p>
   <p>Is but a fool, to seek uncertainties.”</p>
</div>
<div type="chapter" n="6">
   <p>A <persName>man</persName>, who kept a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">horse</name>, along the way unladen used to lead him, and to lay his burden on an aged <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">ass</name>, who groaned, and coming to the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">horse</name> his fate bemoaned.</p>
   <p>11 “Wouldst thou but share my load, I might survive,” said he, “but else I sha’n’t be long alive.” “Move on,” the other cried; “don’t worry me!”</p>
   <p>The <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">ass</name> crept on reproved; and presently sank under toil, and died as he had said; his master therefore set the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">horse</name> instead beside him, shifted all the weight, and laid this and the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">ass</name>’s skin, when it was flay’d, with all its trappings, on the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">horse</name>’s back:</p>
   <p>He cried, “Ah, ill advised! alack, alack! I would not bear a part, however small; and now constraint hath laid upon me all.”</p>
   <p>An <persName>Arab</persName>, having heap’d his <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">camel</name>’s back, ask’d if he chose to take the upward track or downward; and the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">beast</name> had sense to say, “Am I cut off then from the level way?”</p>
   <div type="section" n="9">
      <p>12 <persName>IX</persName>. THE <persName>FISHERMAN</persName> PIPING. (P. F. 27.)</p>
      <p>A <persName>fisher</persName> play’d the pipes with wondrous skill, and hoping shoals of <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">fish</name>, of their own will would to the sweet sound of his piping throng, let down his net, and piped a tuneful song.</p>
      <p>But when his breath was spent, his piping nought, he cast again, and <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">fish</name> in numbers caught.</p>
      <p>These panting here and there ashore he spied, and, as he wash’d his net, thus sharply cried;</p>
      <p>“Dance without music now! Had ye been wise, ye had before danced to my melodies.”</p>
      <p>Indifference is oft a losing game; but when you catch the prize, at which you aim, then is your time to ridicule and blame.</p>
   </div>
</div>
<div type="section" n="7">
   <p>A <persName>man</persName>, enamour’d of his ugly slave, <persName>An arrant slut</persName>, to her for asking gave whate’er she would. Hence, as more gauds she wins, and trails fine purple o’er her slattern shins, at wife and mistress she defiance flings; but <name type="deity">Venus</name>, as the cause of these good things, with lamps she fain would honour, and each day make offering, supplicate, pay vows, and pray; till to her came the goddess, in her sleep, and, while the house was hush’d in slumber deep, said, “Thank me not, as tho’ I’d made thee fair; to him that thinks thee so, a hate I bear.” Whoso in what is foul can beauty find, is surely God-abhorr’d, and halt in mind.</p>
   <p>A <persName>man</persName>, that on his <name type="plant">vines</name>’ and <name type="plant">orchards</name>’ foe, the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">fox</name>, a strange affront design’d to throw, bandag’d its tail with tow, applied a light, and sent it forth. Now Heaven’s just oversight led the flame-bearer to its captor’s fields; it was the time for crops, when harvest yields a hopeful prospect of abundant share; the man pursued, deploring wasted care; and <name type="deity">Ceres</name> did not bless his threshing-floor. One should be meek, and ne’er be vexèd sore. Anger, a vengeance worth avoidance hath, that bringeth damage to the quick-to-wrath.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="8">
   <p>Far from men’s fields the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">swallow</name> forth had flown,</p>
   <p>When she espied amid the woodlands lone</p>
   <p>The <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">nightingale</name>, sweet songstress. Her lament</p>
   <p>Was <persName>Itys</persName> to his doom untimely sent.</p>
   <p>Each knew the other through the mournful strain,</p>
   <p>Flew to embrace, and in sweet talk remain.</p>
   <p>Then said the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">swallow</name>, “Dearest, liv’st thou still?</p>
   <p>Ne’er have I seen thee, since thy <placeName>Thracian</placeName> ill.</p>
   <p>Some cruel fate hath ever come between;</p>
   <p>Our virgin lives till now apart have been.</p>
   <p>Come to the fields: revisit homes of men:</p>
   <p>Come dwell with me, a comrade dear, again,</p>
   <p>Where thou shalt charm the swains, no savage brood:</p>
   <p>Dwell near men’s haunts, and quit the open wood:</p>
   <p>One roof, one chamber, sure, can house the two,</p>
   <p>Or dost prefer the nightly frozen dew,</p>
   <p>And day-god’s heat? a wild-wood life and drear?</p>
   <p>Come, clever songstress, to the light more near.”</p>
   <p>To whom the sweet-voiced <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">nightingale</name> replied:</p>
   <p>“Still on these lonesome ridges let me bide;</p>
   <p>Nor seek to part me from the mountain glen;</p>
   <p>I shun, since <placeName>Athens</placeName>, man, and haunts of men;</p>
   <p>To mix with them, their dwelling place to view,</p>
   <p>Stirs up old grief, and opens woes anew.”</p>
   <p>Some consolation for an evil lot</p>
   <p>Lies in the wise words, in song, in crowds forgot.</p>
   <p>But sore the pang, when, where you once were great,</p>
   <p>Again men see you, housed in mean estate.</p>
</div>
<div type="chapter" n="12">
   <p>Fab. XII. — This fable is based on the mythical story of <persName>Procne</persName>, <persName>Philomela</persName>, and <persName>Itys</persName>. The former of the sisters was transformed into a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">swallow</name>, the latter into a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">nightingale</name>. And the fable expresses the habits of each bird, the one building its nest near men’s homes, and under their roofs, the other apart in far retreats. See <quote>Ov. Met. vi. 668</quote>. For a full account of the legend, the English reader may consult <persName>Grote</persName>’s <title>History of Greece</title>, Vol. I. p. 269-271. Compare also <persName>Babrius</persName>, Part II, Fab. XXXVII. and Part II, Fab. XC on the same subject.</p>
</div>
<div type="chapter" n="22">
   <p>Ibid, v. 22 — <persName>Philomela</persName>’s woes began after she had left <placeName>Athens</placeName>, on a visit to her sister <persName>Procne</persName>, whose husband <persName>Tereus</persName> conceived for her a fatal passion, which caused all the tragic tale, on which the Greek poets so much delight to dwell.</p>
   <p>Thin nets a farmer o’er his furrows spread, And caught the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">cranes</name> that on his tillage fed: And him a limping <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">stork</name> began to pray, Who fell with them into the farmer’s way: 17 “I am no <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">crane</name>: I don’t consume the grain: That I’m a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">stork</name> is from my colour plain; A <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">stork</name>, than which no better bird doth live: I to my father aid and succour give.” The man replied: “Good <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">stork</name>, I cannot tell Your ways of life: but this I know full well, I caught you with the spoilers of my seed: With them, with whom I found you, you must bleed.” Walk with the bad, and hate will be as strong ’Gainst you as them, e’en though you no man wrong.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="10">
   <p>A <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">bear</name> for man was boasting fondness rare, Whose corpse, he urged, he was not wont to tear. To whom quoth <persName>Reynard</persName>, “Were the choice my own, “You should tear corpses, but let life alone; “Let none that hurt my life, my death bemoan.”</p>
   <p>A <persName>Theban</persName> and <persName>Athenian</persName> took one road, And thence, no marvel, conversation flow’d. They came to speak of heroes, in their walk, And, after long and needless talk, The <persName>Theban</persName> fain <persName>Alcmena</persName>’s son would prove Greatest of men, and now of gods above. Th’ <persName>Athenian</persName> argued, that far nobler fate Was that of <persName>Theseus</persName>, so divine his state, Compared with <persName>Herc’les</persName> and his servile lot: And soon the wordy talker victory got. The other, <persName>Theban</persName>-like, in words outmatch’d, Thus, with rough wit, the argument despatch’d: “There: you prevail! So then may we displease <persName>Theseus</persName>: and you <persName>Athenians</persName> <persName>Hercules</persName>!”</p>
   <p>A country nurse, to fright her babe to peace, Said, “<name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Wolf</name> shall have thee, or thy cries must cease.” The <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">wolf</name> o’erheard, believed the scolding crone, And stay’d in hopes to find the feast his own. But evening came; the babe was hush’d to rest: The <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">wolf</name> still gaped, with rav’ning hunger prest. At last his hopes to utter dulness grew: Then to his anxious helpmate he withdrew. “How cam’st thou empty?” said she. He replied, “Because upon a female I relied.”</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="11">
   <p>A <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">cat</name> that ambush’d for some house-<name type="animal" xml:lang="en">birds</name> lay, Swung itself, baglike, from a peg one day. ’Twas seen by a sagacious shrewd-<foreign xml:lang="en">tongued</foreign> <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">cock</name>, Which shrilly thus began the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">cat</name> to mock; “Full many bags I’ve noticed heretofore: But none the grinders of a live <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">cat</name> bore.”</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="12">
   <p>Betwixt the North <name type="wind" xml:lang="en">wind</name> and the <name type="deity">Sun</name> arose A contest, which would soonest of his clothes Strip a wayfaring <persName>clown</persName>, so runs the tale. First <placeName>Boreas</placeName> blows an almost <placeName>Thracian</placeName> gale, Thinking perforce to steal the man’s <foreign xml:lang="fr">capote</foreign>: He loos’d it not: but as the cold <name type="wind" xml:lang="en">wind</name> smote More sharply, tighter round him drew the folds, And sheltered by a <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">crag</name> his station holds. But now the <name type="deity">Sun</name> at first peer’d gently forth, And thaw’d the chills of the uncanny north; Then in their turn his beams more amply plied, Till sudden heat the <persName>clown</persName>’s endurance tried: Stripping himself, away his <foreign xml:lang="fr">cloak</foreign> he flung: The <name type="deity">Sun</name> from <placeName>Boreas</placeName> thus a triumph wrung. The fable means, “My son, at mildness aim: Persuasion more results than force may claim.”</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="13">
   <p>There hung some bunches of the purple <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">grape</name> On a <name type="place" xml:lang="en">hill</name>-<name type="side" xml:lang="en">side</name>. A cunning <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">fox</name>, agape For these full clusters, many times essay’d To cull their dark bloom, many vain <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">leaps</name> made. They were quite ripe, and for the vintage fit: But when his <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">leaps</name> did not avail a whit, He journey’d on, and thus his grief composed: “The bunch was sour, not ripe, as I supposed.”</p>
</div>
<div type="chapter" n="12">
   <p>A <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">carter</name> from the village drove his wain: And when it fell into a rugged lane, Inactive stood, nor lent a helping hand; But to that <name type="deity">God</name>, whom of the heavenly band He really honour’d most, <name type="deity">Alcides</name>, pray’d: “Push at your wheels,” the <name type="deity">God</name> appearing said, “And goad your team; but, when you pray again, Help yourself likewise, or you’ll pray in vain.”</p>
   <p>Some <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">oxen</name> wish’d the <persName>butcher</persName> tribe to kill, Who boasted a to them destructive skill. But when they met, and now for direful fray Whetted their horns, an <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">ox</name> of ancient day Among them, who for years had borne the plough, Said, “These at least have hands experienced, how To kill and carve us, not to hack and hew: But if we chance on <persName>men</persName> to slaughter new, We shall die twice. One will not lack to fell The <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">ox</name>, but one perhaps to do it well.”</p>
   <p>A <persName>man</persName> in haste from present woes to flee Should see his path from worse disaster free.</p>
   <p>A <persName>man</persName> on whom mid-age its mark had set, — He was no longer young, nor old as yet, — Was wont to brush his black hair mixt with grey, And then in <name type="deity">Love</name>’s sweet revels spend his day. He wooed two loves, a young one and an old; The young one was desirous to behold Her lover youthful. Age would mate with age. Hence evermore the damsel strove to wage War against each grey hair she chanc’d to find: The elder tried to leave no black behind; Til each in turn, by plucking out his hair, Young love and old, had left him bald and bare. Woe worth the <persName>man</persName> entrapp’d by <name type="deity">woman</name>’s lure, For such are ever pluck’d and stripp’d, be sure.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="13">
   <p>To a far forest for a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">bull</name> that stray’d, A well-horn’d beast, a drover quest had made.</p>
   <p>Then to the mountain <name type="deity">nymphs</name> and <name type="deity">gods</name> around, <persName>Hermes</persName> and <persName>Pan</persName>, he sware, in case he found The thief, a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">lamb</name> should fall a sacrifice.</p>
   <p>Crossing a hill, his noble <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">bull</name> he spies Feasting a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">lion</name>.</p>
   <p>Then he vows in grief, To add an <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">ox</name>, if he escape the thief.</p>
   <p>Hence, it would seem, this lesson we are taught, Not to uplift a vow devoid of thought, By instant trouble’s pressure overwrought.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="123">
   <p>The <persName>Sun</persName>’s espousals were at summer’s prime, Hence all the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">beasts</name> enjoy’d a jovial time.</p>
   <p>The <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">frogs</name> too led the dance in march and mere, Till a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">toad</name> check’d them, saying, “Nought is here “To call for joy, bur rather grief and moan, For if he dries each spring, while yet alone, How by this union are we not undone, If like himself he should beget a son?”</p>
   <p>Many o’er trifles needlessly exult, For which too often sorrow will result.</p>
   <p>To end their days the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">hares</name> made up their mind, And since they were of <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">beasts</name> the feeblest kind, Timid of heart, and dull in all but flight, To hide themselves in some dark pool from light.</p>
   <p>But as to a broad swamp they drew more near, Upon its margin hosts of <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">frogs</name> appear, Which into slimy depths affrighted leap.</p>
   <p>As the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">hares</name> paused, one said, “Your courage keep. Let us return! To die we need not seek, For here are others than ourselves more weak.”</p>
</div>
<div type="chapter" n="14">
   <p>A <persName>farmer</persName>’s land, fresh sown with <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">wheaten grain</name>, Was being wasted by the hurtful <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">crane</name>. Long did the <persName>farmer</persName> lift an empty sling, By fear alone their troop discomfiting. But when they found he only smote the air, To fly at his approach they did not care: Till he no longer made a feint to throw, But laid with stones the greater number low. Quitting the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">corn</name>, the rest began to cry, “Come, to the land of <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">pygmies</name> let us fly. This <persName>man</persName>, it seems, content no more with fright, Is now beginning to put forth his might.”</p>
   <p>A <persName>man</persName> had trapped a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">weasel</name>, which to drown, He in a water-vessel tied it down. But when she said, “How shamefully my aid In catching <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">mice</name> and <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">lizards</name> have you paid!” “I own the debt,” cried he; “but did not you Stifle each <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">bird</name>, and rob each dwelling too, And empty every meat-pot? You shall die! For I’m more hurt than profited thereby.”</p>
   <p>An <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">ox</name> at water once a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">toadling</name> crush’d, Whose <persName>dam</persName>, then absent, quickly homeward rush’d, And question’d all its brethren where it was: “<persName>Mother</persName>, ’tis dead. Before its time, alas, Beneath the hoof of a huge <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">quadruped</name> ’Twas trampled down!” “Was it as large,” she said, “As this?” She tried her proper size to strain. “<persName>Mother</persName>,” cried they, “forbear! nor fume in vain. You’ll rend yourself in sunder, ere you rise, Howe’er you ape it, to that <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">monster</name>’s size.”</p>
</div>
<div type="chapter" n="15">
   <p>Once an old <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">horse</name> was sold to work the mill: And yok’d each eve a grinder’s task to fill. At last it groan’d and said: “What courses past, Round what strange millers’ turns I wheel at last!” Be not too much with fortune’s hopes elate: Age ends for many in a troubled state.</p>
   <p>A man had wrought a <name type="deity">Mercury</name> for sale In marble. Would-be buyers did not fail. One for a pillar (he’d just lost a son) To buy it wish’d, for a god’s statue one. Night came: yet it the sculptor had not sold, So he agreed at morn again t’ unfold The statue, if they’d come. In slumber deep He gazed on <foreign xml:lang="grc">Hermes</foreign> at the gates of sleep, Who said, “Good measure of my worth you take, Since god or corpse of me you mean to make.”</p>
</div>
<div type="book" n="1">
  <div type="chapter" n="16">
    <p>Between the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">cats</name> and <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">mice</name> of old there raged A truceless war: a feud no blood assuaged. The <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">cats</name> were victors. And the vanquished <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">mice</name> Deem’d this the cause, and this their army’s vice,</p>
    <p>32 A lack of leaders of distinguisht front, And discipline, to meet the battle’s brunt. Then chose they <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">mice</name> for rank, might, counsel, famed, And, as to prowess, more than all unblamed.</p>
    <p>Who marshalling their squadrons soon devise A mimic phalanx, troops, and companies. Now, all array’d and marshall’d, forth there stood A <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">mouse</name>, and challenged all the feline brood.</p>
    <p>Thin straws from mud walls every chief had bound Before his brows. Beheld of all around, They took the lead, the foremost of the host: Alas! again the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">mice</name> the day have lost.</p>
    <p>Safe to their holes the undistinguish’d fled: But for each vainly-ornamented head The narrow entrance proved, alack, too small: Alone outside were ta’en the heroes all.</p>
    <p>Meetly o’er them the foe a trophy set: For each <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">mouse</name>-chief a feline captor met.</p>
    <p>Our fable’s moral is, that safety lies Less in high rank that that which most despise.</p>
  </div>
</div>
<div type="section" n="17">
   <p>A <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">cat</name>, that loved a handsome <persName>man</persName>, was blest By the <name type="deity">Loves</name>’ mother granting her request: To change her shape permission <name type="deity">Venus</name> gave For lovely woman’s: such who would not rave Unless he won? ’Twas now the man’s to bend To love and marriage. At the banquet’s end A <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">mouse</name> ran past. Down the deep couch’s side Intent upon its capture sprang the bride. The nuptials ceased. <name type="deity">Love</name> vanish’d from among His mocking sports. For nature was too strong.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="18">
   <p>The Pleiads set, ’twas time to cast the seed: A farmer sow’d his fallow: then took heed To watch and guard it; for a countless host Of <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">black and croaking daws</name> had o’er it cross’d, 34 And <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">starlings</name>, bent the tillage to destroy. With empty sling there follow’d him a boy. Now with the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">starlings</name> ’twas the usual thing, To list the farmer calling for his sling; And fly ere he discharged it. Hence he sought A new device, and thus the stripling taught To act. “My lad, since we must needs outwit “This clever race of <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">birds</name>, a plan I’ve hit. So when they come, and I for bread shall ask, To hand the sling, not bread, will be your task.” The <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">starlings</name> came, and on the tillage fed; And he, as was agreed on, ask’d for bread. They did not fly. The lad supplied the stones And sling. The old man aim’d and brake the bones Of many a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">starling</name>: shoulders, crowns, and shins: Till from his land the remnant flight begins. Some <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">cranes</name> that met them ask’d them “how they fare?” Then said a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">daw</name>: “Of base mankind beware! Each speaks to other, words unlike his deeds.” Dread is the race that but by guile succeeds.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="19">
   <p>What time with <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">vineboughs</name> men the broad-floor strew, A <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">bull</name> to <name type="deity">Ceres</name> once the rustics slew. Tables of meat and casks of <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">wine</name> were there; But one poor <persName>lad</persName> had gorged too large a share Of the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">bull</name>’s entrails. Swoln he homeward hies, And sore bewails his <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">stomach</name>’s weight and size. Once in his <persName>mother</persName>’s arms, “Alas!” cried he. “What is’t?” she said. “Oh, all is o’er with me! My wretched fate is present death, no doubt; For, mother, see, my <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">bowels</name> gushing out.” “Don’t try to keep it down!” the dame replied; “’Tis not your own, dear! but the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">bull</name>’s, inside!” So when an <persName>orphan</persName>’s substance <persName>guardians</persName> spend, And retribution comes to a faithless <persName>friend</persName>, To such, deep-groaning at disgorging hour, Methinks this fable one might quote with power.</p>
   <p><name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Twins</name> at each birth the female <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">monkey</name> bears, Yet gives not them her love in equal shares. For, by her illstarr’d fondness one opprest Is kill’d with kindness in her rugged breast. The other as a useless <foreign xml:lang="en">idiot</foreign> thrown Adrift, an outcast, thrives when left alone. <persName>Men</persName>’s natures oft are such, that friendliness In them than <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">hate</name> is to be chosen less.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="20">
   <p>A <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">mountain-wind</name> tore from its roots an <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">oak</name>, A wondrous old-world <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">plant</name>, with sweeping stroke; And lodg’d it in a <name type="stream" xml:lang="en">stream</name>, where to and fro The eddies sway’d it. Close beside there grow
   <p>Upon the bank, by rippling water fed, Unnumber’d <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">reeds</name>. “’Twas strange,” the stout <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">oak</name> said, “That <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">plants</name> so frail and feeble did not fall, While giant <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">oaks</name> are riven up roots and all.” Sagely the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">reed</name> made answer: “Marvel not: Through struggling with the blasts, a fall you got: If but our slender tops the light breeze fill, We meekly bend us with a yielding will.” So spake the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">reed</name>. Our fable, look you, shows ’Tis best to bow to might, and not t’ oppose.</p>
</p>
<div type="section" n="38">
   <p>A <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">heifer</name> yet unbroken, roaming free, A <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">bull</name> hard-work’d in ploughing chanced to see; And said, “Poor wretch, how grievous is thy toil!” Nought said the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">bull</name>, but still upturn’d the soil. Soon, when the rustics held their solemn feast, The aged <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">bull</name> to pasture went released; But ropes that bound its horns the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">heifer</name> drew, That it with blood the altar might bedew. To whom this sentence then the elder spoke: “’Twas for this end they kept thee from the yoke. Young before old, thou dost the altar deck; The axe, and not the yoke, will bruise thy neck.”</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="21">
   <p>Some <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">woodmen</name>, bent a <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">forest pine</name> to split,</p>
   <p>Into each fissure sundry <foreign xml:lang="en">wedges</foreign> fit,</p>
   <p>To keep the void, and render work more light.</p>
   <p>Out groan’d the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">pine</name>, “Why should I vent my spite</p>
   <p>Against the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">axe</name>, which never touch’d my root,</p>
   <p>So much as these curst <foreign xml:lang="en">wedges</foreign>, mine own fruit;</p>
   <p>Which rend me through, inserted here and there!”</p>
   <p>39 A <foreign xml:lang="en">fable</foreign> this, intended to declare,</p>
   <p>That not so dreadful is a stranger’s blow,</p>
   <p>As wrongs which men receive from those they know.</p>
   <p>’Twixt <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">whales</name> and <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">dolphins</name> there was difference great:</p>
   <p>And to them came a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">crab</name> to mediate.</p>
   <p>Just as, in states, if one of small renown</p>
   <p>Should act peacemaker for each rival crown.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="22">
   <p>’Tis said a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">lizard</name> burst its back in twain</p>
   <p>In vain attempts a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">dragon</name>’s size t’ attain.</p>
   <p>Hurt to thyself will be thy certain fate,</p>
   <p>If men far higher thou shouldst imitate.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="22">
   <p>High feast a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">cit</name> was holding, at the end of sacrifice. His house-<name type="animal" xml:lang="en">dog</name> ask’d a friend, whom he had met, to come and share his meal.</p>
   <p>He came. The cook upraised him by the heel and toss’d him o’er the wall into the street. Whom when each <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">dog</name> did with the question greet, “What cheer?”</p>
   <p>He said, “What more could be desired, when I scarce know by what way I retired?”</p>
   <p>An antler’d <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">stag</name>, athirst in midday heat, drank of a silent pool beneath his feet. At these and at his hoofs he felt disdain, as the clear stream reflected them again.</p>
   <p>Not thus his horns with swelling heart he eyed; but <name type="deity">Nemesis</name> was near, to chasten pride.</p>
   <p>For soon a train of huntsmen fill’d the ground, with ample nets and keenly-scenting <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">hound</name>. He saw and fled, nor stay’d to quench his thirst, and with fleet foot across the champain burst.</p>
   <p>A thickly-tangled wood at last he gain’d, and found his antlers in its boughs detain’d.</p>
   <p>“Mistaken wretch!” he cried, “with scorn to treat, in pride of treacherous horns, my saving feet; had those been true, these had secured retreat.”</p>
   <p>When you on your affairs deliberate, hold nought beforehand in a certain state. Yet cast off nought as hopeless in disgust, our greatest traitors oft are hopes we trust.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="23">
   <p>Three <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">bulls</name> together in one pasture grazed: Of seizing these a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">lion</name>’s hopes were raised. He thought their union all his aims would foil, So with deep-festering slanders to embroil The friends he bent his mind. Asunder they Became, in turns, the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">lion</name>’s easy prey. If thou wouldst live securely to the end, Distrust a foe, but hold thou fast a friend.</p>
   <p>’Twas snowy weather: and a <persName>goatherd</persName> led Into a cave, he deem’d untenanted, His <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">goats</name>, all-white with snow descending thick; But thither, as he found, had come more quick Some hornèd wild <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">goats</name>, a far larger stock, And finer, too, than his accustom’d flock. Green shoots to them he soon began to fling: But to his own let tedious famine cling; Till, when the sky grew clear, he found dead. Meanwhile the wild <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">goats</name> hurried off to tread The trackless thickets of unpastured heights. Hence ridicule upon the <persName>goatherd</persName> lights, Returning goat-less. Seeking prizes new, He lost the profit of his old one too.</p>
   <p>A <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">stag</name>, whose lissome joints grew stiff, had made A grassy couch outside a woodland shade. Hence ample fodder to his need he found. Till soon, to see their neighbour, gathered round Whole tribes of beasts: (a right good neighbour he!) Each came, and each with his supplies made free By thoughtless nibbling, ere it sought the wood. Thus sank, not by disease, but want of food, A <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">stag</name> that scarce had yet two crow-lives told: Had he lack’d friends, he haply had died old!</p>
</div>
<div type="chapter" n="46">
   <p>Fab. XLVI. v. 9, 10.</p>
   <p>The <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">stag</name> was anciently supposed to be an exceedingly long lived animal; but the opinion is confuted by Aristotle, <persName>H. A.</persName> vi. 29, and by later experience. Its life is at most from thirty-five to forty years in duration, according to <persName>Buffon</persName> and <persName>Cuvier</persName>.</p>
   <p>Among old worthies lived an ancient man With many sons: and since his life began To wane at last, that truth might so be taught, He bade that there should be before him brought A bundle of thin rods. ’Twas soon at hand. “Now use,” said he, “the strength you each command, To break the sticks, my sons, thus closely bound.” “Well,” he rejoined, when force in vain was found, Then take them one by one.” Each broke with ease. “E’en thus,” he cried, “my children, if ye please To live in union, none have power to mar Your bond of strength, e’en though superior far. 45 But if ’twixt brothers’ hearts exists a breach, The single rod pourtrays the fate of each.” Love between brothers is man’s best of gifts, And oft the humble to high fortune lifts.</p>
   <p>Close to a well a workman slept one night, Unwittingly. But Fortune met his sight. He seem’d to hear; “What ho, there, sirrah, wake! Lest of thy tumble I the blame should take Among mankind, and earn an uglier name: For each man’s trips and haps I bear the blame, Howe’er his own the fault, ’tis just the same.”</p>
</div>
<div type="chapter" n="25">
   <p>Hard on a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">fox</name> a hunter in full chase Was pressing. <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Reynard</name>, needing breathing-space, Spying a woodman, cried, “By those who save, ’Neath yonder just-fell’d <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">poplars</name> let me crave A shelter. To the field betray me not.” The woodman sware. The <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">fox</name> a shelter got.</p>
   <p>The hunger came, and of the man would know, “Did the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">fox</name> enter there, or onward go?” Said he, “I saw not;” but his finger showed Meanwhile to <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Reynard</name>’s hiding-place the road. In haste at once the hunter passing on Believed the words. Her hottest danger gone, Our <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">fox</name> began from out the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">poplar</name>-heap With fawning tail, but spiteful grin, to peep.</p>
   <p>The old man said, “You owe your life to me. ’Twas I from risk of capture set you free; 47 Be grateful therefore.” “To be sure,” she cried, “For the vast help, I saw your acts supplied. Farewell! The Oath-<name type="deity">god</name> will exact his due. If your voice saved me, yet your finger slew.”</p>
   <p>Let none (Heaven’s purpose errs not) think to flee The sure deserts of secret perjury.</p>
   <p>A widow kept at home a single <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">sheep</name>: Out of whose fleece a larger gain to reap She clipp’d it rudely, press’d the shears too near Its flesh, and kept them not from wounding clear. The smarting <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">sheep</name> cried: “Do not torture me, My blood in weight will small addition be. Nay, mistress, nay! My flesh if you require, To kill me quick, a practis’d butcher hire. But if ’tis fleece and wool, not flesh, you need, Shearers will shear me, yet not make me bleed.”</p>
</div>
<div type="chapter" n="26">
   <p>Strong <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">bulls</name> to town upon their shoulders drew A four-wheel’d wain. Its creakings were not few. Then was the driver wroth; and drawing near, He spoke so plain, it could not choose but hear. “Thou worst of goods, will not thy groaning cease, Though they whose shoulders draw thee, hold their peace?” It is a base man’s way, to raise a moan, As if the toil of others were his own!</p>
   <p>A hapless <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">fox</name> fell in a wild <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">wolf</name>’s way, And pray’d him her old life to spare, not slay. “I will, by <name type="deity">Pan</name>, I will;” the wolf replied, If in thy next three words thou hast not lied.”</p>
   <p>49 “Well: first then,” said she, “would we had not met! Next, that a blind <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">wolf</name> had my path beset! And third and last,” she added, “go for ever! “I trust from this day forth to meet thee never!”</p>
   <p>With a she-<name type="animal" xml:lang="en">ass</name>, best shift his means allow’d, A tiller yoked his only <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">ox</name>, and plough’d. When these he was preparing to unyoke, Their work being over, thus the ass bespoke The ox: “Who carries home the old man’s gear?” “The beast whose wont it is,” said he, “’tis clear.”</p>
   <p>A baby-show with prizes <persName>Jove</persName> decreed For all the beasts, and gave the choice due heed. A <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">monkey</name>-<persName>mother</persName> came among the rest; A naked, snub-nosed pug upon her breast She bore, in mother’s fashion. At the sight Assembled Gods were moved to laugh outright. Said she, “<persName>Jove</persName> knoweth where his prize will fall! “I know, my child’s the beauty of them all.”</p>
   <p>This Fable with a general law attest, That each one deems that what’s his own, is best</p>
</div>
<div type="chapter" n="58">
   <p>Hermes had laden once a cart with lies, And much deceit, and divers villanies. This he essay’d to drive from race to race, Passing near every nation’s dwelling-place. And giving each a share. He came at last To the <placeName xml:lang="en">Arabian</placeName> land. As this he passed, Down brake his wagon suddenly, ’tis said, And stuck. The <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Arabs</name>, eager for a raid, And hoping here a merchant’s precious load, Rifled the wain, nor sent it on its road To other tribes beyond them. Hence I find That false and knavish is each <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Arab</name>’s mind. And, as experience proves, to <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Arab</name> tongue No particle of truth hath ever hung.</p>
   <p><persName>Jove</persName> in a cask all blessings pack’d and hid, A charge for man: but first secured the lid. Unbridled man, agog to scan the gift And its contents, essay’d the top to lift. Releas’d, each blessing mounted to the sky And would not bide below, when free to fly. Hope only tarried. Her the lid secured, When closed at last. And thus hath Hope endured In human homes. In her sole form we see Earnest of all the goods, that then did flee.</p>
</div>
<div type="chapter" n="28">
   <p>Pallas, ’tis said, with Neptune and with Jove, Which should create a thing most perfect, strove.</p>
   <p>Jove makes the choicest of created things, A <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">man</name>.</p>
   <p>A dwelling to him Pallas brings: Neptune a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">bull</name>.</p>
   <p>They gave the umpire’s post To <persName>Momus</persName>: Heaven as yet he had not lost.</p>
   <p>And he, as was his nature, hating all, At blaming the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">bull</name>’s horns to work must fall,</p>
   <p>Because they were not set beneath his eyes, For then he’d see to strike.</p>
   <p><name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Man</name> lost the prize,</p>
   <p>Because not open was his breast, but closed, Else each would see his neighbour’s plans exposed:</p>
   <p>He blamed the house, because no wheels were made Of iron at its base; that it, convey’d To other climes might pass with roving lord.</p>
   <p>What purports then to us the Fable’s word? Prefer not thou to carp: but strive to do.</p>
   <p><persName>Momus</persName> will nought in pleasant aspect view.</p>
   <p>A <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">mouse</name> into a lid-less broth-pot fell:</p>
   <p>Choked with the grease, and bidding life farewell,</p>
   <p>He said: “My fill of meat and drink have I, And all good things: ’tis time that I should die.”</p>
   <p>Thou art that dainty <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">mouse</name> among mankind,</p>
   <p>If hurtful sweets are not by thee declined.</p>
</div>
<div type="chapter" n="29">
   <p>A <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">huntsman</name> going laden from the <placeName>hill</placeName>, A <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">fisher</name> too, whose <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">fish</name> his <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">basket</name> fill, As luck would have it, chanced one day to meet, And lo! the hunger thought the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">fish</name> a treat;</p>
   <p><num type="line" n="55">The <persName>fisherman</persName> preferr’d the <persName>hunter</persName>’s game.</num> So they exchanged their spoil. They did the same, Each for a time, to suit the other’s taste, With all they took: till some one said, “You’ll waste And mar by use the present charm of these: And each again will seek what used to please.”</p>
   <p>A <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">mule</name>, in lazy <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">manger</name> fed on <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">hay</name>, And fresh with <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">corn</name>, began to leap and say, Kicking his heels, “A <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">racer</name> is my <foreign xml:lang="la">dam</foreign>, And I for her a match in fleetness am.” Yet with sad visage soon his course he check’d, Constrain’d his sire, the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">ass</name>, to recollect.</p>
   <p>A good man for a <name type="deity">hero</name>’s <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">fane</name> assign’d Space in his <placeName>court-yard</placeName>. Here he loved to bind Wreaths on the <name type="placeName">altars</name>, rich libations pay, And, sacrificing oft, devoutly pray. “<persName>Loved hero</persName>, hail! thy fellow-lodger bless With plenteous gifts.” At midnight his address Met answer. “<name type="deity">Heroes</name> can vouchsafe no good To man; for these ’twere meet the <name type="deity">Gods</name> were sued. ’Tis rather all the ills that fall to men, That we dispense: when seeking evil then, Pray us! Ask one, and many I’ll bestow. So now to whom to sacrifice you know!”</p>
</div>
<div type="chapter" n="63">
   <p>Fab. LXIII. — Ancient writers, such as <persName>Xenocrates</persName>, <persName>Empedocles</persName>, and to a certain extent <persName>Plato</persName>, treat the remnants of the half wicked silver age as <name type="deity">dæmons</name>; not good, as <persName>Hesiod</persName> held and represented them, but malignant and wicked. See <persName>Grote</persName> <foreign xml:lang="la">H. G.</foreign> i. pp. 95-7. Ibid. 570-1, note. Here the heroes are confounded with these <name type="deity">dæmons</name>. Compare <persName>Plut.</persName> <foreign xml:lang="la">Quæst. Græc.</foreign> c. vi. p. 292, where it appears that with the <placeName>Locrians</placeName> at <placeName>Opus</placeName> <foreign xml:lang="grc">δαίμων</foreign> was equivalent to <foreign xml:lang="grc">Ἥρως</foreign>.</p>
   <p>For the custom of wreathing the altars with fillets, alluded to in v. 3 of this fable, compare <persName>Theocr.</persName> <foreign xml:lang="la">Id.</foreign> xxvi. 3-9, <persName>Horat.</persName> <foreign xml:lang="la">Od.</foreign> iv. xi. 6, i. xix. 13. <persName>Virg.</persName> <foreign xml:lang="la">Ecl.</foreign> viii. 64.</p>
   <p>A <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">fir-tree</name> and a <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">bramble</name> disagreed, For the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">fir</name> always paid to self the meed Of praise. “I’m fine, well-grown in point of size: And my straight top is neighbour to the skies. ’Tis I, am roof of mansions, keel of ships: So much my comeliness all trees outstrips.” To whom the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">bramble</name> said, “Keep well in view The axe, whose business is thy trunk to hew, And saws, that cut thee: haply thou’lt prefer To be the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">bramble</name>, rather than the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">fir</name>.” All men of mark more rank and credit gain Than meaner folks, but still more risks sustain.</p>
</div>
<div type="chapter" n="31">
   <p>To a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">peacock</name>, bright-plumaged, smart and vain, this sharp retort fell from an <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">ashen crane</name>.</p>
   <p>“Through these dull wings, whose colour you decry, I scram aloft, in starry heights I fly.</p>
   <p>You, <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">cock</name>-like, flap your wings. The tail you spread,</p>
   <p>With all its gold, is never seen o’erhead.”</p>
   <p>Rather would I in threadbare coat aspire,</p>
   <p>Than live inglorious, tho’ in rich attire.</p>
   <p><persName>Prometheus</persName> was a <name type="deity">God</name>, an elder <name type="deity">God</name>:</p>
   <p><persName>Man</persName>, the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">brutes’</name> lord, he fashion’d of the sod,</p>
   <p>’Tis said, and round his neck two <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">wallets</name> hung,</p>
   <p>Full of all ills, that rise mankind among:</p>
   <p>One, holding others’ faults, in front was thrown:</p>
   <p>The larger, slung behind him, held his own.</p>
   <p>Hence others’ falls, methinks, men clearly see:</p>
   <p>But when one should look homeward, blind are we.</p>
</div>
<div type="chapter" n="32">
   <p>Chase-partners were the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">lion</name> and <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">wild ass</name>: That did in prowess, this in speed surpass: A booty of fat beasts their hunt supplied, Which into three the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">lion</name> would divide.</p>
   <p>“This first,” said he, “as foremost, I shall take In right of kinghood. That my equal stake Marks as my part. And, for the hindmost lot, ’Twill cause you hurt, unless you flee, I wot.”</p>
   <p>Measure your strength, nor, with a man more strong, To company, or partnership belong.</p>
   <p>Said the far-darter to the <name type="deity">Gods</name> on high, “Not one can farther shoot or throw than I.”</p>
   <p>In sport great <persName>Jove</persName> <persName>Apollo</persName>’s challenge took, And quick the lots in <persName>Mars</persName>’ cap <persName>Hermes</persName> shook.</p>
   <p>Luck was with <persName>Phœbus</persName>. Soon the golden bow And string he circles; lets the arrow go, And shoots within the gardens of the West.</p>
   <p>Said <persName>Jove</persName>, when the same range his feet had prest, “Space fails me, boy. To what point can I shoot?” Thus without shaft he won the arrow’s fruit.</p>
</div>
<div type="book" n="33">
  <div type="section" n="123">
    <p>A <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">dog</name>, no novice in the chase, pursued a rough-pawed <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">hare</name>, disturb’d from tangled wood, and soon was left behind. A <persName>goatherd</persName> near, “Fine runners beat you!” said, the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">hound</name> to jeer.</p>
    <p>Said he, “One needs must use far more despatch to save one’s own, than other lives to snatch.”</p>
    <p>The <name type="deity">Gods</name> were wedding. Each had found a mate. To <persName>War</persName> it chanced till last of all to wait. And so with <foreign xml:lang="en">Insolence</foreign>, left all alone, in love he fell, and won her for his own.</p>
    <p>So runs the <foreign xml:lang="en">Fable</foreign>. Hence, devoted swain, where’er she goes, he follows in her train.</p>
    <p>62 Oh then may <foreign xml:lang="en">Insolence</foreign>, most apt to smile on Commons, and to lead them wrong the while, be ever from our states and nations far, for close behind her comes her husband, <persName>War</persName>.</p>
    <p>A countryman beheld a crowded ship its prow beneath the arching surges dip; “Would thou hadst ne’er been ploughed,” he cried, “thou <placeName>main</placeName>! Harsh element, of which all men complain.”</p>
    <p>The <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">sea</name> o’erheard, assumed a woman’s tone, and said, “I pray you, leave my name alone. For ’tis not I that cause you all these woes: but every blast that round about me blows, see me and sail me, yonder winds removed, and gentler than your earth you’ll own me proved.”</p>
    <p>Bad natures oft turn many goods to worse, thus e’en a blessing comes to seem a curse.</p>
    <p><quote>Fab. LXXI. — Compare <quote>Cicero Pro Cluentio</quote>, c. 49, <quote>Herodot. vii. 16</quote>.</quote></p>
  </div>
</div>
<div type="section" n="34">
   <p>A contest in Heaven’s courts for beauty’s prize,
   <persName>Bright Iris</persName>, who with the <name type="deity">Gods</name>’ tidings hies,
   Proclaim’d to birds. The news soon spread to all,
   And to himself each hoped the meed would fall.
   Rose from a rock, that rarely <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">goat</name> had scaled,
   A spring, whose clear wave ne’er in summer fail’d.
   To it resorted all the feather’d race,
   Intent on washing, each, its wings and face,
   Shaking its wings, its plumage combing clean;
   When, lo! a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">jackdaw</name> to approach was seen,
   A <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">crow</name>’s now-ancient son. From ev’ry plume
   And each wet shoulder he made haste to assume
   A stolen feather. Soon his various guise
   In the <name type="deity">Gods</name>’ sight the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">eagle</name>’s form outvies.
   Him <persName>Jove</persName>, astonished, victor had declared,
   Had not the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">swallow</name>, <persName>Pallas</persName>-like, unbared
   <foreign xml:lang="la">The cheating rogue</foreign>, her feathers quick to claim;
   “Pray,” said the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">daw</name>, “expose me not to shame.”
   To pluck him, next, the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">thrush</name> and <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">turtle-dove</name>,
   Tomb-haunting <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">lark</name>, and <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">jay</name>, together strove;
   The <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">hawk</name>, a-watch for birds not yet full grown,
   Nay, all the birds. Thus was the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">jackdaw</name> known.
   My son, array thee in thy proper dress:
   For borrow’d clothes will leave thee garmentless.</p>
</div>
<div type="chapter" n="72">
   <p>Fab. LXXII. v. 6. — Grote, in his History of Greece, Vol. II. p. 289, remarks upon the inadequacy and irregularity of the supply of water in the low grounds of Greece. “Most of the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">rivers</name> are torrents in the early spring, and dry before the end of the summer. Rain runs of as rapidly as it falls, and springs are rare.” Horace refers to this fable of the <foreign xml:lang="la">daw</foreign> in his <quote>Epistles</quote>, i. iii. 18-20.</p>
   <p>Of old far other was the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">kite</name>’s shrill cry! Till once she heard a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">horse</name> neigh tunefully. She needs must ape the steed; and then nor heard Her former voice, nor that which she preferred.</p>
   <p>A <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">horse</name>, an <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">ox</name>, a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">dog</name>, distrest by cold, To seek the warmth of a man’s house made bold. He let them enter by his open’d door, And was not slack to give them of his store, Warming his guests withal beside his hearth: The <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">horse</name> found corn, of vetch the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">ox</name> no dearth, While the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">dog</name> shared the table of his host. Then fain would they requite their supper’s cost; And so its life’s chief habit each bestows. The <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">horse</name> gave first. Hence each among us glows With leaping spirit in our early prime. The <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">ox</name> came next. Therefore, at mid-life’s time, Man toils, and dearly loves to hoard and save. The <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">dog</name>, ’tis said, life’s latest features gave. Whence, <persName>Branchus</persName>, each, as age steals o’er him, grows Peevish apace, caressing only those To whom he looks for food. A stranger’s face Provokes his bark, and never wins his grace.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="36">
   <p>There lived a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">quack</name>. And all but he could tell A sick man not to fear; he’d soon be well: “Diseases run their time, but then are over;” The doctor came and said, “You won’t recover! Make all your preparations. You must die! I scorn to cheat: I’m not the man to lie. To morrow at the most you’ll scarce get o’er!” He said, nor visited his patient more.</p>
   <p>But, lo! the man from his disorder rose, Pallid, and somewhat shaky on his toes. Taking his walk, the doctor met him so: “Good morrow! How goes on the world below?” “Oh! deadly lively! Lethe’s draught is flat! But if you’d know what hell’s high powers were at, Doctors just now incurr’d their fiercest threats, Because each sick man well so quickly gets.</p>
   <p>They were proscribing all. Among the first They talk’d of posting you. But forth I burst A little timid from the shadowy crowd, And suppliant before their sceptres bow’d; And sware to them the truth I could not hide, You were no doctor, but had been belied.”</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="37">
   <p>A <persName>knight</persName> his <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">charger</name> pamper’d day by day,</p>
   <p>So long as war was rife, with corn and hay,</p>
   <p>As his brave comrade in the battle’s din;</p>
   <p>But when war ceas’d, and peace at last came in,</p>
   <p>When from his <placeName>deme</placeName> the <persName>knight</persName> drew pay no more,</p>
   <p>Oft from the woods to town his <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">charger</name> bore</p>
   <p>Huge logs of timber, and with various load</p>
   <p>Toil’d as a hireling on a weary road;</p>
   <p>On sorry chaff he barely life preserv’d,</p>
   <p>And yoked for draught, no longer knighthood serv’d.</p>
   <p>But war again was heard without the walls,</p>
   <p>On each to burnish arms the trumpet calls,</p>
   <p>To whet his steel, his war-horse to array:</p>
   <p>Again our <persName>knight</persName> has bridled for the fray</p>
   <p>His <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">charger</name>, led for him to take the field,</p>
   <p>But its weak limbs began to sink and yield.</p>
   <p>“Go rank thyself with infantry,” it said:</p>
   <p>“If thou could’st me from horse to <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">ass</name> degrade,</p>
   <p>“Nor more can I my former self be made.”</p>
   <p>A <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">crow</name> upon his perch was munching <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">cheese</name>,</p>
   <p>When a sly <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">fox</name> by arguments like these,</p>
   <p>To suit herself, beguiled him of his prize :—</p>
   <p>“Fair are thy plumes, good <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">crow</name>, and bright thine eyes,</p>
   <p>“Charming thy neck, and <foreign xml:lang="la">eagle</foreign>’s breast thou hast,</p>
   <p>“In talons thou art by no brute surpass’d.</p>
   <p>“’Tis strange that dumb should be a bird so smart!”</p>
   <p>The flatter’d <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">crow</name> became elate in heart,</p>
   <p>And, cawing, from his mouth the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">cheese</name> let fall;</p>
   <p>This <persName>Reynard</persName> snatch’d, and tauntingly did call,</p>
   <p>“’Tis true thou wast not dumb, for thou canst speak,</p>
   <p>“Yet, spite of all thou hast, thy mind is weak.”</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="38">
   <p>A sick <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">crow</name> to its weeping mother said, “Weep not, but pray the <name type="deity">Gods</name> that from the bed “Of sad disease and suffering I may rise.” “Will any <name type="deity">God</name>,” said she, “child, hear my cries, “And save thee? Is there one of whom ’tis true, “His altar never has been robb’d by you?”</p>
   <p><name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Tray</name> from the shambles stole a piece of meat; And, as he cross’d a stream, upon its sheet Of crystal saw the shadow magnified; Which, letting go the flesh, to grasp he tried. He gain’d nor it, nor that which he had lost, And, supperless, again the river cross’d. All avaricious men consume in vain Uncertain lives, in fleeting hope of gain.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="123">
   <p>A drinking master would his <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">camel</name> bring To dance to flutes, and brazen cymbal’s ring. “Would that I could on a plain road advance, Causing no laughter,” said she, “much less dance.”</p>
   <p>A <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">fox</name> said to an <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">ape</name>, “The stone you see Records my sire’s and grandsire’s memory.” Said Pug to Reynard, “Lie, as likes you best, For none remain our story’s truth to test.” It marks a bad man not to shrink from lies, When, lying, he can shun detective eyes.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="39">
   <p>A <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">mouse</name> ran o’er a sleeping <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">lion</name>’s mane, And the roused brute his wrath could not restrain: So bristling up, he leapt from out his lair.</p>
   <p>A neighbour-<name type="animal" xml:lang="en">fox</name> derision did not spare, That on a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">mouse</name> the king of brutes should spend His ire. Said he, “I fear not, cunning friend, Lest <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">mice</name> my skin should nettle, and escape: But roads o’er me take an ill-habit’s shape.” The boldness of the impudent repress, Small though it be, before it can progress! Nor let it by the mean be lightly dreamt, That thou wilt be a butt for their contempt.</p>
   <p>A groom each day his <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">horse</name> kept currying, Yet each day too the corn-bin emptying. Then said the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">horse</name>, “If sleek you really would Behold me, prythee, do not sell my food.” True love will study things expedient And useful. Vain, indeed, is ornament As a makeweight, when needful things are spent.</p>
   <p>A <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">gnat</name> on a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">bull</name>’s horn his seat had made, And, pausing first, thus with a buzz he said: “If I bear down or bend your neck a whit, I’ll go and on yon <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">river-poplar</name> sit.” The <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">bull</name> cried, “Stay or go, for aught I care, I did not even know when you came there.” Absurd is he, who, being nought, will try To cope with great men, and ape something high.</p>
</div>
<div type="chapter" n="40">
  <p>A feud between the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">dogs</name> and <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">wolves</name> arose, And of their host the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">dogs</name> as leader chose One from <placeName>Achaia</placeName>: who, like general sage, Kept holding back. His troops began to rage At his preferring ambush to fair fight. “Why I delay,” he answered, “hear aright, And why I’m careful. Prudence can’t be wrong. Our foes I see are one united throng; But some of us have from <placeName>Molossia</placeName> come, Others from <placeName>Crete</placeName>, from <placeName>Acarnania</placeName> some: Some are <foreign xml:lang="la">Dolopian</foreign>: others <placeName>Cyprus</placeName> boast, Or <placeName>Thrace</placeName> their home: in short, a various host. We differ, unlike these, in colour too, Being, some black, and some of ashen hue: While some are bright and mottled in the chest, Others are white. Discordant bands at best How can I marshal, with an eye to war, ’Gainst troops that all alike in all things are?” For aught more good than harmony to seek Is vain. Disunion slavish is, and weak.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="41">
   <p>An aged <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">oak</name> was at its roots decay’d, Wherein the wallet of a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">hind</name> was laid, Ragged and brimful of stale bread and meat; A <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">fox</name> ran in, and its contents did eat.</p>
   <p>Her stomach thence, no marvel, wax’d so stout, That through the opening she could not get out. She wept.</p>
   <p>Another <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">fox</name>, that came that way, Said jeeringly, “Till you are fasting, stay! You won’t find egress, till you grow as thin In stomach, as you were when you got in.”</p>
   <p>Chasing a mountain <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">hare</name>, a certain <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">hound</name> Would one while bite her, if a chance he found. And one while turn and lick her as a friend;</p>
   <p>Said <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">puss</name> at last, “Let double-dealing end. “Be a true brute. If friend, why do you bite? “But if a foe, why fawn, nor be downright?”</p>
   <p>Of an uncertain class of minds are those; Whom, if no trust or distrust, no one knows.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="42">
   <p>In the green corn a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">lark</name>, that nurs’d his young, At dawn, in answer to the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">lapwing</name> sung. And now his brood had fed on corn so long, That they had crests, and on their wings were strong.</p>
   <p>So the field’s owner, when he came to see The harvest ripe, said, “Now ’tis time for me “To gather all my friends, that I may reap.” But one of the young crestlings chanc’d to keep Watch on his words, and ran, his sire to tell, That to remove them elsewhere it were well.</p>
   <p>But he replied, “’Tis not yet time to flee! Who trusts to friends, not over-fast is he.” When the man came, and saw the sun’s bright ray Had caused the ear o’er-ripe to fall away. And said, he’d hire reapers the next morn, And pay all hands to bind and sheave the corn, Then the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">lark</name> to his novice children cries, “’Tis time, my sons, that each one elsewhere flies, Since on himself, not friends, the man relies.”</p>
   <p>A <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">wolf</name> beheld a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">lambkin</name> once astray, And did not give brute force at once its way, But, bent to seize it, found this specious plea: “Small though you were last year, you slander’d me.”</p>
   <p>“Nay! how last year? A year I’ve not been born.” “Well, then, you nibbled my own field of corn!” “I eat nor grass nor corn! A nursling still!” “Have you not drunk then of my private rill?” “As yet, my mother’s milk’s my beverage.” Upsprang the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">wolf</name>, and ate the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">lamb</name> in rage. “A <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">wolf</name>,” said he, “can’t for his supper wait, Though all his pleas you may invalidate.”</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="43">
   <p>A <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">lion</name> raved. A <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">fawn</name> from woods hard by Saw, and began, “Ah! wretched we!” to cry. “How must we, when he’s mad, expect to fare, Whom, in his sane state, none of us could bear?”</p>
   <p>Once , in a cave the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">goatherds</name> had forsaken, A <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">bull</name> had from a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">lion</name> refuge taken, But to contest his entrance there remain’d One <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">goat</name> within, who hornèd war maintain’d. “Pshaw!” said the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">bull</name>, “could I yon <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">beast</name> elude, I’d bear a little space to see you rude! Just let the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">lion</name> pass, and you shall note How wide the difference ’twixt <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">bull</name> and <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">goat</name>.”</p>
   <p>A <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">lion</name>-<persName>hunter</persName> once, who courage lack’d, In the hill-forests dense his game had track’d. A <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">woodman</name> near a tall <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">fir</name> met his view, Whom by the <name type="deity">Nymphs</name> he pray’d, if aught he knew, To point the wild <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">beast</name>’s steps, that harbour’d near. The other said, “Good luck has brought you here! The <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">lion</name>’s self to you I’ll quickly show.” Pale, and with chattering teeth, he cried, “No, no!” Pray don’t oblige me, friend, beyond your task: To see the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">lion</name>’s track, not him, I ask.”</p>
   <p>The <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">wolf</name>-tribe sent the flock an embassy, And proffer’d oaths of peace and amity. The terms were that the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">dogs</name> should be disgraced, Who caused the feud now sought to be effaced. The <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">sheep</name>, weak, silly creatures, were disposed To scout old friends. An old <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">ram</name> interposed, And said, his thick wool bristling from below, “A novel mediation this, I trow!” How, if unguarded, am I safe with you, When even now my perils are not few, Though, while I feed, I keep my watch-<name type="animal" xml:lang="en">dog</name> true?”</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="44">
   <p>A <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">bone</name> in the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">wolf</name>’s throat was firmly set: Then covenanted he the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">hern</name> should get A due reward, if, letting down his neck, He’d draw the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">bone</name>, and thus his suffering check. The <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">hern</name> extracted it, and claim’d his prize. “Nay,” said the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">wolf</name>, with grinning teeth and eyes, “A meed of healing great enough you’ve found, Your head from out the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">wolf</name>’s jaw safe and sound.” It is ill wages, when the bad you aid, To take no hurt, is to be well-repaid.</p>
</div>
<div type="chapter" n="45">
   <p>Sick in a rocky cleft a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">lion</name> lay, Glad on the ground his failing limbs to stay. With him a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">fox</name> was chiefly intimate, To whom he said, “Wouldst have me ’scape my fate? Then know, I hunger for the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">stag</name> that dwells ’Neath yon wild pine amide the woodland dells. And I, you wot, can hunt the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">stag</name> no more; But if you choose your honied words to pour Into his ears and trap him, mine’s the prize!”</p>
   <p>Away went <persName>Reynard</persName> where the wild wood lies She found him leaping o’er the mossy grass, And, first embracing, then began to pass High compliments, and say she came to bring Good new. “My neighbour is the forest king, “The <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">lion</name>; he is sick, nay well nigh dead: And he was thinking who should rule instead</p>
   <p>84 O’er beasts. To find a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">pig</name> with sense is hard! The <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">bear</name> is dull; and wrathful is the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">pard</name>. The braggart <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">tiger</name> ever stands alone. He deems the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">stag</name> is meetest for his throne. ’Tis light of form; it lives unnumber’d years; Fearful to reptiles is the horn it rears, Branching like trees, to bulls’ horn un-allied; Need I say more? The choice is ratified. You are to rule the beasts that roam the hills; Oh! then, whene’er the throne your highness fills, Pray think of <persName>Reynard</persName>, who first let you know These news. I’ve said. Good-bye, my dear! I go To join the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">lion</name>; he may need me back: My counsel now in all things he would lack. You’ll come, child, too, if the advice you heed Of an old head. ’Tis fitting you should speed To counsel him, and cheer him in his woes: Small things win much at life’s extre</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="46">
   <p>mest close, And souls are in the eyes of them that die:” Thus spake the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">fox</name>. The <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">stag</name>’s heart leapt on high At her feign’d words. He sought the cavern home Of the wild <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">beast</name>, and wist not what should come.</p>
   <p>85 Reckless upsprang the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">lion</name> from his lair, And fail’d, through haste, of more than just to tear The <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">stag</name>’s ear with his talon-tips. Afraid, Straight from the door it fled to woodland shade. The <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">fox</name> to clap her paws in spite was fain, Because her labour had been spent in vain.</p>
   <p>Gnashing his teeth the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">lion</name> raised a groan; Chagrin and famine seiz’d him, both in one. Again he call’d the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">fox</name>, again he pray’d The <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">stag</name> by some fresh trick might be betray’d.</p>
   <p>Revolving schemes from her heart’s inmost core, “I’ll do your will,” she said, “tho’ hard, once more.” Then follow’d she, like sage <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">dog</name>, on the scent, Weaving her wily tricks, as on she went; Asking each <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">shepherd</name> ever and anon, “Knew he which way a bleeding <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">stag</name> had gone?”</p>
   <p>Each that had seen it, pointing led the way To where, she found, the fleet <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">stag</name> resting lay, Tired with the chase, in deeply shaded wood, And there with forehead unabash’d she stood. A shudder smote the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">stag</name> in back and knees, Wrath overflow’d his heart. His words were these:</p>
   <p>86 “Now you pursue me, wheresoe’er I fly: But, hated one, discomfiture is nigh, If you approach, and dare to mutter aught. Go play the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">fox</name> to others yet untaught In wiles. Stir others up, and make them reign.” But <persName>Reynard</persName> heard unmoved. In blameful strain She said, “Art thou so mean, so</p>
</div>
<div type="chapter" n="47">
   <p>full of fear? And dost thou thus suspect associates dear? The <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">lion</name> planning what might profit thee, And how to rouse thee from past apathy, Just touch’d thine ear, a dying father’s act, For he desired no precept should be lack’d By thee for keeping sovereignty so great; But thou his weak claw’s tickling couldst not wait, And, tearing thyself off, wast wounded sore.</p>
   <p>Hence he, than thou, is now offended more, For trial shows thee weak, unfit to trust; So into kinghood he the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">wolf</name> will thrust.</p>
   <p>Ah me! an evil lord! What will befall? Thou art a cause of ills to one and all. Nay, come and show more courage than of old, Nor cower, like <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">sheep</name>, just straying from the fold.</p>
   <p>87 Now may my oath by springs and leaves be known, So may I subject be to thee alone, As he intends no harm, but in good will, Bids thee the lordship of the beasts to fill.”</p>
   <p>Cajoling thus the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">brocket</name>, him she won Into the selfsame fate again to run. So when he lay, inclosed within the lair, The <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">lion</name> had, himself, most dainty fare, Gorging the flesh, the marrow from each bone And entrails lapping. Famishing, alone Stood the decoyer, till she slily stole And ate the heart, which near her chanc’d to roll; The single gain of all her toil was this: Which soon the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">lion</name>, counting, came to miss, Of all the inward parts.</p>
   <p>Indignant then He search’d each lair, and hunted every den. And <persName>Reynard</persName> said, to cheat him of the truth, “Don’t search in vain! It had no heart in sooth. To own a fine heart he was likely, who A second time</p>
</div>
<div type="chapter" n="100">
  <p>came visitor to you!”</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="48">
  <p><quote>Fab. XCV. 22. . — Of the hatred of stags for all the serpent tribe, see Plin. Nat. His. viii. 50, xxii. 37, Ælian,. N. A. II. 9.</quote></p>
  <p><quote>Dioscorides De Mat. Med. III. 73, and Pliny l. c. state that serpents do not take hurt from the bites of serpents, if they feed on the plane “<foreign xml:lang="la">elaphoboscos</foreign>”; and that the seed of this plant mixed with wine is a cure for the bites of serpents.</quote></p>
  <p>A <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">wolf</name> pass’d by a wall; and from its top A young <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">ram</name> peeping much abuse let drop. Gnashing his teeth the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">wolf</name> said bitterly, “Boast not thyself. They place abuses me!” Let no one then, whom luck or accident Makes strong awhile to insolence give vent.</p>
  <p>A <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">lion</name> once conceiving a design Against a wild <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">bull</name>, feign’d that at the shrine Of <name type="deity">Cybele</name> he meant to sacrifice, And bade the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">bull</name>; who, blind to his device, Promis’d to join the feast, and came and stood At his host’s door. Seeing the kitchen strew’d With cauldrons of hot water, cleavers bright, Sharp carving-knives, but nought for food in sight, Save a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">cock</name> bound, he to the hills made off: Much did the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">lion</name>, when he met him, scoff. “Nay,” said the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">bull</name>, “this token proves I came. Your ample kitchens larger victims claim.”</p>
</div>
<div type="chapter" n="49">
   <p>A <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">lion</name>, smitten with a beauteous maid, Ask’d her in marriage of her sire, who said, Without show of dislike or hollowness, “I’d give consent, and gladly, I profess! What sire a mighty <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">lion</name> would refuse! But timid are young maids’ and children’s views. Just think how large your teeth! how long you wear Your talons! What maid, do you think, will dare To clasp you boldly, see you unalarm’d? If you would wed, against these fears be arm’d. Be a wild beast no more, but suitor mild.” On wings of promise, by the words beguil’d, The <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">lion</name> drew his teeth, his talons pared With surgeon’s knife, then to the sire repair’d, And showing them he claim’d his bride. But all With stones or clubs on him began to fall. He lay inactive, e’en as dying <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">swine</name>, Taught by a crafty old man to divine, That ’tis not nature’s will that men should burn For <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">lions</name>, or they love mankind in turn</p>
</div>
<div type="chapter" n="50">
   <p>There met a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">wolf</name> a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">dog</name> exceeding sleek, Of whom the former soon began to seek, “In what abode he grew so fat and large.” Said he, “I live at a rich master’s charge.” 91 “But how,” said <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Wolf</name>, “became they neck so bare?” “Rub’d by the iron collar which I wear: My master had it forg’d, and placed on me.” The <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">wolf</name> on this made answer mockingly: “Adieu! for me, the nurture I refuse, Through which the iron is my neck to bruise.”</p>
   <p>An <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">eagle</name> to a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">lion</name> flew, and pray’d To be his partner. “What should let?” he said In answer. “Only you must certify, You will not let your faith take wings and fly: On friend unsettled how could I rely?”</p>
   <p>A fine-grown <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">wolf</name> his tribe in size outvied, The rest surnamed him “<name type="animal" xml:lang="en">lion</name>.” Puff’d with pride He could not bear renown, but left his kin, And with the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">lions</name> friendship strove to win. Then said a jeering <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">fox</name>, “From me be far That frenzy, in the mists of which you are. For you, no doubt, to <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">wolves</name> a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">lion</name> seem, But <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">lions</name> count you <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">wolf</name>, in their esteem.”</p>
   <p>A <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">lion</name> : no brawling <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">lion</name> he, Nor fierce, nor one who used brute force with glee; But mild and just, as any child of man. ’Twas in his reign, or so the story ran, 93 The wild beasts held a congress, with this aim, Each to do justice, and receive the same. And when each brute accounted, as by law, <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Wolves</name> to the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">lambs</name>, the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">pard</name> to the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">chamois</name>, <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Tiger</name> to <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">stag</name>, and peace pervaded all, A cow’ring <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">hare</name> said, “Ever did I call Upon the <name type="deity">Gods</name>, to grant this day ere long, Which makes the weak a terror to the strong.”</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="51">
   <p>A <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">lion</name> hunting could no longer go, He had grown old full many a year ago. So in his cave he laid him, feigning sick, And gasping, not in truth, ’twas all a trick. His once deep voice now seem’d so faint and low: Quickly did <name type="deity">Rumour</name> to each beast’s den go: Her tale, the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">lion</name>’s sickness, grieved them all, And each went in, on the old king to call.</p>
   <p>These, in their turn, he took with ease, though weak, And, feasting on them, found his age grow sleek. Yet one, who guess’d his trick, a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">fox</name>, afar Ask’d, “Prythee, good my liege, say how you are?” He answer’d, “Best of creatures, how d’ye do? Come nearer, nor from far your old friend view. Come, sweet one, with the balm your words can give, And comfort me who have not long to live.” Said <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">fox</name>, “Good-bye, my leaving you’ll forgive; I must be off, forewarn’d by many a track Of beasts, which you can scarcely prove came back.” He that is taught by strange calamity And is not first in falling, blest is he!</p>
   <p>A <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">dog</name> was fond of biting “on the sly,” Whose master, this ill trick to notify Abroad, a brazen bell around him tied. On this the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">dog</name> began to ring with pride His bell in every square. Then to him said An elder <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">dog</name>, “Why proudly lift your head, Poor wretch? no badge of worth you sound in this, But a plain proof of what you do amiss.”</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="52">
   <p>A <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">wolf</name> was bearing home a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">sheep</name> one day
   Snatch’d from the fold. A <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">lion</name> in the way
   Captur’d his spoil. The <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">wolf</name>, far off, made moan:
   “ Wrongly, ” he cried, “you’ve robb’d me of my own.” 96
   The mocking <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">lion</name> answer’d with delight;
   “Of course ’twas given by friends, and your’s by right .”
   </p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="53">
   <p>A <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">lion</name> once the noblest life of <persName>men</persName> Would emulate, and in his spacious den “At home,” with kindness to entreat essay’d All the best kinds of <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">beasts</name> of hill or glade.</p>
   <p>Large grew the crowd of various <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">brutes</name> apace, For which his kindly “menage” found a space: While each his loved and feasted as a guest, Meting to all the food they fancied best, He ’d ta’en a friendly <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">fox</name> his den to share, With whom his life was mostly smooth and fair;</p>
   <p>But carver to him was an ancient <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">ape</name>, Each messmate’s share to parcel out and shape. This <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">ape</name>, if guest unwonted cross’d the door, Set the same meal his lord and him before, The <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">lion</name>’s chase some recent spoil had ta’en, While <persName>Reynard</persName> did but scraps of stale <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">meat</name> gain.</p>
   <p>So when a purposed silence she maintain’d, And now from food and feast her paws restrain’d, Her conduct’s motive fain the host would seek: “Sage <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">fox</name>, in wonted fashion, prythee, speak; Share, dearest, share the feast with cheerful face.”</p>
   <p>“Best,” cried the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">fox</name>, “of all the wild-<name type="animal" xml:lang="en">beast</name> race, With much solicitude I waste my heart; Nor do things present merely cause the smart; But what is coming, I with grief foresee: For if fresh guests come hither constantly, One after other, and this habit grows, I shall miss even stale <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">meat</name>, I suppose.”</p>
   <p>A <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">lion</name>’s smile o’er the pleased <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">lion</name> came: “I told the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">ape</name> so. Me then do not blame.”</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="54">
   <p>The lion, having captured a mouse, thought: “But on the verge of fate the wretch besought (Poor household thief) the beast, in words of fear; ‘Twere meet that, hunting <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">hornèd bulls</name> and <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">deer</name>, With suchlike meat you should your paunch make fat; But a poor <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">mouse</name>! ’tis wrong such food as that Should ever touch your lips. Oh, spare me, pray! Small as I am, this boon I may repay.’</p>
   <p>The beast let go his suppliant with a smile; But, himself netted in a little while, By youthful hunters he was made secure. [Slyly] the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">mouse</name> stole to an aperture, Nibbled with tiniest teeth the sturdy twine, And let the beast again see daylight shine, Unbound: requiting thus his former gift.</p>
   <p>To men of sense plain is our fable’s drift.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="55">
   <p>Two <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">mice</name>, of whom one spent a-field his day, The other’s hold in rich town storehouse lay, To have their food in common both agreed: And so the town-bred <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">mouse</name> came first, to feed Where now the field was fresh with verdant <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">fruits</name>; And nibbling there the moist and bitter <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">roots</name> Of <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">corn</name>, from dingy clods by no means free, “The life of wretched <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">ant</name> is yours,” said he, Eating scant <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">barley</name> in the depths of earth. For me — I find much plenty and no dearth. I dwell in plenty’s horn, compared with you. Come and feast freely, as you’d wish to do, Leaving the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">moles</name> to burrow in the soil.”</p>
   <p>He won the simple <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">mouse</name> from rustic toil, Men’s homes to enter, ’neath their walls to bore; And show’d him where there is of <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">pulse</name> a store, A cask of <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">figs</name>, and where the meal-bags are; Where the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">date</name>-chest; and where the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">honey</name>-jar.</p>
   <p>When, spurr’d and much delighted by all these, He from a basket dragg’d a piece of <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">cheese</name>, Lo! some one oped the door; away he leapt, And trembling, to his hole’s aperture crept, Crowding his host, and venting hideous squeaks.</p>
   <p>But in a while from his retreat he sneaks, Intent a Camirœan <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">fig</name> to taste; But, after something, upon them in haste Came some one else. They hid. The country <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">mouse</name> Said, “Feast, and fare you well, in plenty’s house: Of these abundant revels take your fill; You’ll find them mainly fraught with risk and ill, Meanwhile, desert my sooth clod will not I, Where I munch <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">barley</name>, and all fears defy!”</p>
</div>
<div type="chapter" n="56">
   <p>Fab. <rs type="work" ref="Hor.Sat.II.vi.79">CVIII</rs>, — Compare <quote>Hor. Sat. II. vi. 79</quote>. See also Fab. <rs type="work" ref="Fab.XCIX">XCIX</rs> above. As to the <name type="place">Camiræan</name> [or <name type="place">Camirœan</name>] <name type="plant">fig</name> mentioned in v. 25, see <quote>Smith’s Dict. Gr. Rom. Geogr.</quote> Vol. I. pp. 713, 5. <placeName>Camirus</placeName> was a town of <placeName>Rhodes</placeName>, one of the three most ancient in the island, which was famous for its wine, raisins, and <name type="plant">figs</name>.</p>
   <p>“Don’t walk aslant, nor o’er the moist rock draw Crosswise,” its dam said to the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">crab</name>, “thy claw.”</p>
   <p>“Nay, first,” cried he, “<persName>Mother</persName> and <persName>mentor</persName> too, Walk straight yourself: I ’ll watch and follow you.”</p>
   <p>“Gape not,” a man about to travel cried To his <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">dog</name> near him; “but to start provide; For you must go with me.” It wagg’d its tail, And said, “I’m right! ’Tis you in quickness fail.”</p>
</div>
<div type="chapter" n="117">
  <p>A <persName>huckster</persName>, who contrived an <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">ass</name> to keep, Hearing that salt on the sea-coast was cheap, Chose to invest in it. With goodly load Homeward he drove. When fairly on the road, Into a stream the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">ass</name> unconscious rolled, And, the salt melting, had no weight t’ uphold, So rose with greater ease, and lightly sought And reach’d the bank. More salt the owner bought; Again he brought his <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">ass</name> to load: again Piled his bags heavier. Then, in toil and pain, Crossing the stream that caused his former fall, The <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">ass</name>, on purpose, slipt, lost salt and all; And, at his luck triumphant, lightly rose. Now did the huckster a new scheme propose; ’Twas this: — “To carry inland from the sea Whole loads of porous sponges: salt-bags he Was sick of.” So the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">ass</name>, in knavish sort, When to the stream again his load he brought, Fell down on purpose. Every sponge was soak’d At once, and he to heavier burden yoked; Home on his back he bore a double bale. Where men have oft succeeded, they may fail.</p>
</div>
<div type="chapter" n="58">
   <p>A <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">bull</name> was bitten by a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">mouse</name>. In pain He tried to catch it: but ’twas first to gain The <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">mouse</name>-hole. With his horns, to raze its walls, The <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">bull</name> essays, until asleep he falls, Sinking, fatigued, hard by. Forth straightway hies The peeping <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">mouse</name>, bites him again, and flies. Uprose the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">bull</name>, perplext what now to do, And the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">mouse</name> squeak’d to him this moral true: “Not always mighty are the great. ’Tis seen Sometimes, that stronger are the small and mean.”</p>
   <p>A <persName>man</persName> about to fold his <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">sheep</name> at eve, Was going a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">wolf</name> with them to leave Penn’d up. The <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">sheep</name>-<name type="animal" xml:lang="en">dog</name> saw, and said, “What haste To save the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">sheep</name>, you bring him in to waste!”</p>
   <p>A <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">lamp</name> that swam with oil, began to boast At eve, that it outshone the starry host, And gave most light to all. Her boast was heard: Soon the wind whistled: soon the breezes stirred, And quench’d its light. A <persName>man</persName> rekindled it, And said, “Brief is the faint <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">lamp</name>’s boasting-fit, But the star-light ne’er needs to be re-lit.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="59">
   <p>
      <foreign xml:lang="grc">Once</foreign> to the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">divers</name>, <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">gulls</name>, and <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">wild sea-mews</name> a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">sluggish tortoise</name> thus expressed her views.
      “Would that I, too, had had the luck to fly!” An <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">eagle</name> chanced to hear, and made reply:
      “Tortoise, how much shall be the eagle’s prize,
      If to the air he makes thee lightly rise?”
      “Thou shalt have all and each of ocean’s gifts!”
      “Agreed!” the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">eagle</name> cries, and lightly lifts
      the other to the clouds, upon her back,
      Then lets her fall, and on the hill-side crack
      her brittle coat of shell.
      He heard her cry,
      At the last gasp:
      “I well deserve to die!
      Where was to me of clouds and wings the need,
      Who on my mother earth could make no speed?”
   </p>
   <p>
      A <persName>youth</persName> was singing sweetly at mid-night;
      A <persName>wife</persName> that heard him, rose, and in delight
      peep’d from her windows, whence a view she had,
      By the bright <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">moon-beam</name>, of a handsome <persName>lad</persName>.
      She therefore left her <persName>spouse</persName> asleep to snore,
      Came down the halls, and passed without the door,
      And quickly gain’d the object she desired.
      Her <persName>husband</persName> rose in haste: his eyes enquir’d
      Where was his mate, whom in the house he lack’d?
      Soon did the song his doubting steps attract.
      Then cried he to his <persName>wife</persName>:
      “Be not dismay’d,
      This <persName>youth</persName> within our house to sleep persuade.”
      He took him in: the <persName>youth</persName> found both were bent
      To please, and of the <persName>wife</persName> grew negligent.
   </p>
   <p>
      So runs the fable.
      Read its moral right,
      ’Tis ill to triumph, when one may requite.
   </p>
</div>
<div type="chapter" n="60">
   <p>The sea engulfed a ship and all its <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">crew</name>,</p>
   <p>Which one beholding this conclusion drew.</p>
   <p>“That the <name type="deity">Gods</name> rule unjustly: for that they</p>
   <p>A host of harmless <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">men</name> agreed to slay,</p>
   <p>Because one godless wretch was in the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">ship</name>.”</p>
   <p>But as the words were just upon his lip,</p>
   <p>A swarm of <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">ants</name> surprised him, urged by haste</p>
   <p>(’Tis nothing strange), some <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">barley</name> <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">chaff</name> to taste.</p>
   <p>Stung by one <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">ant</name>, on all the grumbler trod:</p>
   <p><name type="deity">Hermes</name> appear’d, and tapp’d him with his rod.</p>
   <p>Said he, “will you not let the <name type="deity">Gods</name> then do</p>
   <p>To you that justice, the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">ants</name> meet from you?”</p>
   <p>Accustom’d ever to <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">men</name>’s haunts to cling,</p>
   <p>Her nest a tawny <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">swallow</name> built in spring</p>
   <p>On walls, that skirted some old <persName>judges</persName>’ homes;</p>
   <p>Where of seven nestlings mother she becomes;</p>
   <p>Nestlings, unfringed with purplish feathers yet;</p>
   <p>And these, each one in turn, a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">serpent</name> ate,</p>
   <p>Gliding from out his hole. The <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">bird</name> forlorn</p>
   <p>Forthwith began, in words like these, to mourn</p>
   <p>For her ill-fated babies, untimely ta’en:</p>
   <p>“Alas, my sad fate,” thus did she complain,</p>
   <p>Since, where <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">men</name>’s laws and ordinances are,</p>
   <p>Thence a poor <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">swallow</name>, injured, flies afar.”</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="61">
   <p>A <persName>man</persName>, a craftsman, cherish’d, wrought in wood, A <name type="deity">Hermes</name>, before whom each day he stood With offerings of meat and drink: yet still, Much to his indignation, he fared ill.</p>
   <p>He took the image by its leg, and dash’d It on the ground; so when its head was smash’d, Out fell some gold. He pick’d it up, and said, “Ungrateful <name type="deity">God</name> to friends, and wrong of head! For when we served thee, thou didst nowise aid, But when we scoff’d, our wrongs with good hast paid. Would I had known before that nought was due, Save this new service, <foreign xml:lang="la">Mercury</foreign>, to you.”</p>
   <p>In fables <quote><persName>Æsop</persName> Gods</quote> doth introduce, To teach us how to act in daily use. Honour to cross-grain’d folks is toil in vain; Insult them, and their kindnesses you gain.</p>
   <p>That tenant of the swamp, and friend of shade, The <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">frog</name>, who in the dykes his dwelling made, Came on dry land, and thus each creature told: “I am a doctor, who the science hold Of drugs more rare than <foreign xml:lang="la">Pœan</foreign>’s art can reach, Whom high <foreign xml:lang="la">Olympus</foreign> deems the heavenly leech.”</p>
   <p>“How then,” asked <persName>Reynard</persName>, “if you often cure, Your own sad lameness come you to endure?”</p>
   <p>A <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">hen</name> was sick. To her a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">cat</name> inclined Her head. “How do? For what have you a mind? I’ll get you all you wish. But don’t say ‘die!’ ”</p>
   <p>“If you’ll be off,” said she, “that will not I.”</p>
</div>
<div type="chapter" n="62">
   <p>An <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">ass</name> went lame, from treading on a stake; He spied a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">wolf</name>, and fearing he might take Death for his certain doom, said, “<name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Wolf</name>, I die: Hear my last breath: I’d rather thou wert nigh To sup on me, than <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">vulture</name>, or than <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">crow</name>. Yet this slight harmless bone on me bestow; The splinter from my foot extract, I pray; That painless thus my soul may wing its way To Hades.” “This I grudge not,” he replied. T’ extract the stake his teeth their aid supplied.</p>
   <p>But now the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">ass</name>, his pain and anguish sped, Kick’d the gray gaping <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">wolf</name>, and turn’d, and fled, When he had bump’d his snout, and grinders too. “Ah!” said the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">wolf</name>, “this luck to me is due! Why was it that to cure the lame I took, Who from the first knew nought, but how to cook?”</p>
   <p>When golden eggs a fine <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">hen</name> daily laid, Its owner thought to find his fortune made From endless treasure in its bowels stored: He slaughter’d it, to pounce upon the hoard. Its inward parts like other birds he found, And mourn’d his baffled hopes with grief profound. Thus oftentimes doth greediness of more Rob men of even what they had before.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="63">
   <p>In a lone spot, with no one by her side, and much cast down, a traveller espied <persName>a noble dame</persName>, who seem’d in evil case.</p>
   <p>Said he, “Why dost thou tarry in this place? What ails thee, <persName>lady</persName>? Who art thou, in sooth?”</p>
   <p>“If thou wouldst know,” she answer’d, “I am <name type="deity">Truth</name>!”</p>
   <p>At this amazed, the traveller ask’d her, “Why, haunting lone spots, from cities dost thou fly?”</p>
   <p>To which the <name type="deity">Goddess</name> of deep mind replied, “Because aforetime there were few that lied.</p>
   <p>But now hath falsehood spread o’er all mankind, and if thou’lt hear, and I may speak my mind, man’s life in these days evil we shall find.”</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="64">
   <p>A <persName>man</persName> a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Maltese dog</name> kept, and an <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">ass</name>; The latter, as was usual, <foreign xml:lang="en">corn</foreign> and <foreign xml:lang="en">grass</foreign> Ate in a courtyard, to a manger tied; But graceful gambols were the pet-<name type="animal" xml:lang="en">dog</name>’s pride, While round its lord with various leaps it pressed, And oft by him was fondled in his breast, A pleasant toy, of solace the best.</p>
   <p>The <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">ass</name> meanwhile was used to grind by night The grain of <name type="deity">Ceres</name>, fetching, while ’twas light, Wood from the hill, things needful from the field; Hence did his spirit to sore anguish yield To see the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">whelp</name> in luxury’s own lap.</p>
   <p>Losing no time his manger’s bonds to snap, With awkward capers to the hall he came, With what strange fawning! What attempts at game! The table thrown into the midst he smash’d, And all the plates at once to atoms dash’d. Next, near his master as he supp’d, he drew, His hoofs, to hug him, o’er his back he threw:</p>
   <p>But now the servant marking how he fared From this rough usage that the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">ass</name> had dared, To save their master, interposing, rushed And rescued him, when he was well-nigh crush’d.</p>
   <p>Then, as the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">ass</name> was gasping his last breath, (With <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">cornel</name> clubs they beat him near to death,) Said he, “As I deserv’d, a luckless <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">ass</name>, I suffer! Wherefore did I scorn to pass My days among the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">mules</name>? Why, wretchedly, A tiny lap-<name type="animal" xml:lang="en">dog</name>’s rival strive to be?”</p>
   <p>All are not fit for every fate, be sure: Nor is the lot of envious men secure!</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="65">
   <p>Fab. CXXV. — This fable should be carefully compared with the <foreign xml:lang="la">54th</foreign> fable in the second part of the original. The object of the translator has been to include in the <foreign xml:lang="la">125th</foreign> fable of this part, the result of a careful comparison of the two slightly differing texts.</p>
   <p>This fable is one which has been reduced to <foreign xml:lang="en">choliambic metres</foreign>, from the prose MSS. of the <placeName>Vatican</placeName>, see <persName>F. De Furia</persName>, p. 150. <name type="deity">Aristotle</name> <quote>H. A. x. 6.</quote> mentions the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Maltese dog</name>, <foreign xml:lang="grc">κυνίδιον Μελιταῖον</foreign>.</p>
   <p>Mounting a roof, an <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">ass</name> the tiling broke With his rough sport; whom with a switch’s stroke A man compell’d his downward course to track.</p>
   <p>The <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">ass</name> to him who outraged thus his back Remark’d, “Why, yesterday, and ere that too, An <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">ape</name> by this same sport delighted you.”</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="66">
   <p>Upon a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">bird-catcher</name> a <persName>friend</persName> dropt in,</p>
   <p>His meal of <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">herbs</name> just going to begin.</p>
   <p><name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Nought</name> had the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">bird-cage</name>. <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Nothing</name> had he caught.</p>
   <p>So he to slay a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">speckled partridge</name> thought,</p>
   <p>A <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">bird</name> he’d tamed and kept for a <foreign xml:lang="en">decoy</foreign>;</p>
   <p>But thus it pray’d that he would not destroy</p>
   <p>Its life: “How will you manage with your <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">net</name></p>
   <p>In <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">fowling</name> henceforth? Who for you will get</p>
   <p>Together a bright flock of social <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">birds</name>?</p>
   <p>To the sweet music of what <foreign xml:lang="en">minstrel’s</foreign> words</p>
   <p>Will you repose?” He set the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">partridge</name> free,</p>
   <p>And chose a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">bearded cock</name> for butchery.</p>
   <p>But from its perch a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">crowing</name> voice was borne,</p>
   <p>“Whence will you learn, how much it wants to morn,</p>
   <p>When you have slain the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">hour-seer</name>? or know,</p>
   <p>When sleeps <name type="deity">Orion</name> of the golden bow?</p>
   <p>Who shall of morning duties monish you,</p>
   <p>What time the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">bird-trap</name> now is moist with dew?”</p>
   <p>“True! you,” quoth he ‘the useful hours divine,</p>
   <p>Yet must my <persName>friend</persName> have wherewithal to dine!”</p>
   <p><name type="deity">Jove</name> order’d <name type="deity">Hermes</name> to write each <persName>man’s</persName> sin</p>
   <p>On <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">earthen tablets</name>, and to pile them in</p>
   <p>A <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">coffer</name>: thus to make bad <persName>men</persName> atone.</p>
   <p>But as the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">tablets</name> in a heap were thrown,</p>
   <p>Into <name type="deity">Jove’s</name> hands, at every settling day,</p>
   <p>Some quickly, others slowly find their way.</p>
   <p>We must not therefore be surprised, if some</p>
   <p>Early do ill, but late to judgment come.</p>
</div>
<div type="chapter" n="67">
   <p>Fab. <persName>CXXVIII</persName>. — This fable, like the <persName>125th</persName>, had been restored to its metrical choliambic form before the discovery of the MS. of <persName>Babrius</persName>. See the edition of <persName>F. De Furia</persName>, Fab. <persName>365</persName>. The translation is based on a comparison of this fable and of Fab. <persName>51</persName>, in the second part.</p>
   <p>In winter time, an <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">ant</name> dragged forth, to dry, Some corn, by him last summer heap’d on high. A starved <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">grasshopper</name> begg’d that he would give Some share to it, lest it would cease to live.</p>
   <p>“What did you,” asked he, “all the summer long?” “I lagg’d not, but was constant in my song.” Laughing, the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">ant</name> said, as he barr’d his wheat, “Dance in the cold, since you sang in the heat!” Of needful things ’tis better thought to take, Than joy and revels our mind’s study make</p>
   <p>A <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">sheep</name> one day addressed its <persName>shepherd</persName> thus:</p>
   <p>“You keep our fleeces after shearing us; Our teeming milk you drain, and turn to <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">cheese</name>. Your countless <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">lambs</name>, our young, not yours, are these; We get no gain, I wot! But all the earth E’en on the hills, for thee gives verdure birth, Gives tender <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">herbage</name>, laden with the dew; These are our food, yet at no cost to you. Yon <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">dog</name> the while midst us, to you so cheap, On as good food as feeds yourself, you keep.”</p>
   <p>The <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">dog</name> o’erheard and said, “Were I elsewhere And not amongst you, yours were sorry fare. Now, running round about you every way, The inroads of the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">wolf</name> and <persName>thief</persName> I stay.”</p>
</div>
<div type="book" n="2">
   <div type="chapter" n="20">
      <p>Son , to this second book thine ear incline. Should it embitter thee far more than brine, Yet afterward a sweeter taste I leave Than honey. Yet not me, I pray, receive As him that spake these fables. The belong To <name type="person">Sardian Æsop</name>, whom most grievous wrong, And god-abhor’d, at <placeName>Delphian</placeName> hands befell, So ill they treated one who sang so well . Fools that they were, they forced him down a steep, And left their sons a hateful name to keep.</p>
   </div>
</div>
<div type="chapter" n="69">
   <p>Among old saws this also <persName>Æsop</persName> said: ’Ere other birds, ’ere e’en the earth was made, A first existence had the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">lark</name>; Whose darling child reach’d life’s allotted mark, And death, it chanced, by some disorder met.</p>
   <p>Now, as the earth was not in being yet, She knew not were, (how should she?) to inter Her dead. Five days ’twas left expos’d by her: Then, sore perplex’t, for grave she lent her head.</p>
   <p>’Tis holy, gather hence, t’ entomb the dead: And filial love is a time-honour’d thing, Of laws the best; and nature’s ordering.</p>
   <p><foreign xml:lang="la">Fab.</foreign> II, — Cf. <quote><persName>Aristoph.</persName> <foreign xml:lang="la">Av.</foreign> 474.</quote></p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="126">
   <p>At leisure to indulge in seeing sights, The gaze of <persName>Æsop</persName> on a dockyard lights. He chanced on shipwrights there, with nought to do, Who at the sage their gibes full rudely threw, And by their mocking challenged his reply.</p>
   <p>His words in this not pointless fable lie. “<foreign xml:lang="la">Chaos</foreign> and <name type="water" xml:lang="en">Water</name> from the first had been; But <name type="deity">Jove</name> desired that <name type="placeName" xml:lang="en">Earth</name>, till then unseen, Above the mass of waters should arise: Then did he her ‘to swallow thrice’ advise ‘The waterfloods.’ At the first draught she made, Behold the mountains in their height display’d.</p>
   <p>When now the earth her second gulp had ta’en, Naked to view stood many a <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">grassy plain</name>. And should she soon to take a third see fit Your craft, methinks, will straight her craftsmen quit.”</p>
   <p>Who use to betters silly words and light, Alway against themselves the laugh invite.</p>
</div>
<div type="chapter" n="70">
   <p>An <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">eagle</name> once was netted by a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">hind</name>; Who, having clipp’d its wings, no more confined Its freedom midst the birds about his cot. A fowler soon this bird by purchase got, Let its wings grow, that late had been cut short, And kept it thus for purposes of sport. Soon it essay’d a flight, and seized a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">hare</name>, A gift ’twas glad to its new lord to bear. A <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">fox</name> looked on, and to the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">eagle</name> said: “To thy first lord, not this, be honour paid, Lest he again should catch thee in his toil, And thee, by clipping, of thy wings despoil.” These words the sacred <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">eagle</name>’s answer are: “Good men I must respect, from bad keep far.”</p>
   <p>A <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">vine</name> with foliage and ripe clusters bloom’d. Its shoots a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">goat</name> with nibbling tooth consumed, Whom thus the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">vine</name> addrest: “Why injure me? And browse my leaves? Is there no grass for thee? Yet thou ere long thy just deserts shalt meet. Though now my shoots thou to the quick dost eat, To me no less shall satisfaction rise, When juice o’er thee I pour in sacrifice.”</p>
   <p>Fab. V. — Compare <quote>Ovid. Fast. I. 357</quote>. See, too, <quote>Virg. Georg. II. 374-9</quote>.</p>
   <p>A <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">lion</name> and a <persName>man</persName>, together thrown, Held conversation each in boastful tone. Their gaze, in walking, on a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">statue</name> lit, A <persName>man</persName> astride a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">lion</name>, strangling it. <pb n="128"/> This <persName>man</persName> this sculpture bade the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">lion</name> see, And said, “O’er <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">lions</name> note our mastery.” “Nay,” said the beast, “if <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">lions</name> only knew The sculptor’s art, on mortals not a few By <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">lions</name> rush’d and strangled you might gaze.” Each doth himself in his own talk be-praise.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="71">
   <p>To feed a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">swan</name>, one purchase[d] with a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">goose</name>, A different reason did a <persName>man</persName> induce. One for the table, one for song was fed. So when he came the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">goose</name>’s blood to shed, (It had been fatted for its master’s board,) Night, drawing on, her film o’er all things pour’d. Best of all times for catching <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">birds</name> is night; Yet fail’d the owner to distinguish right Which was the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">swan</name>, and which the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">goose</name> might be — Hence for the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">goose</name>, by accident left free,</p>
   <p>129 Away to doom the tuneful <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">swan</name> was led; But when his song his species heralded, That song was able to postpone his end. Speech used in season many doth befriend.</p>
   <p>In marshy swamp two <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">frogs</name> were wont to bide. When in the summer season this was dried, They left, it, for another home to look, And in their road a well of water took. Beholding this, thus spake the first of these: “Into this well descend we, if you please, Since both for food and dwelling it bids fair.” The other said, with blame-suggestive air,</p>
   <p>130 “Nay, but suppose this too should chance to fail, How from a depth so great could we avail To re-ascend?” Hence learn a moral true, Without forethought ’tis useless aught to do.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="72">
   <p>The curse of an <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">frog</name> the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">frogs</name> annoy’d; Who to Heaven’s throne an embassy employ’d, To ask, if <persName>Jove</persName> would furnish them a king.</p>
   <p>He knew the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">frog</name> was but a silly thing; So order’d <persName>Hermes</persName> right into the bog To throw, for king of croakers, a mute <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">log</name>.</p>
   <p>As the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">log</name> fell, the waters felt the blow, And the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">frogs</name> hasten’d to the depths below, In terror for the moment at the sound.</p>
   <p>But a short space, after these things, went round; And when they saw their sov’reign motionless, They cast off fear, scorn only to profess; So much so, that on it the boldly stept, And mounted there, seats undisputed kept.</p>
   <p>Such king to own, occasion’d high disdain; And up they went to the <placeName>Gods’ courts</placeName> again, Where they the chief of rulers much besought To send them such a monarch as they ought To have. “That <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">beam</name> was quite unfit to sway Mute <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">logs</name>, far more such living beings as they.</p>
   <p>That <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">stump</name> was grown but to be food for fire.”</p>
   <p>Next <persName>Jove</persName> sent down an <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">eel</name> for their desire.</p>
   <p>They saw that this was also a mere fool, And would not have it over them to rule.</p>
   <p>A third legation then they sent of <persName>Jove</persName>, With earnest pray’r their second king to move. And give them one with better sense supplied, Fitly o’er them with justice to preside.</p>
   <p>Their message, heard, led <persName>Jove</persName> offence to take, And send them for their king a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">water-snake</name>; Who, getting all in turn within his power, Did each poor <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">frog</name> with ruthless maw devour; No more to cry “coäx,” no more to croak!</p>
</div>
<div type="chapter" n="73">
   <p>they their love revoke.</p>
   <p>An archer at an <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">eagle</name> took his aim. The shaft he sent, true to the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">eagle</name> came. To whom when, as he turn’d his head, ’twas known, The shaft was wing’d with feathers of his own; With mine own feather I have made my bed.” “Ah! luckless me!” his dying accents said: With mine own feathers I have made my bed.” Most from their own, much loss have sufferèd.</p>
   <p>Their wain some <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">oxen</name> to a village drew. And at its creaking axle wrathful grew. Turning to it, they said, “Why creak you thus? When all the burden has been laid on us.” When others work, some call the toil their own, And, over what they had no hand in, moan.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="11">
   <p>Fab. XI. — Compare the slightly varied fable of Babrius, Part I Fab. 52.</p>
   <p>Two <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">frogs</name> were dwelling each to other near; Now one abode in a deep marshy mere, Which at no distance from the highroad lay; One in a puddle on the carriage-way.</p>
   <p>He of the mere the other recommends To change his quarters, come, and live as friends, And thus a safer dwelling to obtain. The other said, declining, “’Twould be pain Too great for him accustom’d haunts to quit,” And held his way, till passing over it A wagon came by; by which the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">frog</name> was crushed, And thus on fate, by not complying, rush’d.</p>
</div>
<div type="chapter" n="74">
  <p>For common use to <persName>Rhea</persName>’s vagrant priests Was sold an <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">ass</name>, most luckless among beasts, That it might carry for these begging knaves Rites, food, whate’er from thirst or hunger saves.</p>
  <p>These roam’d, as is their wont, the country through, And craved provisions, asking, “Who but knew, 135 Among the swains, how <persName>Attis</persName> fair was maim’d? To <persName>Rhea</persName>’s drum who would not be ashamed To fail in gifts of first-rate pulse and bread?”</p>
  <p>At length the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">ass</name>, o’erburden’d, fell down dead, Poor wretch, and said good-bye to all his toil. Him the rogues hasten’d of his hide to spoil, And stretch’d it, closely-fitted, o’er a drum:</p>
  <p>On other roguish priests they chanced to come, As they were roaming through the villages, Furnished with drums. And they were asked by these, How fared their <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">ass</name>. “It died long time ago,” They answered, “yet it now receives a blow So often, that, had it been still alive, ’Neath these it could by no means long survive.”</p>
</div>
<div type="chapter" n="75">
   <p>Ibid. v. 6, 7. — <persName>Atys</persName> or <persName>Attis</persName> was a beautiful shepherd of <placeName>Phrygia</placeName>, beloved by <name type="deity">Cybele</name>, whence arose all his misfortunes. See <quote>Ovid. <foreign xml:lang="la">Fast.</foreign> iv. 221-44</quote>. His death was annually bewailed by the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Galli</name>. Compare the poem on the subject of <persName>Atys</persName> in <quote><persName>Catullus</persName>, LXIII</quote>. — These references will explain the allusions in the text of this fable.</p>
   <p>A rustic saw an <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">eagle</name> in the snare, And, as he much admired its beauty rare, He loosed it from its fetters forth to roam: Thence did the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">eagle</name> a warm friend become To its preserver. For, t’avoid the heat And catch the breeze, it saw him take his seat Beneath a wall. It snatch’d, as o’er it flew, A burden from his head, and this it threw Far off. The rustic, eager to pursue His pack, made for it. Down the walling fell: And thus the rustic was requited well. Kind acts, if <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">birds</name> in grateful memory set, Can any, save the worst of <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">men</name>, forget?</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="76">
   <p>Gold <foreign xml:lang="la">,</foreign> as the earth he dug, a labourer found, And every day with garlands wreath’d the ground, Seeing that thence he reap’d undoubted good: But with this speech dame <persName>Fortune</persName> o’er him stood: “Why ever, man, dost thou my gifts mistake For earth’s? ’Twas I that did thy riches make, I, by whose help ’tis said that some are blest, Who chance to find me kinder than the rest; And those unblest, to whom bad luck I bring. Now I enrich thee thus, as purposing To try thy judgment, while this wealth I send, Whether thou wilt it well or ill expend. ’Twere meet, thou shouldst feel gratitude to me; For if thy nature changed with times should be, And thou unworthily shouldst squander all, On me, and not on earth, the blame would fall.”</p>
   <p>If any to thee do an office kind, See that they never thee unmindful find.</p>
   <p>A very careful dame, of busy way, Kept <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">maids</name> at home, and these, ere break of day, She used to rouse as early as <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">cock</name>-<name type="animal" xml:lang="en">crow</name>. They thought ’twas hard to be awaken’d so, And o’er wool-spinning be at work so long; Hence grew within them all a purpose strong To kill the house-<name type="animal" xml:lang="en">cock</name>, whom they thought to blame For all their wrongs. But no advantage came. Worse treatment than the former them befell; For when the hour their mistress could not tell At which by night the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">cock</name> was wont to crow, She roused them earlier, to their work to go. A harder lot the wretched <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">maids</name> endured. Back judgment oft hath such results procured.</p>
</div>
<div type="chapter" n="XVI">
  <p>Fab. <name type="section" n="2">XVI. 2</name>, — A slight emendation of the Greek text suggests itself to the translator, viz. to read <foreign xml:lang="grc">ἅσπερ</foreign> for <foreign xml:lang="grc">ὥσπερ</foreign>, and to omit the comma after <foreign xml:lang="grc">εἰώθει</foreign>. This gives an intelligible sense to the passage, and facilitates translation. In the next fable verses 13-17 are evidently imperfect, and it is hopeless to attempt a literal translation. An approximatory guess is the translator’s only resource.</p>
  <p>A woman boasted the divining art, And that, when <name type="deity">Gods</name> make the wrongdoer smart Her spells could bar the curse of ancient sin. Large fee paid those who would her secret win. She found this trade all arts of life surpass’d; So when the witch much substance had amass’d, Some, on this charge, an accusation wrote, And she was sentenced by a fateful vote.</p>
  <p>One saw her led away for death, and cried; “What! was it not thy promise and thy pride, From other mortals wrath <name type="deity">divine</name> to turn? Thy jurors’ votes why didst thou fail to earn By thy persuasion? This escaped thy plan, (Thinking t’ upset things sacred, and to man The counsels of the <name type="deity">Gods</name>-above unseal, And how much anger they toward sinners feel,) To avert thy dragging o’er the fatal way.”</p>
  <p>A just atonement lying prophets pay.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="78">
   <p>Afflicted with disorder in the eyes, An ancient dame a famous doctor tries, In hopes that he her malady may cure. Now ’twas greed, before a witness sure, That if that woman’s eyesight he should save, An ample fee the oculist should have: But if the healer rid not of disease His patient, he should forfeit all his fees.</p>
   <p>As then with oils he did her eyes anoint, And of his daily visit made a point, Blindfolding her withal, her sight to shade, Free with his patient’s property he made. Thus he continued every day to do, And when he by degrees her goods withdrew, And all her stock had actually ta’en, At last the woman did her sight regain.</p>
   <p>Of course the healer further claim’d his fee. The dame, with sight recover’d, fail’d to see Aught of her chattels, and refused to pay A doctor, who with these had made away.</p>
   <p>The healer pressed his suit, his payment sought; She put him off, and would not pay him aught. Before the courts he therefore brings the case, And then the woman, standing face to face Before the jurors, told them all the truth:</p>
   <p>“This doctor, gentlemen, pretends, in sooth, He heal’d mine eyes, which healing balms did need; But I maintain that blindness sore indeed I suffer still; for with mine ailing eyes I saw goods, chattels, riches, all I prize, At home. But now, when yon rogue says I see, Not one of these, I say, is seen by me.”</p>
   <p>’Tis thus, to love of gain when bad men yield, By their own hands their doings are reveal’d.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="79">
   <p>One day some <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">dogs</name> a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">lion</name>’s skin had found; To tear it hasten’d each audacious hound; And when a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">fox</name> their impudence beheld,</p>
   <p>“If still,” said she, “his place the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">lion</name> held Amid the living, ye should find his claws Would, oh! how much, surpass your feebler jaws.”</p>
   <p>To lesser men who, left alone, assail An absent better, use this simple tale!</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="80">
   <p>A <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">dragon</name> and an <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">eagle</name> fiercely met, Contending, which should which as captive get.</p>
   <p>The <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">dragon</name> got the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">eagle</name> ’neath his yoke, And bound him fast, so as almost to choke.</p>
   <p>A farmer saw, and loosed the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">dragon</name>-chain, And bade the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">eagle</name> roam at large again.</p>
   <p>At this the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">dragon</name> deep resentment bore, And in the farmer’s cup did venom pour.</p>
   <p>So when he was about to lift it up, Not knowing its contents, and drain the cup,</p>
   <p>On this the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">eagle</name> pounced with flapping wings, And from the farmer’s grasp the vessel flings.</p>
   <p>Thus him that saved him did the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">eagle</name> save, Thus to his champion grateful succour gave.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="81">
   <p>Some busy <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">bees</name>, beneath an old <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">oak</name>’s roots Were making wax of gather’d <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">flowers</name> and <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">fruits</name>.</p>
   <p>A shepherd saw them in sweet toil partake, And of their comb a capture fain would make.</p>
   <p>Round him they buzz’d, outvying one another T’ avert the theft, the thief with stings to smother.</p>
   <p>At last the shepherd, stung and smitten sore, Exclaim’d, “I go! no honey want I more, If I must needs encounter stings of <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">bees</name>!”</p>
   <p>Keep from another’s goods, and dwell at ease.</p>
</div>
<div type="chapter" n="80">
  <p>A <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">shipwreck’d man</name>, by <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">ocean</name> cast ashore,</p>
  <p>Slept when his weary toil at last was o’er;</p>
  <p>But, in a while, up-rising out of sleep,</p>
  <p>He blamed with many a charge the treach’rous <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">deep</name>;</p>
  <p>Saying, that she had <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">sailors</name> oft beguiled,</p>
  <p>Wearing for these a surface calm and mild,</p>
  <p>And a fair face, betokening placid <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">seas</name>,</p>
  <p>And yet o’erwhelm’d them, if they tried the breeze.</p>
  <p>But she to him in words like these replied:</p>
  <p>“<persName>Sailor</persName>, who crossest oft the <name type="placeName">ocean-tide</name>,</p>
  <p>The <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">winds</name>, not me, I pray thee, learn to blame;</p>
  <p>For my calm nature ever is the same,</p>
  <p>As thou beholdest even at this hour;</p>
  <p>But when, unlook’d for, boist’rous <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">tempests</name> lour,</p>
  <p>With anger’d <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">waves</name> my depths they agitate.”</p>
  <p>Let blame on causes, not their agents, wait.</p>
</div>
<div type="chapter" n="81">
   <p>A deep-toned <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">ass</name>, with over-weening bray, Proclaim’d to every beast a congress-day.</p>
   <p>The meeting’s object was a king to name, From whose wise rule the brutes might justice claim.</p>
   <p>An <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">ape</name> amongst them danced to music’s sound, And hence as king of beasts was named, and crowned.</p>
   <p>The envious <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">fox</name> was bent to play the cheat: Fixt in some nets she saw a piece of meat, And led the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">monkey</name> to the guilesome snare, Saying, “I’ve found a treasure vast and rare, A prize, by human custom, due to kings.”</p>
   <p>Into the nets the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">monkey</name> thus she brings.</p>
   <p>Said <persName>Reynard</persName>, mocking, “Being such a fool, Dost think, good <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">ape</name>, among the beasts to rule? Fare as befits thee, and not ill thou’lt fare; But over-strength will heavier damage share.</p>
</div>
<div type="chapter" n="82">
   <p>Prometheus, <name type="deity">Jove</name>, and the <name type="deity">Tritonian</name> maid, That each would make one thing, agreed and said.</p>
   <p><name type="deity">Jove</name> made a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">bull</name>; <persName>Prometheus</persName> fashion’d <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">men</name>; <persName>Pallas</persName> a dwelling.</p>
   <p><persName>Momus</persName> then Was critic. He, of hatred ever full To works divine, said, “<name type="deity">Jove</name> had spoil’d the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">bull</name>; Whereas o’er horns he should have placed the eyes, Eye below horn in <name type="deity">Jove</name>’s construction lies.”</p>
   <p><persName>Prometheus</persName> was to blame: he fail’d to place Man’s mind outside, “that none in actions base Might lack detection, each might plainly read Of what each sev’ral <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">man</name> stood most in need.”</p>
   <p>Nor did the work of <persName>Pallas</persName> pass unblamed; “Unfixt, of right, should be the house she framed, With wheels beneath, that if an evil one Should sojourn near, with ease it might begone.”</p>
   <p>Justly was <name type="deity">Jove</name> with <persName>Momus</persName> wroth, I wot, Who the Gods’ gifts to censure scrupled not.</p>
   <p>My son, this fable’s teaching is not small; Into oblivion do not let it fall.</p>
   <p>For ever toward mankind the Gods are good; Yet, not e’en these escape maligners rude; And if, in fact, Gods could not <persName>Momus</persName> flee, What must not <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">men</name> endure from such as he?</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="83">
   <p>A herald to the fight the host did stir: No warrior he, but a good <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">trumpeter</name>. Now he, when taken, to his captors spake, “My life, for I am guiltless, do not take; For never man in the wild battle-plain Have I, nor e’en my faithful <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">trumpet</name>, slain. No metal beside this do I possess.” This was to him their answer pitiless:</p>
   <p>149 “Why, ’tis for this thou art about to die, More than all else. Thou giv’st the battle-cry To others, though no fighter. That man kills, Who any work, through which we die, fulfils.</p>
   <p>Along a narrow lane went <persName>Hercules</persName>; And something <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">sheep</name>-like on the ground he sees, Which with his club t’ exterminate he tries; But it, once struck, began to grow in size. Seeing it to such bulk so quickly swell, To heavier blows with all his might he fell. To wondrous bulk again the monster rose, And block’d the way, all passage to oppose. <persName>Hercules</persName> marv’l’d how the thing could end, Cast down his club, and halted. Where to wend He knew not. Lo! <name type="deity">Athena</name> met his sight.</p>
   <p>“Spare toil,” quoth she, “and, hero, learn aright, Strife is the strange appearance which you see. Let it but, as before, unhinder’d be, And unincreas’d ’twill bide. In contest thus Swoll’n, as you see, it masters all of us.”</p>
</div>
<div type="chapter" n="84">
   <p>Ridden to feast at each immortal’s side, The hero once with men, now deified, Sweet converse with each <name type="deity">God</name> held <persName>Hercules</persName>, Till he had come to <name type="deity">Plutus</name>, last of these.</p>
   <p>To speak to him the hero’s soul disdain’d, Nor converse with him, like the rest, maintain’d.</p>
   <p><persName>Jove</persName> in amazement for an answer press’d, Why he had ev’ry other <name type="deity">God</name> address’d,</p>
   <p>But not one syllable to <name type="deity">Plutus</name> said.</p>
   <p>Then <persName>Hercules</persName> to <persName>Jove</persName> this answer made:</p>
   <p>“Why, because him, abhorr’d on earth by me, I never saw but in rogues’ company.”</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="1">
   <p>For beauty’s prize once strove the <name type="plant">apple-tree</name> With the <name type="plant">pomegranate</name>. Each strove angrily.</p>
   <p>The thorn-inflicting <name type="animal">bramble</name>, dwelling nigh, Heard all the strife, and utter’d language high To both.</p>
   <p>“Let us from rivalry desist For beauty’s prize, my friends.” Bid that man list This fable, who himself, tho’ vastly less, Would thrust mid nobler men, through foolishness.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="2">
   <p><quote><persName>Fab.</persName> XXVIII. — Compare the epimyth of this fable, which has a political end in view, with Fable 39, Part I. v. 3, 4.</quote></p>
   <p>As men to work did from a village go, Upon their path came suddenly a <name type="animal">crow</name>, Flying above, and blind in his left eye:</p>
   <p>And one man said that this was reason why They should turn back: the omen did not bode Good luck to them, if they pursued their road.</p>
   <p>Not without wit the other answer’d thus:</p>
   <p>“How could that <name type="animal">bird</name> tell aught of fate to us, Which not her own bereavement had foreknown, Or round her eyes a guard she would have thrown.”</p>
</div>
<div type="chapter" n="85">
   <p>
      Bearing aloft a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">snake</name> the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">kite</name> up-flew,
      Whom with a bite its captive turning slew,
      And thus addrest him as he breath’d his last:
      “Into such phrensy wherefore wast thou cast,
      As to have injured me, who hurt thee not?
      What thou for me designedst, is thy lot.”
   </p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="86">
   <p>A <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">troop</name> unto a <placeName>village</placeName> hies,
   A muster strong of over-ruling <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Lies</name>.
   Of broider’d purple were the robes they wore;
   Each of their <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">steeds</name> its golden cheek-piece bore.</p>
   <p>Behind, a throng audacious follow’d quick,
   <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Deceit</name> and <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Guile</name>, and every knavish <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Trick</name>.
   And lo! they met a <persName>maiden</persName> on their road,
   Her dress and fashion of a simple mode,
   Nay, somewhat poor. Yet stately was her mien,
   And long unfed, poor sufferer, had she been.</p>
   <p>Her did these <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Lies</name> accost, and sought to know
   Whither, and on what errand she would go.
   She answer’d, “Pardon sirs, if no reply
   Comes from a throat with thirst and hunger dry.”</p>
   <p>So then <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Lies</name> thus answer’d her again: —
   “To yon near <placeName>village</placeName> follow in our train;
   ’Tis but a small one, yet ‘’tis well supplied;
   Well-victuall’d hostels will good cheer provide;
   Come as our guest, and you shall eat your fill.”</p>
   <p>She followed them, deject, and downcast still,
   Into the inn: but ne’er a word she said.</p>
   <p>Mine host on their arrival quickly spread
   For them a table fill’d with various <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">meats</name>,
   Whence each one, as he lists, his fancy treats.
   This done, they bridled <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">steeds</name>, and cried “to horse!”</p>
   <p>When for his reckoning asks the host, of course.
   On this the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Lies</name> were wroth at his demand,
   Which they nor paid, nor yet would understand.
   The brood of impudence in vain he sues:
   They answer straight: “That he has had his dues,
   That they have paid, like gentlemen, the cost.”
   To press each for his share was labour lost:
   And much less could he force the banded throng:
   Against a troop</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="87">
   <p>was ever one man strong? Upon the door-step stay’d the fellow-guest, Without a word, but still with look deprest. The landlord now despair’d to see his own: And “Truth, where art thou?” cried in heighten’d tone. She answer’d: “Here, good sir, but what to do I knew not: till I met yon reckless crew, My want of food was wholly unsupplied; Ay, and without them, I had long since died.”</p>
   <p>A <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">lion</name> met a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">goat</name>, beside a spring, In summer thirst to all brings suffering, To beasts, and soil, and plants no less than man. For the first sip a quarrel then began. Dire was the strife, and would have led to death. But that the parted, to recover breath For further conflict, just a little space, Looking each other fiercely in the face: And gathering <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">vultures</name> suddenly they spied, Which, from aloft, their wrathful struggle eyed, In expectation of a well-timed treat, Since he that fell would furnish dainty meat. Now, as on these the weary champions gaze,</p>
   <p>“Come, cease we fighting,” each to other says; Better be friends, than yield the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">vultures</name> food!” By thee, my son, too, be dire strife eschew’d, For homes and cities it hath ever strew’d.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="88">
   <p>A <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">crow</name> the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">swans</name> their fair complexion grudged: He would have been quite as white-skinn’d, he judged, Did he but float on river, or on lake: He left the hearths, where he was wont to take His food, and to the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">swans</name>’ dank dwelling went. To him no change of hue ablution lent, But famine kill’d him, when no food he got. Nature a change of dwelling alters not.</p>
   <p>To <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">swallow</name> eggs was a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">dog</name>’s wonted fun: Seeing a <foreign xml:lang="la">cockle</foreign>, this he took for one, And gorged it with a gulp immediately: Then sorely griped in bowels by and by, “A just reward,” quoth he, “my sin hath found Because for eggs I took whate’er was round.” Choose thou the real, not what fair may sound.</p>
   <p>A <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">bull</name> a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">lion</name> wrapt in slumber caught, Whose death by goring with his horns he wrought; His dame came up, and o’er her cub made wail: A wild <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">boar</name> overheard her piteous tale. Standing afar, — “How many more,” quoth he, “Of mothers weep for offspring bitterly, Which having slaughter’d, ye your banquet keep.” Know that ill-doers their deserts shall reap.</p>
</div>
<div type="chapter" n="89">
   <p>A <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">gnat</name> boasting drew to a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">lion</name> near: And said: “No greater strength for me to fear
   Has thou! What is thy force? — with claws to scratch,
   With teeth to bite? — this might a <persName>woman</persName> match:
   Nay, oft she does, when striving with her mate
   For no great ends. My strength is far more great.
   But come! let us the strength of each compare!” It buzz’d, and fixed on parts devoid of hair,
   And the poor <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">lion</name>’s face and nostrils stung.
   That <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">lion</name>’s claws to his own visage clung,
   <pb n="160"/>
   Reeking with blood. He yielded in despair.
   Then the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">gnat</name>’s trumpet sounded triumph rare.
   It flew aloft, in <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">lion</name>-victor’s pride,
   Till, captured in a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">spider</name>’s web, it cried,
   “Alas, my wretched fate, since e’en tho’ I
   The greatest conqueror, by the small I die!”
   Weakness ’gainst strength may something seem to do,
   Yet pays the cost to foes it never knew.</p>
   <p>A <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">swallow</name> twittering hail’d a husky <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">crow</name>.
   “Me for a royal maid of <placeName>Athens</placeName> know!
   And as a daughter of her kings of yore:
   Not small renown our home of heroes bore.”
   To this vague prattle (love of talk was strong:)
   She adds the tale of <persName>Tereus</persName>, and his wrong.
   <pb n="161"/>
   These words to her the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">crow</name> in answer said:
   “<persName>Pandion</persName>’s boastful child, <placeName>Athenian</placeName> maid!
   Had you a tongue, to what lengths would you go,
   Since, when it is cut off, you twitter so!”</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="90">
   <p>A <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">gull</name> once gorged a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">fish</name>, fell down, and died, Because its throat to pass the spoil denied. A <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">kite</name> looked on, and said: “Just fate ensues, Since, though a fowl, a fishy food you choose.” Aim your own station, and no more, to fill, Work nature’s hests, and you escape from ill.</p>
   <p>At summer season, o’er a <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">flowery mead</name> A well maned <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">horse</name> was wont at large to feed; And ill brook’d he that any other <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">beast</name> Should graze the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">herbage</name>, where he loved to feast. For his sole use he deemed the meads unfold Their verdure. But a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">stag</name>, not over bold, Came oft, and nibbled at the grassy plain; So how to punish her he wrack’d his brain. Seeing a <persName>man</persName>, he ask’d his sage advice, Who said that he would help him in a trice To take upon the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">stag</name> a vengeance just, If to the bridle he his mouth would trust, And on his saddled back the <persName>man</persName> might ride. The <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">horse</name> — a slave since then till now — complied. Observe, I pray, the grievous curse entail’d, Where selfishness has over sense prevail’d.</p>
</div>
<div type="chapter" n="91">
   <p>A <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">lion</name> sick within his cave reclined; Then came each beast of all the savage kind To visit and enquire for their king. Beyond the rest the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">fox</name> kept loitering.</p>
   <p>Now, the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">wolf</name> fixt on this auspicious time Slily to charge the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">fox</name> with treason’s crime, “Since she alone with negligence did treat The king of brutes, to which the earth is meat, When she to ease his sufferings should be near, As wise in counsel, and in judgment clear:”</p>
   <p>— Up came the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">fox</name>, as the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">wolf</name> closed his speech, And his last words chanc’d <persName>Reynard</persName>’s ears to reach, The <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">lion</name> shook his mane in angry mood, To see the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">fox</name> into his cave intrude; But the sagacious <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">fox</name> was nowise cowed, And only pray’d for right of speech allowed, ’Twas granted. Then said she (the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">wolf</name> stood near):</p>
   <p>164 “Now who, my liege, of beasts assembled here, Hath render’d thee such loyal aid as I? I have the country traversed low and high, And question’d every leech concerning thee, In hopes some one might point a remedy; Aye and I’ve found, nor vainly sought, the way: Physicians learnèd by experience say, That hence the patient certain ease shall win, If from a living <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">wolf</name> he strip the skin, And this, yet warm, around his body wrap.”</p>
   <p>He said. Forthwith the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">wolf</name>, that plann’d a trap, Lay dead; and thus the debt of malice paid.</p>
   <p>O <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">wolf</name>, ill-fated!” <persName>Reynard</persName> laughing said, ’Twas better that thou shouldst not counsel ill The <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">lion</name>, but guide right his kindly will: For whoso against other brings about Evil, the same shall turn and find him out.”</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="92">
   <p>The <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">lion</name> urged it as a constant charge
   Against <name type="deity">Prometheus</name>, that while fine and large
   He made him, and with teeth had arm’d his jaw,
   Fencing withal each foot with horny claw,
   And rank’d from first of <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">brutes</name> for valour’s praise,
   “Such though I am, the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">cock</name> my soul dismays,”
   Quoth he. <name type="deity">Prometheus</name> made him this reply:
   “Pray, why on me should idle censure lie?
   All I could give thou hast, as it was fit;
   But if at times thy spirit quells a whit,
   No marvel! In nought else thou fallest short.”
   So when <name type="deity">Prometheus</name> gave him this retort,
   The <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">lion</name> bitterly his fate bemoan’d,
   And his own cowardice, condemning, own’d.
   He cared no more to live in such disgrace,
   But, in this mind, encounter’d face to face
   <pb n="166"/>
   An <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">elephant</name>, with which to talk he stay’d.
   Seeing its ears were hither thither sway’d,
   He asked, “Why thus in motion keep your ears?
   What <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">beast</name>, good sir, so dread to you appears,
   As thus your hearing-organs to confound?”
   It chanced a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">gnat</name> buzz’d presently around:
   “Seest thou yon buzzing mite?” the huge beast said,
   Let it once pierce mine ear, and I am dead.”
   The <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">lion</name> hearing this, took heart to cry,
   “Why should I any more desire to die,
   Since better far than <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">elephants</name> am I?
   And as much better in my lot have fared,
   As <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">cock</name> beats <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">gnat</name>, when both have been compared.”
   None are unblest, save by comparison:
   This is a wise saw, and an ancient one.</p>
</div>
<div type="chapter" n="41">
  <p>Fab. XLI. 6. — <persName>Pliny</persName>, in his <title type="work">Natural History</title>, x. 24, says of the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">cock</name>, “that it is an object of terror even to <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">lions</name>, the noblest of the brute kind.” The <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">elephant</name> seems to be very sensitive of the attacks of <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">insects</name>, frequently rolling itself in mud, contracting his skin, and so crushing them between its wrinkles, or gathering boughs with his trunk to brush them away, or, if these artifices fail, collecting dust with his trunk, and strewing it over the most sensible parts of his body. See <title type="work">Encycl. Britann.</title> Art. <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Mammalia</name>, vol. 12, pp. 469, 70.</p>
  <p>The fine-helm’d <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">peacock</name> and the <foreign xml:lang="la">Libyan</foreign> <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">crane</name> Were wont to pasture on one grassy plain, Long time in mutual amity they passed, But dire contention made them foes at last, And golden plumage strove with ashen hue, To which a good complexion’s meed was due. Jibes at the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">crane</name> the grinning <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">peacock</name> throws, And mocks its colour with uplifted nose; Claiming his own “to be the perfect wing Of gold and purple, worthy of a king.” To whom the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">crane</name> a fitting answer made: “And yet ’tis I who could-capp’d heights pervade; Nighest the shining stars my notes are heard, While you are but a weak and slow-paced bird, That skim the ground, nor ever upward go; But, like a <foreign xml:lang="en">bantam-cock</foreign>, mid chickens crow.” 168 Fame, tho’ I threadbare went, I’d covet most; Riches, with name unknown, on me were lost.</p>
</div>
<div type="chapter" n="XLII">
   <p>Fab. XLII. — Compare Fab. LXV in Part I. and LXXXV. Part II. Avianus, Fab. 15, says, “<quote>Threiciam volucrem fertur Junonius ales</quote>,” c., and Ælian notes that the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">crane</name> migrates in the autumn to <placeName>Libya</placeName> and <placeName>Ægypt</placeName>, N. A. II. 1, III. 13. Compare Aristoph. <foreign xml:lang="grc">Aves</foreign>. 710. The epimyth here and at Fable LXV. in the first part are very similar.</p>
   <p>A <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">wolf</name>, whom fellow <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">wolves</name> to lead them chose, Would fain to all an equal law propose, That whatsoe’er each took in foraging, To share amongst his fellows he should bring. An <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">ass</name> heard this, and bristling up his mane, To the fair dealer spoke in laughing strain: “Well have you said, intending laws to frame To govern <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">wolves</name>. But tell me how you came In a sly corner of your lair to lay A part the feast, which you stole yesterday?”</p>
   <p>In desert spots a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">wolf</name> had chanced to roam, And, when the day-star near’d its western home, Seeing his shadow long and tall appear, Said, “Being larger, need I <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">lions</name> fear? Sure, to a hundred feet in measure grown, I shall be lord of all, not brutes alone!” Upon the’ exulting <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">wolf</name> a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">lion</name> sprung, And seized and ate him. The confession wrung From his last utterance was, ‘My cause of doom Is, that on self-opinion I presume.’</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="95">
   <p>Bitten by <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">dogs</name>, a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">wolf</name> lay sick and sore, And of a passing <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">sheep</name> began to implore Relief for thirst. A spring of water flow’d Hard by. Then said he, “Were there but bestow’d By thee a draught of this, my thirst to slake, To furnish mine own meat I’d undertake.”</p>
   <p>“I give thee drink! then I should be thy meat!” The <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">sheep</name> replied. Fly foes that use deceit.</p>
   <p>A <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">daw</name> in size his fellows much surpass’d, So on his tribe a scornful glance he cast, And chose to be a tribesman of the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">crows</name>. He therefore sought their presence, to propose Dwelling with them, and clubbing for his food. His form they neither knew, nor understood His accents, with his race in unison; So, beating him, they made him quick begone.</p>
   <p>Driven from these, he sought his own again; But they, at his desertion in disdain — Because they thought his conduct insolent — To take him back by no means would consent. An outlaw’d, homeless <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">daw</name> was he from thence. None will attain with strangers influence.</p>
   <p>On <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">honey</name> in a storeroom spilt, some <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">flies</name> Began to feast in gathering companies. The sweet repast their lingering wills detain’d, And as their feet were by its pow’r constrain’d, Upon the wing no longer could they rise; Then, as they choke, each one to other cries, “Alas! poor creatures, down our lives we lay, Most sadly by brief pleasure led astray.”</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="96">
   <p>The <name type="deity" xml:lang="en">moon</name> her lady mother once besought,</p>
   <p>That a close-fitting tunic might be wrought</p>
   <p>For her. To whom her mother, smiling, said,</p>
   <p>“How shall a dress be wrought or measurèd</p>
   <p>173</p>
   <p>For thy uncertain figure? over-great</p>
   <p>Now, near the full; and then in bursting state;</p>
   <p>Gibbous and crescent-shaped thou wilt be soon.</p>
   <p>All through the month come changes of the moon.”</p>
   <p>A <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">field-mouse</name> to a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">frog</name>, by evil lot,</p>
   <p>Became a friend, and hence destruction got;</p>
   <p>For with the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">field-mouse</name> first they came to eat,</p>
   <p>And then resorted to the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">frog</name>’s retreat.</p>
   <p>But evil soon became the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">frog</name>’s design.</p>
   <p>He tied his friend’s foot to him with a line,</p>
   <p>And dragg’d him to the margin of a lake,</p>
   <p>A bath within its marshy depths to take:</p>
   <p>Drown’d by the waters thus, the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">mouse</name> was choked,</p>
   <p>And perish’d, to a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">frog</name> by being yoked.</p>
   <p>Its corpse then as the eddying surface bore,</p>
   <p>A <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">hawk</name> with eager talons upward tore,</p>
   <p>174</p>
   <p>With it was dragg’d the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">frog</name>, to which ’twas tied:</p>
   <p>Doom’d for the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">hawk</name> two banquets to provide,</p>
   <p>He learn’d what wages want of thought betide.</p>
</div>
<div type="chapter" n="97">
   <p>To a young <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">swallow</name> but one garb was left, Of all but this by reckless waste bereft.</p>
   <p>He saw a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">swallow</name>, out of season, fly Near him, and heard its twittering cry.</p>
   <p>Thinking at once that the spring-tide was near, Of parting with his coat he had no fear; And so he took and sold it, like the rest: But soon, when winter storms about her prest, And suddenly the strong wind round her roll’d, Alas! the wretched <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">swallow</name> died of cold.</p>
   <p>Her for a while the young man looked upon, And said, “Poor <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">bird</name>, much evil hast thou done!</p>
   <p>175 Appearing ere the spring-tide, thou hast wrought Ruin to me, and to thyself, for nought.</p>
   <p>Evil is wastefulness and want-of-thought.</p>
</div>
<div type="chapter" n="98">
  <p>A <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">sheep</name> one day address’d its shepherd thus: “You shear our fleece, and keep it, shorn, from us; You drain our milk, and press it, if you choose: Our young to swell your flock we ne’er refuse.</p>
  <p>For us nought else you do, but simply lead To pasture. All the grass, on which we feed, Is found for you by kind, all-nursing earth. E’en on the hills a fruitful soil gives birth For you, without your help, to venture new, Beneath moist air, and soft descending dew.</p>
  <p>Yet while such profit from us you derive, Still you would have your <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">dog</name> among us thrive, Feeding it, as yourself, on best of food.”</p>
  <p>The <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">dog</name> was near and heard. These words ensued: “O, thou that bleatest foolish-minded talk, Were it not that I oft amidst you walk, Abundant herbage you no more would eat, But be to brutes, that roam the hills, a treat. Now running all around you, timid <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">sheep</name> From busy thief, and ravening <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">wolf</name> I keep.”</p>
  <p>To thankless men this fable is addrest, Who benefactors with ill-names molest.</p>
</div>
<div type="chapter" n="99">
   <p>An <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">ass</name> was fond of eating prickly food, And grinning <persName>Reynard</persName> ask’d, when this she view’d,</p>
   <p>“With tongue so soft, how is it, best of <foreign xml:lang="la">brutes</foreign>,</p>
   <p>That on hard food you live, and thorny fruits?</p>
   <p>How can your tongue from prickly wounds escape?”</p>
   <p>To babblers well this fable thou may’st shape.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="1">
   <p>In <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">lion</name>’s skin an <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">ass</name> once went about,</p>
   <p>And threw the <foreign xml:lang="la">brute</foreign> creation into rout;</p>
   <p>They thought him a true <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">lion</name>, not an <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">ass</name>:</p>
   <p>He therefore tried, when <persName>Reynard</persName> chanced to pass,</p>
   <p>If, like the rest, a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">fox</name> would yield to fright.</p>
   <p>But when he met that wily creature’s sight</p>
   <p>(Now she, by chance, that moment heard him <foreign xml:lang="en">bray</foreign>),</p>
   <p>Quoth she to him, “Be sure of what I say,</p>
   <p>Had I not just now mark’d you when you <foreign xml:lang="en">bray’d</foreign>,</p>
   <p>I, like my fellow-<name type="animal" xml:lang="en">brutes</name>, had been afraid.”</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="2">
   <p>A <persName>countryman</persName> had placed upon his <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">ass</name> An <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">image</name>; and, in driving, made him pass</p>
   <p>Right through a <placeName>village</placeName>. All men homage paid</p>
   <p>Unto the <name type="deity">idol</name>. Then the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">ass</name> betray’d</p>
   <p>Elation, thought himself a <name type="deity">god</name>, and felt</p>
   <p>That ’twas to his <foreign xml:lang="en">divinity</foreign> they knelt.</p>
   <p>Pricking his ears, with an astounding <foreign xml:lang="en">bray</foreign>,</p>
   <p>He presently declined the onward way:</p>
   <p>At seeing which his <persName>driver</persName> angry grew,</p>
   <p>And with a stick compell’d him to pursue</p>
   <p>His journey. “Thou art but an <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">ass</name>,” said he,</p>
   <p>“Though on thy back there rides <foreign xml:lang="en">divinity</foreign>.”</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="100">
   <p>A <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">bird-catcher</name>, while he his springes set, Was by a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">lark</name>, that saw him, quickly met.</p>
   <p>“What dost thou here, so busy on the ground?” Quoth he, “A first-rate <placeName>city</placeName> this, I found!”</p>
   <p>He went and hid himself when this was said.</p>
   <p>Straight came the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">lark</name>, by his false words misled, In haste at once to plant its colony: And in the toils was caught unwittingly.</p>
   <p>Up ran the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">bird-catcher</name> to seize his prey;</p>
   <p>Then did the captive to its captor say, “If <placeName>cities</placeName> such as these, good sir, you plant, The list of dwellers in them will be scant.”</p>
   <p><placeName>Cities</placeName> and homes are most made desolate, When evil heads have care of their estate.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="101">
   <p>A <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">serpent</name>’s tail once claim’d the lead to take, And drag the other members in its wake.</p>
   <p>Then did the body it, as mad, oppose: “How wilt thou lead us without eyes or nose? Unlike the rest of bests, that roam a-field.”</p>
   <p>In vain. The thinking limbs were forced to yield.</p>
   <p>So the tail led the rest with senseless sway, And blindly dragg’d the body every way.</p>
   <p>It fell at last into a cleft of rock, Whence back, head, body, met a fearful shock.</p>
   <p>Then fawningly it did the head beseech: “Save, mistress, save me, pray, from danger’s reach, For of bad judgment now I reap the fruit.”</p>
   <p>This fable to a commons best will suit Which, frensied and perverted, fain would rise And hold dominion over men more wise.</p>
</div>
<div type="chapter" n="LIX">
   <p>In the application of the fable of the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Belly</name> and its Members, as related by <persName>Shakespeare</persName>, (<quote><foreign xml:lang="en">Coriolanus</foreign>, Act. I. Scene 1,)</quote> <persName>Menenius</persName> calls one of the citizens, “the great toe of the assembly,”</p>
   <p>“For that being one of the lowest, basest, poorest, Of his most wise rebellion, thou goest forward.”</p>
   <p>The fables are wholly dissimilar in purpose, but these words of <persName>Shakespeare</persName> are a parallel to the description of the tail in this fable of <persName>Babrius</persName>.</p>
   <p>A <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">snake</name> that by a farmer’s door did hide, Stung his child’s foot, and so the infant died. Great was the sorrow which the parents bore. And the sire, smitten by a blow so sore, Taking a stone, approach’d the serpent’s den, Waiting to kill it coming forth again. Out from its hole it came to hunt for prey: Up ran in eager haste the sire straightway, And at it with main force he cast a stone, Which lack’d success, to little purpose thrown; His aim to hurt the murderous <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">snake</name> did fail, Further than at its end, to bruise its tail. Then fearful lest the reptile him should slay, And thus the fracture of that tail repay, Honey and meal and water he procured, And thus his foe to be at peace adjured.</p>
   <p>But then the monster, hissing from its hole (To which, when wounded, it for shelter stole), Some such defiance at the father threw: “Till you the tomb, the stone I cease to view, “There never can be peace betwixt us two.”</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="102">
   <p>To gather <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">locusts</name> forth a lad had gone, He caught a host, ere he set eyes upon A <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">scorpion</name>. Thinking this a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">locust</name>, he Hollow’d his hand, and stretch’d it eagerly To grasp his prize. The <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">reptile</name> saw the lad Was guileless, and with him this converse had: “Boy, get thee gone, nor hands upon me lay! For, catching me, thou’lt cast thine all away.”</p>
   <p>A boy from school purloin’d a comrade’s slate, And to his mother bore his prize, elate. She took it, did not say his act was wrong, Or warn his hands from what did not belong To them. Ere long the youth had learn’d to thieve, And would not, untouched, things more precious leave. The wonted habit soon became a trade: Then, in the act of sacrilege way-laid And caught, with hand behind him bound he went The road the lawless are with hangmen sent. With tears and moans his mother went behind, And her son begg’d the hangmen to be kind. And to him this one favour to accord, To breathe within her ear some latest word. Ready to list, she near her offspring drew, Who violently bit her ear in two.</p>
   <p>185 When she deplored such treatment from her child, And the bystanders’ language was not mild In blame of one whose acts so impious proved Toward her that bare him; “Surely it behoved Her, first and foremost,” said he, “to deter My youth from theft. I owe my wreck to her. ’Twas she who welcomed first the stolen slate. ’Tis she conducts me now to <name type="deity">Pluto</name>’s gate.”</p>
</div>
<div type="chapter" n="64">
   <p>
      <quote>
         <foreign xml:lang="grc">A-roasting cockles</foreign>, said a farmer’s son, When they to hiss and bubble had begun,
         “Ye <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">senseless creatures</name>, that, with homes on fire,
         Strike up a tuneful strain, and join in choir.”
      </quote>
   </p>
   <p>
      Prometheus erst, when <name type="deity">Jove</name> the order spake,
      Proceeded <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">men</name> and <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">brutes</name>, ’tis said, to make.
      But when <name type="deity">Jove</name> saw that <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">beasts</name> outnumbered <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">men</name>,
      He bade him mix some of the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">brutes</name> again,
      And fashion them into the human mould.
      The <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">brutes</name> into a lump Prometheus rolled,
      And form’d <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">men</name> of it, e’en as <name type="deity">Jove</name> desired.
      But, as for those so moulded, it transpired
      That in the change they gained a human shape,
      Yet did not from their earlier mind escape;
      But kept that to the end, which they began
      By sharing with the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">brutes</name> and not with <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">man</name>.
   </p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="104">
   <p>A thirsty <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">pigeon</name> on a <placeName>sign-board</placeName> spied
   A cup of water, at mid summer-tide.
   Taking the picture for the actual thing,
   She bore down on it with a rustling wing.
   Unwittingly against the board she dash’d,
   And fell to earth with wings and feathers smash’d;
   The <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">cat</name> at once an easy prey secured.</p>
   <p>Rush upon nought, with purpose unmatured,
   If passion guides, quick ruin is ensured.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="105">
   <p>A <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">sportsman</name> in his net a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">partridge</name> caught,
   To sup on which immediately he thought:
   But for her life entreating mournfully
   She cried, “Oh spare, and do not slaughter me,
   And I for thee a crowd of <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">birds</name> will get,
   Decoying ready victims to thy net.”
   Said he, “Thou silly <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">partridge</name>, stay thy cry;
   It is for this cause chiefly thou shalt die,
   That never more thou may’st betray thy friends.”
   Evil design’d for others ever tends
   To thine own hurt. And so doth ev’ry plan
   Thy malice plots against a fellow-<persName>man</persName>.</p>
</div>
<div type="chapter" n="67">
   <p>That foe to every <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">feathered fowl</name>, the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">cat</name>, Caught, as it lay upon the ground, a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">bat</name>; Which, fearing instant doom without delay, Endeavour’d thus with pray’rs her fate to stay:</p>
   <p>“Oh, do not slaughter me, good <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">cat</name>,” said she, “No living thing hath e’er found hurt from me.</p>
   <p>I in the daylight never quit my nest: When beasts go out to hunt, I take my rest, But forth at moonless dusk I always fare, To get my food in dew-encumber’d air.”</p>
   <p>The <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">cat</name> then answer’d thus: “As I’m a foe To birds in general, can I let thee go?”</p>
   <p>“I am no <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">bird</name>,” was next the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">bat</name>’s reply: “Four-footed, fed on bloodless food am I.”</p>
   <p>On hearing this the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">cat</name> its prey resign’d. ‘’Twas saved from no small peril, soon to find</p>
   <p>Another captor of the <foreign xml:lang="en">feline</foreign> brood, Which thought to take it, like a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">mouse</name>, for food.</p>
   <p>But then she pray’d and said, “No <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">mouse</name> was she, For she had wings, and wing’d no <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">mouse</name> could be:”</p>
   <p>Thus came she out of double danger free.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="106">
   <p>To shy <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">hare</name> the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">tortoise</name> smiling spoke,</p>
   <p>When he about her feet began to joke:</p>
   <p>“I’ll pass thee by, though fleeter than the gale.”</p>
   <p>“Pooh!” said the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">hare</name>, “I don’t believe thy tale.”</p>
   <p>“Try but one course, and thou my speed shalt know.”</p>
   <p>“Who’ll fix the prize, and whither we shall go?”</p>
   <p>Of the fleet-footed <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">hare</name> the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">tortoise</name> asked.</p>
   <p>To whom he answer’d, “<persName>Reynard</persName> shall be tasked</p>
   <p>With this; that subtle <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">fox</name>, whom thou dost see.”</p>
   <p>The <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">tortoise</name> then (no hesitater she!)</p>
   <p>Kept jogging on, but earliest reached the post;</p>
   <p>The <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">hare</name>, relying on his fleetness, lost</p>
   <p>Space, during sleep, he thought he could recover</p>
   <p>When he awoke. But then the race was over;</p>
   <p>The <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">tortoise</name> gain’d her aim, and slept her sleep.</p>
   <p>From negligence doth care the vantage reap.</p>
   <p>An <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">amaranth</name> had sprung up near a <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">rose</name>,</p>
   <p>And said, “Than thee no flower more comely grows,</p>
   <p>Long’d for by <name type="deity">Gods</name>, and dear to <persName>man</persName>, as well.</p>
   <p>I count thee blest both for thy fragrant smell,</p>
   <p>And lovely beauty.” Then the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">rose</name> replied,</p>
   <p>“Good <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">amaranth</name>, ’tis vain the truth to hide:</p>
   <p>For me the threads of life are quick outspun;</p>
   <p>For if not pluck’d, I soon am all undone</p>
   <p>By withering. But thou dost always bloom,</p>
   <p>And living, ever-green, escape the tomb.”</p>
   <p>May a fixt lot (no matter small or great)</p>
   <p>Be rather mine, than high but changeful state.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="107">
   <p>A <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">wolf</name>’s young <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">cub</name> was by a <persName>shepherd</persName> caught,
   This, with his <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">dogs</name> to nurture, home he brought.
   In time it grew up, in the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">sheepfold</name> rear’d,
   Where if so be another <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">wolf</name> appear’d,
   Intent to rob of <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">lamb</name> or <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">kid</name> the fold,
   First rank among the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">dogs</name> would this one hold,
   <quote>Quickest the daring robber to pursue.</quote>
   But if the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">dogs</name> of chasing weary grew,
   And toward the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">sheepcot</name>, failing to o’ertake
   The spoiler, chanced their backward road to make.
   Not, as in chase, the tame <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">wolf</name> onward went,
   But for a share fell in by accident.
   Or, should no other <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">wolf</name>, to steal a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">sheep</name>,
   Chance from outside into the fold to leap,
   Then with the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">dogs</name> he made a sly repast
   On one. The <persName>shepherd</persName> caught the rogue at last,
   And from a tree, to kill him, let him swing.
   <quote>Good habits do not from ill natures spring.</quote></p>

   <p><name type="plant" xml:lang="en">Olive</name> and <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">Fig-tree</name> strove for beauty’s prize.
   <quote>“At no time,”</quote> said the first, <quote>“my foliage dies,
   But the fig’s bloom is put forth, once for all,
   At one set season, and is then but small.”</quote>
   So then to her the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">fig-tree</name> made reply:
   <quote>“Nay! but when snows fall from the wintry sky,
   And settle in thy leaves, still in their bloom,
   Thy beauteous freshness doth but bring thee doom.
   Whereas, on finding me of foliage quit,
   Snow falls to earth. I am unhurt by it.”</quote>
   <quote>To man’s disgrace tends beauty void of wit.</quote></p>
</div>
<div type="chapter" n="72">
   <p>Once did a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">spotted pard</name> to boast begin Of all the brute-kind the most various skin, To whom said <persName>Reynard</persName>: “Be it so! Yet I Possess a mind of more variety Than thy skin or thy mind.” Each magnifies That which within his own possession lies.</p>
   <p><quote><foreign xml:lang="la">Fab. LXXII. — Avianus (Fab. 40)</foreign> has a version of this fable, the concluding lines of which are, —</quote></p>
   <p><quote><foreign xml:lang="la">Vade, ait, et pictæ nimium confie figuræ,</foreign><foreign xml:lang="la">Dum mihi consilium pulchrius esse queat,</foreign><foreign xml:lang="la">Miremurque magis quos munera mentis adornant,</foreign><foreign xml:lang="la">Quam qui corporeis enituere bonis.</foreign></quote></p>
</div>
<div type="chapter" n="73">
   <p>Æsop in <placeName>Samos</placeName> to a <persName>chief</persName>, his friend, Upon his trial, wishing aid to lend — This chief was of the wealthiest in the isle — With this apt fable did the mob beguile.</p>
   <p>196 Crossing a rapid stream a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">fox</name> one day By the tide’s violence was borne away Into the deep gorge of a rocky hole, There falling down she lay, poor fainting soul, Wholly unable from her place to move, And long with her sad plight but feebly strove.</p>
   <p>Then upon her a swarm of <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">dog-ticks</name> burst, Craving for food, to suck her blood athirst. But a stray <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">hedgehog</name> spied her troubled state, And, to her sufferings compassionate, Ask’d, runs the story, “If her wish would be The <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">dog-ticks</name>’ slaughter?” “By no means,” said she, I pray you by the <name type="deity">Nymphs</name>, this swarm disperse.”</p>
   <p>“Why would you not be rid of such a curse?” The <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">hedgehog</name> asked again. “Because e’en now These in each vein are full of blood, I trow!” Replied sly <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Reynard</name>, “what they drain is slight. Get rid of these when full, and you invite Others to come, a famine-wasted force, And wholly suck my blood without remorse.”</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="110">
   <p>The <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">sow</name> and <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">bitch</name> betwixt them held dispute
   Which was best breeder. Said he <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">sow</name>, “No brute
   With four legs bearest more quick than I, you’ll find.” “Yes,” said the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">bitch</name>, “but then your whelps are blind.”</p>
   <p>A <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">sow</name> and <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">bitch</name> each other did revile.
   The first, by her who guards <placeName>Cythera</placeName>’s isle,
   Sware with her teeth the other’s bones to break.
   The <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">bitch</name> then mock’d the thought a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">sow</name> should take
   An oath by <name type="deity">Venus</name>, as her favourite. “That thou shouldst swear by <name type="deity">Venus</name>, sure, is fit!
   198 For thou, ’tis plain, by her art most beloved,
   Seeing that she hath from her fane removed
   Farthest the men that make a meal of <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">pork</name>.”</p>
   <p>Then grunts the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">sow</name>, whose wits were all at work:
   “Learn thou that it from this is chiefly seen,
   How much beloved I am by beauty’s queen;
   For hating him that seeks to do me hurt,
   Or dares to kill me, him she doth avert.
   But thou hast an ill-savour, live or dead.”</p>
   <p>A man of sense converts whate’er is said
   By evil speakers, mockery to raise,
   Through skilful handling into real praise.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="111">
   <p>Evils once thrust the blessings all away From their free sojourn midst the sons of clay. For hosts of evils had the earth possest. Then did the blessings soar to Heaven, in quest Of satisfaction on th’ usurping race, Nor deign’d with such to tarry in one place. In blending with them Nature had been to blame! How could they mix, if, evermore the same, Jarring and quick-to-clash are man’s affairs? To fix their rule, to <name type="deity">Jove</name> they lift their pray’rs.</p>
   <p><name type="deity">Jove</name>’s fiat was: “Let ills be mixt below. Singly among men be it yours to go!” Hence then it is, that ills in numbers run: For they are join’d, and go not one by one. But all good things come down from <name type="deity">Jove</name> to men, Each to but one or two, and slowly then.</p>
   <p>Grudging a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">bull</name> its horns the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">camel</name> went, Pray’rs for the like at <name type="deity">Jove</name>’ throne to present. <name type="deity">Jove</name> in disgust, because she wish’d for more, Though she had a fine, stalwart frame before, Not only gives no horns, but also shears, To check her grasping, somewhat from her ears. To seek what fate omits, unmeet appears.</p>
</div>
<div type="chapter" n="LXXVIII">
   <p>To teach some <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">apes</name> bethought him Egypt’s king The Pyrrhic dance. Of every living thing <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">apes</name> are most imitative. What men do Under their notice, they will copy too.</p>
   <p>201 Dress’d then in bright and elegant array, These famous maskers set about their play, With many looking on. Most gracefully Awhile they acted: till a stander-by, A fine smart fellow, from his vest let drop Handfuls of <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">nuts</name>, and brought them to a stop.</p>
   <p>These, spilt around, the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">apes</name> no sooner view, Than they cease dancing, tear their robes in two, Smash all their masks, and rush on these amain, Making their <foreign xml:lang="en">monkey-breeding</foreign> vastly plain. To change one’s nature is but toil in vain.</p>
</div>
<div type="chapter" n="113">
  <p>A <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">goat</name> athirst, when it beheld a pool, Descended a deep gorge, its heat to cool. He drank, ere he discover’d how unwise Was his descent. Alone he could not rise</p>
  <p>From out the pit. He paused, look’d up, and sought Assistance. Thirst had just then <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Reynard</name> brought To pass the opening. She the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">goat</name> espied, And ask’d him, if the stream a draught supplied.</p>
  <p>“Ay! and as clear as crystal!” answered he, “But the hole’s steep, its outlet hard to see.” The <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Fox</name> then to the broad-beard made reply: “Faint not at that: I look’d down from on high, And judg’d that thence ’twas easy to ascend. Come, make thine horns against the pit side bend,”</p>
  <p>Thus said the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Fox</name>, “that I may come down so: Then running up I’ll drag thee from below.” She came down, drank, and went up from the pit, Yet, after all, help’d not the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">goat</name> a bit.</p>
  <p>And when he blamed her base ingratitude, Then the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">fox</name> made this observation rude:</p>
  <p>“Nay! if of sense you’d had as large a share, As you can boast a wavy head of hair, Not without egress had you been down there.”</p>
</div>
<div type="chapter" n="114">
   <p>The <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Hymettian bee</name>, a mother of the combs, Once with a gift approach’d the heavenly homes, Honey for <name type="deity">Jove</name>, fresh-gather’d from the hives, Honey, in which o’er smoke and age survives A flow’ry scent. Delighted with the gift <name type="deity">Jove</name> sware to grant the pray’r she might uplift. “Grant me a sting, that if by men,” she said, “Upon my combs rifling hand be laid, I may, by stinging such, my hurters slay.” Angry was <name type="deity">Jove</name> to hear the insect pray For man’s destruction: yet, however loth, He could but grant where he had pledged his oath. The sting, however, which he gave, was such, That when <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">bees</name> smite, they perish with the touch. Her sting the life, that keeps her on the wing, She leaves that life where’er she leaves her sting.</p>
</div>
<div type="chapter" n="115">
  <p>A timid old man had a valiant boy, And dream’d he saw a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">lion</name> him destroy. So fearing lest the dream should be fulfil’d, A pleasant room for him he set to build: And, as some solace for vexation sore, Had wild beasts painted o’er each wall and door. Among them was the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">lion</name>’s picture shown. So when on this the young man’s glance was thrown, Rage and chagrin more fiercely on him press’d, And standing near, the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">lion</name> he addresst:</p>
  <p>“O worst of brutes, because my father’ eye In dreamy sleep did once behold a lie, I am thus idly prison’d for a dream. On thee what vengeance shall sufficient seem?”</p>
  <p>Threatening the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">lion</name> with his words so grand, The young man through a panel thrust his hand,</p>
  <p>To break a splint from a bush near the wall, Meaning to burn the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">lion</name> as tinder small: But as the prickles chanced to wound his thumb, Quick was the swelling to his waist to come. And soon his anguish took his speech away:</p>
  <p>O’er Acherons steam, poor wretch, another fare. What fate allots thee, be resign’d to bear. Nor seek by shifts thy destiny to cheat. For what must come, ’tis best a man should meet.</p>
  <p>Fab. LXXXI. — Compare the story of <persName>Atys</persName> and <persName>Adrastus</persName>, <quote><foreign xml:lang="grc">Ἡροδότου</foreign> I. 34-45.</quote></p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="116">
   <p>A <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">wild boar</name> once stood at an old tree’s foot, Whetting his tusks. The <persName>Reynard</persName> put: What fancy led him thus his tusks to whet, No risk being near, no hunter to beset His path — in fact, no need. The <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">boar</name> replied, “I, like a fool, should wretchedly have died Oft, had I sought arms but when danger prest.” Man’s life is all a plot. Be ready, lest Evil befall. Precaution’s ever best.</p>
   <p>An answer to the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">quadrupeds</name> once came, That put their boasts of fruitfulness to shame. In truth they went and tax’d the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">lioness</name>, Wishing against her to prove barrenness. “Come tell thou us, how many cubs dost bear?” She smiled, and met them with this answer rare, “But one, yet he is thoroughbred all o’er.” Than hosts of fools one man of sense is more.</p>
   <p>A <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">bald man</name> in a wig did ride a race: A sudden gust dislodged it from its place. It flew aloft, by breezy motion borne, And the by-standers laugh’d the man to scorn. But said the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">bald-head</name>, as he ceased to ride, “What marvel if strange locks refused to bide Where mine own hair had long deserted me?” Vexed at the loss of goods let no man be: For borrowers of this life’s things are we.</p>
</div>
<div type="chapter" n="117">
  <p>The <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Libyan crane</name> and <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">shameless fox</name> agreed
  That each by turns would with the other feed. Sly <persName>Reynard</persName> only set some greasy broth
  Before her guest, pour’d on a broad plate forth; And bade her of the feast to take her fill. Much fun she caused,
  as evermore her bill With useless toil she struck against the ware, Whilst of the broth it failed to gain a share.</p>
  <p>The <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Libyan bird</name> then sought to entertain The roguish <persName>fox</persName>,
  and play the host would fain. Of <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">barley-meal</name> a thin-necked jar was full,
  And out of this her bill thrust in, could pull Enough of food. So now the laugh had she At <persName>Reynard</persName>,
  who stood gaping hungrily. The <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">fox</name>’s snout would not the jar-neck fit.
  For what you do to others, they’ll be quit.</p>
  <p>A <persName>ploughman</persName> was half eaten up by <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">lice</name>.
  Leaving his plough, he shook his garment twice. When a third time they bit him shamelessly,
  Wishing by all means of them to get free, Lest cleanliness should loss-of-work require,
  He doff’d his clothes, and threw them on the fire. I would not have him thrice from fire abstain,
  Who twice hath lost his wits by <name type="deity">woman’s bane</name>.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="118">
   <p>
      <foreign xml:lang="la">A brazier</foreign> in his house a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">pet-dog</name> kept; And while the master forged, the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">spaniel</name> slept; But when the master dined, he rose from sleep, A fawning watch for scraps and bones to keep.
   </p>
   <p>
      The man once shook his staff in angry mood, And said, “Most wretched of the <foreign xml:lang="la">canine</foreign> brood, What shall I do with such a slumbering <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">cur</name>, From laziness so strong, so hard to stir? Dost thou not know that toil alone doth send Gifts that are good?” I’d have thee, without end, An idler’s ears with this sound warning fill; ’Tis idleness that makes a man fare ill.
   </p>
   <p>
      It happen’d to a <persName>labourer</persName> to behold A <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">viper</name> frozen by excessive cold, At winter, in the fields. By pity press’d, He lifted it and placed it in his breast, Hoping to kindle vital warmth anew.
   </p>
   <p>
      Away the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">viper</name>, quick reviving, threw Its numbness, and the friendly <persName>rustic</persName> stung, Who said, a-dying, as from him he flung The <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">snake</name>: “I spared the wretch. My doom is meet, When whole, I should have crush’d it ’neath my feet.”
   </p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="119">
   <p>Hoar Winter strung these words, to jeer at Spring: “To none doth thine appearance quiet bring. One to the groves, to fields another hies In haste, or where the woodland valley lies. To such the choices early <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">flowers</name> are treats, <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">Lilies</name>, or <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">roses</name> ever-breathing sweets, They cull to glad the eye, the wreath to twine: These gifts hath Spring. But these are less than mine.</p>
   <p>For I, who ride upon the sea-dash’d prows, Disturb the waves, the stormy wind arouse. By me the rains and frozen hails are brought; And lumps of <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">snow</name> to icy substance wrought; So that all tarry, while I last, at home, At hearth or board, and do not care to roam; 213 But revel in the sweet sound of the <foreign xml:lang="en">lyre</foreign>, Strains of melodious song, and youthful choir.</p>
   <p>These are all Winter’s makeweights, you must know! And granted that delight and praises flow From men’s lips at thy name; yet while I shed Charms o’er men’s homes, my name is cherishèd By those who rightly judge, as sweet of sound.”</p>
   <p>For thine, o’er strange goods, claim not higher ground; For e’en in these some beauty may be found.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="120">
   <p>Gibes at the snow-white <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">swans</name> the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">swallows</name> threw,</p>
   <p>Because they from men’s company withdrew,</p>
   <p>But love to hover round the meads, and bide</p>
   <p>By the marsh-pools, and by the river side,</p>
   <p>214 Delighting most of all to dwell apart,</p>
   <p>And keep remote from crowds their tuneful art.</p>
   <p>“Our charm is in great cities, men and all,</p>
   <p>In roof, and chamber, corridor and hall.”</p>
   <p>Thus said the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">swallows</name>, “And we chirp our tale</p>
   <p>Most sweetly; yea, the old establish’d wail</p>
   <p>Babbled from ancient days to th’ Attic race,</p>
   <p>Of <placeName>Athens</placeName> and <persName>Pandion</persName>, <placeName>Tereus</placeName>, <placeName>Thrace</placeName>,</p>
   <p>Exile and marriage, mutilated tongue.</p>
   <p>Wrongs, writing-tablets, <persName>Itys</persName> slaughter’d young:</p>
   <p>How we had long a shape with men the same,</p>
   <p>But the, by transformation, birds became.”</p>
   <p>More said the Attic maids in such-like strain,</p>
   <p>Yet did the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">swans</name> to answer scarcely deign,</p>
   <p>Nor then till late. They hated wordy tales.</p>
   <p>Their answer giv’n, of wit in no way fails.</p>
   <p>“Oh, prating children of Athenian birth.</p>
   <p>All men would seek lone corners of the earth,</p>
   <p>From love of song, with gladness for our sakes,</p>
   <p>When <name type="deity">Zephyr</name>, blowing soft and sweetly, makes</p>
   <p>Our wings relax, and idly catch the breeze;</p>
   <p>For such would list to honied melodies.</p>
   <p>215 Therefore it is we sing some trifling song:</p>
   <p>Albeit afar from every human throng,</p>
   <p>And that but rarely. ’Tis our fairest boast</p>
   <p>That measure in our strains we study most,</p>
   <p>Nor let our muses mingle with the crowd,</p>
   <p>But that of you men weary ’tis allowed,</p>
   <p>Nor will your nearness calmly tolerate;</p>
   <p>For your unmeasured twittering they hate.</p>
   <p>Yet in all this ye</p>
</div>
<div type="chapter" n="XC">
   <p>suffer but your due, Since with your <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">tongues</name> cut out, ’twere well ye knew The charm of silence, and your prate gave o’er Of shameful wrongs, which in the house ye bore. But, not the less, ye babble most of all, Yet no melodious utterance let fall; For ever is the maimèd <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">tongue</name> deplored, And <persName>Itys</persName> slain by <persName>Zethus</persName> with the sword.”</p>
   <p>Fab. XC. — Compare with this fable, Fab. XII. Part I. According to <persName>Homer</persName>, <quote>Od. XIX. 517-23</quote>, <persName>Zethus</persName>, king of <placeName>Thebes</placeName>, married <persName>Aedon</persName>, daughter of <persName>Pandareus</persName>, and <persName>Itylus</persName> was the offspring of this union. She slew her son in mistake for the eldest child of <persName>Niobe</persName>, her husband’s brother’s wife. Sir G. C. Lewis suggests reading <foreign xml:lang="grc">μητρὸς</foreign> or <foreign xml:lang="grc">Π ρόκνης</foreign> at the end of v. 42, for <foreign xml:lang="grc">Ζ ήθου</foreign>, and referring the whole, as is most natural, to the tragical tale of <persName>Tereus</persName> and <persName>Procne</persName>. <persName>Itylus</persName> was slain by the sword of <persName>Aedon</persName>, not of <persName>Zethus</persName>.</p>
   <p>A river on its stream two pots convey’d: One was of brass, and one of clay was made. The latter to the former, floating nigh, Cried, “Float afar, and do not sail hard by: “For if you nearer draw, I’m sure to break. A poor man’s house is very apt to shake, When men of greater power are dwelling near, And injury from them may fairly fear.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="122">
   <p>Upon a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">wrestler</name>’s foot once perch’d a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">flea</name>. He moved. It hopp’d and bit him sturdily. Then was he wroth, and fain would it secure; Again it hopp’d, and got off safe and sure. The <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">wrestler</name> worried, though by bites of <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">fleas</name>, Cried groaning, “Wilt not aid me, <name type="deity">Hercules</name>?” It is mere insult to the <name type="deity">Gods</name> above To pray them lesser evils to remove.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="123">
   <p>A <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">flea</name>, which bit his foot, annoy’d a <persName>man</persName>. He caught it, and to ask of it began, “Who art thou that thou dost so sharply bite, And puncture all my body with delight?” Said it to him: “My life I thus sustain. Spare me: of no great harm can you complain.” And he in anger made it this reply, “Therefore by these hands thou shalt straightway die. For what is evil, be it great or small, I would not have exist, to hurt at all.”</p>
   <p>Once of an <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">ox</name> a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">flea</name> this question ask’d: “Why do you bear by mortals to be task’d, And daily toil for them, since surely you Are a courageous brute, a fine one too? Whereas I bite their flesh, though small to see, And fearless drink their red blood greedily.” The <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">ox</name> replied, “To men I know my debt. From them I ever care and kindness met. My forehead and my shoulders oft they stroke, And scratch and rub me, pleasure to provoke.” To the strong <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">ox</name> the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">flea</name> then answer made, “Ah! but to luckless me this rubbing trade, You talk of, would result in death outright, Whene’er upon me men’s nails chanced to light.” We ever love the hand that doth us good. But requite hurt with hurt, in vengeful mood.</p>
</div>
<div type="chapter" n="100">
   <p>A man of Athens on a summer’s day,</p>
   <p>To Megara was fain to make his way</p>
   <p>On a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">pack-ass</name>, he hired for a fixt sum.</p>
   <p>So as he journey’d, when midday was come,</p>
   <p>What time the time the sun pours down his beaming heat,</p>
   <p>Under the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">ass</name>’s shade he sought retreat,</p>
   <p>To shelter from the sun’s excessive rays.</p>
   <p>But the <persName>ass-driver</persName> now his right gainsays;</p>
   <p>“Th’ agreement was for seat, and not for shade.”</p>
   <p>To which the other said, “that he had paid</p>
   <p>For the whole <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">ass</name>, and so its shadow bought.”</p>
   <p>So strifes about a shadow come to nought.</p>
</div>
    </div>
  </body>
</text></TEI>
