<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI.2>
 <teiHeader type="text">
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     De amore prolis
    </title>
    <title type="sub">
     Machine readable text
    </title>
    <author n="Plut.">
     Plutarch
    </author>
    <editor n="Teubner" role="editor">
     Gregorius N. Bernardakis
    </editor>
    <sponsor>
     Perseus Project, Tufts University
    </sponsor>
    <principal>
     Gregory Crane
    </principal>
    <respStmt>
     <resp>
      Prepared under the supervision of
     </resp>
     <name>
      Lisa Cerrato
     </name>
     <name>
      William Merrill
     </name>
     <name>
      Elli Mylonas
     </name>
     <name>
      David Smith
     </name>
    </respStmt>
    <funder n="org:NEH">
     The National Endosment for the Humanities
    </funder>
   </titleStmt>
   <extent/>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>
     Trustees of Tufts University
    </publisher>
    <pubPlace>
     Medford, MA
    </pubPlace>
    <authority>
     Perseus Project
    </authority>
   </publicationStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <biblStruct>
     <analytic/>
     <monogr>
      <author>
       Plutarch
      </author>
      <title>
       Moralia
      </title>
      <editor role="editor">
       Gregorius N. Bernardakis
      </editor>
      <imprint>
       <pubPlace>
        Leipzig
       </pubPlace>
       <publisher>
        Teubner
       </publisher>
       <date>
        1891
       </date>
      </imprint>
      <biblScope type="volume">
       3
      </biblScope>
     </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <editorialDecl>
    <correction method="silent">
     <p>
      optical character recognition
     </p>
     <p lang="it">
      riconoscimento ottico dei caratteri
     </p>
     <p lang="en">
      optical character recognition
     </p>
    </correction>
   </editorialDecl>
   <refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
    <state unit="section"/>
   </refsDecl>
   <refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
    <state n="chunk" unit="stephpage"/>
   </refsDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <langUsage>
    <language id="greek">
     Greek
    </language>
    <language id="eng">
     English
    </language>
   </langUsage>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change>
    <date>
     5/10
    </date>
    <respStmt>
     <name>
      RS
     </name>
     <resp/>
    </respStmt>
    <item>
     tagged and parsed
    </item>
   </change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <body>
   <pb id="v.3.p.278"/>
   <milestone id="stephpage-493a" n="493a" unit="stephpage"/>
   <div1 n="1" type="section">
    <p>
     ἔκκλητοι κρίσεις καὶ ξενικῶν δικαστηρίων ἀγωγαὶ
     <note anchored="yes" place="unspecified" resp="ed">
      <foreign lang="greek">
       ἀγωγαὶ
      </foreign>
      ] vid. Symbolas
     </note>
     τοῖς Ἕλλησι τὸ πρῶτον
               ἀπιστίᾳ τῇ πρὸς
     <milestone id="stephpage-493b" n="493b" unit="stephpage"/>
     ἀλλήλους ἐπενοήθησαν, ἀλλοτρίας δικαιοσύνης ὥσπερ ἑτέρου τινὸς τῶν
               ἀναγκαίων μὴ φυομένου παρʼ αὐτοῖς
     <milestone n="5" unit="tlnum"/>
     δεηθεῖσιν.
               ἆρʼ οὖν καὶ οἱ φιλόσοφοι τῶν προβλημάτων ἔνια διὰ τὰς πρὸς ἀλλήλους
               διαφορὰς ἐπὶ τὴν τῶν ἀλόγων φύσιν ζῴων ὥσπερ ἀλλοδαπὴν πόλιν
               ἐκκαλοῦνται, καὶ τοῖς ἐκείνων πάθεσι καὶ ἤθεσιν ὡς ἀνεντεύκτοις καὶ
               ἀδεκάστοις ἐφιᾶσι τὴν κρίσιν;
     <milestone n="10" unit="tlnum"/>
     ἢ καὶ τοῦτο
               τῆς ἀνθρωπίνης κακίας ἔγκλημα κοινόν ἐστι, τὸ περὶ τῶν ἀναγκαιοτάτων
               καὶ μεγίστων
     <milestone id="stephpage-493c" n="493c" unit="stephpage"/>
     ἀμφιδοξοῦντας ἡμᾶς ζητεῖν ἐν ἵπποις καὶ κυσὶ καὶ ὄρνισι, πῶς γαμοῦμεν
               αὐτοὶ καὶ γεννῶμεν καὶ τεκνοτροφοῦμεν, ὡς μηδὲν ἐν ἑαυτοῖς δήλωμα τῆς
               φύσεως
     <milestone n="15" unit="tlnum"/>
     ὂν τὰ
     <note anchored="yes" place="unspecified" resp="ed">
      <foreign lang="greek">
       τὰ
      </foreign>
      ]
      <foreign lang="greek">
       καὶ τὰ
      </foreign>
      R
     </note>
     τῶν θηρίων ἤθη καὶ πάθη
               προσαγορεῦσαι καὶ καταμαρτυρῆσαι τοῦ βίου ἡμῶν πολλὴν τοῦ κατὰ φύσιν
               ἐκδιαίτησιν καὶ παράβασιν, εὐθὺς ἐν ἀρχῇ καὶ περὶ τὰ πρῶτα συγχεομένων
               καὶ ταραττομένων. ἄκρατον γὰρ ἐν ἐκείνοις ἡ φύσις καὶ ἀμιγὲς καὶ
     <milestone n="20" unit="tlnum"/>
     ἁπλοῦν φυλάττει τὸ ἴδιον· ἐν δʼ
               ἀνθρώποις ὑπὸ τοῦ λόγου καὶ τῆς συνηθείας, ὃ τοὔλαιον ὑπὸ τῶν
     <pb id="v.3.p.279"/>
     μυρεψῶν πέπονθε, πρὸς πολλὰ μιγνυμένη δόγματα καὶ κρίσεις
               ἐπιθέτους ποικίλη γέγονε καὶ ἰδία,
     <note anchored="yes" place="unspecified" resp="ed">
      <foreign lang="greek">
       ἰδία
      </foreign>
      ] i. e.
      <foreign lang="greek">
       ἰδιάζουσα ἑκάστῳ
      </foreign>
     </note>
     τὸ δʼ
     <milestone id="stephpage-493d" n="493d" unit="stephpage"/>
     οἰκεῖον οὐ τετήρηκε. καὶ μὴ θαυμάζωμεν, εἰ
               τὰ ἄλογα ζῷα τῶν λογικῶν μᾶλλον ἕπεται τῇ φύσει · καὶ γὰρ
     <milestone n="5" unit="tlnum"/>
     τὰ φυτὰ τῶν ζῴων,
     <note anchored="yes" place="unspecified" resp="ed">
      <foreign lang="greek">
       τὰ φυτὰ τῶν ζῴων
      </foreign>
      ] intell.
      <foreign lang="greek">
       μᾶλλον ἕπεται τῇ φύσει
      </foreign>
      (R)
     </note>
     οἷς οὔτε φαντασίαν οὔθʼ
               ὁρμὴν ἔδωκεν ἑτέρων
     <note anchored="yes" place="unspecified" resp="ed">
      <foreign lang="greek">
       ἑτέρων
      </foreign>
      ]
      <foreign lang="greek">
       ἐνεργὸν
      </foreign>
      Emperius. malim
      <foreign lang="greek">
       ἢ ἑτέρων
      </foreign>
     </note>
     ὄρεξιν τοῦ κατὰ φύσιν ἀποσαλεύουσαν, ἀλλʼ ὥσπερ
               ἐν δεσμῷ συνειργμένα μένει καὶ κεκράτηται, μίαν ἀεὶ πορείαν ἣν ἡ φύσις
               ἄγει πορευόμενα. τοῖς δὲ θηρίοις τὸ μὲν πραΰτροπον τοῦ
     <milestone n="10" unit="tlnum"/>
     λόγου καὶ περιττὸν καὶ φιλελεύθερον ἄγαν οὐκ
               ἔστιν, ἀλόγους δʼ ὁρμὰς καὶ ὀρέξεις ἔχοντα καὶ χρώμενα πλάναις καὶ
               περιδρομαῖς, πολλάκις οὐ μακρὰν ἀλλʼ ὡς ἐπʼ ἀγκύρας τῆς φύσεως σαλεύει·
               καθάπερ
     <note anchored="yes" place="unspecified" resp="ed">
      <foreign lang="greek">
       καὶ καθάπερ
      </foreign>
      W
      <foreign lang="greek">
       καθάπερ κἑ
      </foreign>
      ] corrupta. X ex cod. vetere scripsit:
      <foreign lang="greek">
       καθάπερ οὖν ὄνον ὑφʼ ἡνίᾳ καὶ χ. βαδ. δείκ. εὐθεῖαν ὁ δεσπότης ὁδόν· οὕτως ἐν ἀνθρώπῳ καὶ ὁ αὐτοκρατής
      </foreign>
      cett.
     </note>
     οὖν
     <milestone id="stephpage-493e" n="493e" unit="stephpage"/>
     ὁδὸν
     <note anchored="yes" place="unspecified" resp="ed">
      <foreign lang="greek">
       ὁδὸν
      </foreign>
      ] del. Stegmannus
     </note>
     ὑφʼ
               ἡνίᾳ καὶ χαλινῷ βαδίζοντα δείκνυσιν εὐθεῖαν.
     <milestone n="15" unit="tlnum"/>
     ὁ δὲ δεσπότης ἐν ἀνθρώπῳ καὶ αὐτοκρατὴς λόγος ἄλλας ἄλλοτε
               παρεκβάσεις καὶ καινοτομίας ἀνευρίσκων οὐδὲν ἴχνος ἐμφανὲς οὐδʼ ἐναργὲς
               ἀπολέλοιπε τῆς φύσεως.
    </p>
    <p lang="it">
     Giudici e giudici di tribunali stranieri 
ἀγογαὶ] vid. Symbolas per i Greci il primo
               infedeltà a

               si punivano a vicenda, di giustizia altruistica come di un altro tipo di giustizia
               quelli necessari non nascono separatamente da loro
 saranno legati.
               Pertanto, i filosofi dei problemi sono uno a causa dei problemi reciproci
               disputa sulla natura dei cavalli come città straniera
               sono chiamati, e a coloro che soffri e imposti come senza risposta e
               adekatois ephiasi il giudizio?
 o anche questo
               È un delitto comune della malizia umana, questione di necessità
               e massimo

               dubitando di noi, ci chiedono nei cavalli, nei gatti e nelle galline, come scopiamo
               loro e noi partoriamo e alleviamo figli, come nulla in sé dichiara
               natura
 ὂν τὰ 
la] e la R della morale e delle passioni delle bestie
               giuri e testimoni della nostra vita molto della natura N
               sfratto e trasgressione, proprio all'inizio e riguardo alle prime cose confuse
               e quelli in difficoltà. Perché in loro la natura è pura e pura
 mantiene semplicemente lo stesso; in dʼ
               gente sotto la parola e l'abitudine, che l'olio sotto i profumi mandava, verso molte dottrine e giudizi contrastanti
               aggettivi vari eventi e particolari, 
ἰδία] i. e. possederne uno
 il d'
 casa non è stata osservata. e non ammirare, eh
               I cavalli sono gli animali della ragione piuttosto seguono la natura e perché;
 le piante degli animali, 
le piante della vita] intelletto. piuttosto segue la natura (R) oἷs o fantasia o oὔθʼ
               una corsa degli altri 
di altri] attivo Emperius. Malim o altri
 appetito per natura, ma
               in un legame congiunto rimane e si mantiene, corso sacro che la natura
               prendere percorsi. ma alle bestie il me praitropon di lui
 discorso e agan inutile e liberale ok
               ἔστιν, cavalli dʼ ὁ rms e appetiti avendo e visioni colorate e
               viaggia, spesso non lontano, ma come su un'ancora della natura ondeggia;
               eccetera 
e kataper W kataper ἑ] corruzione. X ex cod. vetere scripsit: kathaper oὖn ονον ὑφʼ ἀνιᾳ καὶ vad. indicatore lascia che il despota segua una via diritta: così nell'uomo anche l'autocrate cett. oὖ
 strada 
strada] del. Stegmannus ὑφʼ
               marciando con le redini e le briglie rivolte dritte.
 ma il despota che è nell'uomo e l'autocrate a volte ragionano
               digressioni e innovazioni, senza trovarne traccia
               il resto della natura.
    </p>
    <p lang="en">
     Judges and judges of foreign courts 
ἀγογαὶ] vid. Symbolas to the Greeks the first
               unfaithfulness to

               they punished each other, of altruistic justice as of another kind of
               necessary ones not born apart from them
 they will be tied.
               Therefore, the philosophers of the problems are one because of the problems towards each other
               dispute about the nature of horses as a foreign city
               they are called, and to those you suffer and set as unanswered and
               adekatois ephiasi the judgment?
 or this too
               It is a common crime of human malice, the matter of necessities
               and maximum

               doubting us, they ask us in horses and cats and chickens, how we fuck
               they and we give birth and raise children, as nothing in themselves declaration of
               nature
 ὂν τὰ 
the] and the R of the beasts' morals and passions
               you swear and testify of our life much of the nature n
               eviction and transgression, right in the beginning and about the first things confused
               and troubled ones. Because in them the nature is pure and pure
 he just keeps the same; in dʼ
               people under the word and habit, which the oil under the perfumes sent, towards many mixed doctrines and judgments
               adjectives various events and particulars, 
ἰδία] i. e. owning one
 the d'
 house was not observed. and don't admire, eh
               Horses are the animals of reason rather they follow nature; and because
 the plants of the animals, 
the plants of life] intell. rather it follows nature (R) oἷs or fantasy or oὔθʼ
               a rush of others 
of others] active Emperius. malim or others
 appetite by nature, but
               in a joint bond it stays and is kept, a holy course that nature
               take routes. but to the beasts the me praitropon of him
 speech and unnecessary and liberal agan ok
               ἔστιν, horses dʼ ὁ rms and appetites having and colored visions and
               travels, often not far, but as if on an anchor of nature he sways;
               etc 
and kataper W kataper ἑ] corrupta. X ex cod. vetere scripsit: kathaper oὖn ονον ὑφʼ ἀνιᾳ καὶ x. vad. indicator let the despot make a straight path: so in man also the autocrat cett. oὖ
 road 
street] del. Stegmannus ὑφʼ
               marching with reins and bridles pointing straight.
 but the despot in a man and an autocrat reason sometimes
               digressions and innovations, finding no trace of them
               the rest of nature.
    </p>
   </div1>
   <div1 n="2" type="section">
    <p>
     ὅρα περὶ τοὺς γάμους ὅσον ἐστὶν ἐν τοῖς
     <milestone n="20" unit="tlnum"/>
     ζῴοις τὸ κατὰ φύσιν. πρῶτον οὐκ ἀναμένει νόμους ἀγαμίου
     <note anchored="yes" place="unspecified" resp="ed">
      <foreign lang="greek">
       ἀγαμίου καὶ ὀψιγαμίου
      </foreign>
      Doehnerus:
      <foreign lang="greek">
       ἀγάμου καὶ ὀψιγάμου
      </foreign>
     </note>
     καὶ ὀψιγαμίου,
               καθάπερ οἱ Λυκούργου πολῖται καὶ Σόλωνος
     <note anchored="yes" place="unspecified" resp="ed">
      <foreign lang="greek">
       καὶ Σόλωνος
      </foreign>
      ] del. idem
     </note>
     οὐδʼ ἀτιμίας ἀτέκνων δέδοικεν,
               οὐδὲ τιμὰς διώκει τρίπαιδας,
     <note anchored="yes" place="unspecified" resp="ed">
      <foreign lang="greek">
       τριπαιδίας
      </foreign>
      idem
     </note>
     ὡς Ῥωμαίων πολλοὶ
     <pb id="v.3.p.280"/>
     γαμοῦσι καὶ γεννῶσιν, οὐχ ἳνα κληρονόμους ἔχωσιν
     <milestone id="stephpage-493f" n="493f" unit="stephpage"/>
     ἀλλʼ ἵνα κληρονομεῖν δύνωνται. ἔπειτα
               μίγνυται τῷ θήλει τὸ ἄρρεν οὐχ ἅπαντα χρόνον· ἡδονὴν γὰρ οὐκ ἔχει
               τέλος ἀλλὰ γέννησιν καὶ τέκνωσιν. διὰ
     <milestone n="5" unit="tlnum"/>
     τοῦτʼ
               ἔτους ὥρᾳ, ἣ πνοάς τε γονίμους ἔχει καὶ πρόσφορον λοχευομένοις κρᾶσιν,
               συνῆλθεν εἰς ταὐτὸ
     <note anchored="yes" place="unspecified" resp="ed">
      <foreign lang="greek">
       συνῆλθεν εἰς ταὐτὸ
      </foreign>
      Doehnerus:
      <foreign lang="greek">
       ἦλθεν εἰς τὸ αὐτὸ
      </foreign>
     </note>
     τῷ ἄρρενι τὸ θῆλυ χειρόηθες καὶ ποθεινόν, ἡδείᾳ
               μὲν ὀσμῇ χρωτὸς ἰδίῳ δὲ κόσμῳ σώματος ἀγαλλόμενον, δρόσου καὶ
               βοτάνης ἀνάπλεων. καθαρᾶς· αἰσθόμενον
     <milestone n="10" unit="tlnum"/>
     <milestone id="stephpage-494a" n="494a" unit="stephpage"/>
     δʼ ὅτι κύει καὶ
               πεπλήρωται, κοσμίως ἄπεισι καὶ προνοεῖ περὶ τὴν κύησιν καὶ σωτηρίαν τοῦ
               ἀποτεχθέντος. ἀξίως δʼ οὐκ ἔστιν εἰπεῖν τὰ δρώμενα, πλὴν ὅτι γίγνεται
               ἕκαστον αὐτῶν ἐν
     <note anchored="yes" place="unspecified" resp="ed">
      <foreign lang="greek">
       ἐν
      </foreign>
      ]
      <foreign lang="greek">
       ἓν
      </foreign>
      Emperius
     </note>
     τῷ φιλοστόργῳ, ταῖς προνοίαις, ταῖς καρτερίαις, ταῖς
               ἐγκρατείαις. ἀλλὰ
     <milestone n="15" unit="tlnum"/>
     τὴν μέλιτταν ἡμεῖς σοφὴν
               καλοῦμεν καὶ νομίζομεν
     <quote rend="blockquote">
      ξανθὸν μέλι μηδομέναν
     </quote>
     <note anchored="yes" place="unspecified" resp="ed">
      Bergk. 3 p. 411
     </note>
     κολακεύοντες τὸ ἡδὺ καὶ γαργαλίζον ἡμᾶς τῆς γλυκύτητος· τὴν δὲ τῶν
               ἄλλων περὶ τὰς λοχείας καὶ τὰς ἀνατροφὰς σοφίαν καὶ τέχνην παρορῶμεν.
               οἷον
     <milestone n="20" unit="tlnum"/>
     εὐθύς, ἡ ἁλκυὼν κύουσα τὴν νεοττιὰν
               συντίθησι, συλλαμβάνουσα τὰς ἀκάνθας τῆς θαλαττίας βελόνης καὶ ταύτας διʼ
               ἀλλήλων ἐγκαταπλέκουσα καὶ συνείρουσα,
     <milestone id="stephpage-494b" n="494b" unit="stephpage"/>
     τὸ μὲν σχῆμα περιαγὲς ὡς ἁλιευτικοῦ κύρτου
               καὶ πρόμηκες ἀπεργάζεται· τῇ
     <note anchored="yes" place="unspecified" resp="ed">
      <foreign lang="greek">
       τῇ
      </foreign>
      ]
      <foreign lang="greek">
       ἡ
      </foreign>
      Doehnerus
     </note>
     δʼ ἁρμονίᾳ καὶ πυκνότητι
     <milestone n="25" unit="tlnum"/>
     συμφράξασα τὰς ἀκάνθας
     <note anchored="yes" place="unspecified" resp="ed">
      <foreign lang="greek">
       τὰς ἀκάνθας
      </foreign>
      R:
      <foreign lang="greek">
       τῆς ἀκάνθης
      </foreign>
     </note>
     ἀκριβῶς ὑπέθηκε
     <note anchored="yes" place="unspecified" resp="ed">
      <foreign lang="greek">
       ἐπέθηκε
      </foreign>
      Doehnerus
     </note>
     τῷ
     <pb id="v.3.p.281"/>
     κλύσματι τοῦ κύματος, ὡς
     <note anchored="yes" place="unspecified" resp="ed">
      <foreign lang="greek">
       ὡς
      </foreign>
      ]
      <foreign lang="greek">
       ὅπως
      </foreign>
      R
     </note>
     τυπτόμενον ἡσυχῆ καὶ πηγνύμενον
               τὸ πίλημα τῆς ἐπιφανείας στεγανὸν γένηται· γίγνεται δὲ σιδήρῳ καὶ λίθῳ
               δυσδιαίρετον. ὃ δʼ ἐστὶ θαυμασιώτερον, οὕτω τὸ στόμα τῆς νεοττιᾶς
     <milestone n="5" unit="tlnum"/>
     συμμέτρως πέπλασται
     <note anchored="yes" place="unspecified" resp="ed">
      <foreign lang="greek">
       πέπλασται
      </foreign>
      X:
      <foreign lang="greek">
       πεπλάσθαι
      </foreign>
     </note>
     πρὸς τὸ μέγεθος καὶ τὸ
               μέτρον τῆς ἁλκυόνος, ὥστε μήτε μεῖζον ἄλλο μήτε μικρότερον ἐνδύεσθαι
               ζῷον, ὡς δέ φασι, μηδὲ θάλατταν
     <milestone id="stephpage-494c" n="494c" unit="stephpage"/>
     παραδέχεσθαι
     <note anchored="yes" place="unspecified" resp="ed">
      malim
      <foreign lang="greek">
       παρεισδέχεσθαι
      </foreign>
     </note>
     μηδὲ τὰ ἐλάχιστα. μάλιστα δʼ οἱ γαλεοὶ
               ζῳογονοῦσι μὲν ἐν ἑαυτοῖς, ἐκβαίνειν
     <milestone n="10" unit="tlnum"/>
     δὲ
               παρέχουσιν ἐκτὸς καὶ νέμεσθαι τοῖς σκυμνίοις, εἶτα πάλιν ἀναλαμβάνουσι
               καὶ περιπτύσσουσιν ἐγκοιμώμενα τοῖς σπλάγχνοις. ἡ δʼ ἄρκτος, ἀγριώτατον
               καὶ σκυθρωπότατον θηρίον, ἄμορφα καὶ ἄναρθρα τίκτει· τῇ δὲ γλώττῃ
               καθάπερ ἐργαλείῳ διατυποῦσα
     <milestone n="15" unit="tlnum"/>
     τοὺς ὑμένας
     <note anchored="yes" place="unspecified" resp="ed">
      <foreign lang="greek">
       ὑμένας
      </foreign>
      ]
      <foreign lang="greek">
       σκύμνους
      </foreign>
      Doehnerus. cf. Theocr. XI, 41
     </note>
     οὐ
               δοκεῖ γεννᾶν μόνον ἀλλὰ καὶ δημιουργεῖν τὸ τέκνον. ὁ δʼ Ὁμηρικὸς λέων,
     <quote rend="blockquote">
      <l>
       ᾧ ῥά τε νήπιʼ ἄγοντι συναντήσωνται
       <note anchored="yes" place="unspecified" resp="ed">
        <foreign lang="greek">
         ᾧ ῥά τε νήπιʼ ἄγοντι συναντήσωνται
        </foreign>
        Homerus:
        <foreign lang="greek">
         ὃν ῥά τε νήπια τέκνα ἄγοντα συναντήσονται
        </foreign>
       </note>
       ἐν ὕλῃ
      </l>
      <l lang="it">
       ᾧ ῥά te nípiʼ ἄγοτι incontra 
ᾧ ῥά te nīpiʼ ἄγοντι incontrare Omero: ὃν ῥά te nīpia bambini ἄγοντα incontrare
 nel materiale
      </l>
      <l lang="en">
       ᾧ ῥά te nípiʼ ἄγοτι meet 
ᾧ ῥά te nīpiʼ ἄγοντι meet Homerus: ὃν ῥά te nīpia children ἄγοντα meet
 in material
      </l>
      <note anchored="yes" place="unspecified" resp="ed">
       Hom. P 134
      </note>
      <l>
       ἄνδρες ἐπακτῆρες, ὁ δέ τε σθένεϊ βλεμεαίνει,
       <milestone id="stephpage-494d" n="494d" unit="stephpage"/>
      </l>
      <l lang="it">
       andres épaktîres, de te stheney vede,
      </l>
      <l lang="en">
       andres épaktîres, de te stheney sees,
      </l>
      <l>
       πᾶν δὲ τʼ ἐπισκύνιον κάτω ἕλκεται ὄσσε καλύπτων
      </l>
      <l lang="it">
       ma dovunque l'episquinium viene abbattuto da una serie di coperture
      </l>
      <l lang="en">
       but everywhere the episquinium is pulled down by a number of coverts
      </l>
     </quote>
     <milestone n="20" unit="tlnum"/>
     ἆρʼ οὐχ ὅμοιός; ἐστι, διανοουμένῳ πρὸς
               τοὺς κυνηγοὺς σπένδεσθαι περὶ τῶν τέκνων; καθόλου γὰρ ἡ πρὸς τὰ ἔκγονα
     <note anchored="yes" place="unspecified" resp="ed">
      <foreign lang="greek">
       ἔκγονα
      </foreign>
      *:
      <foreign lang="greek">
       ἔγγονα
      </foreign>
     </note>
     φιλοστοργία καὶ τολμηρὰ τὰ δειλὰ
     <note anchored="yes" place="unspecified" resp="ed">
      <foreign lang="greek">
       τολμηρὰ τὰ δειλὰ
      </foreign>
      Emperius:
      <foreign lang="greek">
       τὰ τολμηρὰ δειλὰ
      </foreign>
     </note>
     ποιεῖ, καὶ φιλόπονα τὰ ῥᾴθυμα καὶ
               φειδωλὰ τὰ
     <pb id="v.3.p.282"/>
     γαστρίμαργα καὶ ὥσπερ
     <note anchored="yes" place="unspecified" resp="ed">
      <foreign lang="greek">
       καὶ ὥσπερ
      </foreign>
      ]
      <foreign lang="greek">
       ὥσπερ
      </foreign>
      Stegmannus ut cum pracedentibus iungatur
     </note>
     ἡ Ὁμηρικὴ ὄρνις
               προσφέρουσα τοῖς νεοττοῖς
     <quote rend="blockquote">
      μάστακʼ, ἐπεί κε λάβῃσι,
                  κακῶς δέ τε οἱ πέλει αὐτῇ
      <note anchored="yes" place="unspecified" resp="ed">
       Hom. I 324
      </note>
      <milestone n="5" unit="tlnum"/>
     </quote>
     τῷ γὰρ αὑτῆς τρέφει λιμῷ τὰ ἔκγονα,
     <note anchored="yes" place="unspecified" resp="ed">
      <foreign lang="greek">
       ἔκγονα
      </foreign>
      *:
      <foreign lang="greek">
       ἔγγονα
      </foreign>
     </note>
     καὶ τὴν τροφὴν τῆς
               γαστρὸς ἁπτομένην ἀποκρατεῖ καὶ πιέζει τῷ στόματι , μὴ λάθῃ καταπιοῦσα
     <milestone id="stephpage-494e" n="494e" unit="stephpage"/>
     <quote rend="blockquote">
      <l>
       ὡς δὲ κύων ἀμαλῇσι περὶ σκυλάκεσσι βεβῶσα
      </l>
      <l lang="it">
       Ma da cane sono andato a letto
      </l>
      <l lang="en">
       But as a dog, I went to bed
      </l>
      <note anchored="yes" place="unspecified" resp="ed">
       Hom.
       <foreign lang="greek">
        ν
       </foreign>
       14
      </note>
      <l>
       ἄνδρʼ ἀγνοιήσασʼ ὑλάει μέμονέν τε μάχεσθαι
       <milestone n="10" unit="tlnum"/>
      </l>
      <l lang="it">
       Un uomo che ignora se stesso si ritrova a combattere
      </l>
      <l lang="en">
       A man who ignores himself finds himself fighting
      </l>
     </quote>
     τὸν περὶ τῶν τέκνων φόβον ὡς δεύτερον προσλαβοῦσα θυμόν. αἱ δὲ
               πέρδικες ὅταν διώκωνται μετὰ τῶν τέκνων, ἐκεῖνα μὲν ἐῶσι προπέτεσθαι
               καὶ φεύγειν, αὑταῖς δὲ μηχανώμεναι προσέχειν τοὺς θηρεύοντας ἐγγὺς
               κυλινδούμεναι καὶ καταλαμβανόμεναι,
     <milestone n="15" unit="tlnum"/>
     μικρὸν
               ὑπεκθέουσιν, εἶτα πάλιν ἵστανται καὶ παρέχουσιν ἐν ἐφικτῷ τῆς ἐλπίδος
               ἑαυτάς, ἄχρι ἂν οὕτω προκινδυνεύουσαι τῶν νεοττῶν τῆς ἀσφαλείας
               προαγάγωνται
     <milestone id="stephpage-494f" n="494f" unit="stephpage"/>
     πόρρω τοὺς
               διώκοντας. τὰς δʼ ἀλεκτορίδας ἐν τοῖς ὄμμασι καθʼ ἡμέραν ἔχομεν, ὃν
               τρόπον
     <milestone n="20" unit="tlnum"/>
     τὰ νεόττια περιέπουσι, τοῖς μὲν
               ἐνδῦναι χαλῶσαι τὰς πτέρυγας, τὰ δʼ ἐπιβαίνοντα τῶν νώτων καὶ προσέρποντα
     <note anchored="yes" place="unspecified" resp="ed">
      <foreign lang="greek">
       προσέρποντα
      </foreign>
      (
      <foreign lang="greek">
       προστρέχοντα
      </foreign>
      Doehnerus) W:
      <foreign lang="greek">
       προσέρχονται
      </foreign>
     </note>
     πανταχόθεν ἀναδεχόμεναι μετὰ τοῦ γεγηθός τι
     <note anchored="yes" place="unspecified" resp="ed">
      <foreign lang="greek">
       τι
      </foreign>
      R:
      <foreign lang="greek">
       ἢ
      </foreign>
     </note>
     καὶ προσφιλὲς ἐπιφθέγγεσθαι·
               κύνας δὲ καὶ δράκοντας,
     <note anchored="yes" place="unspecified" resp="ed">
      <foreign lang="greek">
       κύνας δὲ καὶ δράκοτας
      </foreign>
      X:
      <foreign lang="greek">
       κυνέας δὲ καὶ δρακοντίας
      </foreign>
     </note>
     ἂν περὶ αὑτῶν φοβηθῶσι, φεύγουσιν,
     <pb id="v.3.p.283"/>
     ἂν δὲ περὶ τῶν τέκνων, ἀμύνονται καὶ διαμάχονται παρὰ
               δύναμιν. εἶτα
     <note anchored="yes" place="unspecified" resp="ed">
      <foreign lang="greek">
       τὰ
      </foreign>
      Doehnerus
     </note>
     ταῦτʼ οἰόμεθα τὰ πάθη τούτοις ἐνειργάσθαι τὴν φύσιν,
               ἀλεκτορίδων ἐπιγονῆς καὶ κυνῶν
     <note anchored="yes" place="unspecified" resp="ed">
      <foreign lang="greek">
       κυνῶν
      </foreign>
      ]
      <foreign lang="greek">
       ἀλκυόνων
      </foreign>
      idem
     </note>
     καὶ ἄρκτων προνοοῦσαν, ἀλλʼ οὐχ ἡμᾶς
               δυσωποῦσαν
     <milestone n="5" unit="tlnum"/>
     <milestone id="stephpage-495a" n="495a" unit="stephpage"/>
     καὶ τιτρώσκουσαν
               ἐπιλογιζομένους, ὅτι ταῦτα παραδείγματα τοῖς ἑπομένοις, τοῖς δʼ
               ἀναλγήτοις ὀνείδη περίεστι τῆς ἀπαθείας, διʼ ὧν κατηγοροῦσι τῆς
               ἀνθρωπίνης φύσεως μόνης μὴ προῖκα τὸ στέργειν ἐχούσης μηδʼ ἐπισταμένης
               φιλεῖν ἄνευ χρείας
     <milestone n="10" unit="tlnum"/>
     θαυμάζεται γὰρ ἐν τοῖς
               θεάτροις ὁ εἰπών
     <quote rend="blockquote">
      μισθοῦ γὰρ ἄνθρωπον τίς
                  ἄνθρωπον φιλεῖ
     </quote>
     <note anchored="yes" place="unspecified" resp="ed">
      Kock. 3 p. 450
     </note>
     κατʼ
     <note anchored="yes" place="unspecified" resp="ed">
      <foreign lang="greek">
       κατʼ
      </foreign>
      ]
      <foreign lang="greek">
       καὶ κατʼ
      </foreign>
      ? vid. Usener. p 320
     </note>
     Ἐπίκουρον ὁ πατὴρ τὸν υἱόν, ἡ
     <note anchored="yes" place="unspecified" resp="ed">
      <foreign lang="greek">
       ἡ
      </foreign>
      R
     </note>
     μήτηρ τὸ
               τέκνον, οἱ παῖδες τοὺς τεκόντας. ἀλλʼ εἰ λόγου γένοιτο τοῖς θηρίοις
               σύνεσις, καὶ τοῦτό τις εἰς κοινὸν θέατρον
     <milestone n="15" unit="tlnum"/>
     συναγαγὼν ἵππους καὶ βόας καὶ κύνας καὶ
     <milestone id="stephpage-495b" n="495b" unit="stephpage"/>
     ὄρνιθας; ἀναφθέγξαιτο μεταγράψας, ὡς οὔτε
               κύνες ἐπὶ μισθῷ σκύλακας φιλοῦσιν οὔθʼ ἵπποι πώλους
     <note anchored="yes" place="unspecified" resp="ed">
      <foreign lang="greek">
       πώλους
      </foreign>
      ] add.
      <foreign lang="greek">
       οὔτε βόες μόσχους
      </foreign>
      Doehnerus
     </note>
     οὔτʼ ὄρνιθες
               νεοττοὺς ἀλλὰ προῖκα καὶ φυσικῶς, ἐπιγνωσθήσεται τοῖς ἁπάντων πάθεσιν ὡς
               εὖ καὶ
     <milestone n="20" unit="tlnum"/>
     ἀληθῶς λεγόμενον. αἰσχρὸν γάρ, ὦ
               Ζεῦ, τὰς θηρίων γενέσεις καὶ λοχείας καὶ ὠδῖνας καὶ τεκνοτροφίας φύσιν
               εἶναι καὶ χάριν, τὰς δʼ ἀνθρώπων δάνεια καὶ μισθοὺς καὶ ἀρραβῶνας ἐπὶ
               χρείαις διδομένους.
    </p>
    <p lang="it">
     ora parliamo dei matrimoni per quanto li riguarda

               vivi secondo la natura. Innanzitutto non si aspetta leggi celibe 
Doehnerus celibe e poligamo: celibe e poligamo
 e incesto,
               e così il popolo di Licurgo e Solone 
e Solone] del. idem nessun disonore dei bambini
               nessun onore insegue triplette, 
tripaedias idem come Ῥromaeion polloὶ 
               si sposano e partoriscono, non hanno eredi
 Ma in modo che possano ereditare. dopo
               il maschio non si mescola sempre con la femmina, perché non prova alcun piacere
               infine, nascita e figli. per
 Questo
               nel periodo dell'anno in cui respiri sei fecondo,
               siamo arrivati ​​a questo 
È arrivato a questo Doehnerus: è arrivato a questo
 Al maschio la femmina veniva maltrattata e avvelenata, con il permesso
               con un odore e un colore, ma con il mondo del corpo, gioia, rugiada e
               Anafleone erbaceo. pulito; sentire

 vedi che anche lei è incinta
               P è pagato, universalmente fedele e provvede al concepimento e alla salvezza dell'uomo
               impenitente. Vale la pena notare che gli eventi stanno accadendo, tranne che stanno accadendo
               ognuno di loro dentro 
ἐν] un Emperius all'amoroso, alle disposizioni, alle determinazioni, al
               temperanza Ma
 eravamo saggiamente in luna di miele
               chiamiamo e pensiamo che il biondo tesoro non sia niente
Bergk. 15:00 411
               lusingando il qui e solleticandoci con dolcezza;
               degli altri esortiamo sulle lezioni e sull'educazione della saggezza e dell'arte.
               Chi
 a destra, la ninfa portava il tritone
               sintesi, catturando le spine dell'ago della talattia e queste via
               altri li ho intrecciati e cospirati,
 la forma unica di un arco da pesca
               e in breve tempo lavora; 
ῇ] il Doehnerus con armonia e densità
 Ho chiuso le spine 
le spine R: della spina
 sofferto appunto 
Doehnerus ha attaccato il clistere dell'onda COME 
as] mentre R stampava tranquillamente e se ne andava
               il feltro della superficie è reso impermeabile, ma è di ferro e pietra
               indivisibile. Ciò che è più meraviglioso è la bocca di una giovane donna
 piegato proporzionalmente 
peplastai X: peplastai
 alle dimensioni e al
               la misura di un alcione, così che non vi sia né una veste più grande né una più piccola
               la vita, come de fashi, non ha fatto thalatan
 ammissione malim ammissione
 non ultimo. anche i galeo
               Vivendo in se stessi, escono
 non
               provvedono in aggiunta agli altari, poi subentrano nuovamente
               e cadranno nelle viscere. ἡ dʼ arktos, feroce
               e la bestia dal volto cupo, brutta e inarticolato, solletica;
               come strumento di formulazione
 voi ragazzi 
yemenas] scymnus Doehnerus. cfr. Teocr. XI, 41 n
               dimostra che non solo partoriscono, ma creano anche il bambino. il secondo leone omerico, ᾧ ῥά te nípiʼ ἄγοτι incontra 
ᾧ ῥά te nīpiʼ ἄγοντι incontrare Omero: ὃν ῥά te nīpia bambini ἄγοντα incontrare
 nel materiale 
Hom. P134
 andres épaktîres, de te stheney vede,


 ma dovunque l'episquinium viene abbattuto da una serie di coperture 

 Non lo stesso? È un intellettuale
               spendi i cacciatori per i bambini? per niente alle azioni 
ἔγονα*: ἔγωνα

               filantropia e sfidare i codardi 
codardi audaci Emperius: codardi audaci
 canta e anche lui si prende cura delle sue emozioni
               con parsimonia la gastrimarga e così via 
ecc.] così Stegmannus ut cum pracedentibus iungatur l'avvoltoio omerico
               offrendo la gomma da masticare ai giovani, per riceverla,
                  non è male per chi lo manda a Hom. Io 324

 perché dà da mangiare ai suoi figli durante la fame, 
ἔγονα*: ἔγωνα
 e il suo cibo
               La pancia è gonfia e preme contro la bocca, non commettere l'errore di deglutire


 Ma da cane sono andato a letto 
Hom. numero 14
 Uomo Ignoratelo, è una battaglia unica


 la paura dei bambini come seconda fonte di rabbia. IL
               le pernici quando vengono perseguitate insieme ai bambini, così vengono profetizzate
               e se ne vanno, ma chi guida tiene d'occhio la preda vicina
               rotolato e occupato,
 micron
               assumono, ripetono che lo sono e provvedono alla portata della speranza
               te stesso, per non mettere in pericolo i giovani della sicurezza
               vengono promossi
 posso vederli
               inseguendo. Abbiamo i dʼalectoridas tra la gente ogni giorno, chi
               modo
 i giovani parlano, per me
               puoi perdere le ali, quelle sul dorso e strisciare 
rampicanti (Doehnerus creepers) W: avvicinamento

               ovunque accettato dopo il fatto cosa 
cosa R: o
 e cari parenti;
               e un segugio e un drago, 
un cane e un drago X: un cane e un drago permettere
 se hanno paura per loro fuggono, ma riguardo ai bambini si difendono e litigano
               forza Egli ha detto 
i Doehnerus queste sono le passioni che agiscono sulla natura,
               alettoridi della primogenitura e dei cani 
cani] halcyons idem e orsi hanno fornito, ma non noi
               erano infelici

 e tremavano
               considerato, perché questi esempi al successivo, al dʼ
               Dolore non alleviato a causa dell'apatia, di cui è accusato
               la natura umana da sola non ha dotato la sterilità di chi non ha fede
               si baciano inutilmente
 poiché è ammirato tra la gente
               teatri che parlano di salario, perché sono umani
                  bacia un uomo 
Kock. 15:00 450 p 
katʼ] e katʼ? video. Utente. p 320 Il padre aiutava il figlio, p 
ἡ R madre τὸ
               teknon, i bambini i tekonda. Ma è nato dalle bestie
               prudenza, e ciò in un teatro comune

               συγαγὼν ἵ ppus, boa, segugi e
 pollo? anafthengkaito hai trascritto, come nessuno dei due
               kynes ἕπὶ μιθῷ skylakas kiss ὔθʼ ἵπποπος poli 
poli] aggiungono. né i buoi muschiati Doehnerus né i polli
               nuovi ma dote e, naturalmente, è noto agli intervistati come
               ὖ e
 per così dire. bellissimo, ὦ
               Vivi, le nascite delle bestie e le nascite delle bestie
               è anche per la grazia, i prestiti, il salario e l'impegno delle due persone
               hai bisogno di donatori.
    </p>
    <p lang="en">
     now about marriages as far as they are concerned

               you live by nature. First of all, he does not expect celibate laws 
celibate and polygamous Doehnerus: celibate and polygamous
 and incest,
               and so the people of Lycurgus and Solon 
and Solon] del. idem no dishonor of children
               no honor chases triplets, 
tripaedias idem as Ῥromaeion polloὶ 
               they marry and give birth, they have no heirs
 But so that they can inherit. afterward
               the male mingles with the female not all the time, for he has no pleasure
               finally, birth and children. for
 this
               at the time of the year, when you are breathing, you are fruitful,
               came to this 
He came to this Doehnerus: he came to this
 To the male the female was abused and poisoned, with permission
               with an odor and color, but with the world of the body, rejoicing, dew and
               herb anaphleon. clean; feel

 see that she is also pregnant
               p is paid, universally faithful and provides for the conception and salvation of
               unrepentant. It is worth noting that the events are happening, except that they are happening
               each of them in 
ἐν] an Emperius to the loving, the provisions, the determinations, the
               temperance but
 we were on our honeymoon wisely
               we call and think blond honey nothing
Bergk. 3 p.m. 411
               flattering the here and tickling us with sweetness;
               of others we exhort about the lessons and the education of wisdom and art.
               who
 right, the nymph carried the newt
               synthesis, capturing the thorns of the thalattia needle and these by
               others I entwined and conspired,
 the single shape of a fishing bow
               and before long he works; ῇ 
ῇ] the Doehnerus with harmony and density
 I closed the thorns 
the thorns R: of the thorn
 precisely suffered 
Doehnerus attacked the wave's enema as 
as] as R printed quietly and went away
               the felt of the surface is made watertight, but it is made of iron and stone
               indivisible. What is more wonderful is the mouth of a young woman
 proportionally folded 
peplastai X: peplastai
 to the size and the
               the measure of a halcyon, so that there is neither a larger nor a smaller garment
               life, as de fashi, did not thalatan
 admission malim admission
 not the least. even the galeos
               Living in themselves, they go out
 not
               they provide in addition to the altars, then they again take over
               and they will fall into the entrails. ἡ dʼ arktos, fierce
               and the grim-faced beast, ugly and inarticulate, tickles;
               as a formulating tool
 you guys 
yemenas] scymnus Doehnerus. cf. Theocr. XI, 41 no
               it proves that they not only give birth, but also create the child. the second Homeric lion, ᾧ ῥά te nípiʼ ἄγοτι meet 
ᾧ ῥά te nīpiʼ ἄγοντι meet Homerus: ὃν ῥά te nīpia children ἄγοντα meet
 in material 
Hom. P 134
 andres épaktîres, de te stheney sees,


 but everywhere the episquinium is pulled down by a number of coverts 

 Not the same? He is an intellectual
               do you spend the hunters on the children? not at all to the actions 
ἔγονα *: ἔγωνα

               philanthropy and daring the cowards 
bold cowards Emperius: bold cowards
 he sings, and cares for his emotions too
               sparingly the gastrimarga and so on 
and so on] so Stegmannus ut cum pracedentibus iungatur the Homeric vulture
               offering chewing gum to the young, to receive it,
                  it is not bad for those who send it to Hom. I 324

 for he feeds his children in famine, 
ἔγονα *: ἔγωνα
 and her food
               Stomach is swollen and it presses against the mouth, don't make the mistake of swallowing


 But as a dog, I went to bed 
Hom. n 14
 man Ignore it, it's a single battle


 the fear about the children as the second source of anger. the
               partridges when they are persecuted with the children, they are thus prophesied
               and they leave, but those who drive keep an eye on the nearby prey
               rolled and occupied,
 micron
               they assume, say again they are and provide within the reach of hope
               yourself, lest you endanger the youths of the security
               are promoted
 I can see them
               chasing. We have the dʼalectoridas among the people every day, who
               way
 the youth talk, to me
               you can lose your wings, the ones on the backs and crawling 
creepers (Doehnerus creepers) W: approach

               everywhere accepted after the fact what 
what R: or
 and dear relatives;
               and a hound and a dragon, 
a dog and a dragon X: a dog and a dragon let
 if they are afraid about them, they flee, but about the children, they defend themselves and argue over
               strength he said 
the Doehnerus these are the passions that act upon nature,
               alectorids of primogeniture and dogs 
dogs] halcyons idem and bears they provided, but not us
               they were unhappy

 and they trembled
               considered, because these examples to the next, to the dʼ
               Unrelieved pain due to apathy, for which it is accused
               human nature alone did not endow the barrenness of having no faith
               they kiss unnecessarily
 for he is admired among the people
               theaters who speak of wages, because they are human
                  he kisses a man 
Kock. 3 p.m. 450 per 
katʼ] and katʼ? vid. User. p 320 The father helped the son, p 
ἡ R mother τὸ
               teknon, the children the tekondas. But it was born to the beasts
               prudence, and this in a common theater

               συγαγὼν ἵ ppus and boas and hounds and
 chicken? anafthengkaito you transcribed, as neither
               kynes ἕπὶ μιθῷ skylakas kiss ὔθʼ ἵπποπος poles 
poles] add. neither Doehnerus musk oxen nor chickens
               new ones but dowry and of course, it is known to the respondents as
               ὖ and
 so to speak. beautiful, ὦ
               Live, the births of the beasts and the births of the beasts
               it is also for grace, the two people's loans and wages and engagement on
               you need givers.
    </p>
   </div1>
   <div1 n="3" type="section">
    <p>
     ἀλλʼ οὔτʼ ἀληθὴς ὁ λόγος οὔτʼ ἄξιος
     <note anchored="yes" place="unspecified" resp="ed">
      <foreign lang="greek">
       ἄξιος
      </foreign>
      R:
      <foreign lang="greek">
       ἄξιον
      </foreign>
     </note>
     ἀκούειν.
     <milestone n="25" unit="tlnum"/>
     ἡ γὰρ φύσις ὥσπερ ἐν φυτοῖς ἀγρίοις, οἷον οἰνάνθαις
               ἐρινεοῖς κοτίνοις, ἀρχὰς ἀπέπτους καὶ ἀτελεῖς
     <pb id="v.3.p.284"/>
     ἡμέρων
               καρπῶν ἐνέφυσεν·
     <note anchored="yes" place="unspecified" resp="ed">
      <foreign lang="greek">
       ἐνέφυσεν
      </foreign>
      R:
      <foreign lang="greek">
       εἶναι φύσιν
      </foreign>
     </note>
     οὕτω τοῖς μὲν ἀλόγοις
     <milestone id="stephpage-495c" n="495c" unit="stephpage"/>
     τὸ πρὸς τὰ ἔκγονα
     <note anchored="yes" place="unspecified" resp="ed">
      <foreign lang="greek">
       ἔκγονα
      </foreign>
      *:
      <foreign lang="greek">
       ἔγγονα
      </foreign>
     </note>
     φιλόστοργον ἀτελὲς καὶ
               οὐ διαρκὲς πρὸς δικαιοσύνην οὐδὲ τῆς χρείας προσωτέρω προερχόμενον ἔδωκεν
               ἄνθρωπον δέ, λογικὸν καὶ
     <milestone n="5" unit="tlnum"/>
     πολιτικὸν ζῷον,
               ἐπὶ δίκην καὶ νόμον εἰσάγουσα καὶ θεῶν τιμὰς καὶ πόλεων ἱδρύσεις καὶ
               φιλοφροσύνην, γενναῖα καὶ καλὰ καὶ φερέκαρπα τούτων σπέρματα παρέσχε τὴν
               πρὸς τὰ ἔκγονα
     <note anchored="yes" place="unspecified" resp="ed">
      <foreign lang="greek">
       ἔκγονα
      </foreign>
      *:
      <foreign lang="greek">
       ἔγγοα
      </foreign>
     </note>
     χάριν καὶ ἀγάπησιν, ἀκολουθοῦσα ταῖς πρώταις ἀρχαῖς·
               αὗται δʼ ἦσαν
     <milestone n="10" unit="tlnum"/>
     ἐν ταῖς τῶν σωμάτων
               κατασκευαῖς. πανταχοῦ μὲν γὰρ ἡ φύσις ἀκριβὴς καὶ φιλότεχνος
     <note anchored="yes" place="unspecified" resp="ed">
      <foreign lang="greek">
       φιλότεχνος
      </foreign>
      X:
      <foreign lang="greek">
       φιλότεκνος
      </foreign>
     </note>
     καὶ
               ἀνελλιπὴς
     <milestone id="stephpage-495d" n="495d" unit="stephpage"/>
     καὶ
               ἀπερίτμητος
     <note anchored="yes" place="unspecified" resp="ed">
      <foreign lang="greek">
       ἀπερίτμητος
      </foreign>
      ]
      <foreign lang="greek">
       ἀνεπιτίμητος
      </foreign>
      ?
     </note>
     ʽ “οὐδέν” ὡς ἔφησεν Ἐρασίστρατος “ἔχουσα
                  ῥωπικόν·” τὰ δὲ περὶ τὴν γένεσιν ἀξίως οὐκ ἔστιν εἰπεῖν οὐδʼ
               εὐπρεπὲς ἴσως λίαν ἀκριβῶς τῶν
     <milestone n="15" unit="tlnum"/>
     ἀπορρήτων
               ἐφάπτεσθαι τοῖς ὀνόμασι καὶ τοῖς ῥήμασιν, ἀλλʼ ἀποκειμένων καὶ
               κεκρυμμένων
     <note anchored="yes" place="unspecified" resp="ed">
      <foreign lang="greek">
       ἀλλʼ ἀποκειμένων καὶ κεκρυμμένων
      </foreign>
      ]
      <foreign lang="greek">
       καὶ
      </foreign>
      Stegmannus
     </note>
     ἐπινοεῖν τὴν πρὸς τὸ γεννᾶν καὶ λοχεύεσθαι τῶν μορίων
               ἐκείνων εὐφυΐαν. ἀρκεῖ δʼ ἡ τοῦ γάλακτος ἐργασία καὶ οἰκονομία τὴν
               πρόνοιαν αὐτῆς ἐμφῆναι καὶ ἐπιμέλειαν.
     <milestone n="20" unit="tlnum"/>
     τοῦ
               γὰρ αἵματος ὅσον περίττωμα τῆς χρείας ἐν ταῖς γυναιξὶ διʼ ἀμβλύτητα καὶ
               μικρότητα τοῦ
     <milestone id="stephpage-495e" n="495e" unit="stephpage"/>
     πνεύματος
               ἐπιπολάζον ἐμπλανᾶται καὶ βαρύνει, τὸν μὲν ἄλλον χρόνον εἴθισται καὶ
               μεμελέτηκεν ἐμμήνοις
     <note anchored="yes" place="unspecified" resp="ed">
      <foreign lang="greek">
       ἐμμήνοις
      </foreign>
      ] add.
      <foreign lang="greek">
       κηʼ
      </foreign>
      Doehnerus
     </note>
     ἡμερῶν περιόδοις ὀχετοὺς καὶ πόρους αὐτῷ τῆς
     <milestone n="25" unit="tlnum"/>
     φύσεως ἀναστομούσης ἀποχεόμενον τὸ μὲν
               ἄλλο σῶμα κουφίζειν καὶ καθαίρειν, τὴν δʼ ὑστέραν οἷον
     <pb id="v.3.p.285"/>
     ἀρότῳ
     <note anchored="yes" place="unspecified" resp="ed">
      <foreign lang="greek">
       ἀρότῳ
      </foreign>
      R:
      <foreign lang="greek">
       ἀρότρῳ
      </foreign>
     </note>
     καὶ σπόρῳ γῆν ἐν φυτοῖς
     <note anchored="yes" place="unspecified" resp="ed">
      <foreign lang="greek">
       ἐν φυτοῖς
      </foreign>
      ] i. e.
      <foreign lang="greek">
       ἐπὶ τῶν φυτῶν.
      </foreign>
      frustra tentatur
     </note>
     ὀργῶσαν ἐν καιρῷ παρέχειν. ὅταν δὲ
               τὴν γονὴν ἀναλάβῃ προσπεσοῦσαν
     <note anchored="yes" place="unspecified" resp="ed">
      <foreign lang="greek">
       προσπεσοῦσαν
      </foreign>
      W:
      <foreign lang="greek">
       προσπεσοῦσα
      </foreign>
     </note>
     ἡ ὑστέρα καὶ περιστείλῃ ῥιζώσεως
               γενομένης· “ὁ γὰρ ὀμφαλὸς; πρῶτον ἐν μήτρῃσιν” ὥς φησι Δημόκριτος
     <note anchored="yes" place="unspecified" resp="ed">
      <foreign lang="greek">
       Δημόκριτος
      </foreign>
      ] Mullach. 1 p. 359
     </note>
     <milestone n="5" unit="tlnum"/>
     “ἀγκυρηβόλιον σάλου καὶ πλάνης ἐμφύεται, πεῖσμα καὶ κλῆμα” τῷ
               γεννωμένῳ καρπῷ καὶ μέλλοντι·
     <milestone id="stephpage-495f" n="495f" unit="stephpage"/>
     τοὺς μὲν,
     <note anchored="yes" place="unspecified" resp="ed">
      <foreign lang="greek">
       τοὺς μὲν
      </foreign>
      Basileensis:
      <foreign lang="greek">
       καὶ τοὺς μὲν
      </foreign>
     </note>
     ἐμμήνους καὶ καθαρσίους ἔκλεισεν ὀχετοὺς ἡ φύσις,
               τοῦ δʼ αἵματος ἀντιλαμβανομένη φερομένου τροφῇ χρῆται καὶ κατάρδει τὸ
               βρέφος
     <milestone n="10" unit="tlnum"/>
     ἤδη συνιστάμενον καὶ διαπλαττόμενον,
               ἄχρι οὗ τοὺς προσήκοντας ἀριθμοὺς τῇ ἐντὸς; αὐξήσει κυηθὲν
     <note anchored="yes" place="unspecified" resp="ed">
      <foreign lang="greek">
       κυηθὲν
      </foreign>
      X:
      <foreign lang="greek">
       κινηθὲν
      </foreign>
     </note>
     ἑτέρας
               ἀνατροφῆς καὶ χώρας δέηται. τότʼ οὖν τὸ αἷμα παντὸς ἐμμελέστερον
               φυτουργοῦ καὶ ὀχετηγοῦ πρὸς ἑτέραν ἀφʼ ἑτέρας ἐκτρέπουσα καὶ
               μεταλαμβάνουσα
     <milestone n="15" unit="tlnum"/>
     χρείαν, ἔχει παρεσκευασμένας
               οἷον ἐγγείους ἤ τινας
     <note anchored="yes" place="unspecified" resp="ed">
      <foreign lang="greek">
       ἤ τινας
      </foreign>
      ]
      <foreign lang="greek">
       τινὰς
      </foreign>
      R qui recte nunc mihi emendasse vid. cf. Symb. meas
     </note>
     <milestone id="stephpage-496a" n="496a" unit="stephpage"/>
     κρήνας νάματος ἐπιρρέοντος, οὐκ ἀργῶς οὐδʼ ἀπαθῶς ὑποδεχομένας ἀλλὰ
               καὶ πνεύματος ἠπίῳ θερμότητι καὶ μαλακῇ θηλύτητι ἐκπέψαι καὶ λεᾶναι
               καὶ μεταβαλεῖν δυναμένας· τοιαύτην γὰρ ὁ μαστὸς ἔχει
     <milestone n="20" unit="tlnum"/>
     ἐντὸς
     <note anchored="yes" place="unspecified" resp="ed">
      <foreign lang="greek">
       ἐντὸς ἔχει
      </foreign>
      Benselerus
     </note>
     διάθεσιν καὶ κρᾶσιν. ἐκροαὶ δὲ τοῦ γάλακτος οὐκ εἰσὶν
               οὐδὲ κρουνοὶ μεθιέντες ἀθρόως, εἰς δὲ σάρκα πιδακώδη καὶ πόροις ἀτρέμα
               λεπτοῖς διηθοῦσαν ἀπολήγων, εὐμενὲς τῷ τοῦ νηπίου στόματι καὶ προσφιλὲς;
               ψαῦσαι καὶ περιλαβεῖν ἐνδίδωσι ταμιεῖον.
     <note anchored="yes" place="unspecified" resp="ed">
      <foreign lang="greek">
       ταμιεῖον
      </foreign>
      *:
      <foreign lang="greek">
       ταμεῖον
      </foreign>
     </note>
     <pb id="v.3.p.286"/>
     ἀλλὰ τούτων γε
               τῶν τοσούτων ἐπὶ τήν γένεσιν ἐργαλείων καὶ τοιούτων οἰκονομιῶν καὶ
               φιλοτιμίας καὶ προνοίας οὐδὲν ἦν ὄφελος, εἰ μὴ τὸ φιλόστοργον ἡ φύσις
               καὶ κηδεμονικὸν ἐνειργάσατο ταῖς τεκούσαις.
     <milestone n="5" unit="tlnum"/>
     <quote rend="blockquote">
      <l>
       πάντων ὅσσα τε γαῖαν ἔπι πνείει
       <note anchored="yes" place="unspecified" resp="ed">
        <foreign lang="greek">
         ἔπι πνείει
        </foreign>
        Homerus:
        <foreign lang="greek">
         ἐπιπνείει
        </foreign>
       </note>
       τε καὶ ἕρπει·
      </l>
      <l lang="it">
       comunque, qualunque cosa sia, è soffocante 
ἔπ respira Omero: respira
 te ed erpei;
      </l>
      <l lang="en">
       anyway, whatever it is, it's suffocating 
ἔπ breathes Homerus: breathes
 te and erpei;
      </l>
      <note anchored="yes" place="unspecified" resp="ed">
       Hom. P 446
      </note>
     </quote>
     τοῦτʼ οὐ ψεύδεται ὁ
     <note anchored="yes" place="unspecified" resp="ed">
      <foreign lang="greek">
       ὁ
      </foreign>
      R
     </note>
     λέγων ἐπὶ νηπίου καὶ
     <note anchored="yes" place="unspecified" resp="ed">
      <foreign lang="greek">
       καὶ
      </foreign>
      ] del. Doehnerus
     </note>
     ἀρτιγενοῦς. οὐδὲν γάρ
               ἐστιν οὕτως; ἀτελὲς οὐδʼ ἄπορον οὐδὲ γυμνὸν οὐδʼ ἄμορφον οὐδὲ
               μιαρόν, ὡς ἄνθρωπος
     <milestone n="10" unit="tlnum"/>
     ἐν γοναῖς ὁρώμενος· ᾧ
               μόνῳ σχεδὸν οὐδὲ καθαρὰν ἔδωκεν εἰς φῶς ὁδὸν ἡ φύσις, ἀλλʼ αἵματι
               πεφυρμένος καὶ λύθρου περίπλεως καὶ φονευομένῳ μᾶλλον ἢ γεννωμένῳ
               ἐοικὼς οὐδενός ἐστιν ἅψασθαι καὶ ἀνελέσθαι
     <milestone id="stephpage-496c" n="496c" unit="stephpage"/>
     καὶ ἀσπάσασθαι καὶ περιλαβεῖν
     <note anchored="yes" place="unspecified" resp="ed">
      <foreign lang="greek">
       περιλαβεῖν
      </foreign>
      ]
      <foreign lang="greek">
       περιβαλεῖν
      </foreign>
      ?
     </note>
     ἢ τοῦ φύσει
     <milestone n="15" unit="tlnum"/>
     φιλοῦντος. διὸ τῶν μὲν ἄλλων ζῴων ὑπὸ
               τὴν γαστέρα τὰ οὔθατα χαλᾷ τοὺς μαστοὺς,
     <note anchored="yes" place="unspecified" resp="ed">
      <foreign lang="greek">
       χαλᾷ τοὺς μαστοὺς
      </foreign>
      ]
      <foreign lang="greek">
       χαλᾷ
      </foreign>
      Herwerdenus. de vocum distinctione cf. Reiskius
     </note>
     ταῖς δὲ γυναιξὶν ἄνω
               γεγόνασιν
     <note anchored="yes" place="unspecified" resp="ed">
      <foreign lang="greek">
       γεγόνασιν
      </foreign>
      ] del. idem
     </note>
     περὶ τὸ στέρνον ἐν ἐφικτῷ τοῦ φιλῆσαι καὶ περιπτύξαι καὶ
               κατασπάσασθαι τὸ νήπιον, ὡς τοῦ τεκεῖν καὶ θρέψαι τέλος οὐ χρείαν
     <milestone n="20" unit="tlnum"/>
     ἀλλὰ φιλίαν ἔχοντος
    </p>
    <p lang="it">
     Ma la parola non è né vera né degna 
degno R: degno
 ascoltano
 perché la natura è come le piante selvatiche, che ami
               polli maschi, giorni precoci e incompleti
               di frutta soffiata; 
enefisen R: è la natura
 quindi a quelli con i cavalli
 il alle azioni 
ἔγονα*: ἔγωνα
 amorevolmente imperfetto e
               non durano per la giustizia né per il debito venuto dall'aldilà
               umano, anche logico
 vita politica,
               sul giudizio e sulla legge ho introdotto e l'onore degli dei e le fondamenta delle città e
               la filantropia, il coraggio e i semi buoni e fruttuosi di questi hanno fornito il
               verso gli eventi 
ἔγονα*: ἔγωα
 per la grazia e l'amore, seguendo i primi principi;
               loro non erano
 nei corpi
               costruzioni. perché ovunque la natura è precisa e artistica 
filotecno X: filotecnos
 E
               incompleto
 E
               incirconciso 
incirconciso] irreprensibile; ʽ "nessuno" come ἔ Erasistrato disse: "Ho sentito
                  rihopikon;" ma riguardo alla nascita vale la pena dire di no
               dignitoso forse troppo precisamente da parte loro
 segreti
               è legato ai nomi e ai detti, ma anche
               nascosto 
ma di celate e nascoste] e Stegmannus lo inventa verso la generazione e la secrezione delle molecole
               di quei geni. bastano il lavoro e l'economia del latte
               anche la sua cura e custodia sono implicite.
 Di
               per il sangue come escremento necessario nelle donne per oscenità e
               piccolezza di
 spirito
               prevalente è fuorviante e gravoso, l'altra volta si abitua e
               mesi sono stati studiati 
mensile] aggiungi. kiʼ Doehnerus dei giorni periodi di fiumi e torrenti per lui
 natura dell'anastomosi che lascia me
               un altro corpo lo hanno scavato e profanato, lo hanno lasciato a qualcuno 
ἀροτῳ R: ἀροτρῳ
 e seminare tra le piante 
in fi a] i. e. sulle piante. frustra tentatur quando no
               si precipitarono ad assumere la maternità 
digiunato W: veloce
 quest'ultimo e la circoncisione della rizosi
               evento; prima nel grembo materno", come diceva Democrito 
Democrito] Mullah. 1 pag. 359
 "è instillata l'ancora della confusione e dell'errore, dell'ostinazione e della vite" al
               frutto nato e futuro;
 tema 
quelli di Basileensis: e quelli di
 La natura ha chiuso i canali delle mestruazioni e della pulizia,
               del sangue, percepito come cibo, viene consumato e distrutto
               infantile
 già costituito e diffuso,
               dove sono i numeri corrispondenti? aumentare la gravidanza 
spostare X: spostare
 un altro
               dipende dall'educazione e dal paese. allora il sangue è dappertutto
               di una fioriera e di un canale sotterraneo da un lato all'altro
               frequentando
 Ne ho bisogno, ce l'ho preparato
               una nave o t sei 
o tinas] tinas R qui recte nunc mihi emendasse vid. cfr. Sim. mis
 fontana d'acqua corrente, né lenta né spassionata ricevuta ma
               e dello spirito, trasudava calore e morbida femminilità e dicono
               e cambiare con forza, perché è quello che ha il seno
 entro 
Ha carattere e attitudine Benselerus. ma non si sente parlare del latte
               non fontane ebbre all'eccesso, ma in carne fiammeggiante e senza pori
               filtravano attraverso i minuti, dolci e cari alla bocca del bambino?
               cercare e includere una ricevuta di deposito. 
tameion *: tameion

 ma di questi
               di questi sulla generazione di strumenti e tali economie e
               la carità e la provvidenza non avrebbero alcun beneficio, se la natura non fosse stata caritatevole
               e fungeva da guardiano del tecous.


 comunque, qualunque cosa sia, è soffocante 
ἔπ respira Omero: respira
 te ed erpei; 
Hom. P446
 non sta mentendo 
la R dice su bambino piccolo e 
e] del. Doehnerus artigenus. Affatto
               è così? imperfetto, no bisognoso, no nudo, no brutto, no
               allo stesso tempo, come essere umano
 ᾧ
               Non solo la natura ha indicato chiaramente la via, ma il sangue
               ucciso e lythru periple e ucciso piuttosto o nato
               Una casa che non è niente è impura e inespugnabile
 e abbracciare e abbracciare 
circondare] circondare; o soffiare
 baciarsi attraverso altre vite sotto
               i tessuti dello stomaco rovinano il seno, 
χαλᾷ τοὺς μαστοὺς] χαλᾷ Herwerdenus. de vocum distinzione cfr. Reiskius, ma le donne sopra
               evento 
evento] del. idem sullo sterno per poter essere anche baciato e avvolto
               prendi il bambino, mentre corrono e gli danno da mangiare, non ne avevano bisogno
 ma avere amicizia
    </p>
    <p lang="en">
     But the word is neither true nor worthy 
worthy R: worthy
 they listen
 for nature is like wild plants, which you love
               male chickens, early and incomplete days
               of fruit blown; 
enefisen R: it is nature
 so to those with horses
 the to the actions 
ἔγονα *: ἔγωνα
 lovingly imperfect and
               do not last to justice nor to the debt that came from hereafter
               humane, logical too
 political life,
               on judgment and law I introduced and the honor of gods and the foundations of cities and
               philanthropy, bravery and good and fruitful seeds of these provided the
               towards the events 
ἔγονα *: ἔγωα
 for grace and love, following the first principles;
               they were not
 in the bodies
               constructions. because everywhere nature is precise and artistic 
philotechno X: philotechnos
 and
               incomplete
 and
               uncircumcised 
uncircumcised] irreproachable; ʽ "none" as ἔ Erasistratos said "I heard
                  rihopikon;" but about the birth it is worth saying no
               dignified perhaps too precisely of them
 secrets
               it is related to the names and the sayings, but also
               hidden 
but of hidden and hidden ones] and Stegmannus invents it towards the generation and the secreting of the molecules
               of those geniuses. the milk's work and economy are enough
               her care and custody are also implied.
 of
               for blood as excrement of necessity in women through obscenity and
               smallness of
 spirit
               prevalent it is misleading and burdensome, the other time it gets used and
               months were studied 
monthly] add. kiʼ Doehnerus of days periods of rivers and streams to him
 nature of anastomosis leaving the me
               another body they hollowed out and defiled, they left it to someone 
ἀροτῳ R: ἀροτρῳ
 and sow seed among the plants 
in phy to] i. e. on the plants. frustra tentatur when not
               they rushed to take over the motherhood 
fasted W: fast
 the latter and circumcision of rhizosis
               event; first in the womb" as Democritus said 
Democritus] Mullach. 1 p. 359
 "the anchor of confusion and error is instilled, stubbornness and vine" to the
               born fruit and future;
 the me 
those of Basileensis: and those of
 Nature has closed the channels of menstruating and cleansing,
               of the blood, perceived as food, is consumed and destroyed
               infant
 already constituted and spread,
               where are the corresponding numbers in? increase pregnancy 
move X: move
 another
               it depends on upbringing and country. then the blood is all over the place
               of a planter and a culvert to one side from the other side
               attending
 I need it, I have it prepared
               a vessel or t you are 
or tinas] tinas R qui recte nunc mihi emendasse vid. cf. Symb. meas
 fountain of flowing water, neither slow nor dispassionately received but
               and of the spirit, warmth and soft femininity exuded and they say
               and change with strength, because that's what the breast has
 within 
He has Benselerus disposition and attitude. but there is no hearing of the milk
               no fountains intoxicated to excess, but in flesh flamboyant and poreless
               did they percolate through the minutes, sweet to the infant's mouth and dear?
               look for and include a depository receipt. 
tameion *: tameion

 but of these
               of these on the generation of tools and such economies and
               charity and providence had no benefit, if nature had not been charitable
               and he acted as a guardian to the tecous.


 anyway, whatever it is, it's suffocating 
ἔπ breathes Homerus: breathes
 te and erpei; 
Hom. P 446
 he is not lying 
the R saying on toddler and 
and] del. Doehnerus artigenus. not at all
               is that so? imperfect no needy no naked no ugly no
               at the same time, as a human being
 ᾧ
               Nature alone has not clearly shown the way, but blood
               slain and lythru periple and slain rather or born
               A house that is nothing is impure and impregnable
 and embrace and embrace 
surround] surround; or to blow
 kissing through other lives under
               the stomach tissues spoil the breasts, 
χαλᾷ τοὺς μαστοὺς] χαλᾷ Herwerdenus. de vocum distinctione cf. Reiskius, but the women above
               event 
event] del. idem about the sternum in order to be kissed and wrapped as well
               snatch the baby, as they run and feed them, they didn't need
 but having friendship
    </p>
   </div1>
   <div1 n="4" type="section">
    <p>
     ἐπὶ τοὺς παλαιοὺς; ἀνάγαγε τὸν λόγον, ὧν ταῖς μὲν τεκεῖν πρώταις, τοῖς
               δʼ ἰδεῖν συνέβη τικτόμενον βρέφος· οὔτε νόμος ἦν ἐκείνοις τεκνοτροφεῖν
               προστάττων οὔτε προσδοκία χάριτος ἢ τροφείων “ἐπὶ
     <pb id="v.3.p.287"/>
     νέοις δανειζομένων”
     <note anchored="yes" place="unspecified" resp="ed">
      <foreign lang="greek">
       ἐπὶ νέοις δανειζομένων
      </foreign>
      ] cf. p. 479 f.
     </note>
     χαλεπὰς δὲ μᾶλλον εἴποιμʼ ἂν εἶναι καὶ
               μνησικάκους τὰς τεκούσας τοῖς βρέφεσι, κινδύνων τε μεγάλων καὶ πόνων
               αὐταῖς γιγνομένων·
     <milestone id="stephpage-496d" n="496d" unit="stephpage"/>
     <quote rend="blockquote">
      <l>
       ὡς δʼ ὅταν ὠδίνουσαν ἔχῃ βέλος ὀξὺ γυναῖκα
       <note anchored="yes" place="unspecified" resp="ed">
        Hom.
        <foreign lang="greek">
         Λ
        </foreign>
        269
       </note>
       <milestone n="5" unit="tlnum"/>
      </l>
      <l lang="it">
       as dʼ quando omdinusan ὥ᾽ velos ώὺ donna Hom. L269
      </l>
      <l lang="en">
       as dʼ when omdinusan ὥ᾽ velos ώὺ woman Hom. L 269
      </l>
      <l>
       δριμύ, τό τε προϊεῖσι μογοστόκοι Εἰλείθυιαι,
      </l>
      <l lang="it">
       drimy, a te proieissi mogostokoi Eleithyiai,
      </l>
      <l lang="en">
       drimy, to te proieissi mogostokoi Eleithyiai,
      </l>
      <l>
       Ἥρης θυγατέρες, πικρὰς ὠδῖνας ἔχουσαι.
      </l>
      <l lang="it">
       O figlie di Dio, avete un'amara maledizione.
      </l>
      <l lang="en">
       O daughters of God, you have a bitter curse.
      </l>
     </quote>
     ταῦτʼ οὐχ Ὅμηρον αἱ γυναῖκες; ἀλλʼ Ὁμηρίδα γράψαι λέγουσι
               τεκοῦσαν ἢ τίκτουσαν ἔτι καὶ τὸ μῖγμα
     <note anchored="yes" place="unspecified" resp="ed">
      <foreign lang="greek">
       μῖγμα
      </foreign>
      ]
      <foreign lang="greek">
       νύγμα
      </foreign>
      R
     </note>
     τῆς ἀλγηδόνος ὁμοῦ πικρὸν καὶ
               ὀξὺ γιγνόμενον ἐν
     <milestone n="10" unit="tlnum"/>
     τοῖς σπλάγχνοις ἔχουσαν.
               ἀλλὰ τὸ φύσει φιλόστοργον ἔκαμπτε καὶ ἦγεν·
     <note anchored="yes" place="unspecified" resp="ed">
      <foreign lang="greek">
       ἦγεν
      </foreign>
      ]
      <foreign lang="greek">
       ἦγχεν
      </foreign>
      ?
     </note>
     ἔτι θερμὴ καὶ διαλγὴς καὶ
               κραδαινομένη τοῖς πόνοις οὐχ ὑπερέβη τὸ νήπιον
     <milestone id="stephpage-496e" n="496e" unit="stephpage"/>
     οὐδʼ ἔφυγεν, ἀλλʼ ἐπεστράφη καὶ
               προσεμειδίασε καὶ ἀνείλετο καὶ ἠσπάσατο, μηδὲν ἡδὺ καρπουμένη μηδὲ
     <milestone n="15" unit="tlnum"/>
     χρήσιμον ἀλλʼ ἐπιπόνως καὶ ταλαιπώρως
     <note anchored="yes" place="unspecified" resp="ed">
      <foreign lang="greek">
       ἐπιπόνως καὶ ταλαιπώρως
      </foreign>
      ]
      <foreign lang="greek">
       ἔτι πόνους καὶ ταλαιπωρίας
      </foreign>
      Doehnerus
     </note>
     ἀναδεχομένη τῶν σπαργάνων
     <quote rend="blockquote">
      <l>
       ἐρειπίοις
      </l>
      <l lang="it">
       rovine
      </l>
      <l lang="en">
       ruins
      </l>
      <l>
       θάλπουσα καὶ ψύχουσα, καὶ πόνῳ πόνον
      </l>
      <l lang="it">
       Ho allattato e raffreddato, e dolore dopo dolore
      </l>
      <l lang="en">
       I nursed and cooled, and pain after pain
      </l>
      <note anchored="yes" place="unspecified" resp="ed">
       Nauck. p. 839
      </note>
      <l>
       ἐκ νυκτὸς ἀλλάσσουσα τὸν μεθʼ
       <note anchored="yes" place="unspecified" resp="ed">
        <foreign lang="greek">
         μεθʼ
        </foreign>
        Cobetus:
        <foreign lang="greek">
         καθʼ
        </foreign>
       </note>
       ἡμέραν.
      </l>
      <l lang="it">
       di notte ho cambiato il vino 
méthʼ Cobetus: professore
 giorno.
      </l>
      <l lang="en">
       at night I changed the wine 
méthʼ Cobetus: professor
 day.
      </l>
     </quote>
     <milestone n="20" unit="tlnum"/>
     τίνων ταῦτα μισθῶν ἢ χρειῶν ἐκείνοις; ἀλλʼ
               οὐδὲ τοῖς νῦν· αἱ γὰρ ἐλπίδες ἄδηλοι καὶ μακραί. ἄμπελον ἰσημερίας
               ἐαρινῆς σκάψας μετοπωρινῆς ἐτρύγησε, πυρὸν ἔσπειρε δυομένης Πλειάδος
               εἶτʼ ἀνατελλούσης θερίζει, βόες καὶ ἵπποι καὶ ὄρνιθες ἕτοιμα τίκτουσιν
     <milestone n="25" unit="tlnum"/>
     <milestone id="stephpage-496f" n="496f" unit="stephpage"/>
     ἐπὶ τὰς χρείας
               ἀνθρώπου δʼ ἡ μὲν ἐκτροφὴ πολύπονος ἡ δʼ αὔξησις βραδεῖα, τῆς δʼ ἀρετῆς
     <pb id="v.3.p.288"/>
     μακρὰν οὔσης προαποθνῄσκουσιν οἱ πλεῖστοι πατέρες.
               οὐκ ἐπεῖδε τὴν Σαλαμῖνα Νεοκλῆς τὴν Θεμιστοκλέους οὐδὲ τὸν
               Εὐρυμέδοντα Μιλτιάδης τὸν Κίμωνος οὐδʼ ἤκουσε Περικλέους Ξάνθιππος
               δημηγοροῦντος
     <milestone n="5" unit="tlnum"/>
     οὐδʼ Ἀρίστων Πλάτωνος
               φιλοσοφοῦντος, οὐδʼ Εὐριπίδου καὶ Σοφοκλέους νίκας οἱ πατέρες ἔγνωσαν
               ψελλιζόντων καὶ συλλαβιζόντων ἠκροῶντο καὶ κώμους καὶ πότους καὶ ἔρωτας
               αὐτῶν οἷα νέοι
     <note anchored="yes" place="unspecified" resp="ed">
      <foreign lang="greek">
       οἶα νέοι
      </foreign>
      *:
      <foreign lang="greek">
       οἱ ἄνθρωποι
      </foreign>
      . cf. p. 491 f.
     </note>
     <milestone id="stephpage-497a" n="497a" unit="stephpage"/>
     πλημμελούντων ἐπεῖδον· ὥστʼ ἐπαινεῖσθαι καὶ μνημονεύεσθαι
     <milestone n="10" unit="tlnum"/>
     τοῦ Εὐήνου τοῦτο μόνον, ὧν
     <note anchored="yes" place="unspecified" resp="ed">
      <foreign lang="greek">
       ὧν
      </foreign>
      *:
      <foreign lang="greek">
       ὡς
      </foreign>
     </note>
     ἐπέγραψεν,
     <quote rend="blockquote">
      ἢ δέος ἢ
      <note anchored="yes" place="unspecified" resp="ed">
       <foreign lang="greek">
        ἢ δέος ἢ
       </foreign>
       Artemidorus 1, 6:
       <foreign lang="greek">
        ἰδε ὅση.
       </foreign>
       cf. Bergk. 2 p. 270
      </note>
      λύπη παῖς· πατρὶ πάντα χρόνον
     </quote>
     ἀλλʼ
               ὅμως οὐ παύονται παῖδας τρέφοντες μάλιστα δʼ οἱ παίδων ἥκιστα δεόμενοι.
               γελοῖον γάρ, εἴ τις οἴεται τοὺς πλουσίους θύειν καὶ χαίρειν γενομένων
     <milestone n="15" unit="tlnum"/>
     αὐτοῖς τέκνων, ὅτι τοὺς θρέψοντας ἕξουσι
               καὶ τοὺς θάψοντας· εἰ μὴ νὴ Δία κληρονόμων ἀπορίᾳ παῖδας τρέφουσιν· οὐ
               γὰρ ἔστιν εὑρεῖν οὐδʼ ἐπιτυχεῖν τοῦ τἀλλότρια βουλομένου λαμβάνειν.
     <quote rend="blockquote">
      <l>
       ψάμμος ἢ κόνις ἢ πτερὰ ποικιλοθρόων οἰωνῶν
       <note anchored="yes" place="unspecified" resp="ed">
        Bergk. 3 p. 719
       </note>
       <milestone n="20" unit="tlnum"/>
      </l>
      <l lang="it">
       sabbia o polvere o piume di vari presagi Bergk. 15:00 719
      </l>
      <l lang="en">
       sand or dust or feathers of various omens Bergk. 3 p.m. 719
      </l>
      <l>
       τόσσον οὐκ ἂν χεύαιτʼ
       <note anchored="yes" place="unspecified" resp="ed">
        <foreign lang="greek">
         ἂν χεύαιτʼ
        </foreign>
        p. 1067 e:
        <foreign lang="greek">
         ἀχλευταὶ.
        </foreign>
        cf. Praefat. p. XLVIII
       </note>
       ἀριθμόν
      </l>
      <l lang="it">
       purché non abbia importanza 
P. 1067 e: achleutaὶ. cfr. Prefat. P. Numero XLVIII
      </l>
      <l lang="en">
       as long as it doesn't matter 
p. 1067 e: achleutaὶ. cf. Praefat. p. XLVIII number
      </l>
     </quote>
     ὅσος ἐστὶν ὁ τῶν κληρονομούντων.
     <milestone id="stephpage-497b" n="497b" unit="stephpage"/>
     <quote rend="blockquote">
      Δαναὸς ὁ πεντήκοντα θυγατέρων πατήρ
      <note anchored="yes" place="unspecified" resp="ed">
       Nauck. p. 427
      </note>
     </quote>
     εἰ
     <note anchored="yes" place="unspecified" resp="ed">
      <foreign lang="greek">
       εἰ
      </foreign>
      Duebnerus:
      <foreign lang="greek">
       εἰ δὲ
      </foreign>
     </note>
     ἄτεκνος ἦν, πλείονας ἂν εἶχε κληρονομοῦντας καὶ οὐχ ὁμοίως.
     <note anchored="yes" place="unspecified" resp="ed">
      <foreign lang="greek">
       ὁμοίως
      </foreign>
      ]
      <foreign lang="greek">
       ὁμοίως ἀχαρίστους
      </foreign>
      R
     </note>
     οἱ μὲν
               γὰρ παῖδες; χάριν οὐδεμίαν
     <pb id="v.3.p.289"/>
     ἔχουσιν οὐδʼ ἕνεκα τούτου
               θεραπεύουσιν οὐδὲ τιμῶσιν, ὡς ὀφείλημα τὸν κλῆρον ἐκδεχόμενοι· τῶν δʼ
               ἀλλοτρίων περὶ τὸν ἄτεκνον φωνὰς ἀκούεις ταῖς κωμικαῖς ἐκείναις
               ὁμοίας,
     <milestone n="5" unit="tlnum"/>
     <quote rend="blockquote">
      <l>
       ὦ Δῆμε, λοῦσαι
       <note anchored="yes" place="unspecified" resp="ed">
        <foreign lang="greek">
         ὧ Δῆμε, λοῦσαι
        </foreign>
        Iunius:
        <foreign lang="greek">
         ὠδὴ μέλουσαι
        </foreign>
       </note>
       πρῶτον ἐκδικάσας μίαν,
      </l>
      <l lang="it">
       ὦ Dῆme, dimentichi 
ὧ Dῆme, leggi Iunius: ὠὴ melousai
 prima ne hai giudicato uno,
      </l>
      <l lang="en">
       ὦ Dῆme, you forget 
ὧ Dῆme, you read Iunius: ὠὴ melousai
 first you judged one,
      </l>
      <note anchored="yes" place="unspecified" resp="ed">
       Aristoph. Equ. 50
      </note>
      <l>
       ἔνθου, ῥόφησον, ἔντραγʼ , ἔχε
       <note anchored="yes" place="unspecified" resp="ed">
        <foreign lang="greek">
         ἔχε
        </foreign>
        idem:
        <foreign lang="greek">
         ἔχει
        </foreign>
       </note>
       τριώβολον.
      </l>
      <l lang="it">
       ἔθου, ῥοφησον, ἔτραγʼ, ἔhe 
ἔχε idem: ἔχε
 Triobolone.
      </l>
      <l lang="en">
       ἔθου, ῥοφησον, ἔτραγʼ , ἔhe 
ἔχε idem: ἔχε
 Triobolon.
      </l>
     </quote>
     τὸ δʼ ὑπὸ τοῦ Εὐριπίδου λεγόμενον
     <quote rend="blockquote">
      <l>
       τὰ χρήματʼ ἀνθρώποισιν εὑρίσκειν
       <note anchored="yes" place="unspecified" resp="ed">
        <foreign lang="greek">
         εὑρίσκει
        </foreign>
        R
       </note>
       φίλους
      </l>
      <l lang="it">
       i soldi fanno le persone 
trova gli amici R
      </l>
      <l lang="en">
       money makes people 
finds R friends
      </l>
      <note anchored="yes" place="unspecified" resp="ed">
       vid. Nauck. p. 149 adnot. ad hunc l. et Eur. Phoen. 439
      </note>
      <l>
       δύναμίν τε πλείστην τῶν ἐν ἀνθρώποις ἔχειν,
      </l>
      <l lang="it">
       hanno più potere degli uomini,
      </l>
      <l lang="en">
       they have more power than men,
      </l>
     </quote>
     <milestone n="10" unit="tlnum"/>
     <milestone id="stephpage-497c" n="497c" unit="stephpage"/>
     οὐχ ἁπλῶς ἀληθές,
               ἀλλʼ ἐπὶ τῶν ἀτέκνων τούτους οἱ πλούσιοι δειπνίζουσιν, οἱ ἡγεμόνες
               θεραπεύουσιν, οἱ ῥήτορες μόνοις τούτοις
     <note anchored="yes" place="unspecified" resp="ed">
      corrigenda vid. ita:
      <foreign lang="greek">
       τούτους, εἰ πλούσιοι, δειπν. οἱ ἡγεμόνες, θερ. οἱ ῥήτορες, μόνοις τούτοις
      </foreign>
      cett.
     </note>
     προῖκα συνηγοροῦσιν.
     <quote rend="blockquote">
      <l>
       ἰσχυρόν ἐστι πλούσιος ἀγνοούμενον
      </l>
      <l lang="it">
       forte è ricco e ignorante
      </l>
      <l lang="en">
       strong is rich and ignorant
      </l>
      <note anchored="yes" place="unspecified" resp="ed">
       Kock. 3 p. 484
      </note>
      <l>
       ἔχων κληρονόμον.
      </l>
      <l lang="it">
       Ho un erede.
      </l>
      <l lang="en">
       I have an heir.
      </l>
     </quote>
     <milestone n="15" unit="tlnum"/>
     πολλοὺς γοῦν πολυφίλους καὶ πολυτιμήτους
               ὄντας ἓν παιδίον γενόμενον ἀφίλους καὶ ἀδυνάτους ἐποίησεν. ὅθεν οὐδὲ
               πρὸς δύναμιν οὐδέν ἐστιν ὠφέλιμον ἀπὸ τῶν τέκνων, ἀλλὰ τῆς φύσεως τὸ
               πᾶν κράτος οὐχ ἧττον ἐν ἀνθρώποις ἢ θηρίοις.
     <milestone n="20" unit="tlnum"/>
    </p>
    <p lang="it">
     su quelli vecchi? ha riportato la parola, a coloro che hanno parlato per primi, a loro
               Succedeva a un bambino che faceva il solletico; né era legge che allevassero i figli
               mecenati né aspettativa di grazie o borse di studio “ἐπὶ 
                  giovani mutuatari" 
sui giovani mutuatari] cfr. P. 479 segg. ma mi dispiace anche se lo è
               rancori contro i bambini, grandi pericoli e dolori
               questi fatti;


 as dʼ quando omdinusan ὥ᾽ velos ώὺ donna Hom. L269


 drimy, a te proieissi mogostokoi Eleithyiai, 
O figlie di Dio, avete un'amara maledizione. 
 Le donne non sono Omero? Ma Omiris è scritta e detta
               scorrevano o solleticavano e la miscela 
mix] nygma R tis algedonos omo pikron e
               γινόμενον ἐν
 allo stomaco che avevano.
               ma la natura amorevole si piegò e se ne andò; 
era] era anno di calore e separazione e
               scossa dai dolori, non riuscì a vincere il bambino
 Non è andato via, ma torna anche tu
               premeditato, imperdonabile e ininterrotto, niente qui non ha raccolto nulla
 utile ma faticosamente e dolorosamente 
faticosamente e sofferentemente] anno di dolori e sofferenze Doehnerus
               accettato dal nascituro 
 rovine 
 Ho allattato e raffreddato, e dolore dopo dolore 
Nauck. P. 839
 di notte ho cambiato il vino 
méthʼ Cobetus: professore
 giorno. 

 Hanno questi stipendi o debiti? Altrimenti
               non a quelli di adesso, perché le speranze sono vaghe e lontane. ampelon isemerias
               raccolse lo scavo primaverile dell'inverno, seminò il fuoco delle due Pleiadi
               quando l'alba miete, i buoi, i cavalli e le galline sono pronti a chiocciare

 sul debito
               di un uomo, l'educazione di un uomo è dolorosa, la crescita della virtù è lunga
                   molto prima che la maggior parte dei padri morisse.
               Non ha impedito Salamina, Neocle, Temistocle o lui
               Eurimedonte Milziade non ascoltò Cimone Pericle Santippo presiedere
 Non Ariston Platone
               filosofo, né Euripide né Sofocle, i padri lo sapevano
               di cantori e spellatori che udivano e ballavano e bevevano e amavano
               alcuni di loro giovani 
Oia giovani*: la gente. cfr. P. 491 segg.

               contaminazioni; per essere lodato e ricordato
 di Eueninos solo questo, ec 
mentre
 ha scritto, o soggezione o 
Oppure stupore o Artemidoro 1, 6: vedi cosa. cfr. Bergk. 2 pag. 270 il dolore se n'è andato; il padre è sempre un'altra volta
               tuttavia non smettono di nutrire i bambini, anzi i bambini sono molto affezionati a loro.
               divertente perché vede le persone ricche e felici
 a questi figli, perché hanno autorità su coloro che li nutrono
               e quelli che seppelliscono; se Zeus non nutre gli eredi su richiesta di un figlio no;
               poiché non c'è successo nel tallotria bulumenos che ricevono.
                  
 sabbia o polvere o piume di vari presagi Bergk. 15:00 719


 purché non abbia importanza P. 1067 e: achleutaὶ. cfr. Prefat. P. Numero XLVIII 
 chiunque sia uno degli eredi.

Danae, il padre di cinquanta figlie di Nauck. P. 427
 eh 
εἰ Duebnerus: εἰ δὲ

               Non aveva figli, la maggioranza se aveva un erede e non allo stesso modo. 
allo stesso modo] altrettanto ingrato R οἱ ὅν
               bambini? perché nessuno è da biasimare per questo
               guariscono non onorano, accettando la sorte come dovuta;
               senti i comici parlare della voce senza figli
               Piace,


 ὦ Dῆme, dimentichi 
ὧ Dῆme, leggi Iunius: ὠὴ melousai
 prima ne hai giudicato uno, 
Aristof. Eq. 50
 ἔθου, ῥοφησον, ἔτραγʼ, ἔhe 
ἔχε idem: ἔχε
 Triobolone. 
 il secondo nominato da Euripide 
 i soldi fanno le persone 
trova gli amici R 
video. Nauck. P. 149 adnot. ad hunc l. e EUR. Phoen. 439
hanno più potere degli uomini, 


 non solo vero
               ma i ricchi mangiano questi senza figli, i governanti guarire, gli stessi oratori corrigenda vid. ita: questi, se sono ricchi, cena. i governanti, lì. gli oratori, soli cett. sostenitore delle doti. 
 forte è ricco e ignorante 
Kock. 15:00 484
 Ho un erede. 

 molti sono amichevoli e preziosi
               essendo un bambino nato senza amici e debole, scrisse. da nessuna parte
               al potere nulla giova ai bambini, ma alla natura
               ogni stato, né uomo né bestia.
    </p>
    <p lang="en">
     on the old ones? he brought back the word, to those who spoke first, to them
               It happened to a tickling infant; nor was it a law for those to raise children
               patrons nor expectation of grace or scholarships "ἐπὶ 
                  young borrowers" 
on young borrowers] cf. p. 479 f. but I'm sorry if it is too
               grudges against infants, great dangers and pains
               these facts;


 as dʼ when omdinusan ὥ᾽ velos ώὺ woman Hom. L 269


 drimy, to te proieissi mogostokoi Eleithyiai, 
O daughters of God, you have a bitter curse. 
 Are the women not Homer? But Omiris is written and said
               they flowed or tickled, and the mixture 
mix] nygma R tis algedonos omo pikron and
               ώὺ γινόμενον ἐν
 to the stomachs they had.
               but the loving nature bent and went; 
he was] he was year of heat and separation and
               shaken by the pains, she did not overcome the child
 He didn't go away, but come back too
               premeditated and unforgiven and unbroken, nothing here reaped nothing
 useful but laboriously and painfully 
painstakingly and sufferingly] year of pains and suffering Doehnerus
               accepted by the unborn 
 ruins 
 I nursed and cooled, and pain after pain 
Nauck. p. 839
 at night I changed the wine 
méthʼ Cobetus: professor
 day. 

 Do they have these wages or debts? otherwise
               not to those now, because the hopes are vague and distant. ampelon isemerias
               he reaped the spring digging of the winter, he sowed the fire of the two Pleiades
               when the dawn is reaping, oxen and horses and chickens are ready to cluck

 on debt
               of a man, the education of a man is painful, the growth of virtue is long
                   long before most fathers have passed away.
               He did not prevent Salamis, Neocles, Themistocles or him
               Eurymedon Miltiades did not listen to Cimon Pericles Xanthippus presiding
 Not Ariston Plato
               philosopher, neither Euripides nor Sophocles, the fathers knew
               of chanters and spellers they heard and dances and drinks and love
               some of them young 
Oia young people *: the people. cf. p. 491 f.

               defilements; so as to be praised and remembered
 of Eueninos this only, ec 
where *: as
 wrote, or awe or 
Or awe or Artemidorus 1, 6: see what. cf. Bergk. 2 p. 270 sorrow is gone; father always is another time
               however, they do not stop feeding children, in fact, children are very attached to them.
               funny because he sees the rich and happy people
 to these children, because they have authority over those who nourish them
               and the burying ones; if Zeus does not feed the heirs at the request of a child; no
               for there is no success of the tallotria bulumenos they receive.
                  
 sand or dust or feathers of various omens Bergk. 3 p.m. 719


 as long as it doesn't matter p. 1067 e: achleutaὶ. cf. Praefat. p. XLVIII number 
 whoever is the one of the inheritors.

Danae the fifty daughter father of Nauck. p. 427
 eh 
εἰ Duebnerus: εἰ δὲ

               He was childless, a majority if he had an heir and not similarly. 
likewise] likewise ungrateful R οἱ ὅν
               children? for no one is to blame for this
               they heal not they honor, accepting the lot as due; of the
               you hear the comedians talking about the childless voice
               like,


 ὦ Dῆme, you forget 
ὧ Dῆme, you read Iunius: ὠὴ melousai
 first you judged one, 
Aristoph. Eq. 50
 ἔθου, ῥοφησον, ἔτραγʼ , ἔhe 
ἔχε idem: ἔχε
 Triobolon. 
 the second named by Euripides 
 money makes people 
finds R friends 
vid. Nauck. p. 149 adnot. ad hunc l. et Eur. Phoen. 439
they have more power than men, 


 not just true
               but the rich dine on these childless ones, the rulers heal, the orators themselves corrigenda vid. ita: these, if they are rich, dinner. the rulers, ther. the orators, alone cett. dowries advocate. 
 strong is rich and ignorant 
Kock. 3 p.m. 484
 I have an heir. 

 many are friendly and precious
               being a child born friendless and weak, he wrote. from nowhere
               to power nothing is beneficial from children, but to nature
               every state, neither man nor beast.
    </p>
   </div1>
   <div1 n="5" type="section">
    <p>
     ἐξαμαυροῦται γὰρ
     <note anchored="yes" place="unspecified" resp="ed">
      <foreign lang="greek">
       γὰρ
      </foreign>
      ]
      <foreign lang="greek">
       δὲ
      </foreign>
      Amyotus
     </note>
     καὶ ταῦτα καὶ πολλὰ τῶν ἄλλων ὑπὸ τῆς κακίας, ὥσπερ
               λόχμης ἡμέροις σπέρμασι παραβλαστανούσης. ἢ μηδʼ ἑαυτὸν φύσει
     <pb id="v.3.p.290"/>
     στέργειν
     <milestone id="stephpage-497d" n="497d" unit="stephpage"/>
     τὸν ἄνθρωπον λέγωμεν,
     <note anchored="yes" place="unspecified" resp="ed">
      <foreign lang="greek">
       λέγωμεν
      </foreign>
      M:
      <foreign lang="greek">
       λέγομεν
      </foreign>
     </note>
     ὅτι πολλοὶ σφάττουσιν ἑαυτοὺς καὶ
               κατακρημνίζουσιν; ὁ δʼ Οἰδίπους
     <quote rend="blockquote">
      <l>
       ἤρασσʼ βλέφαρα · φοίνιαι δʼ ὁμοῦ
      </l>
      <l lang="it">
       Amavo le mie palpebre;
      </l>
      <l lang="en">
       I loved my eyelids; my palms
      </l>
      <note anchored="yes" place="unspecified" resp="ed">
       Soph. OR 1275
      </note>
      <l>
       γλῆναι γένειʼ ἔτεγγον.
       <note anchored="yes" place="unspecified" resp="ed">
        <foreign lang="greek">
         φοίνιαι - ἔτεγγον
        </foreign>
        Sophocles:
        <foreign lang="greek">
         φοίναι δόμου
        </foreign>
        cum lacuna 18 litt. Urbinas
       </note>
      </l>
      <l lang="it">
       glinai geneiʼ ἔteggon. 
phoinai - ἔteggon Sofocle: phoinai domo cum lacuna 18 litt. Urbina
      </l>
      <l lang="en">
       glinai geneiʼ ἔteggon. 
phoinai - ἔteggon Sophocles: phoinai domo cum lacuna 18 litt. Urbinas
      </l>
     </quote>
     <milestone n="5" unit="tlnum"/>
     Ἡγησίας δὲ
     <note anchored="yes" place="unspecified" resp="ed">
      <foreign lang="greek">
       δὲ
      </foreign>
      Duebnerus
     </note>
     διαλεγόμενος πολλοὺς ἔπεισεν
               ἀποκαρτερῆσαι τῶν ἀκροωμένων
     <quote rend="blockquote">
      πολλαὶ μορφαὶ τῶν
                  δαιμονίων.
     </quote>
     <note anchored="yes" place="unspecified" resp="ed">
      Eur. Alc. 1159. passim
     </note>
     ταῦτα δʼ ἐστὶν ὥσπερ ἐκεῖνα νοσήματα καὶ πάθη ψυχῆς
               τοῦ κατὰ φύσιν ἐξιστάντα τὸν ἄνθρωπον, ὡς
     <milestone n="10" unit="tlnum"/>
     αὐτοὶ καταμαρτυροῦσιν ἑαυτῶν· ἂν γὰρ ὗς τεκοῦσα δελφάκιον ἢ κύων
               διασπαράξῃ σκυλάκιον, ἀθυμοῦσι καὶ ταράττονται, καὶ θεοῖς ἀποτρόπαια
               θύουσι καὶ τέρας νομίζουσιν , ὡς πᾶσι κατὰ φύσιν
     <note anchored="yes" place="unspecified" resp="ed">
      <foreign lang="greek">
       κατὰ φύσιν
      </foreign>
      R:
      <foreign lang="greek">
       καὶ κατὰ φύσιν
      </foreign>
     </note>
     στέργειν τὰ
     <milestone id="stephpage-497e" n="497e" unit="stephpage"/>
     τικτόμενα καὶ τρέφειν οὐκ
               ἀναιρεῖν προσῆκον.
     <milestone n="15" unit="tlnum"/>
     μὴν ἀλλʼ ὥσπερ ἐν τοῖς
               μετάλλοις πολλῇ συμπεφυρμένον γῇ καὶ κατακεχωσμένον ὅμως διαστίλβει τὸ
               χρυσίον, οὕτως ἡ φύσις ἐν αὐτοῖς τοῖς ἡμαρτημένοις ἤθεσι καὶ πάθεσιν
               ἐκφαίνει τὸ πρὸς τὰ ἔκγονα φιλόστοργον. οἱ μὲν γὰρ πένητες οὐ τρέφουσι
               τέκνα,
     <milestone n="20" unit="tlnum"/>
     φοβούμενοι μὴ χεῖρον ἢ προσήκει
               τραφέντα δουλοπρεπῆ καὶ ἀπαίδευτα καὶ τῶν καλῶν πάντων ἐνδεᾶ γένηται·
               τὴν γὰρ πενίαν ἔσχατον ἡγούμενοι κακὸν οὐχ ὑπομένουσι μεταδοῦναι τέκνοις
               ὥσπερ τινὸς χαλεποῦ καὶ μεγάλου νοσήματος.
     <note anchored="yes" place="unspecified" resp="ed">
      lacunam post
      <foreign lang="greek">
       νοσήματος
      </foreign>
      add. X
     </note>
    </p>
    <p lang="it">
     perché si sta facendo buio 
perché] ma Amioto e questi e molti altri sotto malizia, come
               lochmi hmerois spermasi parablastanousis. Oppure non seccarti
 chiamiamo uomo 
diciamo M: diciamo
 perché anche molte persone si fanno del male
               precipitano? il secondo Edipo 
 Amavo le mie palpebre; 
Sof. O 1275
 glinai geneiʼ ἔteggon. 
phoinai - ἔteggon Sofocle: phoinai domo cum lacuna 18 litt. Urbina


Egisia, però 
Ma Duebnerus, essendo stato scelto, convinse molti
               apokarteris di coloro che se ne sentono molte forme
                  demoni.
Euro. Alc. 1159. passim queste non sono come quelle malattie e passioni dell'anima
               che per natura esisteva l'uomo, come

               testimoniano contro se stessi;
               disperdete i cani, sono irrequieti e agitati, e gli dei sono abominevoli
               Pensano di essere malvagi e mostri, come tutti gli altri per natura 
per natura R: e per natura
 Rimuovi il
 tic tac oma e nutriti bene
               annullare l'appuntamento.
 ma non come nelle parole
               di molti metalli il terreno è pieno e occupato, ma il
               oro, quindi la natura in questi peccatori è nata e ha sofferto
               sembra che le azioni siano amorevoli. perché chi ha fame non dà da mangiare
               bambini,
 temendo di non farcela
               nutrito servile e ignorante e di tutte le cose buone nasce;
               perché chi patisce l'ultimo dolore, non sopporta il male, lo trasmette ai figli
               come una specie di lebbra e una grande malattia. lacunam post malattia add. X
    </p>
    <p lang="en">
     because it is getting dark 
because] but Amyotus and these and many others under malice, as
               lochmi hmerois spermasi parablastanousis. Or don't blow yourself dry
 we call man 
we say M: we say
 because many people hurt themselves too
               do they precipitate? the second Oedipus 
 I loved my eyelids; my palms 
Soph. OR 1275
 glinai geneiʼ ἔteggon. 
phoinai - ἔteggon Sophocles: phoinai domo cum lacuna 18 litt. Urbinas


Hegisias, though 
But Duebnerus, being chosen, convinced many
               apokarteris of those who are heard many forms of them
                  demons.
Eur. Alc. 1159. passim these are not like those diseases and passions of the soul
               that by nature existed man, as

               they testify against themselves;
               scatter the dogs, they are restless and agitated, and the gods are abominable
               They think they are evil and a monster, like everyone else by nature 
by nature R: and by nature
 remove the
 tick oma and feed ok
               cancel the appointment.
 but not as in the words
               with many metals the ground is filled and occupied, but the
               gold, so the nature in these sinners was born and suffered
               it appears that the actions are loving. for those who are hungry do not feed
               children,
 fearing that he would not be able to do it
               fed servile and uneducated and of all good things is born;
               because those who suffer the last pain, do not endure evil, they pass it on to their children
               like a kind of leprosy and a great disease. lacunam post disease add. X
    </p>
   </div1>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI.2>
