<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     De respiratione
    </title>
    <author>
     Aristotle
    </author>
    <editor>
     Immanuel Bekker
    </editor>
    <funder>
     Andrew W. Mellon Foundation
    </funder>
    <respStmt>
     <resp>
      Published original versions of the electronic texts
     </resp>
     <orgName ref="http://www.graeco-arabic-studies.org/">
      A Digital Corpus for Graeco-Arabic
						Studies, funded by the Andrew W. Mellon Foundation
     </orgName>
     <persName>
      Mark Schiefsky, Harvard University
     </persName>
     <persName>
      Gregory R. Crane, Universität Leipzig
     </persName>
     <persName>
      Uwe Vagelpohl, University of Warwick
     </persName>
    </respStmt>
    <respStmt>
     <resp>
      Keyboarding
     </resp>
     <orgName xml:id="DDD">
      Digital Divide Data
     </orgName>
    </respStmt>
    <respStmt>
     <resp>
      Editor-in-Chief, Perseus Digital Library
     </resp>
     <persName>
      Gregory R. Crane
     </persName>
    </respStmt>
    <respStmt>
     <resp>
      Project Manager (University of Leipzig), 2016 - present
     </resp>
     <persName>
      Matt Munson
     </persName>
    </respStmt>
    <respStmt>
     <resp>
      Project Assistant (University of Leipzig), 2015 - present
     </resp>
     <persName>
      Annette Geßner
     </persName>
    </respStmt>
    <respStmt>
     <resp>
      Lead Developer (University of Leipzig)
     </resp>
     <persName>
      Thibault Clérice
     </persName>
    </respStmt>
    <respStmt>
     <resp>
      Technical Advisor
     </resp>
     <persName>
      Bruce Robertson
     </persName>
    </respStmt>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <authority>
     A Digital Corpus for Graeco-Arabic Studies, funded by the Andrew W. Mellon
					Foundation
    </authority>
    <publisher>
     University of Leipzig
    </publisher>
    <pubPlace>
     Germany
    </pubPlace>
    <idno type="filename">
     tlg0086.tlg037.1st1K-grc1.xml
    </idno>
    <availability>
     <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">
      Available under a
						Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 International License
     </licence>
    </availability>
    <date>
     2016
    </date>
   </publicationStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <biblStruct>
     <monogr>
      <title>
       Aristotelis Opera
      </title>
      <author>
       Aristotle
      </author>
      <editor>
       Immanuel Bekker
      </editor>
      <imprint>
       <publisher>
        Oxford University Press
       </publisher>
       <pubPlace>
        Oxford
       </pubPlace>
       <biblScope unit="vol">
        3
       </biblScope>
       <biblScope from="329" to="354" unit="pp">
        329-354
       </biblScope>
       <date>
        1837
       </date>
      </imprint>
     </monogr>
     <ref target="https://catalog.hathitrust.org/Record/001222547">
      HathiTrust
     </ref>
    </biblStruct>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <p>
    The following text is encoded in accordance with EpiDoc standards and with the CTS/CITE
				Architecture.
   </p>
   <p lang="it">
    Il testo seguente è codificato secondo gli standard EpiDoc e CTS/CITE
				Architettura.
   </p>
   <p lang="en">
    The following text is encoded in accordance with EpiDoc standards and with the CTS/CITE
				Architecture.
   </p>
   <refsDecl n="CTS">
    <cRefPattern matchPattern="(.+)" n="chapter" replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div/tei:div[@n='$1'])"/>
   </refsDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <langUsage>
    <language ident="greek">
     Greek
    </language>
   </langUsage>
  </profileDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <body>
   <div n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg037.1st1K-grc1" type="edition" xml:lang="grc">
    <pb n="329"/>
    <div n="1" subtype="chapter" type="textpart">
     <head>
      ΠΕΡΙ ΑΝΑΠΝΟΗΣ.
     </head>
     <p>
      Περὶ γὰρ ἀναπνοῆς ὀλίγοι μέν τινες τῶν πρότερον
      <lb/>
      φυσικῶν εἰρήκασιν· τίνος μέντοι
						χάριν ὑπάρχει τοῖς ζῴοις,
      <lb/>
      οἱ μὲν οὐδὲν ἀπεφήναντο, οἱ δὲ εἰρήκασι μέν, οὐ καλῶς δ’
      <lb/>
      εἰρήκασιν ἀλλ’ ἀπειροτέρως τῶν συμβαινόντων. Ἔτι δὲ
      <lb/>
      πάντα τὰ ζῷά φασιν
						ἀναπνεῖν· τοῦτο δ’ οὐκ ἔστιν ἀληθές.
      <lb/>
      Ὥστ’ ἀναγκαῖον περὶ τούτων πρῶτον ἐπελθεῖν,
						ὅπως μὴ
      <lb/>
      δοκῶμεν ἀπόντων κενὴν κατηγορεῖν. Ὅτι μὲν οὖν ὅσα
      <lb/>
      πλεύμονα ἔχει τῶν
						ζῴων, ἀναπνεῖ πάντα, φανερόν. Ἀλλὰ
      <lb/>
      καὶ τούτων αὐτῶν ὅσα μὲν ἄναιμον ἔχει τὸν
						πλεύμονα καὶ
      <lb/>
      σομφόν, ἧττον δέονται τῆς ἀναπνοῆς· διὸ πολὺν χρόνον ἐν
      <lb/>
      τοῖς
						ὕδασι δύνανται διαμένειν παρὰ τὴν τοῦ σώματος
      <lb/>
      ἰσχύν. Τὸν δὲ πλεύμονα σομφὸν ἔχει
						πάντα τὰ ᾠοτοκοῦντα,
      <lb/>
      οἷον τὸ τῶν βατράχων γένος. Ἔτι δὲ αἱ ἑμύδες τε
      <lb/>
      καὶ
						χελῶναι πολὺν χρόνον μένουσιν ἐν τοῖς ὑγροῖς· ὁ γὰρ
      <lb/>
      πλεύμων ὀλίγην ἔχει θερμότητα·
						ὀλίγαιμον γὰρ ἔχουσιν
      <lb/>
      αὐτόν· ἐμφυσώμενος οὖν αὐτὸς τῇ κινήσει καταψύχει καὶ
      <pb n="330"/>
      ποιεῖ διαμένειν πολὺν χρόνον. Ἐὰν μέντοι βιάζηταί τις
      <lb/>
      λίαν κατέχων
						πολὺν χρόνον, ἀποπνίγονται πάντα· οὐδὲν
      <lb/>
      γὰρ τῶν τοιούτων δέχεται τὸ ὕδωρ ὥσπερ οἱ
						ἰχθῦς. Τὰ
      <lb/>
      δ’ ἔναιμον ἔχοντα τὸν πλεύμονα πάντα μᾶλλον δεῖται τῆς
      <lb/>
      ἀναπνοῆς διὰ
						τὸ πλῆθος τῆς θερμότητος· τῶν δ’ ἄλλων ὅσα
      <lb/>
      μὴ ἔχει πλεύμονα, οὐδὲν ἀναπνεῖ.
     </p>
     <p lang="it">
      Perché sulla respirazione, pochi ex fisici litigavano;
						poiché c'è grazia tra i viventi, quelli che non hanno parlato contro di me, ma quelli che hanno litigato con me, non l'hanno fatto
						irikesin, ma infinitamente di più, degli avvenimenti. Che tutti gli animali mangiano
						respirare; questo non è vero. Se è necessario che questi arrivino prima,
						in modo da non cercare di lanciare accuse vuote. Perché non importa quanti polmoni abbia
						vivere, respirare sempre, manifestarsi. Ma anche di questi, purché abbia un'anima
						polmoni e polmoni, sono legati alla respirazione da molto tempo nel
						quindi possono restare nonostante la forza del corpo. Ma ha un palato molle
						tutti i ᾠotokounta, un genere di rane. E le cozze?
						le tartarughe stanno molto tempo nell'acqua, perché la tartaruga marina ha poco calore;
						Infatti ne hanno ben poco: quando viene soffiato, si congela mentre si muove, e lì rimane a lungo. Se gli uomini cercano i tanti proprietari
						molto tempo n, soffocano sempre; perché nessuno di questi riceve l'acqua come il
						pescare. I polmoni che hanno polmoni sono sempre piuttosto visti attraverso la respirazione
						la moltitudine del calore; degli altri, tutto ciò che non ha polmoni, non respira.
     </p>
     <p lang="en">
      Because about breathing, few mints of the former physicists quarreled; whose mints
						for there is grace among the living, those who did not speak against me, but those who quarreled with me, did not
						irikesin, but infinitely more, of the happenings. That all animals eat
						breathe; this is not true. If it is necessary for these to arrive first,
						so that we do not try to make empty accusations. Because no matter how many lungs he has
						living, always breathing, manifest. But even of these, as long as he has a soul
						lungs and lungs, they are tied to breathing; for a long time in the
						thus they can stay despite the strength of the body. But he has a soft palate
						all the ᾠotokounta, a genus of frogs. What about the mussels?
						turtles stay a long time in the water, because the sea turtle has little heat;
						For they have but little of it: when it is blown, it freezes on the move, and where it stays for a long time. If men are looking for the many owners
						a lot of time n, they always suffocate; for none of these receive the water as the
						fish. The lungs having lungs are always rather seen of respiration through
						the multitude of heat; of the others, whatever has no lungs, does not breathe.
     </p>
    </div>
    <div n="2" subtype="chapter" type="textpart">
     <p>
      Δημόκριτος μὲν οὖν ὁ Ἀβδηρίτης καί τινες ἄλλοι τῶν
      <lb/>
      περὶ ἀναπνοῆς εἰρηκότων οὐδὲν
						περὶ τῶν ἄλλων διωρίκασι
      <lb/>
      ζῴων, ἐοίκασι μέντοι λέγειν ὡς πάντων ἀναπνεόντων·
						Ἀναξαγόρας
      <lb/>
      δὲ καὶ Διογένης, πάντα φάσκοντες ἀναπνεῖν, περὶ
      <lb/>
      τῶν ἰχθύων καὶ τῶν
						ὀστρείων λέγουσι τίνα τρόπον ἀναπνέουσιν.
      <lb/>
      Καί φησιν Ἀναξαγόρας μέν, ὅταν ἀφῶσι τὸ
						ὕδωρ
      <lb/>
      διὰ τῶν βραγχίων, τὸν ἐν τῷ στόματι γινόμενον ἀέρα ἕλκοντας
      <lb/>
      ἀναπνεῖν τοὺς
						ἰχθῦς· οὐ γὰρ εἶναι κενὸν οὐδέν·
      <lb/>
      Διογένης δ’ ὅταν ἀφῶσι τὸ ὕδωρ διὰ τῶν βραγχίων,
						ἐκ τοῦ
      <lb/>
      περὶ τὸ στόμα περιεστῶτος ὕδατος ἕλκειν τῷ κενῷ τῷ ἐν
      <lb/>
      τῷ στόματι τὸν
						ἀέρα, ὡς ἐνόντος ἐν τῷ ὕδατι ἀέρος. Ταῦτα
      <lb/>
      δ’ ἐστὶν ἀδύνατα. Πρῶτον μὲν γὰρ τὸ ἥμισυ
						τοῦ πράγματος
      <lb/>
      ἀφαιροῦσι, διὰ τὸ τὸ κοινὸν ἐπὶ θατέρου λέγεσθαι μόνον.
      <lb/>
      Ἀναπνοὴ
						γὰρ καλεῖται, ταύτης δὲ τὸ μὲν ἐκπνοή
      <lb/>
      ἐστι τὸ δ’ εἰσπνοή· περὶ ἧς οὐθὲν λέγουσι,
						τίνα τρόπον
      <lb/>
      ἐκπνέουσι τὰ τοιαῦτα τῶν ζῴων. Οὐδ’ ἐνδέχεται αὐτοῖς
      <lb/>
      εἰπεῖν· ὅταν
						γὰρ ἀναπνεύσωσι, ταύτῃ ᾗ ἀνέπνευσαν πάλιν
      <lb/>
      δεῖ ἐκπνεῖν, καὶ τοῦτο ποιεῖν ἀεὶ
						παραλλάξ, ὥστε συμβαίνει
      <lb/>
      ἅμα δέχεσθαι τὸ ὕδωρ κατὰ τὸ στόμα καὶ ἐκπνεῖν.
      <pb n="331"/>
      Ἀνάγκη δ’ ἀπαντῶντα ἐμποδίζειν θάτερον θατέρῳ. Εἶτα
      <lb/>
      ὅταν ἀφῶσι τὸ ὕδωρ,
						τότε ἐκπνέουσι κατὰ τὸ στόμα ἢ
      <lb/>
      κατὰ τὰ βράγχια, ὥστε συμβαίνει ἅμα ἐκπνεῖν καὶ
						ἀναπνεῖν·
      <lb/>
      τότε γάρ φασιν αὐτὸ ἀναπνεῖν. Ἄμα δ’ ἀναπνεῖν καὶ
      <lb/>
      ἐκπνεῖν ἀδύνατον.
						Ὤστ’ εἰ ἀνάγκη τὰ ἀναπνέοντα ἐκπνεῖν
      <lb/>
      καὶ εἰσπνεῖν, ἐκπνεῖν δὲ μὴ ἐνδέχεται μηδὲν
						αὐτῶν, φανερὸν
      <lb/>
      ὡς οὐδ’ ἀναπνεῖ αὐτῶν οὐδέν.
     </p>
     <p lang="it">
      Democrito, quindi, l'Abderita e il resto delle suffragette riguardo al respiro, niente
						delle altre vite diorikasi, ἔικασι mentis dicono che sono tutte cose che respirano;
						E Anassagora e Diogene, sempre impegnati a respirare, riguardo ai pesci e al
						Dicono che respirano nel modo in cui respirano. E lasciami essere Anassagora, quando lo lascerò andare
						l'acqua attraverso le branchie, l'aria prodotta nella bocca li spinge a respirare
						pesce; poiché non c'è nulla di vuoto;
						dalla presenza di acqua attorno alla bocca allo spazio vuoto nella bocca
						aria, come nell'aria acqua. Questi non sono impossibili. Prima di tutto, senza metà
						della cosa tolta, per il comune sul padre solo sei detto. Respirazione
						poiché si chiama, e questa espirazione è la quarta inspirazione di cui non dicono;
						come espirano le cose dei viventi? Non gli è permesso di dire loro quando;
						poiché hanno inspirato, ciò che hanno inspirato di nuovo lo vedono espirare, e Chi è questo?
						Parallasse, come accade se prendi l'acqua in bocca ed espiri.  Necessità d' risposta per ostacolare il vero al vero. Ha detto quando ha rilasciato l'acqua,
						poi espirano attraverso la bocca o attraverso le branchie, come avviene anche loro
						respirare; poi lasciarli respirare. Se inspirano ed espirano, è impossibile.
						Se necessario, le cose che respirano espirano e inspirano, ma non possono espirare
						di loro, apparentemente come se nessuno di loro respirasse.
     </p>
     <p lang="en">
      Democritus, then, the Abderite and the rest of the suffragettes about breathing, nothing
						about the other diorikasi lives, ἔικασι mentis say that they are all breathing things;
						And Anaxagoras and Diogenes, always busy breathing, about the fishes and the
						They say that they breathe the way they breathe. And let me be Anaxagoras, when I let it go
						water through the gills, the air produced in the mouth pulling them to breathe
						fish; for there is nothing empty; Diogenes iv.
						from the presence of water around the mouth to the gap in the mouth
						air, as in water air. These are not impossible. First of all, without half
						of the thing removed, for the common on the father only you are said. Breathing
						for it is called, and this one exhalation is the fourth inhalation; of which they do not say,
						how do the things of the living breathe out. He is not allowed to tell them; when
						for they breathed in, that which they breathed in again see they breathe out, and Who is this?
						Parallax, as it happens if you take the water in your mouth and exhale.  Necessity d' answer to hinder the true to the true. He said when he released the water,
						then they exhale through the mouth or through the gills, as happens if they also
						breathe; then let them breathe. If they breathe in and out, it's impossible.
						If necessary, breathing things exhale and inhale, but they cannot breathe out
						of them, apparently as if none of them breathes.
     </p>
    </div>
    <div n="3" subtype="chapter" type="textpart">
     <p>
      Ἔτι δὲ τὸ φάναι τὸν ἀέρα ἕλκειν ἐκ τοῦ στόματος ἢ
      <lb/>
      ἐκ τοῦ ὕδατος διὰ τοῦ στόματος
						ἀδύνατον· οὐ γὰρ ἔχουσιν
      <lb/>
      ἀρτηρίαν διὰ τὸ πλεύμονα μὴ ἔχειν, ἀλλ’ εὐθὺς ἡ κοιλία
      <lb/>
      πρὸς τῷ στόματί ἐστιν, ὥστ’ ἀναγκαῖον τῇ κοιλίᾳ ἕλκειν.
      <lb/>
      Τοῦτο δὲ κἂν τἆλλα
						ἐποίει ζῷα· νῦν δὲ οὐ ποιοῦσιν. Κἂν
      <lb/>
      ἐκεῖνα δ’ ἔξω τοῦ ὑγροῦ ὄντα ἐπιδήλως ἂν αὐτὸ
						ἐποίει· φαίνεται
      <lb/>
      δ’ οὐ ποιοῦντ’ αὐτό. Ἔτι πάντων τῶν ἀναπνεόντων
      <lb/>
      καὶ ἑλκόντων
						τὸ πνεῦμα ὁρῶμεν γινομένην κίνησίν τινα
      <lb/>
      τοῦ μορίου τοῦ ἕλκοντος, ἐπὶ δὲ τῶν ἰχθύων
						οὐ συμβαῖνον·
      <lb/>
      οὐδὲν γὰρ φαίνονται κινοῦντες τῶν περὶ τὴν κοιλίαν, ἀλλ’ ἢ
      <lb/>
      τὰ
						βράγχια μόνον, καὶ ἐν τῷ ὑγρῷ καὶ εἰς τὸ ξηρὸν ἐκπεσόντες,
      <lb/>
      ὅταν σπαίρωσιν. Ἔτι ὅταν
						ἀποθνήσκῃ πνιγόμενα
      <lb/>
      ἐν τοῖς ὑγροῖς πάντα τὰ ἀναπνέοντα, γίνονται πομφόλυγες
      <lb/>
      τοῦ πνεύματος ἐξιόντος βιαίως, οἷον ἐάν τις βιάζηται χελώνας
      <lb/>
      ἢ βατράχους ἤ τι
						ἄλλο τῶν τοιούτων γενῶν· ἐπὶ δὲ τῶν
      <lb/>
      ἰχθύων οὐ συμβαίνει πειρωμένοις πάντα τρόπον,
						ὡς οὐκ ἐχόντων
      <lb/>
      πνεῦμα θύραθεν οὐθέν. Ὄν τε τρόπον λέγουσι γίνεσθαι
      <lb/>
      τὴν
						ἀναπνοὴν αὐτοῖς, ἐνδέχεται καὶ τοῖς ἀνθρώποις οὖσιν
      <lb/>
      ἐν τῷ ὑγρῷ συμβαίνειν· εἰ γὰρ
						καὶ οἱ ἰχθύες ἕλκουσιν
      <lb/>
      ἐκ τοῦ πέριξ ὕδατος τῷ στόματι, διὰ τί τοῦτο οὐκ ἂν
      <pb n="332"/>
      ποιοῖμεν καὶ οἱ ἄνθρωποι καὶ τἆλλα ζῷα; Καὶ τὸν ἐκ τοῦ
      <lb/>
      στόματος δ’ ἂν
						ἕλκοιμεν ὁμοίως τοῖς ἰχθύσιν. Ὤστ’ εἴπερ
      <lb/>
      κἀκεῖνα ἦν δυνατά, καὶ ταῦτ’ ἂν ἦν· ἐπεὶ
						δ’ οὐκ ἔστι, δῆλον
      <lb/>
      ὡς οὐδ’ ἐπ’ ἐκείνων ἐστίν. Πρὸς δὲ τούτοις διὰ τίν’ αἰτίαν
      <lb/>
      ἐν τῷ ἀέρι ἀποθνήσκουσι καὶ φαίνονται ἀσπαρίζοντα ὥσπερ
      <lb/>
      τὰ πνιγόμενα, εἴπερ
						ἀναπνέουσιν; Οὐ γὰρ δὴ τροφῆς γε
      <lb/>
      ἐνδείᾳ τοῦτο πάσχουσιν. Ἢν γὰρ λέγει Διογένης
						αἰτίαν,
      <lb/>
      εὐήθης· φησὶ γὰρ ὅτι τὸν ἀέρα πολὺν ἕλκουσι λίαν ἐν τῷ
      <lb/>
      ἀέρι, ἐν δὲ τῷ
						ὕδατι μέτριον, καὶ διὰ τοῦτ’ ἀποθνήσκειν.
      <lb/>
      Καὶ γὰρ ἐπὶ τῶν πεζῶν ἔδει δυνατὸν εἶναι
						τοῦτο συμβαίνειν·
      <lb/>
      νῦν δ’ οὐδὲν τῷ σφόδρα ἀναπνεῦσαι ἀποπνίγεται πεζὸν
      <lb/>
      ζῷον.
						Ἔτι δ’ εἰ πάντα ἀναπνεῖ, δῆλον ὅτι καὶ τὰ ἔντομα
      <lb/>
      τῶν ζῴων ἀναπνεῖ· φαίνεται δ’
						αὐτῶν πολλὰ διατεμνόμενα
      <lb/>
      ζῆν, οὐ μόνον εἰς δύο μέρη ἀλλὰ καὶ εἰς πλείω, οἷον αἱ
						καλούμεναι
      <lb/>
      σκολόπενδραι· ἃ πῶς ἢ τίνι ἐνδέχεται ἀναπνεῖν;
      <lb/>
      Αἴτιον δὲ μάλιστα
						τοῦ μὴ λέγεσθαι περὶ αὐτῶν καλῶς τό
      <lb/>
      τε τῶν μορίων ἀπείρους εἶναι τῶν ἐντός, καὶ μὴ
						λαμβάνειν
      <lb/>
      ἕνεκά τινος τὴν φύσιν πάντα ποιεῖν· ζητοῦντες γὰρ τίνος
      <lb/>
      ἕνεκα ἡ
						ἀναπνοὴ τοῖς ζῴοις ὑπάρχει, καὶ ἐπὶ τῶν μορίων
      <lb/>
      τοῦτ’ ἐπισκοποῦντες, οἷον ἐπὶ
						βραγχίων καὶ πλεύμονος, εὗρον
      <lb/>
      ἂν θᾶττον τὴν αἰτίαν.
     </p>
     <p lang="it">
      Ma cosa succede se l'aria viene aspirata dalla bocca o dall'acqua attraverso la bocca?
						impossibile; poiché non hanno un'arteria che attraversa i polmoni, ma l'addome stesso
						È verso la bocca, come se fosse un'ulcera allo stomaco. Non è nemmeno così
						vivono; ma ora non lo fanno. Se quelli sono fuori dal liquido, è evidente che sia così
						sembra; non sembra. Che dire di tutto ciò che respira e tira?
						lo spirito che vediamo non è fatto per muovere la mole della peste, ma dei pesci
						non succede, perché non sembra che si muovano attorno all'addome, ma il
						solo lamelle, sia nell'umido che nell'asciutto cadente, quando seminano. Cosa quando
						tutto ciò che respira muore annegato nelle acque, si mummifica
						dello spirito che esce violentemente, chi se viene precipitato da una tartaruga o da rane o cosa
						un altro di questi generi, ma con i pesci non è sempre sperimentato in alcun modo,
						come se non ci fosse spirito dalla porta. Come si dice c iniettare il
						respirarli è possibile anche per gli esseri umani, così avviene nell'acqua;
						E i pesci fanno male a causa dell'acqua intorno alla bocca, perché non ne soffrono anche gli esseri umani e gli altri animali? E quello dalla bocca d'an
						Siamo feriti allo stesso modo dei pesci. Soprattutto era forte, e anche se lo era;
						d' οὐκ ἔστι, διλον come οὐδ' su quelli estín. Ma per quale motivo?
						nell'aria muoiono e appaiono bianchi come gli annegati,
						stanno respirando? Poiché non c'è cibo, per questo soffrono. Perché dice Diogene
						perché tu hai benedetto;
						Acqua mediocre, e per questo morì. E perché sui pedoni è forte
						ecco cosa succede; adesso se non respiri forte, soffochi a piedi.
						Poiché tutto respira, sembra che respirino anche gli insetti degli animali;
						molte di queste vite si intersecavano, non solo in due parti ma anche in s pleio, oἷon aἱ
						chiamati scolopendrai; come o cosa possono respirare? Per questo motivo
						per non dire bene che il te delle infinite molecole è delle interne, e non
						ricevono uno la cui natura è tutta chi;
						c'è respiro nei vivi, e nelle particelle del vescovo, che su
						branchie e polmoni, hanno trovato la causa.
     </p>
     <p lang="en">
      But what if the air is drawn from the mouth or from the water through the mouth
						impossible; for they have no artery through the lungs, they do not, but the abdomen itself
						It is towards the mouth, as if it were a stomach ulcer. This is not even the case
						they live; but now they do not. If those are outside of the liquid being manifestly if that
						it seems; it doesn't seem like it. What about everything that breathes and pulls
						the spirit we see is made to move the mole of the plague, but of the fish
						it does not happen, because they do not appear to be moving around the abdomen, but the
						gills only, both in the wet and in the dry falling, when they sow. What when
						everything that breathes dies drowned in the waters, they become mummified
						of the spirit coming out violently, who if rushed by a turtle or frogs or what
						another of such genera; but with fishes it is not always experienced in any way,
						as if there was no spirit from the door. How do they say c inject the
						breathing to them, it is also possible for humans, so it happens in the water; for
						And the fishes hurt from the water around the mouth, why don't humans and other animals also suffer from this? And the one from the mouth d'an
						We are wounded in the same way as fish. Above all it was strong, and even if it was;
						d' οὐκ ἔστι, διλον as οὐδ' on those estín. But for what reason?
						in the air they perish and appear as white as those drowned,
						are they breathing? Because there is no food because of this they suffer. Because it says Diogenes
						cause, thou hast blessed;
						Mediocre water, and because of this he died. And because on the pedestrians it is strong
						this is what happens; now if you don't breathe hard, you suffocate on foot.
						Because everything breathes, it seems that the insects of the animals also breathe; it seems that
						many of these intersected lives, not only in two parts but also in s pleio, oἷon aἱ
						called scolopendrai; how or what can they breathe? Because of that
						not to say about them well that the te of the infinite molecules is of the internals, and not
						they receive one whose nature all who; for asking whose one the
						there is breath in the living, and in the particles of the bishop, who on
						gills and lungs, they found the cause.
     </p>
    </div>
    <div n="4" subtype="chapter" type="textpart">
     <p>
      Δημόκριτος δ’ ὅτι μὲν ἐκ τῆς ἀναπνοῆς συμβαίνει τι τοῖς
      <lb/>
      ἀναπνέουσι λέγει, φάσκων
						κωλύειν ἐκθλίβεσθαι τὴν ψυχήν·
      <lb/>
      οὐ μέντοι ὡς τούτου γ’ ἕνεκα ποιήσασαν τοῦτο τὴν
						φύσιν
      <lb/>
      οὐθὲν εἴρηκεν· ὅλως γὰρ ὥσπερ καὶ οἱ ἄλλοι φυσικοί, καὶ
      <lb/>
      οὗτος οὐθὲν
						ἅπτεται τῆς τοιαύτης αἰτίας. Λέγει δ’ ὡς ἡ
      <lb/>
      ψυχὴ καὶ τὸ θερμὸν ταὐτὸν τὰ πρῶτα
						σχήματα τῶν σφαιροειδῶν.
      <lb/>
      συγκρινομένων οὖν αὐτῶν ὑπὸ τοῦ περιέχοντος
      <pb n="333"/>
      ἐκθλίβοντος, βοήθειαν γίνεσθαι τὴν ἀναπνοήν φησιν. Ἐν
      <lb/>
      γὰρ τῷ ἀέρι πολὺν ἀριθμὸν
						εἶναι τῶν τοιούτων ἃ καλεῖ ἐκεῖνος
      <lb/>
      νοῦν καὶ ψυχήν· ἀναπνέοντος οὖν καὶ εἰσιόντος
						τοῦ
      <lb/>
      ἀέρος συνεισιόντα ταῦτα, καὶ ἀνείργοντα τὴν θλίψιν,
      <lb/>
      κωλύειν τὴν ἐνοῦσαν ἐν
						τοῖς ζῴοις διιέναι ψυχήν. Καὶ διὰ
      <lb/>
      τοῦτο ἐν τῷ ἀναπνεῖν καὶ ἐκπνεῖν εἶναι τὸ ζῆν καὶ
						τὸ ἀποθνήσκειν·
      <lb/>
      ὅταν γὰρ κρατῇ τὸ περιέχον συνθλῖβον, καὶ μηκέτι
      <lb/>
      θύραθεν
						εἰσιὸν δύνηται ἀνείργειν, μὴ δυναμένου
      <lb/>
      ἀναπνεῖν, τότε συμβαίνειν τὸν θάνατον τοῖς
						ζῴοις· εἶναι
      <lb/>
      γὰρ τὸν θάνατον τὴν τῶν τοιούτων σχημάτων ἐκ τοῦ σώματος
      <lb/>
      ἔξοδον
						ἐκ τῆς τοῦ περιέχοντος ἐκθλίψεως. Τὴν δ’
      <lb/>
      αἰτίαν διὰ τί ποτε πᾶσι μὲν ἀναγκαῖον
						ἀποθανεῖν, οὐ μέντοι
      <lb/>
      ὅτε ἔτυχεν ἀλλὰ κατὰ φύσιν μὲν γήρᾳ, βίᾳ δὲ παρὰ
      <lb/>
      φύσιν,
						οὐθὲν δεδήλωκεν. Καίτοι ἐχρῆν, ἐπεὶ ὁτὲ μὲν φαίνεται
      <lb/>
      τοῦτο γινόμενον, ὁτὲ δ’ οὐ
						φαίνεται, πότερον τὸ
      <lb/>
      αἴτιον ἔξωθέν ἐστιν ἢ ἐντός. Οὐ λέγει δὲ οὐδὲ περὶ τῆς
      <lb/>
      ἀρχῆς τοῦ ἀναπνεῖν τί τὸ αἴτιον, πότερον ἔσωθεν ἢ ἔξωθεν·
      <lb/>
      οὐ γὰρ δὴ ὁ θύραθεν
						νοῦς τηρεῖ τὴν βοήθειαν, ἀλλ’ ἔσωθεν
      <lb/>
      ἡ ἀρχὴ τῆς ἀναπνοῆς γίνεται καὶ τῆς κινήσεως,
						οὐχ ὡς βιαζομένου
      <lb/>
      τοῦ περιέχοντος. Ἄτοπον δὲ καὶ τὸ ἅμα τὸ
      <lb/>
      περιέχον συνθλίβειν
						καὶ εἰσιὸν διαστέλλειν. Ἃ μὲν οὖν
      <lb/>
      εἴρηκε καὶ ὥς, σχεδὸν ταῦτ’ ἐστίν. Εἰ δὲ δεῖ
						νομίζειν
      <lb/>
      ἀληθῆ εἶναι τὰ πρότερον λεχθέντα καὶ μὴ πάντα τὰ ζῷα
      <lb/>
      ἀναπνεῖν, οὐ
						περὶ παντὸς θανάτου τὴν αἰτίαν ὑποληπτέον
      <lb/>
      εἰρῆσθαι ταύτην, ἀλλὰ μόνον ἐπὶ τῶν
						ἀναπνεόντων. Οὐ μὴν
      <lb/>
      οὐδ’ ἐπὶ τούτων καλῶς. Δῆλον δ’ ἐκ τῶν συμβαινόντων καὶ
      <lb/>
      τῶν τοιούτων ὧν ἔχομεν πάντες πεῖραν. Ἐν γὰρ ταῖς
      <pb n="334"/>
      ἀλέαις
						θερμαινόμενοι μᾶλλον καὶ τῆς ἀναπνοῆς μᾶλλον
      <lb/>
      δεόμεθα καὶ πυκνότερον ἀναπνέομεν
						πάντες· ὅταν δὲ τὸ
      <lb/>
      πέριξ ᾖ ψυχρὸν καὶ συνάγῃ καὶ συμπηγνύῃ τὸ σῶμα, κατέχειν
      <lb/>
      συμβαίνει τὸ πνεῦμα. Καίτοι τότ’ ἐχρῆν τὸν θύραθεν
      <lb/>
      εἰσιόντα κωλύειν τὴν
						σύνθλιψιν. Νῦν δὲ γίνεται τοὐναντίον·
      <lb/>
      ὅταν γὰρ πολὺ λίαν ἀθροισθῇ τὸ θερμὸν μὴ
						ἐκπνεόντων,
      <lb/>
      τότε δέονται τῆς ἀναπνοῆς· ἀναγκαῖον δ’ εἰσπνεύσαντας
      <lb/>
      ἀναπνεῖν.
						Ἀλεάζοντες δὲ πολλάκις ἀναπνέουσιν,
      <lb/>
      ὡς ἀναψύξεως χάριν ἀναπνέοντες, ὅτε τὸ
						λεγόμενον
      <lb/>
      ποιεῖ πῦρ ἐπὶ πῦρ.
     </p>
     <p lang="it">
      Democrito 4 dice che dalla respirazione accade ciò che accade a chi respira, Faskon
						impedisce all'anima di soffrire; quindi nessun uomo ha fatto questo per undici anni
						la natura non parlava; proprio come gli altri fisici, anche lui
						colpiti da tale causa. Dice che l'anima e il calore sono le prime cose
						forme di sferoidi. confrontandoli quindi sotto il contenuto 
						angosciato, il respiro affannoso diventa un aiuto. Perché nell'aria un gran numero
						è di tale che egli chiama mente e anima respiro quindi anche essere;
						dell'aria questi composti, e rimuovendo il dolore, ostruiscono il respiro
						Dà la vita ai vivi. E per questo motivo, nell'inspirazione e nell'espirazione c'è anche la vita
						perisce; per quando tiene la cotta contenuta, e un velo dalla porta
						se non è in grado di agire, se non è in grado di respirare, allora a quelli accade la morte
						vivere; perché è la morte di tali forme dal corpo ex dente
						dalla depressione contenuta. Non chiedono nulla a meno che non sia necessario
						muoiono non gli uomini quando ciò accadde, ma per natura, per vecchiaia e per violenza contro natura,
						non ha dichiarato. Alcuni hanno detto, quando mi sembra che ciò stia accadendo, che non è così
						si vede se la causa è esterna o interna. Non dice niente di lei
						all'inizio della respirazione, qual è la causa, se viene dall'interno o dall'esterno;
						la mente trattiene l'aiuto, ma dentro l'inizio il respiro diventa anche di movimento,
						non che il contenuto abbia fretta. Atopon e l'ama che lo conteneva furono schiacciati
						e si sta espandendo. Se è così, si è detto che è quasi così. Ma vedi
						pensano che quello detto prima sia vero e non tutti gli animali respirano, no
						per ogni morte la cui causa si presume sia questo delitto, ma solo sul
						respirazione. No, no, non su questi buoni. Sono quattro degli eventi e
						di quelli che abbiamo preso tutti. Perché nelle spiagge riscaldarsi piuttosto che respirare piuttosto vedere e respirare più densamente
						tutti; ma quando l'ambiente circostante è freddo e il corpo si restringe e si condensa, possiedono
						accade lo spirito. Qualcuno ha poi usato la porta per bloccarla
						schiacciare Ma ora accade il contrario; per quando il caldo si accumula
						espirando, allora sono obbligati a respirare; è necessario non inspirare per respirare.
						Mentre macinano, spesso respirano, come se respirassero per rinfrescarsi, quando il
						il cosiddetto poiei fuoco sul fuoco.
     </p>
     <p lang="en">
      Democritus 4 says that from breathing what happens to those who breathe, Faskon
						it hinders the soul from sorrow; no men, therefore, for eleven years, have done this
						nature did not speak; for just like the other physicists, he
						affected by such a cause. He says that the soul and the heat are the first things
						shapes of spheroids. comparing them therefore under the contained 
						distressed, the breathless breath becomes a help. For in the air a great number
						it is of such that he calls mind and soul; breathing therefore also being
						of the air these compounds, and removing the sorrow, obstruct the breath in
						He gives life to the living. And because of this, in inhaling and exhaling is life as well
						it perishes; for when it holds the contained crush, and a veil from the door
						if he is unable to act, if he is unable to breathe, then death happens to those
						living; for it is the death of such forms from the body ex tooth
						from the contained depression. They don't ask for anything unless it's necessary
						die, not men when it happened, but by nature with old age, and by violence against nature,
						he did not declare. Some have said, when it seems to me that this is happening, that it is not
						it is seen whether the cause is external or internal. He doesn't say anything about her
						at the beginning of breathing, what is the cause, whether it is from within or without;
						mind keeps the help, but inside the beginning of breathing also becomes of movement,
						not as if the content is in a hurry. Atopon and the ama that contained it were crushed
						and he is expanding. If so, it was said that it is almost like this. But see
						they think that what was said before is true and not all animals breathe, no
						for every death the cause of which is presumed to be this crime, but only on the
						breathing. No, no, not on these good ones. They are four of the events and
						of the ones that we have everyone took. For in the beaches warming rather than breathing rather see and breathe more densely
						all; but when the surrounding is cold and the body shrinks and condenses, they possess
						the spirit happens. Someone then used the door to block it
						crush But now the opposite happens; for when the heat accumulates
						exhaling, then they are bound to breathing; it is necessary not to inhale to breathe.
						While grinding, they often breathe, as if breathing for the sake of refreshment, when the
						so-called poiei fire on fire.
     </p>
    </div>
    <div n="5" subtype="chapter" type="textpart">
     <p>
      Ἡ δ’ ἐν τῷ Τιμαίῳ γεγραμμένη περίωσις περί τε τῶν
      <lb/>
      ἄλλων ζῴων οὐδὲν διώρικε τίνα
						τρόπον αὐτοῖς ἡ τοῦ θερμοῦ
      <lb/>
      γίνεται σωτηρία, πότερον τὸν αὐτὸν ἢ δι’ ἄλλην τινὰ
						αἰτίαν·
      <lb/>
      εἰ μὲν γὰρ μόνοις τὸ τῆς ἀναπνοῆς ὑπάρχει τοῖς πεζοῖς,
      <lb/>
      λεκτέον τὴν
						αἰτίαν τοῦ μόνοις· εἰ δὲ καὶ τοῖς ἄλλοις, ὁ δὲ
      <lb/>
      τρόπος ἄλλος, καὶ περὶ τούτου
						διοριστέον, εἴπερ δυνατὸν
      <lb/>
      ἀναπνεῖν πᾶσιν. Ἔτι δὲ καὶ πλασματώδης ὁ τρόπος τῆς
      <lb/>
      αἰτίας. Ἐξιόντος γὰρ ἔξω τοῦ θερμοῦ διὰ τοῦ στόματος,
      <lb/>
      τὸν περιέχοντα ὠθούμενον
						ἀέρα φερόμενον ἐμπίπτειν εἰς
      <lb/>
      τὸν αὐτὸν τόπον φησὶ διὰ μανῶν οὐσῶν τῶν σαρκῶν, ὅθεν
						τὸ
      <lb/>
      ἐντὸς ἐξῄει θερμόν, διὰ τὸ μηδὲν εἶναι κενὸν ἀντιπεριισταμένων
      <lb/>
      ἀλλήλοις·
						θερμανθέντα δὲ πάλιν ἐξιέναι κατὰ τὸν αὐτὸν
      <lb/>
      τόπον, καὶ περιωθεῖν εἴσω διὰ τοῦ
						στόματος τὸν ἀέρα τὸν
      <lb/>
      ἐκπίπτοντα θερμόν· καὶ τοῦτο δὴ διατελεῖν ἀεὶ ποιοῦντας,
      <lb/>
      ἀναπνέοντάς τε καὶ ἐκπνέοντας. Συμβαίνει δὲ τοῖς οὕτως
      <lb/>
      οἰομένοις πρότερον τὴν
						ἐκπνοὴν γίνεσθαι τῆς εἰσπνοῆς.
      <lb/>
      Ἔστι δὲ τοὐναντίον. Σημεῖον δέ· γίνεται μὲν γὰρ
						ἀλλήλοις
      <lb/>
      ταῦτα παρ’ ἄλληλα, τελευτῶντες δὲ ἐκπνέουσιν, ὥστ’
      <lb/>
      ἀναγκαῖον εἶναι
						τὴν ἀρχὴν εἰσπνοήν. Ἔτι δὲ τὸ τίνος
      <pb n="335"/>
      ἕνεκα ταῦθ’ ὑπάρχει τοῖς ζῴοις (λέγω
						δὲ τὸ ἀναπνεῖν καὶ
      <lb/>
      τὸ ἐκπνεῖν) οὐθὲν εἰρήκασιν οἱ τοῦτον τὸν τρόπον λέγοντες,
      <lb/>
      ἀλλ’ ὡς περὶ συμπτώματός τινος ἀποφαίνονται μόνον.
      <lb/>
      Καίτοι γε κύρια ταῦθ’
						ὁρῶμεν τοῦ ζῆν καὶ τελευτᾶν· ὅταν
      <lb/>
      γὰρ ἀναπνεῖν μὴ δύνωνται, τότε συμβαίνει γίνεσθαι
						τὴν
      <lb/>
      φθορὰν τοῖς ἀναπνέουσιν. Ἔτι δὲ ἄτοπον τὸ τὴν μὲν τοῦ
      <lb/>
      θερμοῦ διὰ τοῦ
						στόματος ἔξοδον καὶ πάλιν εἴσοδον μὴ
      <lb/>
      λανθάνειν ἡμᾶς, τὴν δ’ εἰς τὸν θώρακα τοῦ
						πνεύματος εἴσοδον
      <lb/>
      καὶ πάλιν θερμανθέντος ἔξοδον λανθάνειν. Ἄτοπον δὲ καὶ
      <lb/>
      τοῦ
						θερμοῦ τὴν ἀναπνοὴν εἴσοδον εἶναι. Φαίνεται γὰρ τοὐναντίον·
      <lb/>
      τὸ μὲν γὰρ ἐκπνεόμενον
						εἶναι θερμόν, τὸ δ’
      <lb/>
      εἰσπνεόμενον ψυχρόν. Ὅταν δὲ θερμὸν ᾖ, ἀσθμαίνοντες
      <lb/>
      ἀναπνέουσιν· διὰ γὰρ τὸ μὴ καταψύχειν ἱκανῶς τὸ εἰσιὸν
      <lb/>
      πολλάκις τὸ πνεῦμα
						συμβαίνει σπᾶν.
     </p>
     <p lang="it">
      Il quarto versetto scritto nel Timeo sulle altre vite non vi ha separati
						In questo modo il caldo diventa per loro una salvezza, dopo averlo bevuto o per qualche altro motivo
						causa; poiché se tra i pedoni esiste solo il respiro, lascia che
						causa sua soltanto; ma anche ad altri, ma la via è diversa, e su questo
						Nominato, tutti respiravano affannosamente. E se i suoi modi fossero fittizi?
						causa. Per essere fuori dal thermos attraverso la bocca, l'otumone contenente
						l'aria, trasportata, cadde nello stesso luogo dalle madri degli esseri carnali, da dove
						mentre emette calore, per nulla è vuoto di opposti;
						ed essendo riscaldato, si dissipa di nuovo nello stesso luogo ed è circondato dal
						bocca l'aria il calore che cade;
						inspirando ed espirando. Ma succede a chi l'ha già visto
						L'espirazione diventa inspirazione. Anzi. È un segno; diventa m Perché
						questi uno dopo l'altro, ma per ultimi espirano, secondo necessità
						la prima inspirazione. Ma la sua unità esiste tra i viventi (dico
						ma lo inspirano e lo espirano) quelli che dicevano così non litigavano,
						ma decidono solo del suo sintomo. Cerchiamo di essere i principali
						lasciali vivere e finire; perché quando respirano non possono, allora succede
						la stanchezza di chi respira. Ma per questo motivo non vedo il calore del sole
						bocca sono uscito e sono entrato di nuovo per non impigliarci, il quarto nel petto
						di spirito entrai e di nuovo riscaldato uscii dormiente. Anche Atopon
						riscalda il respiro dentro di sé. Perché sembra il contrario;
						è caldo, il freddo inalato. Ma quando fa caldo, mi manca il fiato
						respirano, per non congelare troppo spesso l'anima
						succede raramente.
     </p>
     <p lang="en">
      The fourth verse written in Timaeus about other lives did not separate you
						In this way, the heat becomes a salvation for them, after drinking it or for some other reason
						cause; for if the breath alone exists among the pedestrians, let the
						cause of him alone; but also to others, but the way is different, and about this
						Appointed, everyone was breathing hard. What if her manner is fictitious
						cause. For being outside the thermos through the mouth, the containing othumone
						the air, being carried, fell into the same place by the mothers of fleshly beings, whence
						while it emits heat, for nothing it is a void of opposites;
						and being heated, it again dissipates in the same place, and is surrounded by the
						mouth the air the falling heat;
						breathing in and out. But it happens to those who have seen it before
						Exhalation becomes inhalation. On the contrary. It's a sign; it becomes m because
						these one after the other, but last they exhale, as necessary
						the first inhalation. But his oneness exists among the living (I say
						but they breathe it in and breathe it out) those saying this way did not quarrel,
						but they only decide about his symptom. Let's be the main ones
						let them live and end; for when they breathe they cannot, then it happens
						the weariness of those who breathe. But I don't see the heat of the sun because of it
						mouth I went out and came in again do not entangle us, the fourth in the chest of
						of spirit I went in and again heated I went out dormant. Atopon, too
						warm the breath inward it is. For it seems to the contrary;
						it is warm, the d'inhaled cold. But when it's hot, short of breath
						they breathe, for not to freeze the soul too often
						it happens rarely.
     </p>
    </div>
    <div n="6" subtype="chapter" type="textpart">
     <p>
      Ἀλλὰ μὴν οὐδὲ τροφῆς γε χάριν ὑποληπτέον γίνεσθαι
      <lb/>
      τὴν ἀναπνοήν, ὡς τρεφομένου τῷ
						πνεύματι τοῦ ἐντὸς πυρός,
      <lb/>
      καὶ ἀναπνέοντος μὲν ὥσ περ ἐπὶ πῦρ ὑπέκκαυμα
						ὑποβάλλεσθαι,
      <lb/>
      τραφέντος δὲ τοῦ πυρὸς γίνεσθαι τὴν ἐκπνοήν. Ταὐτὰ
      <lb/>
      γὰρ ἐροῦμεν
						πάλιν καὶ πρὸς τοῦτον τὸν λόγον ἅπερ πρὸς
      <lb/>
      τοὺς ἔμπροσθεν· καὶ γὰρ ἐπὶ τῶν ἄλλων
						ζῴων ἐχρῆν τοῦτο
      <lb/>
      συμβαίνειν ἢ τὸ ἀνάλογον τούτῳ· πάντα γὰρ ἔχει θερμότητα
      <lb/>
      ζωτικήν. Ἔπειτα καὶ τὸ γίνεσθαι τὸ θερμὸν ἐκ τοῦ
      <lb/>
      πνεύματος τίνα χρὴ τρόπον
						λέγειν, πλασματῶδες ὄν·
      <lb/>
      μᾶλλον γὰρ ἐκ τῆς τροφῆς τοῦτο γινόμενον ὁρῶμεν. Συμβαίνει
      <lb/>
      τε κατὰ ταὐτὸ δέχεσθαι τὴν τροφὴν καὶ τὸ περίττωμα
      <lb/>
      ἀφιέναι· τοῦτο δ’ ἐπὶ τῶν
						ἄλλων οὐχ ὁρῶμεν
      <lb/>
      γινόμενον.
     </p>
     <p lang="it">
      Ma nessun cibo per amore della grazia diventa respiro, in quanto nutrito dall'
						lo spirito del fuoco e respira come cenere sul fuoco
						è posticipato, ma dopo che il fuoco è stato alimentato, diventa l'espirazione. Perché è quello che siamo
						ancora e questa parola si applica a quelli che stanno davanti; perché anche agli altri
						Nella vita, lascia che accada questo o qualcosa di simile, perché ha sempre calore
						vitale. Allora diventa il calore dello spirito in modo diverso
						dicono, esseri creati, anzi, lo vediamo accadere dal cibo. Succede
						quindi riceve il cibo e lascia gli escrementi;
						altri non li vediamo accadere.
     </p>
     <p lang="en">
      But no food for the sake of grace becomes the breath, as nourished by the
						the spirit of the fire, and breathing like ashes on the fire
						it is postponed, but after the fire is fed, it becomes the exhalation. Because that's what we are
						again and to this word apply to those in front; for also to the others
						In life, let this happen or something similar to it, because it always has heat
						vital. Then it becomes the heat from the spirit in a different way
						they say, created beings; rather, we see this happening from food. It happens
						therefore he receives the food and the excrement is left;
						others we do not see happening.
     </p>
    </div>
    <div n="7" subtype="chapter" type="textpart">
     <p>
      Λέγει δὲ περὶ ἀναπνοῆς καὶ Ἐμπεδοκλῆς, οὐ μέντοι τίνος
      <lb/>
      γ’ ἕνεκα, οὐδὲ περὶ πάντων
						τῶν ζῴων οὐδὲν ποιεῖ δῆλον, εἴτε
      <pb n="336"/>
      ἀναπνέουσιν εἴτε μή. Καὶ περὶ τῆς διὰ τῶν
						μυκτήρων ἀναπνοῆς
      <lb/>
      λέγων οἴεται καὶ περὶ τῆς κυρίας λέγειν ἀναπνοῆς.
      <lb/>
      Ἔστι γὰρ
						καὶ διὰ τῆς ἀρτηρίας ἐκ τῶν στηθῶν ἡ ἀναπνοή,
      <lb/>
      καὶ ἡ διὰ τῶν μυκτήρων· αὐτοῖς δὲ
						χωρὶς ἐκείνης οὐκ
      <lb/>
      ἔστιν ἀναπνεῦσαι τοῖς μυκτῆρσιν. Καὶ τῆς μὲν διὰ τῶν
      <lb/>
      μυκτήρων γινομένης ἀναπνοῆς στερισκόμενα τὰ ζῷα οὐδὲν
      <lb/>
      πάσχουσι, τῆς δὲ κατὰ
						τὴν ἀρτηρίαν ἀποθνήσκουσιν.
      <lb/>
      Καταχρῆται γὰρ ἡ φύσις ἐν παρέργῳ τῇ διὰ τῶν μυκτήρων
      <lb/>
      ἀναπνοῇ πρὸς τὴν ὄσφρησιν ἐν ἐνίοις τῶν ζῴων· διόπερ
      <lb/>
      ὀσφρήσεως μὲν σχεδὸν
						μετέχει πάντα τὰ ζῷα, ἔστι δ’ οὐ
      <lb/>
      πᾶσι τὸ αὐτὸ αἰσθητήριον. Εἴρηται δὲ περὶ αὐτῶν ἐν
						ἑτέροις
      <lb/>
      σαφέστερον. Γίνεσθαι δέ φησι τὴν ἀναπνοὴν καὶ ἐκπνοὴν
      <lb/>
      διὰ τὸ φλέβας
						εἶναί τινας, ἐν αἷς ἔνεστι μὲν αἷμα, οὐ
      <lb/>
      μέντοι πλήρεις εἰσὶν αἵματος, ἔχουσι δὲ
						πόρους εἰς τὸν ἔξω
      <lb/>
      ἀέρα, τῶν μὲν τοῦ σώματος μορίων ἐλάττους, τῶν δὲ τοῦ
      <lb/>
      ἀέρος
						μείζους· διὸ τοῦ αἵματος πεφυκότος κινεῖσθαι ἄνω
      <lb/>
      καὶ κάτω, κάτω μὲν φερομένου
						εἰσρεῖν τὸν ἀέρα καὶ γίνεσθαι
      <lb/>
      ἀναπνοήν, ἄνω δ’ ἰόντος ἐκπίπτειν θύραζε καὶ γίνεσθαι
						τὴν
      <lb/>
      ἐκπνοήν, παρεικάζων τὸ συμβαῖνον ταῖς κλεψύδραις.
     </p>
     <p lang="it">
      E parla del respiro e di Empedocle, non dei suoi terzi undici, non di tutto
						degli esseri viventi nessuno inganna, che respirino o no. E di lei attraverso loro
						dei batteri respiratori, dicono, ovviamente, della signora, dicono anche respiratori. È
						e attraverso l'arteria dai seni la respirazione, e attraverso i polmoni;
						senza di lei, i miziani non possono respirare. E di me per loro
						gli animali che fanno affidamento sulla respirazione dei funghi non soffrono, ma
						l'arteria muore. Perché la natura viene abusata in modo strano attraverso i funghi
						respirare verso l'olfatto negli esseri viventi attraverso l'olfatto senza attingere
						partecipa sempre alla vita, perché non tutti hanno lo stesso sentimento. Si dice di loro in
						altri in modo più chiaro. Inspira ed espira attraverso la vena
						è tuo, in un sangue intriso di sangue, non sei pieno di sangue, ma loro lo hanno
						pori dell'aria esterna, delle molecole difettose del corpo e dell'aria o
						maggiore; attraverso il sangue del peduncolo si muove su e giù, sotto
						lascia entrare l'aria e diventerai respiro
						espirazione, simulando il fenomeno della clessidra.
     </p>
     <p lang="en">
      And he says about breathing and Empedocles, not about his third eleven, not about everything
						of living things no one deceives, whether they breathe or not. And about her through them
						of respiratory bacteria, they say, of course, about the lady, they also say respiratory. It is
						and through the artery from the breasts the respiration, and through the lungs;
						without her, there is no breathing to the myctians. And of me for them
						the animals relying on the respiration of fungi do not suffer, but
						the artery dies. Because nature is abused in a strange way through fungi
						breathing towards the sense of smell in living beings; through sense of smell without drawing
						he always participates in life, because not all of them have the same feeling. It is said about them in
						others more clearly. Inhale and exhale through the vein
						it is yours, in a blood infused with blood, you are not full of blood, but they have
						pores to the outside air, of the body's defect molecules, and of the air o
						major; through the blood of the peduncle it moves up and down, under
						let in the air and you will become breath
						exhalation, simulating the hourglass phenomenon.
     </p>
     <lg>
      <l>
       Ὧδε δ’ ἀναπνεῖ πάντα καὶ ἐκπνεῖ. Πᾶσι λίφαιμοι
      </l>
      <l lang="it">
       Non sempre inspira ed espira. Tutta gente grassa
      </l>
      <l lang="en">
       He doesn't always breathe in and out. All fat people
      </l>
      <l>
       σαρκῶν σύριγγες πύματον κατὰ σῶμα τέτανται,
      </l>
      <l lang="it">
       Siringhe di carne tese sopra il corpo,
      </l>
      <l lang="en">
       Syringes of flesh stretched above the body,
      </l>
      <l>
       καί σφιν ἐπὶ στομίοις πυκναῖς τέτρηνται ἄλοξιν
      </l>
      <l lang="it">
       e i cunei sulle bocche dei boschetti vengono tagliati in diagonale
      </l>
      <l lang="en">
       and wedges on the mouths of the thickets are cut diagonally
      </l>
      <l>
       ῥινῶν ἔσχατα τέρθρα διαμπερές, ὥστε φόνον μέν
      </l>
      <l lang="it">
       ῥινῶν ἔχατα τερθρα παράες, στε φονον MEN
      </l>
      <l lang="en">
       ῥινῶν ἔχατα τερθρα παράες, στε φονον MEN
      </l>
      <l>
       κεύθειν, αἰθέρι δ’ εὐπορίην διόδοισι τετμῆσθαι.
      </l>
      <l lang="it">
       kevethin, aetheri d'euporiin diodoisi tetmisthai.
      </l>
      <l lang="en">
       kevethin, aetheri d'euporiin diodoisi tetmisthai.
      </l>
      <l>
       Ἔνθεν ἔπειθ’ ὁπόταν μὲν ἀπαΐξῃ τέρεν αἷμα,
      </l>
      <l lang="it">
       In qualche modo pensava di voler fare una partita di sangue,
      </l>
      <l lang="en">
       Somehow he thought he wanted to play a game of blood,
      </l>
      <pb n="337"/>
      <l>
       αἰθὴρ παφλάζων καταβήσεται οἴδματι μάργῳ,
      </l>
      <l lang="it">
       l'aria del fuoco è abbattuta dal sangue di marg,
      </l>
      <l lang="en">
       the air of the fire is brought down by the blood of marg,
      </l>
      <l>
       εὖτε δ’ ἀναθρώσκει, πάλιν ἐκπνεῖ, ὥσ περ ὅταν παῖς
      </l>
      <l lang="it">
       quindi non pensare, espira di nuovo, come quando vai
      </l>
      <l lang="en">
       so don't think, breathe out again, like when you go
      </l>
      <l>
       κλεψύδρην παίζησι δι’ εὐπετέος χαλκοῖο.
      </l>
      <l lang="it">
       Clessidra che gioca con il bronzo giubilare.
      </l>
      <l lang="en">
       Hourglass playing with jubilee bronze.
      </l>
      <l>
       Εὖτε μὲν αὐλοῦ πορθμὸν ἐπ’ εὐειδεῖ χερὶ θεῖσα
      </l>
      <l lang="it">
       Così, con una court boat, ci ho messo mano
      </l>
      <l lang="en">
       So, with a court boat, I put my hand on it
      </l>
      <l>
       εἰς ὕδατος βάπτῃσι τέρεν δέμας ἀργυφέοιο,
      </l>
      <l lang="it">
       Battezzare nell'acqua teren demas argyfeoio,
      </l>
      <l lang="en">
       Baptize in water teren demas argyfeoio,
      </l>
      <l>
       οὐδ’ ὅγ’ ἐς ἄγγος δ’ ὄμβρος ἐσέρχεται, ἀλλά μιν εἴργει
      </l>
      <l lang="it">
       no, quando sei un po' di pioggia, non arriva, ma non funziona
      </l>
      <l lang="en">
       no, when you're a little rain, it doesn't come, but it doesn't work
      </l>
      <l>
       ἀέρος ὄγκος ἔσωθε πεσὼν ἐπὶ τρήματα πυκνά,
      </l>
      <l lang="it">
       Un volume d'aria risparmiato cadendo fittamente sui fori,
      </l>
      <l lang="en">
       A volume of air saved falling on holes densely,
      </l>
      <l>
       εἰσόκ’ ἀποστεγάσῃ πυνικὸν ῥόον· αὐτὰρ ἔπειτα
      </l>
      <l lang="it">
       se dà rifugio a un pynic ῥoon;
      </l>
      <l lang="en">
       if he shelters a pynic ῥoon;
      </l>
      <l>
       πνεύματος ἐλλείποντος ἐσέρχεται αὔξιμον ὕδωρ.
      </l>
      <l lang="it">
       mancando lo spirito, entrano le acque che salgono.
      </l>
      <l lang="en">
       lacking spirit, rising water enters.
      </l>
      <l>
       Ὡς δ’ αὕτως ὅθ’ ὕδωρ μὲν ἔχει κατὰ βένθεα χαλκοῦ
      </l>
      <l lang="it">
       È come se ci fosse acqua come una benthea di rame
      </l>
      <l lang="en">
       It's the same as if there's water like a copper benthea
      </l>
      <l>
       πορθμοῦ χωσθέντος βροτέῳ χροῒ ἠδὲ πόροιο,
      </l>
      <l lang="it">
       La barca perduta ha trovato il tempo, nessuna risorsa,
      </l>
      <l lang="en">
       Lost boat found time, no resource,
      </l>
      <l>
       αἰθὴρ δ’ ἐκτὸς ἔσω λελιημένος ὄμβρον ἐρύκει
      </l>
      <l lang="it">
       ἀθὀ δ' ektὸς ὔσο λελιένος ombron yrikei
      </l>
      <l lang="en">
       ἀθὀ δ' ektὸς ὔσο λελιένος ombron yrikei
      </l>
      <l>
       ἀμφὶ πύλας ἰσθμοῖο δυσηχέος, ἄκρα κρατύνων,
      </l>
      <l lang="it">
       ma la porta dell'istmo è difficile, le estremità del
      </l>
      <l lang="en">
       but the gate of the isthmus is difficult, the ends of the
      </l>
      <l>
       εἰσόκε χειρὶ μεθῇ· τότε δ’ αὖ πάλιν, ἔμπαλιν ἢ πρίν,
      </l>
      <l lang="it">
       se la mano è ubriaca, allora ancora, ancora o prima,
      </l>
      <l lang="en">
       if the hand is drunk; then again, again or before,
      </l>
      <l>
       πνεύματος ἐμπίπτοντος ὑπεκθέει αὔξιμον ὕδωρ.
      </l>
      <l lang="it">
       lo spirito che cade presuppone l'acqua che sale.
      </l>
      <l lang="en">
       falling spirit presupposes rising water.
      </l>
      <l>
       Ὡς δ’ αὕτως τέρεν αἷμα κλαδασσόμενον διὰ γυίων
      </l>
      <l lang="it">
       Ὡs d' sos teren sangue potato dai figli
      </l>
      <l lang="en">
       Ὡs d' thus teren blood pruned by sons
      </l>
      <l>
       ὁππότε μὲν παλίνορσον ἐπαΐξειε μυχόνδε,
      </l>
      <l lang="it">
       poi con palinorson suona myhonde,
      </l>
      <l lang="en">
       then with palinorson play myhonde,
      </l>
      <pb n="338"/>
      <l>
       αἰθέρος εὐθὺς ῥεῦμα κατέρχεται οἴδματι θῦον,
      </l>
      <l lang="it">
       ἀθερος ὐθὺς ῥεῦμα discende οιδματι ῦον,
      </l>
      <l lang="en">
       ἀθερος ὐθὺς ῥεῦμα descends οιδματι ῦον,
      </l>
      <l>
       εὖτε δ’ ἀναθρώσκῃ, πάλιν ἐκπνεῖ ἶσον ὀπίσσω.
      </l>
      <l lang="it">
       Quindi non pensare, espira di nuovo.
      </l>
      <l lang="en">
       So don't think, breathe out again.
      </l>
     </lg>
     <p>
      Λέγει μὲν οὖν ταῦτα περὶ τοῦ ἀναπνεῖν, ἀναπνεῖ δ’, ὥσπερ
      <lb/>
      εἴπομεν, τὰ φανερῶς
						ἀναπνέοντα διὰ τῆς ἀρτηρίας, διά τε
      <lb/>
      τοῦ στόματος ἅμα καὶ διὰ τῶν μυκτήρων. Ὥστ’ εἰ
						μὲν
      <lb/>
      περὶ ταύτης λέγει τῆς ἀναπνοῆς, ἀναγκαῖον ζητεῖν πῶς
      <lb/>
      ἐφαρμόσει ὁ εἰρημένος
						λόγος τῆς αἰτίας· φαίνεται γὰρ
      <lb/>
      τοὐναντίον συμβαῖνον. Ἄραντες μὲν γὰρ τὸν τόπον,
						καθάπερ
      <lb/>
      τὰς φύσας ἐν τοῖς χαλκείοις, ἀναπνέουσιν· αἴρειν δὲ τὸ
      <lb/>
      θερμὸν εὔλογον,
						ἔχειν δὲ τὸ αἷμα τὴν τοῦ θερμοῦ χώραν·
      <lb/>
      συνιζάνοντες δὲ καὶ καταπνίγοντες, ὥσπερ
						ἐκεῖ τὰς φύσας,
      <lb/>
      ἐκπνέουσιν. Πλὴν ἐκεῖ μὲν οὐ κατὰ ταὐτὸν εἰσδέχονταί
      <lb/>
      τε τὸν
						ἀέρα καὶ πάλιν ἐξιᾶσιν, οἱ δ’ ἀναπνέοντες κατὰ
      <lb/>
      ταὐτόν. Εἰ δὲ περὶ τῆς κατὰ τοὺς
						μυκτῆρας λέγει μόνης,
      <lb/>
      πολὺ διημάρτηκεν· οὐ γάρ ἐστιν ἀναπνοὴ μυκτήρων ἴδιος,
      <lb/>
      ἀλλὰ παρὰ τὸν αὐλῶνα τὸν περὶ τὸν γαργαρεῶνα, ᾗ τὸ
      <lb/>
      ἔσχατον τοῦ ἐν τῷ στόματι
						οὐρανοῦ, συντετρημένων τῶν
      <lb/>
      μυκτήρων χωρεῖ τὸ μὲν ταύτῃ τοῦ πνεύματος, τὸ δὲ διὰ
      <lb/>
      τοῦ στόματος, ὁμοίως εἰσιόν τε καὶ ἐξιόν. Τὰ μὲν οὖν
      <lb/>
      παρὰ τῶν ἄλλων εἰρημένα
						περὶ τοῦ ἀναπνεῖν τοιαύτας καὶ
      <lb/>
      τοσαύτας ἔχει δυσχερείας.
     </p>
     <p lang="it">
      Quindi dice queste cose sulla respirazione, respira, come diciamo noi, ovviamente
						respirare attraverso l'arteria, attraverso la bocca, ma anche attraverso il muco. Ὥσ'εἰ
						ma riguardo a questo che dice della respirazione, bisogna chiedersi come si applica l'unto
						ragione della causa; sembra invece il contrario. Perché vuoi quel posto,
						vedi le nature nei bronzi, respirano;
						ma il sangue ha il paese caldo;
						lì respira la natura. Tuttavia, non lo accettano lì
						aria e respira di nuovo, chi non respira secondo questo. Ma su di lei contro di loro
						Myctiras dice da solo, molto dimartiken; perché non è il respiro di Myctears stesso,
						ma invece del gorgoglio attorno al gorgoglio, la fine in bocca
						del cielo, schiacciato dai funghi, regge il me dello stesso spirito, e il
						della bocca, allo stesso modo eision te ed eision. Quelli diversi dagli altri n rotto
						riguardo alla respirazione di questo e quello c'è difficoltà.
     </p>
     <p lang="en">
      So he says these things about breathing, he breathes, as we say, obviously
						breathing through the artery, through the mouth, but also through the mucus. Ὥσ' εἰ
						but about this he says of breathing, it is necessary to ask how the anointed one applies
						reason of the cause; for the contrary seems to be the case. Because you want the place,
						see the natures in the bronzes, they breathe;
						but the blood has the warm country;
						there the natures breathe. However, they do not accept him there
						air and breathe again, those who do not breathe according to this. But about her against them
						Myctiras says alone, much dimartiken; for it is not the breath of myctears itself,
						but instead of the gurgling around the gurgling, the end of it in the mouth
						of heaven, crushed by the fungi, the me of the same spirit holds, and the
						of the mouth, likewise eision te and eision. The ones that are different from the others n broken
						about the breathing of such and such there is difficulty.
     </p>
    </div>
    <div n="8" subtype="chapter" type="textpart">
     <p>
      Ἐπεὶ δὲ εἴρηται πρότερον ὅτι τὸ ζῆν καὶ ἡ τῆς ψυχῆς
      <lb/>
      ἕξις μετὰ θερμότητός τινός
						ἐστιν· οὐδὲ γὰρ ἡ πέψις, δι’ ἧς
      <lb/>
      ἡ τροφὴ γίνεται τοῖς ζῴοις, οὔτ’ ἄνευ ψυχῆς οὔτ’
						ἄνευ θερμότητός
      <lb/>
      ἐστιν· πυρὶ γὰρ ἐργάζεται πάντα. Διόπερ ἐν ᾧ
      <pb n="339"/>
      πρώτῳ
						τόπῳ τοῦ σώματος καὶ ἐν ᾧ πρώτῳ τοῦ τόπου τούτου
      <lb/>
      μορίῳ τὴν ἀρχὴν ἀναγκαῖον εἶναι
						τὴν τοιαύτην, ἐνταῦθα
      <lb/>
      καὶ τὴν πρώτην τὴν θρεπτικὴν ψυχὴν ἀναγκαῖον ὑπάρχειν.
      <lb/>
      Οὗτος δ’ ἐστὶν ὁ μέσος τόπος τοῦ τε δεχομένου τὴν
      <lb/>
      τροφὴν καὶ καθ’ ὃν ἀφίησι τὸ
						περίττωμα. Τοῖς μὲν οὖν
      <lb/>
      ἀναίμοις ἀνώνυμον, τοῖς δ’ ἐναίμοις ἡ καρδία τοῦτο τὸ
						μόριόν
      <lb/>
      ἐστιν. Ἡ τροφὴ μὲν γὰρ ἐξ ἧς ἤδη γίνεται τὰ μόρια
      <lb/>
      τοῖς ζῴοις, ἡ τοῦ
						αἵματος φύσις ἐστίν. Τοῦ δ’ αἵματος καὶ
      <lb/>
      τῶν φλεβῶν τὴν αὐτὴν ἀρχὴν ἀναγκαῖον εἶναι·
						θατέρου
      <lb/>
      γὰρ ἕνεκα θάτερόν ἐστιν, ὡς ἀγγεῖον καὶ δεκτικόν. Ἀρχὴ
      <lb/>
      δὲ τῶν φλεβῶν ἡ
						καρδία τοῖς ἐναίμοις· οὐ γὰρ διὰ ταύτης,
      <lb/>
      ἀλλ’ ἐκ ταύτης ἠρτημέναι πᾶσαι
						τυγχάνουσιν. Δῆλον δ’
      <lb/>
      ἡμῖν τοῦτο ἐκ τῶν ἀνατομῶν. Τὰς μὲν οὖν ἄλλας δυνάμεις
      <lb/>
      τῆς ψυχῆς ἀδύνατον ὑπάρχειν ἄνευ τῆς θρεπτικῆς (δι’ ἣν δ’
      <lb/>
      αἰτίαν, εἴρηται
						πρότερον ἐν τοῖς περὶ ψυχῆς), ταύτην δ’ ἄνευ
      <lb/>
      τοῦ φυσικοῦ πυρός· ἐν τούτῳ γὰρ ἡ
						φύσις ἐμπεπύρευκεν
      <lb/>
      αὐτήν. Φθορὰ δὲ πυρός, ὥσ περ εἴρηται πρότερον, σβέσις
      <lb/>
      καὶ
						μάρανσις. Σβέσις μὲν ἡ ὑπὸ τῶν ἐναντίων· διό περ
      <lb/>
      ἀθρόον τε ὑπὸ τῆς τοῦ περιέχοντος
						ψυχρότητος, καὶ
      <lb/>
      θᾶττον ὅτι σβέννυται διασπώμενον. Αὕτη μὲν οὖν ἡ
      <lb/>
      φθορὰ βίαιος
						ὁμοίως ἐπὶ τῶν ἐμψύχων καὶ τῶν ἀψύχων
      <lb/>
      ἐστίν· καὶ γὰρ ὀργάνοις διαιρουμένου τοῦ
						ζῴου, καὶ πηγνυμένου
      <lb/>
      διὰ ψύχους ὑπερβολήν, ἀποθνήσκουσιν. Ἡ δὲ μάρανσις
      <lb/>
      διὰ
						πλῆθος θερμότητος· καὶ γὰρ ἂν ὑπερβάλλῃ τὸ
      <lb/>
      πέριξ θερμόν, καὶ τροφὴν ἐὰν μὴ λαμβάνῃ,
						φθείρεται τὸ
      <lb/>
      πυρούμενον, οὐ ψυχόμενον ἀλλὰ μαραινόμενον. Ὥστ’
      <lb/>
      ἀνάγκη γίνεσθαι
						κατάψυξιν, εἰ μέλλει τεύξεσθαι σωτηρίας·
      <lb/>
      τοῦτο γὰρ βοηθεῖ πρὸς ταύτην τὴν φθοράν.
     </p>
     <p lang="it">
      E quando prima si diceva che la vita e l'anima sono sei con il calore di una cosa sola
						poiché non è la digestione, mediante la quale viene dato il cibo agli esseri viventi, né senza anima né
						È senza calore, perché il fuoco funziona sempre. Dioper ἐν ᾧ protoῳ
						al luogo del corpo e nel quale, come prima particella di questo luogo, si trova il principio necessario
						questo, in questa e nella prima anima nutritrice, esiste necessariamente.
						Questo è il luogo intermedio di colui che ha ricevuto il cibo e al quale ha lasciato il cibo
						escrementi. A coloro che sono morti in modo anonimo, a coloro che sono morti, il cuore di questo
						è una molecola. Per il cibo da cui sono già costituite le molecole degli animali, il
						la natura del sangue è. Del sangue e delle vene è necessario questo principio;
						poiché c'è un solo padre, come vaso e ricevitore. Ma l'inizio delle vene
						cuore alle anime: perché non per questo, ma da questo tutti sono legati
						accadono. Impariamo questo dagli anatomisti. Le altre forze dell’anima impossibile esistere senza nutrimento (per quale ragione lo è
						precedentemente in quelli sull'anima), questo senza il fuoco naturale poiché in questo il
						la natura lo ha causato. Ma quando il fuoco si consuma, come detto prima, lo spegni anche tu
						Maransis. Svesis con o sotto gli avversari; da per athroon e sotto quello del contenimento
						di freddezza, e che si estingue per disintegrazione. Questa, dunque, la distruzione è violenta
						allo stesso modo sull'animato e sull'inanimato; poiché sono organi divisi dell'anima
						della vita, ed essendo consumati dal freddo eccessivo, muoiono. Ma i maransis di
						una moltitudine di calore; perché se il calore circostante è eccessivo, e il cibo non riceve,
						il fuoco consuma, non raffreddando ma appassindo. Se necessario, verrà fatto
						il congelamento, se si vuole salvarlo, perché questo aiuta contro questo deterioramento.
     </p>
     <p lang="en">
      And when it was said before that the life and the soul are six with the warmth of one
						for it is not digestion, by which food is given to living things, neither without a soul nor
						It is without heat, for fire always works. Dioper ἐν ᾧ protoῳ
						to the place of the body and in which, as the first particle of this place, the necessary principle is
						this, in this and the first nourishing soul, necessarily exists.
						This is the middle place of the one who received the food and to whom he left the
						excrement. To those who have died anonymously, to those who have died, the heart of this
						it is a molecule. For the food from which the molecules of the animals are already made, the
						blood nature is. Of the blood and veins this principle is necessary;
						for there are only one father, as a vessel and a receiver. But the beginning of the veins
						heart to the souls: for not through this, but from this are all bound
						they happen. Let us learn this from the anatomists. The other forces of the soul impossible to exist without nourishment (for what reason, it is
						previously in those about the soul), this one without the natural fire; for in this the
						nature caused it. But when the fire wears out, as mentioned before, you also put it out
						maransis. Svesis with or under the opponents; by per athroon and under that of the containing
						of coldness, and that it is extinguished by disintegration. This one, then, the destruction is violent
						likewise on the animate and the inanimate; for they are divided organs of the
						of life, and being consumed by excessive cold, they die. But the maransis di
						a multitude of heat; for if the surrounding heat is excessive, and food if it does not receive,
						the burning wears out, not cooling but withering. If necessary, it will be done
						freezing, if it is to be saved, because this helps against this deterioration.
     </p>
    </div>
    <pb n="340"/>
    <div n="9" subtype="chapter" type="textpart">
     <p>
      Ἐπεὶ δὲ τῶν ζῴων τὰ μὲν ἔνυδρα, τὰ δ’ ἐν τῇ γῇ ποιεῖται
      <lb/>
      τὴν διατριβήν, τούτων τοῖς
						μὲν μικροῖς πάμπαν καὶ
      <lb/>
      τοῖς ἀναίμοις ἡ γινομένη ἐκ τοῦ περιέχοντος ἢ ὕδατος ἢ ἀέρος
      <lb/>
      ψύξις ἱκανὴ πρὸς τὴν βοήθειαν τῆς φθορᾶς ταύτης·
      <lb/>
      μικρὸν γὰρ ἔχοντα τὸ θερμὸν
						μικρᾶς δέονται τῆς βοηθείας.
      <lb/>
      Διὸ καὶ βραχύβια σχεδὸν πάντα τὰ τοιαῦτ’ ἐστίν· ἐπ’
						ἀμφότερα
      <lb/>
      γὰρ μικρᾶς ὄντα τυγχάνει ῥοπῆς. Ὅσα δὲ μακροβιώτερα
      <lb/>
      τῶν ἐντόμων
						(ἄναιμα γάρ ἐστι πάντα τὰ ἔντομα),
      <lb/>
      τούτοις ὑπὸ τὸ διάζωμα διέσχισται, ὅπως διὰ
						λεπτοτέρου
      <lb/>
      ὄντος τοῦ ὑμένος ψύχηται· μᾶλλον γὰρ ὄντα θερμὰ
      <lb/>
      πλείονος δεῖται τῆς
						καταψύξεως, οἷον αἱ μέλιτται (τῶν γὰρ
      <lb/>
      μελιττῶν ἔνιαι ζῶσι καὶ ἑπτὰ ἔτη) καὶ τἆλλα
						δὲ ὅσα βομβεῖ,
      <lb/>
      οἷον σφῆκες καὶ μηλολόνθαι καὶ τέττιγες. Καὶ γὰρ
      <lb/>
      τὸν ψόφον
						ποιοῦσι πνεύματι, οἷον ἀσθμαίνοντα· ἐν αὐτῷ
      <lb/>
      γὰρ τῷ ὑποζώματι, τῷ ἐμφύτῳ πνεύματι
						αἴροντι καὶ συνίζοντι,
      <lb/>
      συμβαίνει πρὸς τὸν ὑμένα γίνεσθαι τρίψιν· κινοῦσι
      <lb/>
      γὰρ
						τὸν τόπον τοῦτον, ὥσπερ τὰ ἀναπνέοντα ἔξωθεν τῷ
      <lb/>
      πλεύμονι καὶ οἱ ἰχθύες τοῖς
						βραγχίοις. Παραπλήσιον γὰρ
      <lb/>
      συμβαίνει κἂν εἴ τίς τινα τῶν ἀναπνεόντων πνίγοι, τὸ
      <lb/>
      στόμα κατασχών· καὶ γὰρ ταῦτα ποιήσει τῷ πλεύμονι τὴν
      <lb/>
      ἄρσιν ταύτην. Ἀλλὰ
						τούτοις μὲν οὐχ ἱκανὴν ἡ τοιαύτη
      <lb/>
      ποιεῖ κίνησις κατάψυξιν, ἐκείνοις δ’ ἱκανήν. Καὶ
						τῇ τρίψει
      <lb/>
      τῇ πρὸς τὸν ὑμένα ποιοῦσι τὸν βόμβον, ὥσπερ λέγομεν,
      <lb/>
      οἷον διὰ τῶν
						καλάμων τῶν τετρυπημένων τὰ παιδία, ὅταν
      <lb/>
      ἐπιθῶσιν ὑμένα λεπτόν. Διὰ γὰρ τοῦτο καὶ
						τῶν τεττίγων
      <lb/>
      οἱ ᾄδοντες ᾄδουσιν· θερμότεροι γάρ εἰσι, καὶ ἔσχισται αὐτοῖς
      <lb/>
      ὑπὸ
						τὸ ὑπόζωμα· τοῖς δὲ μὴ ᾄδουσι τοῦτ’ ἐστὶν ἄσχιστον.
      <pb n="341"/>
      Καὶ τῶν ἐναίμων δὲ καὶ
						πλεύμονα ἐχόντων, ὀλίγαιμον δ’
      <lb/>
      ἐχόντων καὶ σομφόν, ἔνια διὰ τοῦτο πολὺν χρόνον
						δύνανται
      <lb/>
      ἀπνευστὶ ζῆν, ὅτι ὁ πλεύμων ἄρσιν ἔχει πολλήν, ὀλίγον
      <lb/>
      ἔχων τὸ αἷμα
						καὶ τὸ ὑγρόν· ἡ γὰρ οἰκεία κίνησις ἐπὶ πολὺν
      <lb/>
      χρόνον διαρκεῖ καταψύχουσα. Τέλος δ’
						οὐ δύναται,
      <lb/>
      ἀλλ’ ἀποπνίγεται μὴ ἀναπνεύσαντα, καθάπερ εἴρηται καὶ
      <lb/>
      πρότερον·
						τῆς γὰρ μαράνσεως ἡ διὰ τὸ μὴ ψύχεσθαι φθορὰ
      <lb/>
      καλεῖται πνίξις, καὶ τὰ οὕτω
						φθειρόμενα ἀποπνίγεσθαί
      <lb/>
      φαμεν. Ὅτι δ’ οὐκ ἀναπνεῖ τὰ ἔντομα τῶν ζῴων, εἴρηται
      <lb/>
      μὲν καὶ πρότερον, φανερὸν δὲ καὶ ἐπὶ τῶν μικρῶν ἐστὶ
      <lb/>
      ζῴων, οἷον μυιῶν καὶ
						μελιττῶν· ἐν γὰρ τοῖς ὑγροῖς πολὺν
      <lb/>
      χρόνον ἀνανήχεται, ἂν μὴ λίαν ᾖ θερμὸν ἢ ψυχρόν.
						Καίτοι
      <lb/>
      τὰ μικρὰν ἔχοντα δύναμιν πυκνότερον ζητεῖ ἀναπνεῖν.
      <lb/>
      Ἀλλὰ φθείρεται
						ταῦτα καὶ λέγεται ἀποπνίγεσθαι πληρουμένης
      <lb/>
      τῆς κοιλίας καὶ φθειρομένου τοῦ ἐν τῷ
						ὑποζώματι
      <lb/>
      ὑγροῦ. Διὸ καὶ ἐν τῇ τέφρᾳ χρονισθέντα ἀνίσταται.
      <lb/>
      Καὶ τῶν ἐν τῷ ὑγρῷ
						δὲ ζώντων ὅσα ἄναιμα, πλείω χρόνον
      <lb/>
      ζῇ ἐν τῷ ἀέρι τῶν ἐναίμων καὶ δεχομένων τὴν
						θάλατταν,
      <lb/>
      οἷον τῶν ἰχθύων· διὰ γὰρ τὸ ὀλίγον ἔχειν τὸ θερμὸν ὁ ἀὴρ
      <lb/>
      ἱκανός
						ἐστιν ἐπὶ πολὺν χρόνον καταψύχειν, οἷον τοῖς τε
      <lb/>
      μαλακοστράκοις καὶ τοῖς πολύποσιν.
						Οὐ μὴν εἰς τέλος
      <lb/>
      γε διαρκεῖ πρὸς τὸ ζῆν, διὰ τὸ ὀλιγόθερμα εἶναι, ἐπεὶ
      <lb/>
      καὶ τῶν
						ἰχθύων οἱ πολλοὶ ζῶσιν ἐν τῇ γῇ, ἀκινητίζοντες
      <lb/>
      μέντοι, καὶ εὑρίσκονται ὀρυττόμενοι.
						Ὅσα γὰρ ἢ μηδ’
      <lb/>
      ὅλως ἔχει πλεύμονα ἢ ἄναιμον, ἐλαττονάκις δεῖται
      <lb/>
      καταψύξεως.
     </p>
     <p lang="it">
      Ma delle cose viventi che sono umide, di quelle che sono nella terra, di queste è scritta la tesi
						ai piccoli, e alle anime, la cosa fatta di contenere o acqua o aria
						hai abbastanza freddo per alleviare questa stanchezza, perché hanno poco calore
						i più piccoli hanno bisogno di aiuto. Perché quasi tutto è di breve durata;
						perché entrambi sono piccole creature. Ma gli insetti più longevi
						(poiché tutti gli insetti sono inanimati), questo è incrociato sotto il diazoma, come da
						l'essenza più sottile del calore si raffredda;
						del gelo, che le api (perché la vita delle api è di sette anni) e fiorisce
						ma cosa ronza, dove vespe e meli e vespe. Ma il sogno
						Il cui spirito è colui che respira;
						Ironia e armonia, ti capita di diventare uno strofinaccio;
						questo posto, come le cose che respirano fuori dai polmoni e altre pesci al
						branchie. Perché avviene quasi come se le cose di chi respira fossero soffocate, ts
						bocca delle confische: e queste cose le farà ai polmoni. Ma
						tuttavia, se non è in grado di congelarsi, quelli non lo sono. E
						per strofinarti contro chi è la bomba, come diciamo, chi per il
						come le canne dei bambini storpi, quando ti cercano poco. Anche per questo
						dei quattro, l'ᾄdontes ᾄdusin è più caldo perché lo sono, e si spacca sotto di loro
						i calzoni; ma non vedranno che è intatto.  E del sangue
						molti di quelli che ne avevano, pochi di quelli che ne avevano e sofhon, uno per così tanto tempo
						possono vivere senza respirare, perché l'uomo che nuota ha tanto, ha poco sangue
						e il liquido, perché il movimento intimo dura a lungo congelandosi. fine d'
						non può, ma soffoca senza respirare, come si è detto prima;
						a causa dell'avvizzimento, il decadimento dovuto al mancato raffreddamento è detto pn ixis e così via
						fenomeni di decomposizione e soffocamento. Che gli insetti degli animali non respirano, si dice
						e prima, ed evidentemente anche sugli animaletti, che sono muscolosi e
						di miele; poiché tra le bestie rimane a lungo, sia caldo che freddo.
						Coloro che hanno il piccolo potere più densamente chiedono di respirare. Ma si consuma
						questo si chiama anche soffocamento quando la pancia è piena e stanca
						sottosuolo d'acqua. Perché anche dalle ceneri risorge. E quelli nell'acqua
						ma coloro che vivono come anime, ora vivono nell'aria delle anime e accettano la
						talatano, uno dei pesci: perché l'aria ha il calore per un po'
						Viene congelato a lungo, il che è adatto a chi ha il palato molle e a chi ha molto appetito.
						Non dura per tutta la vita, a causa dell'oligotermo che è, oltretutto
						Molti pesci vivono sulla terra, immobilizzando le zecche, e vengono ritrovati sepolti.
						Dopotutto, che abbia o meno i polmoni o l'anemia essendo, gli ellatonakis possono essere visti congelati.
     </p>
     <p lang="en">
      But about the living things that are moist, the things that are in the earth, the thesis is written, of these
						to the little ones, and to the souls, the thing made of containing either water or air
						you are cold enough to help this weariness, for they have little heat
						little ones need help. Because almost everything is short-lived; on
						because both of them are small creatures. But the longer-lived insects
						(since all insects are inanimate), this one is crossed under the diazoma, as by
						the finer being of the heat is cooled;
						of freezing, which the bees (for the life of the bees is seven years) and flowers
						but what is buzzing, where wasps and apple trees and wasps. But the dream
						Whose spirit is he who breathes;
						Irony and harmony, it happens to you that you become a rub; for move
						this place, like the things that breathe outside the lungs and others fishes to the
						gills. For it happens almost as if the things of the breathing ones are suffocated, ts
						mouth of confiscations: and he will do these things to the lungs. But
						however, if she is not capable of freezing, those are not. And
						to rub in towards you who is the bomb, as we say, who for the
						like reeds of the crippled children, when they seek you thinly. Because of this too
						of the four, the ᾄdontes ᾄdusin; warmer because they are, and it splits under them
						the breeches; but they shall not see that it is uncut.  And of the blood
						many of those who had, few of those who had and sofhon, one for this long time
						they can live without breathing, because the man who swims has a lot, he has little blood
						and the liquid, because intimate movement lasts for a long time freezing. end d'
						he cannot, but suffocates without breathing, as was said before;
						because of wilting, the decay due to not being cooled is called pn ixis, and so on
						decaying suffocating phenomena. That the insects of the animals do not breathe, it is said
						and before, and evidently also on the little animals, which are muscular and
						of honey; for among the beasts it lingers for a long time, whether it be hot or cold.
						Those who have the small power more densely ask to breathe. But it wears out
						this is also called suffocation when the belly is full and worn out
						underbody of water. For even in the ashes he is resurrected. And those in the water
						but those who live as souls, now live in the air of souls and accepting the
						thalatan, one of the fishes: for the air has the heat for a little
						It is frozen for a long time, which is suitable for those with a soft palate and those with a lot of appetite.
						It doesn't end up lasting for life, because of the oligotherm it is, on top of the
						Many fishes live on the earth, immobilizing mints, and they are found being buried.
						After all, whether or not he has lungs or anemia being, ellatonakis can be seen frozen.
     </p>
    </div>
    <pb n="342"/>
    <div n="10" subtype="chapter" type="textpart">
     <p>
      Περὶ μὲν οὖν τῶν ἀναίμων, ὅτι τοῖς μὲν ὁ περιέχων ἀὴρ
      <lb/>
      τοῖς δὲ τὸ ὑγρὸν βοηθεῖ πρὸς
						τὴν ζωήν, εἴρηται· τοῖς
      <lb/>
      δ’ ἐναίμοις καὶ τοῖς ἔχουσι καρδίαν, ὅσα μὲν ἔχει πλεύμονα,
      <lb/>
      πάντα δέχεται τὸν ἀέρα καὶ τὴν κατάψυξιν ποιεῖται
      <lb/>
      διὰ τοῦ ἀναπνεῖν καὶ
						ἐκπνεῖν. Ἔχει δὲ πλεύμονα τά τε
      <lb/>
      ζῳοτοκοῦντα ἐν αὑτοῖς καὶ μὴ θύραζε μόνον (τὰ γὰρ
						σελάχη
      <lb/>
      ζῳοτοκεῖ μέν, ἀλλ’ οὐκ ἐν αὑτοῖς) καὶ τῶν ᾠοτοκούντων
      <lb/>
      τά τε πτερυγωτά,
						οἷον ὄρνιθες, καὶ τὰ φολιδωτά, οἷον
      <lb/>
      χελῶναι καὶ σαῦραι καὶ ὄφεις. Ἐκεῖνα μὲν οὖν
						ἔναιμον,
      <lb/>
      τούτων δὲ τὰ πλεῖστα τὸν πλεύμονα ἔχει σομφόν. Διὸ καὶ
      <lb/>
      τῇ ἀναπνοῇ
						χρῆται μανότερον, ὥσπερ εἴρηται καὶ πρότερον.
      <lb/>
      Χρῆται δὲ πάντα καὶ ὅσα διατρίβει καὶ
						ποιεῖται τὸν
      <lb/>
      βίον ἐν τοῖς ὕδασιν, οἷον τὸ τῶν ὕδρων γένος καὶ βατράχων
      <lb/>
      καὶ
						κροκοδείλων καὶ ἑμύδων καὶ χελῶναι αἵ τε θαλάττιαι
      <lb/>
      καὶ αἱ χερσαῖαι καὶ φῶκαι· ταῦτα
						γὰρ πάντα
      <lb/>
      καὶ τὰ τοιαῦτα καὶ τίκτει ἐν τῷ ξηρῷ, καὶ καθεύδει ἢ ἐν
      <lb/>
      τῷ ξηρῷ, ἢ
						ἐν τῷ ὑγρῷ ὑπερέχοντα τὸ στόμα διὰ τὴν ἀναπνοήν.
      <lb/>
      Ὅσα δὲ βράγχια ἔχει, πάντα
						καταψύχεται δεχόμενα
      <lb/>
      τὸ ὕδωρ· ἔχει δὲ βράγχια τὸ τῶν καλουμένων σελαχῶν
      <lb/>
      γένος
						καὶ τῶν ἄλλων ἀπόδων. Ἄποδες δ’ οἱ ἰχθύες
      <lb/>
      πάντες· καὶ γὰρ ἃ ἔχει, καθ’ ὁμοιότητα
						τῶν πτερυγίων
      <lb/>
      ἔχουσιν. Τῶν δὲ πόδας ἐχόντων ἓν ἔχει βράγχιον μόνον
      <lb/>
      τῶν
						τεθεωρημένων ὁ καλούμενος κορδύλος. Ἅμα δὲ πλεύμονα
      <lb/>
      καὶ βράγχια οὐδὲν ὦπταί πω
						ἔχον. Αἴτιον δ’ ὅτι ὁ
      <lb/>
      μὲν πλεύμων τῆς ὑπὸ τοῦ πνεύματος καταψύξεως ἕνεκέν ἐστιν
      <lb/>
      (ἔοικε δὲ καὶ τοὔνομα εἰληφέναι ὁ πνεύμων διὰ τὴν τοῦ
      <pb n="343"/>
      πνεύματος
						ὑποδοχήν), τὰ δὲ βράγχια πρὸς τὴν ἀπὸ τοῦ
      <lb/>
      ὕδατος κατάψυξιν· ἓν δ’ ἐφ’ ἓν ὄργανον
						χρήσιμον, καὶ
      <lb/>
      μία κατάψυξις ἱκανὴ πᾶσιν. Ὤστ’ ἐπεὶ μάτην οὐδὲν ὁρῶμεν
      <lb/>
      ποιοῦσαν
						τὴν φύσιν, δυοῖν δ’ ὄντοιν θάτερον ἂν ἦν μάτην,
      <lb/>
      διὰ τοῦτο τὰ μὲν ἔχει βράγχια τὰ δὲ
						πνεύμονα, ἄμφω δ’
      <lb/>
      οὐδέν.
     </p>
     <p lang="it">
      Quanto alle anime, perché a loro il contenuto dell'aria, ma a loro il liquido aiuta
						la vita, si dice; a coloro che hanno sangue e a coloro che hanno un cuore, quanti hanno polmoni,
						accetta sempre l'aria e il congelamento viene effettuato in modo che possa respirare
						espirare Ma lui ha un polmone, gli esseri viventi nelle orecchie, e non solo li portava (perché
						selahi vive con me, ma non in loro) e di coloro che vivono con le ali,
						che galline, e quelle squamose, che tartarughe e lucertole e tu vedi. Ecco, allora
						ventoso, ma la maggior parte di loro ha i polmoni. A causa della respirazione
						è necessario un genitore, come accennato in precedenza. Ma è sempre necessario, e qualunque cosa lo dimostra
						la vita nelle acque, che è il genere delle acque e delle rane e
						di coccodrilli, mitili e tartarughe così che gli animali dei mari e della terra e le foche;
						perché anche tutto e così ticchetta nell'asciutto, e si siede nell'asciutto, o
						nell'acqua rimasta in bocca per respirare. Quanto a non importa, sempre
						ghiaccia quando riceve acqua; è dotato di branchie, il genere dei cosiddetti selaci
						e gli altri modi. Apodes 4 tutti i pesci: e ciò che ha, a somiglianza
						delle ali che hanno. E di quelli che hanno le gambe, solo quelli hanno le branchie
						considerato il cosiddetto nastro. Per quanto riguarda i polmoni e le branchie, non sento niente
						loro hanno Il motivo 4 è che colui che naviga con lo spirito del congelamento è uno
						(Ma la casa e la casa dello spirito sono estatiche a causa dello spirito
						ricezione) e le branchie verso il congelamento dall'acqua;
						utile e basta un congelatore. In realtà non sappiamo chi fossero
						natura, due non sarebbero morti se fosse morto, per questo ha branchie e
						polmone, amfo d'nessuno.
     </p>
     <p lang="en">
      As for souls, because to them the content of air, but to them liquid helps to
						life, it is said; to those who have blood and to those who have a heart, as many as have lungs,
						it always accepts the air and the freezing is done so that it can breathe
						exhale But he has a lung, the living things in his ears, and he did not only carry them (because
						selahi lives with me, but not in them) and of those who live with wings,
						which hens, and the scaly ones, which turtles and lizards and you see. There, then
						windy, but most of them have the lungs. Because of breathing
						a parent is needed, as mentioned earlier. But it is always necessary, and whatever it is that proves it
						the life in the waters, which is the genus of waters and frogs and
						of crocodiles and mussels and turtles so that the seas and the land animals and seals; these
						for everything and such also ticks in the dry, and sits either in the dry, or
						in the water remaining in the mouth for breathing. As for never mind, always
						it freezes when it receives water; it has gills, the genus of the so-called selachians
						and the other ways. Apodes 4 the fishes all: and what he has, in likeness
						of the wings they have. And of those who have legs, only those have gills
						considered the so-called ribbon. As for lungs and gills, I can't hear anything
						they have Reason 4 is that the one who sails under the spirit of freezing is one
						(But the house and the house of the spirit are ecstatic because of the spirit
						reception), and the gills towards freezing from the water;
						useful, and a freezer is enough. In fact, we don't know who they were
						nature, two would not be dead if it were dead, for this reason it has gills and
						lung, amfo d' none.
     </p>
    </div>
    <div n="11" subtype="chapter" type="textpart">
     <p>
      Ἐπεὶ δὲ πρὸς μὲν τὸ εἶναι τροφῆς δεῖται τῶν ζῴων
      <lb/>
      ἕκαστον, πρὸς δὲ τὴν σωτηρίαν τῆς
						καταψύξεως, τῷ αὐτῷ
      <lb/>
      ὀργάνῳ χρῆται πρὸς ἄμφω ταῦτα ἡ φύσις, καθάπερ ἐνίοις
      <lb/>
      τῇ
						γλώττῃ πρός τε τοὺς χυμοὺς καὶ πρὸς τὴν ἑρμηνείαν,
      <lb/>
      οὕτω τοῖς ἔχουσι τὸν πλεύμονα τῷ
						καλουμένῳ στόματι
      <lb/>
      πρός τε τὴν τῆς τροφῆς ἐργασίαν καὶ τὴν ἐκπνοὴν καὶ τὴν
      <lb/>
      ἀναπνοήν. Τοῖς δὲ μὴ ἔχουσι πνεύμονα μηδ’ ἀναπνέουσι τὸ
      <lb/>
      μὲν στόμα πρὸς τὴν
						ἐργασίαν τῆς τροφῆς, πρὸς δὲ τὴν
      <lb/>
      κατάψυξιν τοῖς δεομένοις καταψύξεως ἡ τῶν βραγχίων
      <lb/>
      ὑπάρχει φύσις. Πῶς μὲν οὖν ἡ τῶν εἰρημένων ὀργάνων
      <lb/>
      δύναμις ποιεῖ τὴν
						κατάψυξιν, ὕστερον ἐροῦμεν. Πρὸς δὲ
      <lb/>
      τὸ τὴν τροφὴν μὴ διακωλύειν παραπλησίως τοῖς τ’
						ἀναπνέουσι
      <lb/>
      συμβαίνει καὶ τοῖς δεχομένοις τὸ ὑγρόν· οὔτε γὰρ
      <lb/>
      ἀναπνέοντες ἅμα
						καταδέχονται τὴν τροφήν· εἰ δὲ μή, συμβαίνει
      <lb/>
      πνίγεσθαι παρεισιούσης τῆς τροφῆς ἢ
						τῆς ὑγρᾶς
      <lb/>
      ἢ τῆς ξηρᾶς ἐπὶ τὸν πνεύμονα διὰ τῆς ἀρτηρίας· πρότερον
      <lb/>
      γὰρ κεῖται ἡ
						ἀρτηρία τοῦ οἰσοφάγου, δι’ οὖ ἡ τροφὴ πορεύεται
      <lb/>
      εἰς τὴν καλουμένην κοιλίαν. Τοῖς
						μὲν οὖν τετράποσι
      <lb/>
      καὶ ἐναίμοις ἔχει ἡ ἀρτηρία οἷον πῶμα τὴν ἐπιγλωττίδα·
      <lb/>
      τοῖς
						δ’ ὄρνισι καὶ τῶν τετραπόδων τοῖς ᾠοτόκοις οὐκ ἔπεστιν,
      <lb/>
      ἀλλὰ τῇ συναγωγῇ τὸ αὐτὸ
						ποιοῦσιν· δεχόμενα γὰρ
      <lb/>
      τὴν τροφὴν τὰ μὲν συνάγει, τὰ δ’ ἐπιτίθησι τὴν ἐπιγλωττίδα.
      <lb/>
      Προελθούσης δὲ τὰ μὲν ἐπαίρει, τὰ δὲ διοίγει καὶ
      <pb n="344"/>
      καταδέχεται τὸ
						πνεῦμα πρὸς τὴν κατάψυξιν. Τὰ δ’ ἔχοντα
      <lb/>
      βράγχια, ἀφέντα διὰ τούτων τὸ ὑγρόν, διὰ
						τοῦ στόματος
      <lb/>
      καταδέχεται τὴν τροφήν· ἀρτηρίαν μὲν γὰρ οὐκ ἔχουσιν,
      <lb/>
      ὥστε ταύτῃ
						μὲν οὐθὲν ἂν βλάπτοιντο ὑπὸ τῆς τοῦ ὑγροῦ
      <lb/>
      παρεμπτώσεως, ἀλλ’ εἰς τὴν κοιλίαν
						εἰσιόντος. Διὸ ταχεῖαν
      <lb/>
      ποιεῖται τὴν ἄφεσιν καὶ τὴν λῆψιν τῆς τροφῆς, καὶ τοὺς
      <lb/>
      ὀδόντας ὀξεῖς ἔχουσι, καὶ καρχαρόδοντες σχεδὸν πάντες
      <lb/>
      εἰσίν· οὐ γὰρ ἐνδέχεται
						λεαίνειν τὴν τροφήν.
     </p>
     <p lang="it">
      E quando verso di me si vede il cibo di ciascuno degli animali, ma verso la salvezza degli
						del congelamento, a quest'organo è richiesta la natura per entrambi, come talvolta
						parlano con i succhi e con l'interpretazione, quindi hanno i polmoni per farlo
						bocca invitata al lavoro del cibo e dell'espirazione e
						respirazione Ma non hanno polmoni, non respirano con la bocca
						lavorazione degli alimenti e per il congelamento delle branchie
						c'è la natura. Come fa dunque la potenza degli organi separati?
						Congelatore, arriveremo più tardi. Per quanto riguarda il cibo, non interferire con il
						respirano, succede anche a chi riceve il liquido;
						accettano il cibo; in caso contrario, c'è soffocamento del cibo o
						dell'umido o del secco sul polmone presso l'arteria;
						arteria dell'esofago, quindi il cibo viaggia verso i calumeni e Olio. A loro
						ma l'arteria che chiude l'epiglottide ha quattro vasi sanguigni;
						f uccelli e quadrupedi non cadono negli ᾠotokoi, ma nella sinagoga
						chi sono, poiché accettando il cibo, deducono che attaccano l'epiglottide.
						Quando viene, li prende, li dirige e li accoglie
						spirito verso il congelatore. I quattro hanno le branchie, attraverso le quali scorre il liquido
						della bocca riceve il cibo; perché non hanno arteria, quindi
						a meno che non sia stato danneggiato dalla penetrazione del fluido, ma nell'addome
						entrando Perché il dare e prendere il cibo avviene velocemente, e il
						hanno denti aguzzi e quasi tutti hanno denti di squalo;
						mangiano il cibo.
     </p>
     <p lang="en">
      And when towards me the food is seen of each of the animals, but towards the salvation of the
						of freezing, to this organ nature is required for both of these, as sometimes
						speak to the juices and to the interpretation, so they have the lungs to the
						invited mouth to the work of food and exhalation and
						breathing But they have no lungs, they do not breathe with their mouths to the
						processing of the food, and for the freezing of the gills
						there is nature. How, then, does the power of the separated organs do it?
						Freezer, we will come later. As for the food, do not interfere with the
						they breathe, it also happens to those who receive the liquid;
						they accept the food; if not, there is choking of the food or
						of the wet or of the dry on the lung by the artery; for first lies the
						artery of the esophagus, so the food travels to the calumeni and Oil. To them
						but the artery that closes the epiglottis has four blood vessels;
						f fowls and quadrupeds do not fall to the ᾠotokoi, but to the synagogue
						who are they, for by accepting the food, they infer that they attack the epiglottis.
						When he comes, he takes them, he directs them and accepts them
						spirit towards the freezer. The four having gills, through which the liquid
						of the mouth receives food; for they have no artery, so that
						unless it was damaged by the penetration of the fluid, but in the abdomen
						entering Because the giving and taking of food is done quickly, and the
						they have sharp teeth, and they are almost all shark-toothed;
						they eat the food.
     </p>
    </div>
    <div n="12" subtype="chapter" type="textpart">
     <p>
      Περὶ δὲ τὰ κητώδη τῶν ἐνύδρων ἀπορήσειεν ἄν τις, ἔχει
      <lb/>
      δὲ κἀκεῖνα κατὰ λόγον, οἷον
						περί τε τοὺς δελφῖνας καὶ
      <lb/>
      τὰς φαλαίνας, καὶ τῶν ἄλλων ὅσα ἔχει τὸν καλούμενον
						αὐλόν.
      <lb/>
      Ταῦτα γὰρ ἄποδα μέν ἐστιν, ἔχοντα δὲ πνεύμονα
      <lb/>
      δέχεται τὴν θάλατταν.
						Αἴτιον δὲ τούτου τὸ νῦν εἰρημένον·
      <lb/>
      οὐ γὰρ καταψύξεως ἕνεκεν δέχεται τὸ ὑγρόν. Τοῦτο
      <lb/>
      μὲν γὰρ γίνεται αὐτοῖς ἀναπνέουσιν· ἔχουσι γὰρ πλεύμονα.
      <lb/>
      Διὸ καὶ καθεύδουσιν
						ὑπερέχοντα τὸ στόμα, καὶ
      <lb/>
      ῥέγχουσιν οἵ γε δελφῖνες. Ἔτι δὲ κἂν ληφθῶσι τοῖς
      <lb/>
      δικτύοις, ταχὺ ἀποπνίγονται διὰ τὸ μὴ ἀναπνεῖν· καὶ ἐπιπολάζοντα
      <lb/>
      φαίνεται τὰ
						τοιαῦτα ἐπὶ τῆς θαλάττης διὰ τὴν
      <lb/>
      ἀναπνοήν. Ἀλλ’ ἐπειδὴ ἀναγκαῖον ποιεῖσθαι τὴν
						τροφὴν
      <lb/>
      ἐν ὑγρῷ, ἀναγκαῖον δεχόμενα τὸ ὑγρὸν ἀφιέναι, καὶ διὰ
      <lb/>
      τοῦτ’ ἔχουσι
						πάντα τὸν αὐλόν· δεξάμενα γὰρ τὸ ὕδωρ,
      <lb/>
      ὥσπερ οἱ ἰχθύες κατὰ τὰ βράγχια, ταῦτα κατὰ
						τὸν
      <lb/>
      αὐλόν, ἀνασπᾷ τὸ ὕδωρ. Σημεῖον δὲ καὶ ἡ θέσις τοῦ αὐλοῦ·
      <lb/>
      πρὸς οὐθὲν γὰρ
						περαίνει τῶν ἐναίμων, ἀλλὰ πρὸ τοῦ ἐγκεφάλου
      <lb/>
      τὴν θέσιν ἔχει, καὶ ἀφίησι τὸ ὕδωρ.
						Διὰ ταὐτὸ δὲ
      <lb/>
      τοῦτο δέχεται καὶ τὰ μαλάκια τὸ ὕδωρ καὶ τὰ μαλακόστρακα,
      <lb/>
      λέγω δ’
						οἷον τοὺς καλουμένους καράβους καὶ τοὺς
      <lb/>
      καρκίνους. Καταψύξεως μὲν γὰρ αὐτῶν οὐδὲν
						τυγχάνει δεόμενον·
      <pb n="345"/>
      ὀλιγόθερμον γάρ ἐστι καὶ ἄναιμον ἕκαστον αὐτῶν,
      <lb/>
      ὥσθ’ ἱκανῶς καταψύχεται ὑπὸ τοῦ περιέχοντος ὑγροῦ· ἀλλὰ
      <lb/>
      διὰ τὴν τροφήν, ὅπως
						μὴ ἅμα δεχομένοις εἰσρέῃ τὸ ὑγρόν.
      <lb/>
      Τὰ μὲν οὖν μαλακόστρακα, οἷον οἵ τε καρκίνοι καὶ
						οἱ κάραβοι,
      <lb/>
      παρὰ τὰ δασέα ἀφιᾶσι τὸ ὕδωρ διὰ τῶν ἐπιπτυγμάτων,
      <lb/>
      σηπίαι δὲ καὶ
						πολύποδες διὰ τοῦ κοίλου τοῦ ὑπὲρ τῆς
      <lb/>
      καλουμένης κεφαλῆς. Γέγραπται δὲ περὶ αὐτῶν
						δι’ ἀκριβείας
      <lb/>
      μᾶλλον ἐν ταῖς περὶ τῶν ζῴων ἱστορίαις. Περὶ
      <lb/>
      μὲν οὖν τοῦ
						δέχεσθαι τὸ ὑγρόν, εἴρηται ὅτι συμβαίνει διὰ
      <lb/>
      κατάψυξιν καὶ διὰ τὸ δεῖν δέχεσθαι τὴν
						τροφὴν ἐκ τοῦ
      <lb/>
      ὑγροῦ τὰ τὴν φύσιν ὄντα τῶν ζῴων ἔνυδρα.
     </p>
     <p lang="it">
      Per quanto riguarda i cetacei acquatici, chissà se lo sono, ma ce ne sono alcuni a ragione,
						sui delfini e sulle balene e sugli altri che hanno i cosiddetti
						AọLON. Perché queste cose vengono da me, ma avendo un polmone, accetta il talatano.
						Il motivo è che il liquido non può congelare. Questo
						poiché non è loro possibile respirare, poiché hanno polmoni. Perché si siedono
						sovrastante la foce, e rhenchousin dove ci sono i delfini. E se gli venisse portato via?
						reti, soffocano presto perché non respirano e il
						quindi sulla spiaggia per respirare. Ma per necessità si fa
						cibo in liquidi, accettando necessariamente il liquido che bevono, e per questo hanno
						sempre le branchie;
						l'avlon, abbraccia l'acqua. E anche la posizione del cortile è un segno;
						passa attraverso il sangue, ma ha il suo posto vicino al cervello, e lascia che il acqua.
						Per questo motivo accetta anche molluschi, acqua e crostacei, dico d'
						che chiamava le navi e i granchi. Non c'è congelamento senza di loro
						succede a ciascuno di loro,
						in modo che sia sufficientemente congelato dal liquido contenuto ma dal cibo, come
						Non lasciare entrare l'acqua se ricevuta. Cosa sono i crostacei, cosa sono i tumori
						le navi, malgrado le onde, lasciano passare l'acqua attraverso le vele, e dormono anche
						polipi attraverso la cavità della cosiddetta testa. È scritto su di loro
						per accuratezza piuttosto nelle storie sui vivi. Su di me allora
						accetta il liquido, si dice che avvenga per congelamento e per questo accetta il
						cibo dal liquido, le creature della natura sono umide.
     </p>
     <p lang="en">
      As for the aquatic cetaceans, I wonder if they are, but there are some according to reason,
						about the dolphins and the whales, and about the others that have the so-called
						AọLON. For these things are from me, but having a lung, he accepts the thalatan.
						The reason for this is that the liquid is not allowed to freeze. This
						for it is not possible for them to breathe; for they have lungs. Because they sit down
						overhanging the mouth, and rhenchousin where there are dolphins. What if it is taken from them
						nets, they quickly suffocate because they do not breathe; and the
						so on the beach for breathing. But because of necessity it is done
						food in liquid, necessarily accepting the liquid they drink, and because of this they have
						always the gills;
						the avlon, embraces the water. And the position of the courtyard is also a sign;
						it passes through the blood, but it has its place near the brain, and let the water.
						For this reason, this also accepts molluscs, water and crustaceans, I say d'
						who called the ships and the crabs. There is no freezing without them
						it happens to each one of them,
						so that it is sufficiently frozen by the contained liquid; but by the food, as
						Do not let the water enter if received. What are crustaceans, what are cancers
						the ships, in spite of the waves, let the water through the sails, and sleep also
						polyps through the cavity of the so-called head. It is written about them
						for accuracy rather in the stories about the living. About me then
						it accepts the liquid, it is said that it happens due to freezing and because of that it accepts the
						food from the liquid, the creatures of the nature are moist.
     </p>
    </div>
    <div n="13" subtype="chapter" type="textpart">
     <p>
      Περὶ δὲ τῆς καταψύξεως, τίνα γίνεται τρόπον τοῖς τ’
      <lb/>
      ἀναπνέουσι καὶ τοῖς ἔχουσι
						βράγχια, μετὰ ταῦτα λεκτέον.
      <lb/>
      Ὅτι μὲν οὖν ἀναπνέουσιν ὅσα πνεύμονα τῶν ζῴων ἔχουσι,
      <lb/>
      πρότερον εἴρηται. Διὰ τί δὲ τοῦτο τὸ μόριον ἔχουσιν
      <lb/>
      ἔνια, καὶ διὰ τί τὰ ἔχοντα
						δεῖται τῆς ἀναπνοῆς, αἴτιον τοῦ
      <lb/>
      μὲν ἔχειν ὅτι τὰ τιμιώτερα τῶν ζῴων πλείονος
						τετύχηκε
      <lb/>
      θερμότητος· ἅμα γὰρ ἀνάγκη καὶ ψυχῆς τετυχηκέναι τιμιωτέρας·
      <lb/>
      τιμιώτερα γὰρ τὰ τοιαῦτα τῆς φύσεως τῆς τῶν φυτῶν.
      <lb/>
      Διὸ καὶ τὰ μάλιστα ἔναιμον
						ἔχοντα τὸν πνεύμονα καὶ
      <lb/>
      θερμὸν μείζονά τε τοῖς μεγέθεσι, καὶ τό γε καθαρωτάτῳ
      <lb/>
      καὶ πλείστῳ κεχρημένον αἵματι τῶν ζῴων ὀρθότατόν
      <lb/>
      ἐστιν ὁ ἄνθρωπος, καὶ τὸ ἄνω
						πρὸς τὸ τοῦ ὅλου ἄνω ἔχει
      <lb/>
      μόνον διὰ τὸ τοιοῦτον ἔχειν τοῦτο τὸ μόριον. Ὥστε τῆς
      <lb/>
      οὐσίας καὶ τούτῳ καὶ τοῖς ἄλλοις θετέον αἴτιον αὐτό, καθάπερ
      <lb/>
      ὁτιοῦν ἄλλο τῶν
						μορίων. Ἔχει μὲν οὖν ἕνεκα τούτου.
      <lb/>
      Τὴν δ’ ἐξ ἀνάγκης καὶ τῆς κινήσεως αἰτίαν καὶ τὰ
						τοιαῦτα
      <pb n="346"/>
      νομίζειν συνεστάναι ζῷα, καθάπερ καὶ μὴ τοιαῦτα πολλὰ
      <lb/>
      συνέστηκεν· τὰ μὲν γὰρ ἐκ γῆς πλείονος γέγονεν, οἷον τὸ
      <lb/>
      τῶν φυτῶν γένος, τὰ δ’
						ἐξ ὕδατος, οἷον τὸ τῶν ἐνύδρων·
      <lb/>
      τῶν δὲ πτηνῶν καὶ πεζῶν τὰ μὲν ἐξ ἀέρος τὰ δ’ ἐκ
						πυρός.
      <lb/>
      Ἕκαστα δ’ ἐν τοῖς οἰκείοις τόποις ἔχει τὴν τάξιν αὐτῶν.
     </p>
     <p lang="it">
      Quanto al congelamento, diventa un modo per chi lo respira e per chi ce l’ha
						branchie, dopo questa lezione. Perché poi respirano tanti polmoni quanti ne hanno gli animali,
						precedentemente citato. Perché hanno questa molecola e perché l'hanno avuta?
						si vede del respiro, perché mi hanno che il più nobile degli esseri viventi
						si scioglieva nel calore; perché se il bisogno e l'anima fossero resi più onorevoli
						poiché più onorevoli sono quelli della natura delle piante. Perché sta addirittura piovendo
						avendo il polmone e il calore maggiori dei grandi e dei puri
						e per la maggior parte il sangue degli animali utilizzati è quello dell'uomo retto, e quanto sopra
						verso il tutto sopra ha solo perché ha questa particella. È lei
						a questo e agli altri non va data alcuna ragione, poiché fanno altro che
						molecole. Ha una ragione per questo. Il d' per necessità e la causa del movimento e il
						in questo pensano che consista la vita, ma non così tanto
						co nesteken; per le cose che vennero dalla terra, come il genere delle piante, i quattro
						dall'acqua, che è quella degli animali acquatici; e degli uccelli e dei pedoni, uno dall'aria, l'altro dall'aria
						fuoco. Ciascuno dei luoghi familiari ha la sua classe.
     </p>
     <p lang="en">
      As for freezing, it becomes a way for those who breathe it and those who have it
						gills, after this lecteon. Because then they breathe as many lungs as the animals have,
						previously mentioned. Why do they have this molecule, and why did they have it?
						is seen of breathing, because they have me that the noblest of living things
						he melted into warmth; for if need and soul were made more honorable
						for more honorable are those of the nature of plants. Because it's even raining
						having the lung and heat greater than the great, and the pure
						and for the most part the blood of animals used is the upright man, and the above
						towards the whole above it has only because it has this particle. It's her
						no reason should be given to this and to the others, as they do other than
						molecules. He has one reason for this. The d' out of necessity and the cause of the movement and the
						that's what they think life consists of, but not so much
						co nesteken; for the things that came from the earth, like the genus of plants, the four
						from water, which is that of aquatic animals; and of birds and pedestrians, one from air, the other from
						fire. Each of the familiar places has its class.
     </p>
    </div>
    <div n="14" subtype="chapter" type="textpart">
     <p>
      Ἐμπεδοκλῆς δ’ οὐ καλῶς τοῦτ’ εἴρηκε, φάσκων τὰ θερμότατα
      <lb/>
      καὶ πῦρ ἔχοντα πλεῖστον
						τῶν ζῴων ἔνυδρα εἶναι,
      <lb/>
      φεύγοντα τὴν ὑπερβολὴν τῆς ἐν τῇ φύσει θερμότητος, ὅπως
      <lb/>
      ἐπειδὴ τοῦ ψυχροῦ καὶ τοῦ ὑγροῦ ἐλλείπει, κατὰ τὸν τόπον
      <lb/>
      ἀνασώζηται ἐναντία
						ὄντα· θερμὸν γὰρ εἶναι τὸ ὑγρὸν
      <lb/>
      ἧττον τοῦ ἀέρος. Ὅλως μὲν οὖν ἄτοπον πῶς ἐνδέχεται
      <lb/>
      γενόμενον ἕκαστον αὐτῶν ἐν τῷ ξηρῷ μεταβάλλειν τὸν
      <lb/>
      τόπον εἰς τὸ ὑγρόν· σχεδὸν
						γὰρ καὶ ἄποδα τὰ πλεῖστα
      <lb/>
      αὐτῶν ἐστίν. Ὁ δὲ τὴν ἐξ ἀρχῆς αὐτῶν σύστασιν λέγων
      <lb/>
      γενέσθαι μὲν ἐν τῷ ξηρῷ φησί, φεύγοντα δ’ ἐλθεῖν εἰς τὸ
      <lb/>
      ὑγρόν. Ἔτι δ’ οὔτε
						φαίνεται θερμότερα ὄντα τῶν πεζῶν·
      <lb/>
      τὰ μὲν γὰρ ἄναιμα πάμπαν, τὰ δ’ ὀλίγαιμα αὐτῶν
      <lb/>
      ἐστίν. Ἀλλὰ ποῖα μὲν δεῖ λέγειν θερμὰ καὶ ψυχρά, καθ’
      <lb/>
      αὑτὰ τὴν ἐπίσκεψιν
						εἴληφεν· περὶ δ’ ἧς αἰτίας εἴρηκεν Ἐμπεδοκλῆς,
      <lb/>
      τῇ μὲν ἔχει τὸ ζητούμενον λόγον, οὐ
						μὴν ὅ γε
      <lb/>
      φησὶν ἐκεῖνος ἀληθές. Τῶν μὲν γὰρ ἕξεων τὰς ὑπερβολὰς
      <lb/>
      ἔχοντας οἱ
						ἐναντίοι τόποι καὶ ὧραι σώζουσιν, ἡ δὲ φύσις
      <lb/>
      ἐν τοῖς οἰκείοις σώζεται μάλιστα
						τόποις. Οὐ γὰρ ταὐτὸν
      <lb/>
      ἥ θ’ ὕλη τῶν ζῴων ἐξ ἧς ἐστὶν ἕκαστον, καὶ αἱ ἕξεις καὶ
      <lb/>
      διαθέσεις αὐτῆς. Λέγω δ’ οἷον εἴ τι ἐκ κηροῦ συστήσειεν
      <pb n="347"/>
      ἡ φύσις, οὐκ
						ἂν ἐν θερμῷ θεῖσα διέσωσεν, οὐδ’ εἴ τι ἐκ κρυστάλλου·
      <lb/>
      ἐφθάρη γὰρ ἂν ταχὺ διὰ
						τοὐναντίον· τήκει γὰρ
      <lb/>
      τὸ θερμὸν τὸ ὑπὸ τοῦ ἐναντίου συστάν. Οὐδ’ εἴ τι ἐξ ἁλὸς
      <lb/>
      ἢ νίτρου συνέστησεν, οὐκ ἂν εἰς ὑγρὸν φέρουσα κατέθηκεν·
      <lb/>
      φθείρει γὰρ τὰ ὑπὸ
						θερμοῦ καὶ ξηροῦ συστάντα τὸ ὑγρόν.
      <lb/>
      Εἰ οὖν ὕλη πᾶσι τοῖς σώμασι τὸ ὑγρὸν καὶ τὸ
						ξηρόν,
      <lb/>
      εὐλόγως τὰ μὲν ἐξ ὑγροῦ καὶ ψυχροῦ συστάντα ἐν ὑγροῖς
      <lb/>
      ἐστί, καὶ εἰ
						ψυχρά, ἔσται ἐν ψυχρῷ, τὰ δ’ ἐκ ξηροῦ ἐν
      <lb/>
      ξηρῷ. Διὰ τοῦτο τὰ δένδρα οὐκ ἐν ὕδατι
						φύεται, ἀλλ’ ἐν
      <lb/>
      τῇ γῇ. Καί τοι τοῦ αὐτοῦ λόγου ἐστὶν εἰς τὸ ὕδωρ, διὰ
      <lb/>
      τὸ εἶναι
						αὐτὰ ὑπέρξηρα, ὥσπερ τὰ ὑπέρπυρά φησιν ἐκεῖνος·
      <lb/>
      οὐ γὰρ διὰ τὸ ψυχρὸν ἦλθεν εἰς
						αὐτό, ἀλλ’ ὅτι ὑγρόν.
      <lb/>
      Αἱ μὲν οὖν φύσεις τῆς ὕλης, ἐν οἵῳπερ τόπῳ εἰσί, τοιαῦται
      <lb/>
      οὖσαι τυγχάνουσιν, αἱ μὲν ἐν ὕδατι ὑγραί, αἱ δ’ ἐν τῇ γῇ
      <lb/>
      ξηραί, αἱ δ’ ἐν τῷ
						ἀέρι θερμαί. Αἱ μέντοι ἕξεις αἱ μὲν
      <lb/>
      ὑπερβάλλουσαι θερμότητι ἐν ψυχρῷ, αἱ δὲ τῇ
						ψυχρότητι ἐν
      <lb/>
      θερμῷ τιθέμεναι σώζονται μᾶλλον· ἐπανισοῖ γὰρ εἰς τὸ
      <lb/>
      μέτριον ὁ
						τόπος τὴν τῆς ἕξεως ὑπερβολήν. Τοῦτο μὲν
      <lb/>
      οὖν δεῖ ζητεῖν ἐν τοῖς οἰκείοις τόποις
						ἑκάστης ὕλης, καὶ
      <lb/>
      κατὰ τὰς μεταβολὰς τῆς κοινῆς ὥρας· τὰς μὲν γὰρ ἕξεις
      <lb/>
      ἐνδέχεται τοῖς τόποις ἐναντίας εἶναι, τὴν δ’ ὕλην ἀδύνατον.
      <lb/>
      Ὅτι μὲν οὖν οὐ διὰ
						θερμότητα τῆς φύσεως τὰ μὲν ἔνυδρα τὰ
      <lb/>
      δὲ πεζὰ τῶν ζῴων ἐστί, καθάπερ Ἐμπεδοκλῆς
						φησίν, τοσαῦτ’
      <lb/>
      εἰρήσθω, καὶ διότι τὰ μὲν οὐκ ἔχει πνεύμονα τὰ δὲ
      <lb/>
      ἔχει.
     </p>
     <p lang="it">
      Empedocle 4 non lo disse bene, perché aveva le torce più calde e ardenti.
						degli esseri viventi sono umidi, lasciando l'eccesso di calore in natura, come
						a causa della mancanza di freddo e di acqua, invece
						essendo, perché il calore è l'ottavo liquido dell'aria. Anche se non so come possa
						ognuno di loro nascendo nel luogo asciutto cambia quasi il luogo in quello umido;
						perché anche la maggior parte di loro è povera. Ma la costituzione iniziale di queste parole
						Sono nato nella terra asciutta, lasciandomi per venire sull'umido. Cosa no
						sembrano essere creature più calde dei pedoni;
						È Ma quelli che mi vedono lo dicono con calore e freddezza, durante questa visita
						elifen; riguardo alla quarta causa di cui parlava Empedocle, non ha la ragione richiesta
						quello che ha detto è vero. A causa delle esagerazioni delle famiglie, avendo il
						Luoghi e tempi opposti si salvano, ma la natura in famiglia si salva facilmente Veramente
						luoghi. Perché non è ciò che è la fonte degli esseri viventi da cui ciascuno è, e le azioni e
						i suoi stati d'animo. I say d'oἷon eἴ ti ქალერიმები მელილებილები, οὐκ
						Se lo metto al fuoco si salva, ma non è di cristallo, perché se viene cotto in fretta muore
						al contrario; poiché il calore scioglie secondo il principio contrario. Niente di straordinario
						Oppure consigliavano il nitro, non se si depositava nell'acqua, perché consuma il
						componente caldo e asciutto il liquido. Eὖ ὖ Ιλι πασι τοις σομαι il liquido e il
						secco, fortunatamente le cose che sono liquide e fredde consistono in liquidi, e se
						freddo, stare al freddo, il d' da secco a secco. Questo è il motivo per cui gli alberi non sono nell'acqua
						cresce, ma nella terra. E quelli di questa parola sono nell'acqua, perché lo è
						questi erano estremamente asciutti, come se fossero estremamente caldi; poiché non era a causa del freddo che entrò
						questo, ma perché è bagnato. La natura della materia in cui ti trovi è
						così accade, quelli che sono nell'acqua sono bagnati, quelli che sono nella terra sono asciutti, quelli che sono nell'acqua sono asciutti no, sì
						aria calda Le mentine piperite agiscono come calore eccessivo al freddo, ma al
						la freddezza viene posta nel caldo piuttosto che si salvino, poiché con moderazione il
						luogo di eccedenza una tantum. Questo è ciò che vede nei suoi luoghi familiari
						di ogni materia, e secondo i mutamenti del tempo comune;
						è capace di luoghi, ma è impossibile il secondo oggetto. Perché in caso contrario non sarà possibile
						il calore della natura è l'acqua, ma i piedi degli animali lo sono, come dice Empedocle
						Guarda, sono così arrabbiato, e perché il mio non ha un polmone e non ce l'ha.
     </p>
     <p lang="en">
      Empedocles 4 didn't say this well, because he had the hottest and most fiery torches.
						of living things are moist, leaving the excess of heat in nature, as
						because of the lack of cold and water, instead of
						being, for heat is the liquid eighth of the air. Even though I don't know how he can
						each one of them being born in the dry place changes the place to the wet; almost
						because most of them are also poor. But the initial constitution of these words
						I was born in dry land, leaving to come to the wet. What not
						seem to be warmer creatures than pedestrians;
						is But those who see me say warmly and coldly, during this visit
						elifen; about the fourth cause that Empedocles spoke of, he has the requested reason, not
						what he said is true. Because of the exaggerations of the families, having the
						Opposite places and times save, but nature in the family is saved easily really
						places. For it is not that which is the source of the living things from which each one is, and the actions and
						her moods. I say d'oἷon eἴ ti ქალერიმები მელილებილები, οὐκ
						If I put it in heat, it saved it, but it is not made of crystal, for it perishes if it is quickly
						on the contrary; for the heat melts under the contrary principle. Nothing out of the ordinary
						Or nitre they recommended, not if it was deposited in water, for it wears out the
						warm and dry component the liquid. Eὖ ὖ Ιλι πασι τοις σομαι the liquid and the
						dry, blessedly the things that are made of liquid and cold consist in liquids, and if
						cold, be in cold, the d' from dry to dry. This is why the trees are not in water
						it grows, but in the earth. And those of this word are in the water, because it is
						these were exceedingly dry, as if they were exceedingly hot; for it was not because of the cold that he came into
						this, but because it is wet. The natures of matter, in which place you are, are
						so it happens, those who are in the water are wet, those who are in the land are dry, those who are in the water are dry n tặs
						hot air Peppermints act as excessive heat in the cold, but in the
						coldness is placed in heat rather they are saved, for in moderation the
						place of one-time excess. This is what he sees in his familiar places
						of every material, and according to the changes of the common time;
						it is capable of places, but it is, the second object impossible. Because if not then not through
						the heat of nature is water, but the feet of animals are, as Empedocles says
						Look, I'm so angry, and because mine doesn't have a lung and it doesn't.
     </p>
    </div>
    <div n="15" subtype="chapter" type="textpart">
     <p>
      Διὰ τί δὲ τὰ ἔχοντα δέχεται τὸν ἀέρα καὶ ἀναπνέουσι,
      <lb/>
      καὶ μάλιστ’ αὐτῶν ὅσα ἔχουσιν
						ἔναιμον, αἴτιον τοῦ μὲν ἀναπνεῖν
      <pb n="348"/>
      ὁ πνεύμων σομφὸς ὢν καὶ συρίγγων πλήρης.
						Καὶ
      <lb/>
      ἐναιμότατον δὴ μάλιστα τοῦτο τὸ μόριον τῶν καλουμένων
      <lb/>
      σπλάγχνων. Ὅσα δὴ
						ἔχει ἔναιμον αὐτό, ταχείας μὲν
      <lb/>
      δεῖται τῆς καταψύξεως διὰ τὸ μικρὰν εἶναι τὴν ῥοπὴν
						τοῦ
      <lb/>
      ψυχικοῦ πυρός, εἴσω δ’ εἰσιέναι διὰ παντὸς διὰ τὸ πλῆθος
      <lb/>
      τοῦ αἵματος καὶ
						τῆς θερμότητος. Ταῦτα δ’ ἀμφότερα ὁ
      <lb/>
      μὲν ἀὴρ δύναται ῥᾳδίως ποιεῖν· διὰ γὰρ τὸ
						λεπτὴν ἔχειν
      <lb/>
      τὴν φύσιν διὰ παντός τε καὶ ταχέως διαδυόμενος διαψύχει·
      <lb/>
      τὸ δ’
						ὕδωρ τοὐναντίον. Καὶ διότι δὴ μάλιστ’ ἀναπνέουσι
      <lb/>
      τὰ ἔχοντα τὸν πνεύμονα ἔναιμον, ἐκ
						τούτων δῆλον· τό τε
      <lb/>
      γὰρ θερμότερον πλείονος δεῖται τῆς καταψύξεως, ἅμα δὲ
      <lb/>
      καὶ
						πρὸς τὴν ἀρχὴν τῆς θερμότητος τῆς ἐν τῇ καρδίᾳ πορεύεται
      <lb/>
      τὸ πνεῦμα ῥᾳδίως.
     </p>
     <p lang="it">
      Perché quelli che hanno ricevono l'aria e respirano, e al loro posto quello che hanno
						respiro, perché i polmoni sono pieni e pieni di fistole.
						E la più cruenta nemmeno questa molecola dei cosiddetti visceri. Cosa no
						piove, fa freddo perché è mattina
						di fuoco mentale, forse non è per tutti a causa della moltitudine di sangue e
						di calore. Entrambe queste cose possono essere fatte dai non morti, perché
						minuto ha la natura di ogni cosa e rapidamente si raffredda il d';
						acqua al contrario. E poiché chi ha i polmoni in realtà non respira, da
						di questi, più fa caldo, maggiore è il gelo, ma anche
						verso l'inizio del suo calore nel cuore, lo spirito marcia in flagrante.
     </p>
     <p lang="en">
      Why do those who have receive the air and breathe, and instead of them what they have
						breath, because the lungs are full and full of fistulas.
						And the bloodiest not even this molecule of the so-called viscera. What not
						it's raining, it's freezing fast because it's the morning
						of mental fire, perhaps it is not for all because of the multitude of blood and
						of heat. Both of these things can be done by the undead, because
						minute has the nature of everything and quickly diffuses cools; the d'
						water on the contrary. And because those who have the lungs do not actually breathe, from
						of these, for the warmer it is, the greater the freezing, but also
						towards the beginning of its warmth in the heart, the spirit marches red-handed.
     </p>
    </div>
    <div n="16" subtype="chapter" type="textpart">
     <p>
      Ὃν δὲ τρόπον ἡ καρδία τὴν σύντρησιν ἔχει πρὸς τὸν
      <lb/>
      πλεύμονα, δεῖ θεωρεῖν ἔκ τε τῶν
						ἀνατεμνομένων καὶ τῶν
      <lb/>
      ἱστοριῶν τῶν περὶ τὰ ζῷα γεγραμμένων. Καταψύξεως
      <lb/>
      μὲν οὖν
						ὅλως ἡ τῶν ζῴων δεῖται φύσις διὰ τὴν ἐν τῇ καρδίᾳ
      <lb/>
      τῆς ψυχῆς ἐμπύρωσιν. Ταύτην δὲ
						ποιεῖται διὰ τῆς ἀναπνοῆς,
      <lb/>
      ὅσα μὴ μόνον ἔχουσι καρδίαν ἀλλὰ καὶ πνεύμονα τῶν
      <lb/>
      ζῴων. Τὰ δὲ καρδίαν μὲν ἔχοντα, πνεύμονα δὲ μή, καθάπερ
      <lb/>
      οἱ ἰχθύες διὰ τὸ
						ἔνυδρον αὐτῶν τὴν φύσιν εἶναι, τῷ ὕδατι
      <lb/>
      ποιοῦνται τὴν κατάψυξιν διὰ τῶν βραγχίων.
						Ὡς δ’ ἡ θέσις
      <lb/>
      ἔχει τῆς καρδίας πρὸς τὰ βράγχια, πρὸς μὲν τὴν ὄψιν ἐκ
      <lb/>
      τῶν
						ἀνατομῶν δεῖ θεωρεῖν, πρὸς δ’ ἀκρίβειαν ἐκ τῶν ἱστοριῶν·
      <lb/>
      ὡς δ’ ἐν κεφαλαίοις εἰπεῖν
						καὶ νῦν, ἔχει τόνδε τὸν
      <lb/>
      τρόπον. Δόξειε μὲν γὰρ ἂν οὐχ ὡσαύτως ἔχειν τὴν θέσιν
      <lb/>
      ἡ καρδία τοῖς τε πεζοῖς τῶν ζῴων καὶ τοῖς ἰχθύσιν, ἔχει
      <lb/>
      δ’ ὡσαύτως. Ἧι γὰρ
						νεύουσι τὰς κεφαλάς, ἐνταῦθ’ ἡ καρδία
      <pb n="349"/>
      τὸ ὀξὺ ἔχει. Ἐπεὶ δὲ οὐχ ὡσαύτως αἱ
						κεφαλαὶ νεύουσι
      <lb/>
      τοῖς τε πεζοῖς τῶν ζῴων καὶ τοῖς ἰχθύσι, πρὸς τὸ στόμα ἡ
      <lb/>
      καρδία τὸ ὀξὺ ἔχει. Τείνει δ’ ἐξ ἄκρου τῆς καρδίας αὐλὸς
      <lb/>
      φλεβονευρώδης εἰς τὸ
						μέσον, ᾗ συνάπτουσιν ἀλλήλοις πάντα
      <lb/>
      τὰ βράγχια. Μέγιστος μὲν οὖν οὗτός ἐστιν, ἔνθεν
						δὲ
      <lb/>
      καὶ ἔνθεν τῆς καρδίας καὶ ἕτεροι τείνουσιν εἰς ἄκρον ἑκάστου
      <lb/>
      τῶν βραγχίων,
						δι’ ὧν ἡ κατάψυξις γίνεται πρὸς τὴν καρδίαν,
      <lb/>
      διαυλωνίζοντος ἀεὶ τοῦ ὕδατος διὰ τῶν
						βραγχίων.
      <lb/>
      Ὡσαύτως δὲ τοῖς ἀναπνέουσιν ὁ θώραξ ἄνω καὶ κάτω κινεῖται
      <lb/>
      πολλάκις
						δεχομένων τὸ πνεῦμα καὶ ἐξιέντων, ὡς τὰ
      <lb/>
      βράγχια τοῖς ἰχθύσιν. Καὶ τὰ μὲν ἀναπνέοντα
						ἐν ὀλίγῳ
      <lb/>
      ἀέρι καὶ τῷ αὐτῷ ἀποπνίγονται· ταχέως γὰρ ἑκάτερον
      <lb/>
      αὐτῶν γίνεται
						θερμόν· θερμαίνει γὰρ ἡ τοῦ αἵματος θίξις
      <lb/>
      ἑκάτερον. θερμὸν δ’ ὂν τὸ αἷμα κωλύει τὴν
						κατάψυξιν· καὶ
      <lb/>
      μὴ δυναμένων κινεῖν τῶν μὲν ἀναπνεόντων τὸν πνεύμονα τῶν
      <lb/>
      δ’
						ἐνύδρων τὰ βράγχια διὰ πάθος ἢ διὰ γῆρας, τότε συμβαίνειν
      <lb/>
      τὴν τελευτήν.
     </p>
     <p lang="it">
      Ma se il cuore ha una connessione con i polmoni, pensano
						ricordando le storie scritte sugli animali. Congelare con oὖ
						Tutta la vita è vista come natura attraverso l'ardore nel cuore dell'anima. Ma questo
						è fatto attraverso la respirazione, che non ha solo un cuore ma anche un polmone
						della vita. Ma quelli che non avevano cuore, ma nemmeno polmoni, i pesci morirono a causa di essi
						La loro natura è acquatica, usano l'acqua per congelare attraverso le branchie.
						Qual è la posizione del cuore verso le branchie, verso l'occhio dal
						degli anatomisti, ritengono, secondo l'esattezza delle storie, come dicono in maiuscolo
						e ora è così. Buona fortuna, perché altrimenti hanno anche la posizione
						il cuore degli animali ambulanti e dei pesci ha lo stesso. Perchè è
						annuiscono con la testa, mentre il cuore è amareggiato. Ma non altrettanto bene
						le loro teste accennano ai piedi degli animali e ai pesci, verso la bocca del ha il cuore amaro. Tende dall'estremità del cuore all'atrio venoneurotico
						medio, al quale si uniscono tutte le lamelle. Maximus me oὖn ὗtos estin, ἐνθεν
						e dall'interno del cuore, e altri tendono all'estremità di ciascuna branchia,
						attraverso il quale avviene il congelamento verso il cuore, facendo passare l'acqua attraverso il
						branchie. Allo stesso modo, in chi respira, il torace si muove spesso su e giù
						ricevendo lo spirito e uscendo, come le branchie dei pesci. E quelli non traspiranti
						soffocano in un breve soffio d'aria, perché presto uno di loro diventa
						calore; perché il calore del sangue riscalda. il calore del sangue ostruisce il
						congelamento; e incapacità di muovere chi non respira
						se le branchie sono acquose a causa della passione o della vecchiaia, allora accade quest'ultima.
     </p>
     <p lang="en">
      But if the heart has a connection with the lungs, they consider
						remembering the stories written about the animals. Freezing with oὖ
						The whole of life is seen as nature through the burning in the heart of the soul. But this one
						it is done through breathing, which not only have a heart but also a lung of the
						of life. But those who had no heart, but no lungs, the fish perished because of
						Their nature is aquatic, they use water to freeze through their gills.
						What is the position of the heart towards the gills, towards the eye from the
						of anatomists, they consider, to the accuracy of the stories; as they say in capitals
						and now, he has that way. Good luck, because if not, they also have the position
						the heart of the walking animals and the fishes, has the same. Because it is
						they nod their heads, while the heart is bitter. But not as well
						their heads nod to the foot of the animals and to the fish, towards the mouth of the he has a bitter heart. It tends from the end of the heart to the venoneurotic atrium
						medium, to which all the gills join each other. Maximus me oὖn ὗtos estin, ἐνθεν
						and from the inside of the heart, and others tend to the end of each of the gills,
						through which the freezing takes place towards the heart, passing the water through the
						gills. In the same way, in those who breathe, the chest often moves up and down
						receiving the spirit and passing out, as the gills of fishes. And the non-breathable ones
						they suffocate in a short breath of air, for quickly one of them becomes
						heat; for the heat of the blood heats one. heat d' ὂn the blood obstructs the
						freezing; and not being able to move the non-breathing
						if the gills are watery due to passion or old age, then the latter happens.
     </p>
    </div>
    <div n="17" subtype="chapter" type="textpart">
     <p>
      Ἔστι μὲν οὖν πᾶσι τοῖς ζῴοις κοινὸν γένεσις καὶ θάνατος,
      <lb/>
      οἱ δὲ τρόποι διαφέρουσι
						τῷ εἴδει· οὐ γὰρ ἀδιάφορος ἡ
      <lb/>
      φθορά, ἀλλ’ ἔχει τι κοινόν. Θάνατος δ’ ἐστὶν ὁ μὲν
						βίαιος
      <lb/>
      ὁ δὲ κατὰ φύσιν, βίαιος μὲν ὅταν ἡ ἀρχὴ ἔξωθεν ᾖ, κατὰ
      <lb/>
      φύσιν δ’ ὅταν ἐν
						αὐτῷ. Καὶ ἡ τοῦ μορίου σύστασις ἐξ
      <lb/>
      ἀρχῆς τοιαύτη, ἀλλὰ μὴ ἐπίκτητόν τι πάθος. Τοῖς
						μὲν οὖν
      <lb/>
      φυτοῖς αὔανσις, ἐν δὲ τοῖς ζῴοις καλεῖται τοῦτο γῆρας.
      <lb/>
      Ἔστι δὲ θάνατος
						καὶ ἡ φθορὰ πᾶσιν ὁμοίως τοῖς μὴ
      <lb/>
      ἀτελέσιν· τούτοις δὲ παρομοίως μέν, ἄλλον δὲ
						τρόπον.
      <lb/>
      Ἀτελῆ δὲ λέγω οἷον τά τε ᾠὰ καὶ τὰ σπέρματα τῶν φυτῶν,
      <lb/>
      ὅσα ἄρριζα.
						Πᾶσι μἐν οὖν ἡ φθορὰ γίνεται διὰ θερμοῦ
      <pb n="350"/>
      τινὸς ἔκλειψιν, τοῖς δὲ τελείοις,
						ἐν ᾧ τῆς οὐσίας ἡ ἀρχή.
      <lb/>
      Αὕτη δ’ ἐστίν, ὥσπερ εἴρηται πρότερον, ἐν ᾧ τό τε ἄνω καὶ
      <lb/>
      τὸ κάτω συνάπτει, τοῖς μὲν φυτοῖς μέσον βλαστοῦ καὶ
      <lb/>
      ῥίζης, τῶν δὲ ζῴων τοῖς
						μὲν ἐναίμοις ἡ καρδία, τοῖς δ’ ἀναίμοις
      <lb/>
      τὸ ἀνάλογον. Τούτων δ’ ἔνια δυνάμει πολλὰς
						ἀρχὰς
      <lb/>
      ἔχουσιν, οὐ μέντοι γε ἐνεργείᾳ. Διὸ καὶ τῶν ἐντόμων ἔνια
      <lb/>
      διαιρούμενα
						ζῶσι, καὶ τῶν ἐναίμων ὅσα μὴ ζωτικὰ λίαν
      <lb/>
      εἰσί, πολὺν χρόνον ζῶσιν ἐξῃρημένης τῆς
						καρδίας, οἷον αἱ
      <lb/>
      χελῶναι καὶ κινοῦνται τοῖς ποσίν, ἐπόντων τῶν χελωνίων,
      <lb/>
      διὰ
						τὸ μὴ συγκεῖσθαι τὴν φύσιν αὐτῶν εὖ, παραπλησίως δὲ
      <lb/>
      τοῖς ἐντόμοις. Ἡ δ’ ἀρχὴ τῆς
						ζωῆς ἐκλείπει τοῖς ἔχουσιν,
      <lb/>
      ὅταν μὴ καταψύχηται τὸ θερμὸν τὸ κοινωνοῦν αὐτῆς.
      <lb/>
      Καθάπερ γὰρ εἴρηται πολλάκις, συντήκεται αὐτὸ
      <lb/>
      ὑφ’ αὑτοῦ. Ὅταν οὖν τοῖς μὲν ὁ
						πλεύμων τοῖς δὲ τὰ
      <lb/>
      βράγχια σκληρύνηται, διὰ χρόνου μῆκος ξηραινομένων τοῖς
      <lb/>
      μὲν
						τῶν βραγχίων τοῖς δὲ τοῦ πλεύμονος, καὶ γινομένων
      <lb/>
      γεηρῶν, οὐ δύναται ταῦτα τὰ μόρια
						κινεῖν οὐδ’ αἴρειν καὶ
      <lb/>
      συνάγειν. Τέλος δὲ γινομένης ἐπιτάσεως καταμαραίνεται
      <lb/>
      τὸ πῦρ. Διὸ καὶ μικρῶν παθημάτων ἐπιγινομένων ἐν τῷ
      <lb/>
      γήρᾳ ταχέως τελευτῶσιν·
						διὰ γὰρ τὸ ὀλίγον εἶναι τὸ θερμόν,
      <lb/>
      ἅτε τοῦ πλείστου διαπεπνευκότος ἐν τῷ πλήθει τῆς
      <lb/>
      ζωῆς, ἥτις ἂν ἐπίτασις γένηται τοῦ μορίου, ταχέως ἀποσβέννυται·
      <lb/>
      ὥσπερ γὰρ
						ἀκαριαίας καὶ μικρᾶς ἐν αὐτῷ φλογὸς
      <lb/>
      ἐνούσης διὰ μικρὰν κίνησιν ἀποσβέννυται. Διὸ
						καὶ ἄλυπός
      <lb/>
      ἐστιν ὁ ἐν τῷ γήρᾳ θάνατος· οὐδενὸς γὰρ βιαίου
      <lb/>
      πάθους αὐτοῖς
						συμβαίνοντος τελευτῶσιν, ἀλλ’ ἀναίσθητος ἡ
      <pb n="351"/>
      τῆς ψυχῆς ἀπόλυσις γίνεται
						παντελῶς. Καὶ τῶν νοσημάτων
      <lb/>
      ὅσα ποιοῦσι τὸν πνεύμονα σκληρὸν ἢ φύμασιν ἢ
						περιττώμασιν
      <lb/>
      ἢ θερμότητος νοσηματικῆς ὑπερβολῇ, καθάπερ
      <lb/>
      ἐν τοῖς πυρετοῖς,
						πυκνὸν τὸ πνεῦμα ποιοῦσι διὰ τὸ μὴ
      <lb/>
      δύνασθαι τὸν πνεύμονα μακρὰν αἴρειν ἄνω καὶ
						συνίζειν.
      <lb/>
      Τέλος δ’, ὅταν μηκέτι δύνωνται κινεῖν, τελευτῶσιν
      <lb/>
      ἀποπνεύσαντες.
     </p>
     <p lang="it">
      Infatti la nascita e la morte sono comuni a tutti gli esseri viventi, ma le modalità differiscono
						per lui, perché la decadenza non è indifferente, ma ha qualcosa in comune. La morte non sono io
						ma è violento per natura, violento solo quando il principio è dall'esterno x, per natura d' quando è interno
						a se stesso. E la costituzione della molecola da quel principio, ma nessuna passione viene acquisita. A loro
						Ma per le piante questa si chiama vecchiaia. Cos'è la morte?
						e la corruzione non sarà fatta allo stesso modo degli altri;
						modo Ma imperfetti chiamo quelli che sono gli ᾠὰ e i semi delle piante, che ho colto.
						Tutto tranne il danno è causato da un'eclissi calda, ma per quelle finite,
						in ᾧ dell'essenza il principio. Questo è, come accennato prima, in cui quanto sopra e
						quello inferiore unisce alle piante la metà del germoglio e della radice, e dei vivi alla
						col sangue il cuore, a quelli col sangue lo stesso. È passato molto tempo da allora
						Hanno un inizio, non hanno energia. Anche a causa degli insetti divisibile
						vita, e delle anime poco vitali vivranno a lungo
						del cuore, che le tartarughe e si spostano nei posini, delle tartarughe,
						Non danneggia la loro natura, ma è vicino agli insetti. Il 4° inizio di
						manca la vita a chi ce l’ha, quando non si ghiaccia il calore della sua comunione.
						Poiché viene detto molte volte, si fonde con se stesso. Quando poi per me il
						le branchie delle pinne si induriscono, col tempo si seccano
						delle branchie, ma dei polmoni, e quando invecchiano, queste particelle non possono più
						non muovono né inferenza né inferenza. Ma alla fine di un attacco, viene maledetto
						il fuoco Perché anche le piccole sofferenze causate nella vecchiaia finiranno presto;
						poiché piccolo è il caldo, ma il più soffocante nella moltitudine di
						della vita, che, se tentata, è fatta di molecola, si estingue rapidamente per quanto
						istantanea e piccola in lui una fiamma di rabbia attraversata il piccolo movimento è smorzato. Perché
						E la morte nella vecchiaia è miserabile, perché per loro non c'è passione violenta
						accadendo eventualmente, ma inconsciamente, avviene la dissoluzione dell'anima
						assolutamente. E delle malattie che rendono i polmoni duri o fanno fumo o
						escrementi o calore di eccesso morboso, come nelle febbri,
						il cui spirito è ottuso perché non riesce a sollevare i polmoni molto al di sopra e
						Essere d'accordo Alla fine, quando riescono a malapena a muoversi, finiscono senza fiato.
     </p>
     <p lang="en">
      For, therefore, birth and death are common to all living things, but the ways differ
						to him, for decay is not indifferent, but it has something in common. Death is not me
						but he is violent by nature, violent only when the principle is from outside x, by nature d' when in
						to himself. And the constitution of the molecule from that principle, but no passion is acquired. To them
						But to plants this is called old age. What is death?
						and corruption shall not be done in the same way as in others;
						way But imperfect I call those who are the ᾠὰ and the seeds of the plants, which I plucked.
						All but the damage is done by a hot eclipse, but for the finished ones,
						in ᾧ of the essence the principle. This one is, as mentioned before, in which the above and
						the lower one joins, to the plants the middle of the shoot and the root, and of the living to the
						with blood the heart, to those with blood the same. It's been a long time since then
						They have a beginning, they don't have energy. Because of the insects as well divisible
						life, and of the souls that are not very vital, they will live for a long time
						of the heart, which the turtles and move to the posins, of the turtles,
						It doesn't hurt their nature, but it is close to the insects. The 4th beginning of
						of life is lacking to those who have it, when the warmth of their communion is not frozen.
						Because it is said many times, it merges with itself. When then to me the
						the gills of the fins harden, over time they dry up
						of the gills, but of the lungs, and when they become old, these particles cannot
						they move neither inference nor inference. But at the end of an attack, it is cursed
						the fire Because even small sufferings caused in old age will quickly end;
						for the little is the heat, but of the most suffocating in the multitude of
						of life, which, if attempted, is made of the molecule, is quickly extinguished; for as
						instantaneous and small in him a flame of anger through small movement is damped. Why
						And death in old age is miserable, for there is no violent passion for them
						happening eventually, but unconsciously, the dissolution of the soul takes place
						absolutely. And of the diseases that make the lungs hard or smoke or
						excrement or heat of morbid excess, as in fevers,
						whose spirit is thick because he cannot lift his lungs far above and
						agree Finally, when they are barely able to move, they end up out of breath.
     </p>
    </div>
    <div n="18" subtype="chapter" type="textpart">
     <p>
      Γένεσις μὲν οὖν ἐστὶν ἡ πρώτη μέθεξις ἐν τῷ θερμῷ τῆς
      <lb/>
      θρεπτικῆς ψυχῆς, ζωὴ δ’ ἡ
						μονὴ ταύτης. Νεότης δ’ ἐστὶν ἡ
      <lb/>
      τοῦ πρώτου καταψυκτικοῦ μορίου αὔξησις, γῆρας δ’ ἡ
						τούτου
      <lb/>
      φθίσις, ἀκμὴ δὲ τὸ τούτων μέσον. Τελευτὴ δὲ καὶ φθορὰ
      <lb/>
      βίαιος μὲν ἡ τοῦ
						θερμοῦ σβέσις καὶ μάρανσις· φθαρείη γὰρ
      <lb/>
      ἂν δι’ ἀμφοτέρας ταύτας τὰς αἰτίας, ἡ δὲ
						κατὰ φύσιν τοῦ
      <lb/>
      αὐτοῦ τούτου μάρανσις διὰ χρόνου μῆκος γινομένη καὶ τελειότητα.
      <lb/>
      Τοῖς μὲν οὖν φυτοῖς αὔανσις, ἐν δὲ τοῖς ζῴοις
      <lb/>
      καλεῖται θάνατος. Τούτου δ’ ὁ
						μὲν ἐν γήρᾳ θάνατος μάρανσις
      <lb/>
      τοῦ μορίου δι’ ἀδυναμίαν τοῦ καταψύχειν ὑπὸ γήρως.
      <lb/>
      Τί μὲν οὖν ἐστὶ γένεσις καὶ ζωὴ καὶ θάνατος, καὶ διὰ τίνας
      <lb/>
      αἰτίας ὑπάρχουσι
						τοῖς ζῴοις, εἴρηται.
     </p>
     <p lang="it">
      La Genesi è quindi la prima inebriante nel calore dell'anima nutriente, la vita 4
						solo uno. La giovinezza è l'età della prima molecola congelante della crescita, la vecchiaia è l'età
						di questo cadi, ma non nel mezzo di questi. E, ultimo ma non meno importante, anche violento
						calore che spegni e appassisci;
						secondo la natura di questo, col tempo, diventerà lungo e perfetto.
						Per gli uomini è phytoès ahanceis, ma per i vivi è chiamata morte. Questo quarto
						ma in età avanzata la morte della molecola è causata dall'incapacità di congelarsi in età avanzata.
						Che cosa sono dunque la nascita, la vita e la morte? E per questa ragione esistono?
						ai vivi, si dice.
     </p>
     <p lang="en">
      Genesis is therefore the first intoxicating in the heat of the nourishing soul, life 4
						only one. Youth is the age of the first freezing molecule of growth, old age is the
						of this you fall, but not the middle of these. And last but not least, violent as well
						heat you put out and wither;
						according to the nature of this, over time, it will become long and perfect.
						To men oὖn phytoès ahanceis, but to the living it is called death. This fourth
						but in old age death maransis of the molecule due to inability to freeze under old age.
						What, then, is birth and life and death, and for this cause do they exist
						to the living, it is said.
     </p>
    </div>
    <div n="19" subtype="chapter" type="textpart">
     <p>
      Δῆλον δ’ ἐκ τούτων καὶ διὰ τίν’ αἰτίαν τοῖς μὲν ἀναπνέουσι
      <lb/>
      τῶν ζῴων ἀποπνίγεσθαι
						συμβαίνει ἐν τῷ ὑγρῷ, τοῖς
      <lb/>
      δ’ ἰχθύσιν ἐν τῷ ἀέρι· τοῖς μὲν γὰρ διὰ τοῦ ὕδατος ἡ
						κατάψυξις
      <lb/>
      γίνεται, τοῖς δὲ διὰ τοῦ ἀέρος, ὧν ἑκάτερα στερίσκεται
      <lb/>
      μεταβάλλοντα
						τοὺς τόπους. Ἡ δ’ αἰτία τῆς κινήσεως
      <lb/>
      τοῖς μὲν τῶν βραγχίων τοῖς δὲ τοῦ πνεύμονος,
						ὧν αἰρομένων
      <lb/>
      καὶ συνιζόντων τὰ μὲν ἐκπνέουσι καὶ εἰσπνέουσι τὰ
      <lb/>
      δὲ δέχονται τὸ
						ὑγρὸν καὶ ἐξιᾶσιν, ἔτι δ’ ἡ σύστασις τοῦ
      <lb/>
      ὀργάνου, τόνδ’ ἔχει τὸν τρόπον.
     </p>
     <p lang="it">
      Qual è il quarto e perché il respiro degli esseri viventi è soffocato?
						succede nell'acqua, a chi non pesca nell'aria, a chi sta nell'acqua
						avviene il congelamento, e ad essi attraverso l'aria, dove ciascuno è privato del mutamento
						I posti. La seconda causa di movimento sono le branchie e i polmoni,
						in coloro che sono unti e simpatizzanti, in coloro che espirano e inspirano e in coloro che ricevono
						umido e asciutto, quando l'organizzazione dell'organo non c'è, allora ha il modo.
     </p>
     <p lang="en">
      What is the fourth of these and why do the breathing of living things suffocate
						it happens in the water, to those who do not fish in the air, for to those who are in the water
						freezing takes place, and to them through the air, where each is deprived of changing
						the places. The second cause of movement is the gills and the lungs,
						in those who are anointed and sympathizers, those who breathe out and breathe in, and those who receive
						wet and dry, when the organization of the organ is not, then it has the way.
     </p>
    </div>
    <div n="20" subtype="chapter" type="textpart">
     <p>
      Τρία ἐστὶ τὰ συμβαίνοντα περὶ τὴν καρδίαν, ἃ δοκεῖ
      <pb n="352"/>
      τὴν αὐτὴν φύσιν ἔχειν,
						ἔχει δ’ οὐ τὴν αὐτήν, πήδησις καὶ
      <lb/>
      σφυγμὸς καὶ ἀναπνοή. Πήδησις μὲν οὖν ἐστὶ σύνωσις
      <lb/>
      τοῦ θερμοῦ τοῦ ἐν αὐτῇ διὰ κατάψυξιν περιττωματικὴν ἢ
      <lb/>
      συντηκτικήν, οἷον ἐν τῇ
						νόσῳ τῇ καλουμένῃ παλμῷ, καὶ ἐν
      <lb/>
      ἄλλαις δὲ νόσοις, καὶ ἐν τοῖς φόβοις δέ· καὶ γὰρ οἱ
						φοβούμενοι
      <lb/>
      καταψύχονται τὰ ἄνω, τὸ δὲ θερμὸν ὑποφεῦγον
      <lb/>
      καὶ συστελλόμενον ποιεῖ
						τὴν πήδησιν, εἰς μικρὸν συνωθούμενον
      <lb/>
      οὕτως ὥστ’ ἐνίοτ’ ἀποσβέννυσθαι τὰ ζῷα καὶ
						ἀποθνήσκειν
      <lb/>
      διὰ φόβον καὶ διὰ πάθος νοσηματικόν. Ἡ δὲ συμβαίνουσα
      <lb/>
      σφύξις τῆς
						καρδίας, ἣν ἀεὶ φαίνεται ποιουμένη συνεχῶς,
      <lb/>
      ὁμοία φύμασίν ἐστιν, ἣν ποιοῦνται
						κίνησιν μετ’ ἀλγηδόνος
      <lb/>
      διὰ τὸ παρὰ φύσιν εἶναι τῷ αἵματι τὴν μεταβολήν. Γίνεται
      <lb/>
      δὲ μέχρι οὗ ἂν πυωθῇ πεφθέν. Ἔστι δ’ ὅμοιον
      <lb/>
      ζέσει τοῦτο τὸ πάθος· ἡ γὰρ ζέσις
						γίνεται πνευματουμένου
      <lb/>
      τοῦ ὑγροῦ ὑπὸ τοῦ θερμοῦ· αἴρεται γὰρ διὰ τὸ πλείω
      <lb/>
      γίνεσθαι τὸν ὄγκον. Παῦλα δ’ ἐν μὲν τοῖς φύμασιν, ἐὰν
      <lb/>
      μὴ διαπνεύσῃ, παχυτέρου
						γινομένου τοῦ ὑγροῦ, σῆψις, τῇ
      <lb/>
      δὲ ζέσει ἡ ἔκπτωσις διὰ τῶν ὁριζόντων. Ἐν δὲ τῇ
						καρδίᾳ
      <lb/>
      ἡ τοῦ ἀεὶ προσιόντος ἐκ τῆς τροφῆς ὑγροῦ διὰ τῆς
      <lb/>
      θερμότητος ὄγκωσις
						ποιεῖ σφυγμόν, αἰρομένη πρὸς τὸν
      <lb/>
      ἔσχατον χιτῶνα τῆς καρδίας. Καὶ τοῦτ’ ἀεὶ γίνεται
						συνεχῶς·
      <lb/>
      ἐπιρρεῖ γὰρ ἀεὶ τὸ ὑγρὸν συνεχῶς, ἐξ οὗ γίνεται
      <lb/>
      ἡ τοῦ αἵματος φύσις·
						πρῶτον γὰρ ἐν τῇ καρδίᾳ δημιουργεῖται.
      <lb/>
      Δῆλον δ’ ἐν τῇ γενέσει ἐξ ἀρχῆς· οὔπω γὰρ
						διωρισμένων
      <lb/>
      τῶν φλεβῶν φαίνεται ἔχουσα αἷμα. Καὶ διὰ τοῦτο
      <lb/>
      σφύζει μᾶλλον τοῖς
						νεωτέροις τῶν πρεσβυτέρων· γίνεται
      <pb n="353"/>
      γὰρ ἡ ἀναθυμίασις πλείων τοῖς
						νεωτέροις. Καὶ σφύζουσιν
      <lb/>
      αἱ φλέβες πᾶσαι, καὶ ἅμα ἀλλήλαις, διὰ τὸ ἠρτῆσθαι ἐκ
      <lb/>
      τῆς καρδίας. Κινεῖ δ’ ἀεί· ὥστε κἀκεῖναι αἰεί, καὶ ἅμα ἀλλήλαις,
      <lb/>
      ὅτε κινεῖ.
						Ἀναπήδησις μὲν οὖν ἐστὶν ἡ γινομένη
      <lb/>
      ἄντωσις πρὸς τὴν τοῦ ψυχροῦ σύνωσιν, σφύξις δ’
						ἡ τοῦ
      <lb/>
      ὑγροῦ θερμαινομένου πνευμάτωσις.
     </p>
     <p lang="it">
      Tre sono le cose che accadono al cuore, che ha questa natura,
						ha la stessa cosa, saltare, pulsare e respirare. Pedisis me oὖ est sinossi
						del calore in esso contenuto mediante congelamento escretore o fusionale, che in
						malattia della palma callosa, e in altre malattie, e nei timori per il
						temendo, quelli sopra sono congelati, ma il calore è evitato e si restringe
						il salto, restringendosi in uno piccolo in modo che gli animali si estinguano e
						morì di paura e di passione morbosa. Ma l'incidente della sua sfissi
						del cuore, che sembra ardere continuamente, è come il fumo che arde
						movimento con gli algidoni perché è nella natura del sangue cambiare. Sta succedendo
						ma fino a dove cade. È la stessa persona che vive questa passione, perché lo zelo
						si fa come lo spirito del liquido sotto il fuoco, perché è sollevato di lato
						diventare il volume. Paul D' in me al fumo, se non respira, più spesso
						Essendo fatto d'acqua marcisce, ma in essa vive la discesa attraverso gli orizzonti. Altrimenti
						dal cuore dell'animale dal cibo liquido per il rigonfiamento del caldo
						pulsa, profumato fino all'ultimo strato del cuore. E questo sta accadendo
						continuamente; poiché il sangue scorre continuamente, da cui deriva la natura del sangue;
						perché è prima creato nel cuore. È stato fatto nella creazione fin dall'inizio, perché lo adoro
						vene separate sembra che avessi sangue. E per questo motivo li picchia piuttosto
						il più giovane dei più anziani: poiché in mezzo a loro avviene l'anatimiasi del popolo
						quelli più giovani. E le vene pulsano ovunque, e se sei diverso, è per la soddisfazione che ti dà
						del cuore. Si muove per sempre, quindi è per sempre, e se sei diverso, quando si muove.
						Ti riprendi, quindi è la resistenza finita verso l'incontro freddo, ti stringi.
						la pneumatosi riscaldata dal liquido.
     </p>
     <p lang="en">
      There are three things that happen to the heart, which has this nature,
						it has the same thing, leaping and pulse and breathing. Pedisis me oὖ est synossis
						of the heat in it by excretory or fusional freezing, which in
						disease of the calloused palm, and in other diseases, and in fears; for the
						fearing, the above are frozen, but the heat is shunned and shrinking
						the jump, shrinking into a small one so that the animals are extinguished and
						he died of fear and morbid passion. But the incident of her sphyxis
						of the heart, which seems to be burning constantly, is like smoke, which is burning
						movement with algidons because it is the blood's nature to change. It's happening
						but up to where it falls. He is the same person who lives this passion, because the zeal
						it is done as the spirit of the liquid under the heat, because it is lifted by the side
						become the volume. Paul D' in me to the smoke, if it does not breathe, thicker
						Being made of water, it rots, but in it lives the descent through horizons. If not
						by the heart of the animal from the liquid food due to the swelling of the heat
						it pulses, perfumed to the last layer of the heart. And this is happening
						continuously; for blood flows continuously, from which the nature of blood is made;
						because it is first created in the heart. It was done in creation from the beginning, because I love it
						separated veins it looks like I had blood. And because of this, it beats rather to them
						the younger of the elders: for the anathimiasis of the people takes place among them
						younger ones. And the veins throb everywhere, and if you are different, because of the satisfaction from
						of the heart. It moves forever, so that it is forever, and if you are different, when it moves.
						You bounce back, so it's the finished endurance towards the cold meeting, you tighten up.
						the liquid heated pneumatosis.
     </p>
    </div>
    <div n="21" subtype="chapter" type="textpart">
     <p>
      Ἡ δ’ ἀναπνοὴ γίνεται αὐξανομένου τοῦ θερμοῦ, ἐν ᾧ ἡ
      <lb/>
      ἀρχὴ ἡ θρεπτική. Καθάπερ γὰρ
						καὶ τἆλλα δεῖται τροφῆς,
      <lb/>
      κἀκεῖνο, καὶ τῶν ἄλλων μᾶλλον· καὶ γὰρ τοῖς ἄλλοις
      <lb/>
      ἐκεῖνο τῆς τροφῆς αἴτιόν ἐστιν. Ἀνάγκη δὴ πλέον γινόμενον
      <lb/>
      αἴρειν τὸ ὄργανον.
						Δεῖ δ’ ὑπολαβεῖν τὴν σύστασιν
      <lb/>
      τοῦ ὀργάνου παραπλησίαν μὲν εἶναι ταῖς φύσαις ταῖς ἐν
      <lb/>
      τοῖς χαλκείοις· οὐ πόρρω γὰρ οὔθ’ ὁ πνεύμων οὔθ’ ἡ καρδία
      <lb/>
      πρὸς τὸ δέξασθαι
						σχῆμα τοιοῦτον· διπλοῦν δ’ εἶναι τὸ
      <lb/>
      τοιοῦτον· δεῖ γὰρ ἐν τῷ μέσῳ τὸ θρεπτικὸν εἶναι
						τῆς φυσικῆς
      <lb/>
      δυνάμεως. Αἴρεται μὲν οὖν πλεῖον γενόμενον, αἰρομένου
      <lb/>
      δ’ ἀναγκαῖον
						αἴρεσθαι καὶ τὸ περιέχον αὐτὸ μόριον.
      <lb/>
      Ὅπερ φαίνονται ποιεῖν οἱ ἀναπνέοντες· αἴρουσι
						γὰρ τὸν
      <lb/>
      θώρακα διὰ τὸ τὴν ἀρχὴν τὴν ἐνοῦσαν αὐτῷ τοῦ τοιούτου
      <lb/>
      μορίου ταὐτὸ
						τοῦτο ποιεῖν· αἰρομένου γάρ, καθάπερ εἰς τὰς
      <lb/>
      φύσας, ἀναγκαῖον εἰσφέρειν τὸν ἀέρα
						τὸν θύραθεν, καὶ
      <lb/>
      ψυχρὸν ὄντα καὶ καταψύχοντα σβεννύναι τὴν ὑπεροχὴν
      <lb/>
      τὴν τοῦ
						πυρός. Ὥσπερ δ’ αὐξανομένου ᾔρετο τοῦτο τὸ
      <lb/>
      μόριον, καὶ φθίνοντος ἀναγκαῖον
						συνίζειν, καὶ συνίζοντος
      <lb/>
      ἐξιέναι τὸν ἀέρα τὸν εἰσελθόντα πάλιν, εἰσιόντα μὲν ψυχρὸν
      <lb/>
      ἐξιόντα δὲ θερμὸν διὰ τὴν ἁφὴν τοῦ θερμοῦ τοῦ ἐνόντος
      <lb/>
      ἐν τῷ μορίῳ τούτῳ, καὶ
						μάλιστα τοῖς τὸν πνεύμονα ἔναιμον
      <pb n="354"/>
      ἔχουσιν· εἰς πολλοὺς γὰρ οἷον αὐλῶνας
						τὰς σύριγγας
      <lb/>
      ἐμπίπτειν τὰς ἐν τῷ πνεύμονι, ὧν παρ’ ἑκάστην παρατέτανται
      <lb/>
      φλέβες, ὥστε δοκεῖν ὅλον εἶναι τὸν πνεύμονα πλήρη
      <lb/>
      αἵματος. Καλεῖται δ’ ἡ μὲν
						εἴσοδος τοῦ ἀέρος ἀναπνοή, ἡ
      <lb/>
      δ’ ἔξοδος ἐκπνοή. Καὶ ἀεὶ δὴ τοῦτο γίνεται συνεχῶς,
						ἕως
      <lb/>
      περ ἂν ζῇ καὶ κινῇ τοῦτο τὸ μόριον συνεχῶς. Καὶ διὰ
      <lb/>
      τοῦτο ἐν τῷ ἀναπνεῖν
						καὶ ἐκπνεῖν ἐστὶ τὸ ζῆν. Τὸν αὐτὸν
      <lb/>
      δὲ τρόπον καὶ τοῖς ἰχθύσιν ἡ κίνησις γίνεται τῶν
						βραγχίων.
      <lb/>
      Αἰρομένου μὲν γὰρ τοῦ θερμοῦ τοῦ ἐν τῷ αἵματι
      <lb/>
      διὰ τῶν μορίων
						αἴρονται καὶ τὰ βράγχια, καὶ διιᾶσι τὸ
      <lb/>
      ὕδωρ· κατιόντος δὲ πρὸς τὴν καρδίαν διὰ τῶν
						πόρων καὶ
      <lb/>
      καταψυχομένου συνίζουσι, καὶ ἀφιᾶσι τὸ ὕδωρ. Ἀεὶ δ’ αἰρομένου
      <lb/>
      τοῦ ἐν
						τῇ καρδίᾳ, ἀεὶ δέχεται πάλιν καταψυχομένου.
      <lb/>
      Διὸ κἀκείνοις τοῦ ζῆν καὶ μὴ ζῆν τὸ
						τέλος ἐστὶν
      <lb/>
      ἐν τῷ ἀναπνεῖν, καὶ τούτοις ἐν τῷ δέχεσθαι τὸ ὑγρόν.
     </p>
     <p lang="it">
      Il quarto respiro avviene con calore crescente, in cui l'inizio è il nutrimento. Dopotutto, Kathaper
						e la bellezza si vede nel cibo, cattivo, e piuttosto negli altri;
						quella del cibo è la causa. Non è più necessario rimuovere l'organo.
						Non si occupano dell’organizzazione dell’organo di prossimità a me se è nella loro natura
						ai ramaioli; poiché né lo spirito né il cuore sono in grado di accettarlo
						la forma di uno simile; non piegano quello; perché vedere nel mezzo è il nutrimento
						di forza fisica. Si prende con il nostro genomenon plurale
						anche la molecola che lo contiene sale. Perché si vedono coloro che respirano gloria;
						poiché il petto era unito a lui dall'inizio di questa molecola
						cosa fanno?
						dalla porta, ed essere freddo e gelido spegne la bellezza di
						fuoco. Man mano che questa molecola aumenta, diminuisce il necessario
						sono d'accordo, e come sono d'accordo, l'aria che è entrata di nuovo, è fredda
						e irradia calore a causa del rilascio del calore della sostanza in questa molecola, e
						infatti hanno il respiro dei polmoni;
						le siringhe cadono nei polmoni, dove vengono estese
						vene, in modo che sentano il sapore di tutto il polmone pieno di sangue. Si chiama d'or me
						l'ingresso dell'aria è l'inalazione, la quarta uscita è l'espirazione. E ehi, non succede sempre così?
						finché questa molecola vive e si muove continuamente. E per questo motivo mentre respiri
						E la vita muore. Allo stesso modo anche il movimento dei pesci lo fanno loro
						branchie. A causa del calore del sangue attraverso le molecole
						anche le branchie sono sollevate e l'acqua è divisa e scende verso il cuore attraverso il
						poro e congelato insieme, e lasciare l'acqua. Santo dello Spirito Santo
						il cuore, aeὶ riceve di nuovo ghiacciato. A causa di qualcuno vivere e non vivere
						il fine è respirare, e questo nel ricevere il liquido.
     </p>
     <p lang="en">
      The fourth breath takes place with increasing heat, in which the beginning is the nourishing. After all, Kathaper
						and beauty is seen in food, bad, and rather in others; for in others
						that of food is the cause. There is no longer any need to remove the organ.
						They do not take care of the organization of the organ of proximity to me if it is their nature in
						to the coppersmiths; for neither the spirit nor the heart is able to accept it
						the shape of such a one; they fold not that one; for see in the middle is the nourishing
						of physical force. It is taken with oὖn plural genomenon
						the molecule containing it also rises. Because they are seen who are breathing; glory
						for the chest was united to him by the beginning of this molecule
						what do they do?
						from the door, and being cold and freezing extinguishes the beauty of
						fire. As this molecule increases, it decreases the necessary
						they agree, and as they agree, the air enters again, being cold
						and it radiates heat due to the release of the heat of the substance in this molecule, and
						in fact, they have the breath of the lungs;
						the syringes fall into the lungs, where they are extended
						veins, so that they taste the whole lung full of blood. It is called d' or me
						air inlet is inhalation, the fourth outlet is exhalation. And hey, doesn't this happen all the time,
						as long as this molecule lives and moves continuously. And because of this while breathing
						And life dies. In the same way, the movement of the fishes is also done by them
						gills. Because of the heat of the blood through the molecules
						the gills are also raised, and the water is divided; and descending towards the heart through the
						pore and frozen together, and leave the water. Saint of the Holy Spirit
						the heart, aeὶ receives again chilled. Because of someone to live and not to live
						the end is in breathing, and this in receiving the liquid.
     </p>
     <p>
      Περὶ μὲν οὖν ζωῆς καὶ θανάτου καὶ τῶν συγγενῶν ταύτης
      <lb/>
      τῆς σκέψεως, σχεδὸν εἴρηται
						περὶ πάντων. Περὶ δὲ
      <lb/>
      ὑγιείας καὶ νόσου οὐ μόνον ἐστὶν ἰατροῦ ἀλλὰ καὶ τοῦ φυσικοῦ
      <lb/>
      μέχρι του τὰς αἰτίας εἰπεῖν. Ἧι δὲ διαφέρουσι καὶ ᾗ
      <lb/>
      διαφέροντα θεωροῦσιν, οὐ
						δεῖ λανθάνειν, ἐπεὶ ὅτι γε σύνορος
      <lb/>
      ἡ πραγματεία μέχρι τινός ἐστι, μαρτυρεῖ τὸ
						γινόμενον·
      <lb/>
      τῶν τε γὰρ ἰατρῶν ὅσοι κομψοὶ ἢ περίεργοι, λέγουσί τι
      <lb/>
      περὶ φύσεως
						καὶ τὰς ἀρχὰς ἐκεῖθεν ἀξιοῦσι λαμβάνειν, καὶ
      <lb/>
      τῶν περὶ φύσεως πραγματευθέντων οἱ
						χαριέστατοι σχεδὸν
      <lb/>
      τελευτῶσιν εἰς τὰς ἀρχὰς τὰς ἰατρικάς.
     </p>
     <p lang="it">
      Della vita e della morte e dei parenti di questo pensiero, è quasi detto
						su tutto. Per quanto riguarda la salute e la malattia, non riguarda solo il medico ma anche il fisico
						fino a quando non verranno spiegate le ragioni. Ma cosa differiscono e cosa considerano diverso, no
						vedi lantanain, che il trattato è confine finché non lo si è, testimonia
						accadendo; perché di questi medici, quelli che sono eleganti o curiosi, dicono che cosa dicono della natura
						e da lì ricevono i principi del merito e delle cose svolte intorno
						felici, quasi finiscono nelle autorità mediche.
     </p>
     <p lang="en">
      About life and death and the relatives of this thought, it is almost said
						about everything. As for health and disease, it is not only for the physician but also for the physicist
						until the reasons are told. But what do they differ and what do they consider different, no
						see lantanain, that the treatise is a border until one is, testifies to
						happening; for of those physicians, those who are elegant or curious, say what about nature
						and from there they receive the principles of merit, and of the things carried out about
						happy, they almost end up in the medical authorities.
     </p>
    </div>
   </div>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
