<TEI.2>
	<teiHeader type="text">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>Bruta Animalia Ratione Uti</title>
				<author>Plutarch</author>
				<editor role="editor">William W. Goodwin</editor>
				<funder n="org:Google">Google Digital Humanities Awards Program</funder>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
				<pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
				<authority>Perseus Project</authority>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<monogr>
						<title>Bruta Animalia Ratione Uti</title>
						<author>Plutarch</author>
				<editor role="editor">William W. Goodwin</editor>
						<imprint>
							<publisher>Little, Brown and company</publisher>
							<place>Boston</place>
							<publisher>Press Of John Wilson and son</publisher>
							<place>Cambridge</place>
							<date>1874</date>
						</imprint>
						<respStmt>
							<name>Translated from the Greek by several hands</name>
							<resp>translation</resp>
							<name>William W. Goodwin</name>
							<resp>correction and revision</resp>
						</respStmt>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
				<p>Keyboarding</p>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
				<state unit="chapter"/>
			</refsDecl>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<langUsage>
				<language id="english">English</language>
			</langUsage>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<div1 type="chapitre" n="1">				<div2 type="section" n="1">					<p> ULYSSES. All these things, Circe, I believe that Ihave learned and well remember. But I would willingly ask thee, whether thou hast any Grecians here,which being men thou hast transformed into wolves andlions. CIRCE. Very many, dearest Ulysses, but wherefore doyou ask the question? ULYSSES. Because in good truth I am of opinion Ishould gain a high reputation among the Greeks, if bythy favor I could restore these men to human shape again,and not suffer them through any negligence of mine towax old in the bodies of beasts, where they lead a miserable and ignominious life. CIRCE. Surely, this man, fool as he is, believes it requisite that his ambition should be unfortunate not only tohimself and his friends, but to those that nothing belongto him. ULYSSES. Thou art now jumbling and mixing anothervillanous potion of twittle twattle, and wouldst plainlyturn me into a beast too, if thou couldst make me believethat it were a misfortune to be transformed from a beastto a man. CIRCE. What hast thou made thyself better than abeast, who, forsaking an immortal life, free from the miseries of old age, with me, art making such haste througha thousand threatening calamities to a mortal and (asI may say) old wife, pursuing an empty good and a shadowinstead of real truth, and all this, thinking to be more conspicuous and famous than thou art. ULYSSES. Well, Circe, let it be as thou sayest; forwhy should we be always contending about the samething? However, do me the favor to restore these men,and give them into my custody. CIRCE. By Hecate, not so fast neither; these are noordinary fellows. But ask them first whether they arewilling. If they refuse, do you, being such an eloquentgentleman, discourse them and persuade them; if youcannot persuade them, being too hard for ye at your ownweapon, then let it suffice ye that you have ill consultedyour own and the good of your friends. ULYSSES. Blessed woman, wherefore dost thou mockme thus? For how can they either talk or hear reason,so long as they are asses, hogs, and lions? CIRCE. Be of good comfort, most ambitious of men; Iwill so order the business, that they shall both understandand discourse; or rather, let one suffice to hear and returnanswers instead of all the rest. Look ye, here is one athand; pray talk to him. ULYSSES. Prithee, Circe, by what name shall we callhim? Who is this fellow of all the men in the world?CIRCE. What's this to the purpose? Call him Gryllus,if you please; and for my part, I'll leave ye together,that ye may not suspect him for speaking contrary to hismind to please me. </p>				</div2> 				<div2 type="section" n="2">					<p> GRYLLUS. Save ye, Mr. Ulysses. ULYSSES. And you too, by Jove, Mr. Gryllus. GRYLLUS. What is't your worship would have withme? ULYSSES. Knowing you were all born men, I pity thecondition ye are now in; and I pity ye the more, for thatbeing Greeks ye are fallen under this misfortune; andtherefore I made it my request to Circe that she wouldrestore ye again to your former shape, as many of you aswere desirous, to the end ye might return home againwith us. GRYLLUS. Hold, Mr. Ulysses, not a word more of this,I beseech your worship. For we all contemn thee, as onethat none but fools call cunning, and as vainly vauntestthyself to be wiser than other men, and yet art afraid ofbeing changed from worse to better; like children thatare frightened at physician's doses and hate going toschool, although the medicines and the precepts makethem healthy and learned of diseased and fools; just sothou refusest to be transformed out of one thing intoanother. And now thy bones rattle in thy skin for dreadof living with Circe, lest she should transform thee into ahog or a wolf; and thou wouldst persuade us living inplenty of all enjoyments not only to forsake these blessings, but to abandon her that has so well provided for us,to sail along with thee, and to become men again, the mostmiserable of all creatures. ULYSSES. In my opinion, Gryllus, this same wicked cuphas not only deprived thee of thy shape, but of thy senseand reason too; or else thou art got drunk with thoseopinions which are everywhere exploded as nasty andvillanous, unless some voluptuous pleasure of custom andhabit has bewitched thee to this body. GRYLLUS. Neither of these, O king of the Cephallenians.But if thou art come hither to dispute, and not to rail andswagger, we shall soon convince thee, having experienceof both manners of living, that our way is to be preferredbefore that which thou so much applaudest. ULYSSES. Nay, then go on; I'll listen with both ears tohear this paradox discussed. </p>				</div2> 				<div2 type="section" n="3">					<p> GRYLLUS. Have at ye then, sir. But it behooves usto begin first with those virtues which you so presumptuouslyassume to yourselves, and for which you so highly advanceyourselves before the beasts, such as justice, prudence,fortitude, &amp;c. Now answer me, thou the wisest amongmortals; for I have heard thee telling a story to Circe ofthe territory of the Cyclops, that being neither ploughednor planted by any person, it is so fertile and generouslyproductive, that it bears all sorts of fruits and herbs spontaneously Now which do you prefer, this country, oryour own goat-feeding stony Ithaca, which being cultivatedwith great labor and hardship, yet answers the expectations of the husbandmen with only a mean and scantyreturn? Now take it not amiss that I forewarn ye lestyour love to your country sway ye to give an answer contrary to truth. ULYSSES. No, no, I will not lie for the matter; I mustconfess I love and honor my own country more; but Iapplaud and admire theirs far beyond it. GRYLLUS. Hence we must conclude that it is so as thewisest of men has affirmed; that there are some things tobe praised and approved, others to be preferred by choiceand affection. And I suppose you believe the same concerning the soul. For the same reasons hold in referenceto the soul as to the ground; that such a soul should bethe best, that produces virtue like spontaneous fruit, without labor and toil. ULYSSES. Grant all this. GRYLLUS. Then you confess that the souls of beasts arethe more perfect, and more fertilely endued for the production of virtue; seeing that without any command or instruction—as it were without sowing or ploughing—itproduces and increases that virtue which is requisite forevery one. ULYSSES. Prithee, Gryllus, don't rave, but tell me whatthose virtues are that beasts partake of?  </p>				</div2> 				<div2 type="section" n="4">					<p> GRYLLUS. Rather what virtues do they not partake ofin a higher degree than the wisest of men? Look uponfortitude in the first place, of which you vaunt and brag tohave such a terrible share, being not ashamed of the magnificent titles of Ulysses the bold and city-stormer, whenindeed, like a pitiful knave as thou art, thou dost onlycircumvent by tricks and artifices men that understandonly the simple and generous way of making war, ignorantaltogether of fraud and faith-breaking, and by that meanscoverest thy deceit with the name of virtue, which neveradmits of any such coney-catching devices. But do you observe the combats and warfare of beasts, as well oneagainst another as against yourselves, how free from craftand deceit they are, and how with an open and nakedcourage they defend themselves by mere strength of body;and how, neither afraid of the law that calls them forth tobattle nor the severe edicts against deserters, but only outof scorn to be overcome, they fight with obstinacy to thelast for conquest and victory. For they are not vanquished when their bodies are worsted, neither does despair cowardize them, but they die upon the spot. Andyou shall see many times that the strength of many, whilethey are expiring, being retired and crowded together insome part of the body, still makes resistance against thevictor, and pants and fumes till at length it fails like extinguished fire that goes out for want of fuel. But thereis no crying for quarter, no begging of mercy, no acknowledgment of being beaten; nor will the lion be a slave tothe lion, nor the horse to the horse, as one man is a slaveto another, willingly and patiently embracing servitude,which derives its name (<foreign lang="greek">doulei/a</foreign>) from that of cowardice(<foreign lang="greek">deili/a</foreign>). On the other side, such beasts as men by nets andtreacherous snares get into their power, if fully grown,rather choose to die than serve, refusing nourishment andsuffering extremity of drought. But as for their youngones,—being tractable and supple by reason of theirage, and fed with the deceitful mixtures and food thatmen provide for them, their inbred fierceness languishingthrough the taste of preternatural delights,—they sufferthat which is called domestication, which is only an effeminating of their natural fury. Whence it is apparent that beasts are naturally inclinedto be courageous and daring, but that the martial confidence of men is preternatural. Which, most noble Ulysses,you may chiefly observe from hence; for that in beastsNature keeps an equal balance of strength; so that thefemale, being but little inferior to the male, undergoes allnecessary toils, and fights in defence of her young ones.And thus you hear of a certain Cromyonian sow, which,though a female, held Theseus tack, and found him worksufficient. Neither had the wisdom of that same femaleSphinx that sat on Phicium, with all her riddles and enigmas, availed her, had she not far excelled the Cadmeansin strength and fortitude. Not far from whence the Telmesian fox had his den, a great propounder of questionsalso; not to omit the female serpent that fought withApollo for his oracle at Delphi. Your king also took themare Aetha from the Sicyonian, as a bribe to dischargehim from going to the wars; and he did well, therebyshowing how much he esteemed a valiant and generousmare above a timorous coward. You yourself have alsoseen female panthers and lionesses little inferior to themales in strength and courage; when your own wife,though a Lacedaemonian, when you were hectoring andblustering abroad, sat at home in the chimney-corner, notdaring to do so much as the very swallows in encounteringthose who plagued both her and her family. Why need Istill speak of the Carian and Maeonian women? Whenceit is apparent that fortitude is not natural to men, for thenthe women would partake of the same strength with men.So that the fortitude which you exercise is only constrainedby law, not natural and voluntary, but subservient to themanners of the place and enslaved to reproach, a thingmade up only of glorious words and adventitious opinion.And you undergo labor and throw yourself into danger,not out of real valor and boldness, but because ye aremore afraid of other things. Therefore, as among thy owncompanions he that first makes haste to snatch up the lightoar does it not because he contemns it, but because he isloath to be troubled with the more heavy; so he thatendures a blow to avoid a wound, and defends himselfagainst an enemy to preserve himself from wounds anddeath, does it not out of daring courage against the one,but out of fear of the other. Thus your fortitude is onlya prudent fear; and your courage a knowing timidity,which understandingly does one thing to avoid another. In short, if you believe yourselves superior to the beastsin fortitude, why do your poets call those that behavethemselves most valiantly against their enemies wolf-breasted, lion-hearted, and compare them to wild boars;but never call the courage of lions man-like, or resemblethe strength of a wild boar to that of a man? But as theycall the swift wind-footed, and the beautiful Godlike-formed, hyperbolizing in their similes; so when they extolthe gallantry of the stout in battle, they derive their comparisons from the superior in bravery. The reason is,because courage is as it were the tincture and edge of fortitude; which the beasts make use of unmixed in theircombats, but in you being mixed with reason, like winediluted with water, it gives way to danger and loses theopportunity. And some of you there are who deny thatcourage is requisite in battle, and therefore laying it asidemake use of sober reason; which they do well for theirpreservation, but are shamefully beside the cushion, inpoint of strength and revenge. How absurd is it thereforefor you to complain of Nature, because she did not furnishyour bodies with goads and teeth and crooked claws todefend yourselves, when at the same time you would disarm the soul of her natural weapons? </p>				</div2> 				<div2 type="section" n="5">					<p> ULYSSES. In good truth, Gryllus, you are grown, inmy conceit, a notable sophister, to discourse at this rateout of a hog's snout, and yet to handle your argument sostrenuously. But why have you not all this while spokea word of temperance? GRYLLUS. Because I thought you would have contradicted first what I have already said. But you are in hasteto hear what I have to say concerning temperance, becausethat, being the husband of a most temperate and chastewife, you believe you have set us an example of temperance by abstaining from Circe's embraces. And yet inthis you differ nothing from all the beasts; for neither dothey desire to approach their superiors, but they pursuetheir pleasures and amours among those of their own tribe.No wonder is it then, if—like the Mendesian goat inEgypt, which is reported to have been shut up with several most beautiful women, yet never to have offered copulation with them, but when he was at liberty, with a lustfulfury flew upon the she-goats—so thou, though a manaddicted greatly to venereal pleasures, yet being a man,hast no desire to sleep with a goddess. And for the chastity of thy Penelope, the ten thousand rooks and daws thatchatter it abroad do but make it ridiculous and exposeit to contempt, there being not one of those birds but,if she loses her mate, continues a widow, not for a smalltime, but for nine ages of men; so that there is not one ofthose female rooks that does not surpass in chastity thyfair Penelope above nine times. </p>				</div2> 				<div2 type="section" n="6">					<p> But because thou believest me to be a sophister, Ishall observe a certain order in my discourse, first givingthee the definition of temperance, and then dividing desireaccording to the several kinds of it. Temperance then isthe contracting and well governing our desires, pruning offthose that are superfluous and encroaching upon our wills,and ruling those that are necessary by the standards ofreason and moderation. Now in desires you observe a vastnumber of distinctions. For it is both natural and necessary to drink; but as for venereal desires, which derivetheir originals from Nature, there is a time when they maybe restrained without any inconvenience; these are therefore called natural but not necessary. But there is anothersort, which are neither natural nor necessary, but infusedfrom without by vain opinion through the mistake of rightand true; and it is these that want but very little of ruining all your natural desires with their number, like a multitude of foreigners outnumbering the natives and expellingthem from their habitations. But the beasts, having theirsouls unmixed and not to be overcome by these adventitiouspassions, and living lives as distant from vain opinion asfrom the sea, are inferior to you in living elegantly and superfluously, but they are extremely wary in preservingtemperance and the right government of their desires, asbeing neither troubled with many, nor those foreign totheir natures. And therefore formerly I was no lesssmitten with the glister of gold than thou art now, as believing nothing else that a man could possess to be comparable to it. Silver also and ivory inveigled me with thesame desires; and he that enjoyed these things in thegreatest measure seemed to be a man most happy and beloved of God, whether a Phrygian or a Carian, whethermore meanly descended than Dolon or more miserable thanPriam. From thenceforward being altogether swayed bymy desires, I reaped no other pleasure nor delight in anyother blessings of my life, with which I abounded, believing that I wanted still and missed my share of those thatwere the chiefest and the greatest. Therefore, I remember, when I beheld thee in Crete, at some solemnity, mostpompously attired, I neither envied thy wisdom nor thyvirtue; but the extraordinary fineness and exquisite workmanship of thy tunic, and the glistering of thy purpleupper garment, and the beauty of the ornaments struck mewith admiration. And the golden clasp, methought, wasa pretty toy that had something of extraordinary gravingin it; and bewitched with these baubles, I followed theeas the women did. But now being altogether estrangedfrom those vain opinions, and having my understandingpurified, I tread both gold and silver under my feet as I dothe common stones; nor did I ever sleep more soundlyupon thy carpets and tapestries, than now I do, rolled overhead and ears in the deep and soft mud. None of thoseadventitious desires reside in our souls, but for the mostpart our manner of living is accustomed to necessarypleasures and desires; and as for those pleasures whichare not necessary but only natural, we make such a use ofthem as is neither without order nor moderation. </p>				</div2> 				<div2 type="section" n="7">					<p> And therefore let us consider these in the first place.The pleasure then that affects the sense of smelling withsweet odors and fragrant exhalations, besides that it hassomething in it which is pure in itself, and as it were bestowed upon us gratis, contributes also in some measure tothe distinction of nourishment. For the tongue is said tobe the judge of sweet, sour, and tart, only when the juiceshave come to be mingled and concorporate with the tastingfaculty, and not before. But our smell, before the taste,becoming sensible of the virtue and qualities of everything, and being more accurate than the tasters attendingupon princes, admits what is familiar to Nature, and expelswhatever is disagreeable to it; neither will it suffer it totouch or molest the taste, but accuses and declares theoffensiveness of the thing smelt, before it do any harm.As to other things, it troubles us not at all as it does you,whom it constrains for the sake of the sweet scents ofcinnamon, nard, malobathrum, and Arabian reed, to seekout for things dissimilar, and to jumble them togetherwith a kind of apothecary's or perfumer's art, and at vastexpense to purchase an unmanly and effeminate delight,for nothing profitable or useful. Now being such, thissense of smelling has not only corrupted all the femalesex but the greatest part of men, insomuch that they carenot to converse with their own wives, unless perfumed withprecious ointments and odoriferous compositions. Whereas sows, she-goats, and other females attract the boars, he-goats, and the males of their own kind, by their own properscents; and smelling of the pure dew, the meadows, andthe fresh grass, they are incited to copulation out of common affection; the females without the coynesses ofwomen, or the practice of little frauds and fascinations,to inflame the lust of their mates; and the males, not withamorous rage and frenzy stimulated, and enforced to purchase the act of generation with expensive hire or servileassiduity, but enjoying their seasonable amours without deceit or purchase of the satisfaction of their venery. ForNature in the spring-time, even as she puts forth the budsof plants, likewise awakens the desires of animals, butpresently quenches them again, neither the female admitting the male nor the male attempting the female afterconception. And thus pleasure has but a small and slender esteem among us; but Nature is all in all. So thateven to this very day, we beasts were never yet taintedwith coupling male with male, and female with female.Of which nevertheless there are many examples to beproduced among the greatest and most celebrated persons;for I pass by those not worth remembrance. Agamemnon hunted all Boeotia in pursuit of Argynnus,who fled his embraces; and after he had falsely accusedthe sea and winds, bravely flung himself into the lake Copais, to quench his love and free himself from the ardorof his lust. Hercules in like manner pursuing his beardless friend,forsook his choicest associates and abandoned the fleet. In the vaulted room belonging to Apollo surnamedPtous, one of you men secretly wrote this inscription,Achilles the fair; when Achilles at that time had a son.[And I hear the inscription is still remaining.] Yet if acock tread a cock in the absence of the hen, he is burnedalive, upon the signification of the soothsayer that it portends some fatal calamity. This is a plain confession inmen themselves, that the beasts excel them in chastity,and that force is not to be put upon Nature for the sakeof pleasure. But your incontinence is such, that Nature,though she have the law to assist her, is not able to keepit within bounds; insomuch that, like a rapid inundation,those inordinate desires overwhelm Nature with continualviolence, trouble, and confusion. For men have copulatedwith she-goats, sows, and mares; and women have runmad after male beasts. And from such copulations sprangthe Minotaurs and Silvans, and, as I am apt to believe, theSphinxes and Centaurs. It is true, that sometimes, constrained by hunger, a dog or a bird has fed upon humanflesh; but never yet did any beast attempt to couple withhuman kind. But men constrain and force the beasts tothese and many other unlawful pleasures. </p>				</div2> 				<div2 type="section" n="8">					<p> Now being thus wicked and incontinent in referenceto the aforesaid lustful desires, it is no less easy to beproved that men are more intemperate than beasts, even inthose things which are necessary, that is to say, in eatingand drinking, the pleasure of which we always enjoy withsome benefit to ourselves. But you, pursuing the pleasuresof eating and drinking beyond the satisfaction of nature,are punished with many and tedious diseases, which,arising from the single fountain of superfluous gormandizing, fill your bodies with all manner of wind and vapors not easy for purgation to expel. In the first place,all sorts of beasts, according to their kind, feed upon onesort of food, which is proper to their natures; some upongrass, some upon roots, and others upon fruits. They thatfeed upon flesh never mind any other sort of food. Neitherdo they rob the weaker animals of their nourishment. Butthe lion suffers the hart, and the wolf the sheep, to feedupon what Nature has provided for them. But man, suchis his voracity, falls upon all, to satisfy the pleasures of hisappetite; tries all things, tastes all things; and, as if hewere yet to seek what was the most proper diet and mostagreeable to his nature, among all the creatures is the onlyall-devourer. And first he makes use of flesh, not forwant, as having the liberty to take his choice of herbsand fruits, the plenty of which is inexhaustible; but out ofluxury and being closed with necessaries, he seeks after inconvenient and impure diet, purchased by the slaughter ofliving creatures; by that means showing himself morecruel than the most savage of wild beasts. For blood,murder, and flesh are proper to nourish the kite, the wolf,and dragon; but to men they are delicious viands. Thenmaking use of all, he does not do like the beasts, whichabstain from most creatures and are at enmity only with afew, and that only compelled by the necessities of hunger;but neither fowl nor fish nor any thing that lives upon theland escapes your tables, though they bear the epithets ofhuman and hospitable. </p>				</div2> 				<div2 type="section" n="9">					<p> Let it be so, that nothing will serve ye but to devourwhatever comes near ye, to pamper and indulge yourvoracious appetites. Yet where is the benefit and pleasureof all this? But such is the prudence of the beasts, asnot to admit of any vain and unprofitable arts. And asfor those that are necessary, they do not acquire them, asbeing introduced by others or taught for reward; neitherdo they make it their study to soder and fasten one contemplation to another, but they are supplied by their ownprudence with such as are true-born and genuine. It istrue, we hear the Egyptians are generally physicians. Butthe beasts are not only every one of them notionally endued with knowledge and art which way to cure themselves, but also to procure their food and repair theirstrength, to catch their prey by slight and cunning, toguard themselves from danger; neither are some ofthem ignorant how to teach the science of music sofar as is convenient for them. For from whom did wehogs learn to run to the rivers, when we are sick, tosearch for crawfish? Who taught the tortoises, whenthey have eaten vipers, to physic themselves with origanum? Who taught the Cretan goats, when shot witharrows that stick in their bodies, to betake themselves todittany, which they have no sooner eaten, but the headsof the darts fall out of the wound? Now if you say that Nature is the schoolmistress that teaches them these things,you acknowledge the prudence of beasts to be derived fromthe chiefest and wisest original of understanding; whichif you think not proper to call reason and wisdom, it istime for ye to find out a more glorious and honorablename for it. Indeed by its effects it shows itself to begreater and more wonderful in power; not illiterate orwithout education, but instructed by itself and wantingnothing from without; not weak and imperfect, but,through the vigor and perfection of its natural virtue,supporting and cherishing that natural contribution ofunderstanding which others attain to by instruction andeducation. So that, whatever men acquire and contemplate in the midst of their luxury and wantonness, thosethings our understanding attains to through the excellencyof our apprehensions, even contrary to the nature of thebody. For not to speak of whelps that learn to draw dryfoot, and colts that will practise figure-dances; there arecrows that will speak, and dogs that will leap throughhoops as they turn around. You shall also see horses andbulls upon the theatres lie down, dance, stop, and movetheir bodies after such a manner as would puzzle evenmen to perform the same things; which, though they areof little use, yet being learned and remembered by beasts,are great arguments of their docility. If you doubt whether we learn arts, be convinced thatwe teach them. For partridges teach their young ones tohide themselves by lying upon their backs just before aclod of earth, to escape the pursuit of the fowlers. Andyou shall observe the old storks, when their young onesfirst begin to take wing, what care they take to instructthem upon the tops of houses. Nightingales also teachtheir young ones to sing; insomuch that nightingales takenyoung out of the nest, and bred up by hand in cages, singworse, as being deprived of their instructors before theirtime. So that after I had been a while transformed intothis shape, I admired at myself, that I was so easily persuaded by idle arguments of the sophisters to believe thatall other creatures were void of sense and reason exceptman. </p>				</div2> 				<div2 type="section" n="10">					<p> ULYSSES. What then, Gryllus? Does your transmutation inform ye also that sheep and asses are rationalcreatures? GRYLLUS. From these very creatures, most worthy andbest of men, Ulysses, the nature of beasts is chiefly to bediscerned to be as it is, neither void of reason nor understanding. For as one tree is neither more or less thananother without a soul, but all are together in the samecondition of insensibility (for there is no tree that is enduedwith a soul); so neither would one animal seem to bemore slow to understand or more indocible than another, ifall did not partake of reason and understanding, thoughsome in a less, some in a greater measure. For you mustconsider that the stupidity and slothfulness of some is anargument of the quickness and subtlety of others, whicheasily appears when you compare a fox, a wolf, or a beewith a sheep or ass; as if thou shouldest compare thyselfto Polyphemus, or thy grandfather Autolycus with theCorinthian [mentioned in] Homer. For I do not believethere is such difference between beast and beast, in pointof reason and understanding and memory, as between manand man. ULYSSES. Have a care, Gryllus; it is a dangerous thingto allow them reason that have no knowledge of a Deity. GRYLLUS. Must we then deny that thou, most nobleUlysses, being so wise and full of stratagems as thou art,wast begotten by Sisyphus? . . . </p>				</div2>
			</div1>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI.2>