<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng"
    type="application/xml"
    schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title xml:lang="en">De Signis Tempestatum</title>
        <author>
          <persName>THEOPHRASTUS</persName>
          
        </author>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Encodage automatique TEI P5</resp>
          <name>zoomathia_encoder.py v3.0</name>
          <date when="2026-07-11">2026-07-11</date>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Projet Zoomathia (ANR-21-CE27-0012)</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Universite Cote d'Azur, Nice, France</pubPlace>
        <date when="2026-07-11">2026-07-11</date>
        <availability>
          <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0</licence>
        </availability>
        <idno type="zoomathia"></idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Encode automatiquement par zoomathia_encoder.py v3.0 - Projet Zoomathia</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language ident="en">anglais</language>
      </langUsage>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="zoomathia">
          <term>Zoomathia</term>
          <term>animaux</term>
          <term>inconnu</term>
          <term>anglais</term>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>Fichier encode automatiquement dans le cadre du projet Zoomathia (ANR).
        Encodage produit par zoomathia_encoder.py v3.0. Verification humaine recommandee.</p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>Balisage automatique des structures textuelles et des entites nommees
        pertinentes pour Zoomathia (animaux, plantes, personnes, lieux).</p>
        <correction status="unknown">
          <p>Encodage automatique - erreurs possibles, revision manuelle recommandee.</p>
        </correction>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
<div type="chapter" n="1">
   <p>§ 1 The signs of rain, wind, storm and fair weather we have described so far as was attainable, partly from our own observation, partly from the information of <persName>persons of credit</persName>.</p>
   <p>Now those signs which belong to the setting or rising of the heavenly bodies must be learnt from astronomy.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="2">
   <p>§ 2 Their settings are twofold, since they may be said to have set when they become invisible.</p>
   <p>And this occurs when the star sets along with the sun, and also when it sets at sunrise.</p>
   <p>In like manner their risings are twofold: there is the morning rising, when the star rises before the sun, and there is the rising at nightfall, when it rises at sunset.</p>
   <p>Now what are called the risings of <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Arcturus</name> occur at both times, his winter rising being at nightfall and his autumn rising at dawn.</p>
   <p>But the rising of most of the familiar constellations is at dawn, for instance, the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Pleiades</name>, <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Orion</name> and the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Dog</name>.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="3">
   <p>Of the remaining signs some belong specially to all such lands as contain high mountains and valleys, specially where such mountains extend down to the sea: for, when the winds begin to blow, the clouds are thrown against such places, and, when the winds change, the clouds also change and take a contrary direction, and, as they become laden with moisture, they settle down in the hollows because of their weight. Wherefore good heed must be taken to the local conditions of the region in which one is placed. It is indeed always possible to find such an observer, and the signs learnt from such persons are the most trustworthy.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="4">
   <p>Thus in some parts have been found good astronomers: for instance, <persName>Matriketas</persName> at <placeName>Methymna</placeName> observed the solstices from <placeName>Mount Lepetymnos</placeName>, <persName>Cleostratus</persName> in <placeName>Tenedos</placeName> from <placeName>Mount Ida</placeName>, <persName>Phaeinos</persName> at <placeName>Athens</placeName> from <placeName>Mount Lycabettus</placeName>: <persName>Meton</persName>, who made the cycle of nineteen years, was the pupil of the last-named. <persName>Phaeinos</persName> was a resident alien at <placeName>Athens</placeName>, while <persName>Meton</persName> was an Athenian. Others also have made astronomical observations in like manner.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="3">
   <p>Again there are other signs which are taken from domestic <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">animals</name> or from certain other quarters and happenings. Most important of all are the signs taken from the <name type="celestial" xml:lang="en">sun</name> and <name type="celestial" xml:lang="en">moon</name>: for the <name type="celestial" xml:lang="en">moon</name> is as it were a nocturnal <name type="celestial" xml:lang="en">sun</name>. Wherefore also the meetings of the months are stormy, because the <name type="celestial" xml:lang="en">moon</name>'s light fails from the fourth day from the end of one month to the fourth day from the beginning of the next: there is therefore a failure of the <name type="celestial" xml:lang="en">moon</name> corresponding to the failure of the <name type="celestial" xml:lang="en">sun</name>.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="6">
   <p>Wherefore anyone who desires to forecast the weather must pay especial heed to the character of the risings and settings of these luminaries. Now the first point to be seized is that the various periods are all divided in half, so that one's study of the year the month or the day should take account of these divisions. The year is divided in half by the setting and rising of the <foreign xml:lang="grc">Πλειάδες</foreign>: for from the setting to the rising is a half year. So that to begin with the whole period is divided into halves:</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="4">
   <p>and a like division is effected by the solstices and equinoxes. From which it follows that, whatever is the condition of the atmosphere when the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Pleiades</name> sets, that it continues in general to be till the winter solstice, and, if it does change, the change only takes place after the solstice: while, if it does not change, it continues the same till the spring equinox: the same principle holds good from that time to the rising of the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Pleiades</name>, from that again to the summer solstice, from that again to the autumnal equinox, and from that to the setting the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Pleiades</name>.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="8">
   <p>So too is it with each month; the full moon and the eighth and the fourth days make divisions into halves, so that one should make the new moon the starting-point of one's survey. A change most often takes place on the fourth day, or, failing that, on the eighth, or, failing that, at the full moon; after that the periods are from the full moon to the eighth day from the end of the month, from that to the fourth day from the end, and from that to the new moon.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="9">
   <p>The divisions of the day follow in general the same principle: there is the sunrise, the mid-morning, noon, mid-afternoon, and sunset; and the corresponding divisions of the night have like effects in the matter of winds storms and fair weather; that is to say, if there is to be a change, it will generally occur at one of these divisions. In general therefore one should observe the periods in the way indicated, though as to particular signs we must follow the accepted method.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="10">
   <p>THE SIGNS OF RAIN Now the signs of rain appear to be as follows: most unmistakable is that which occurs at dawn, when the sky has a reddish appearance before sunrise; for this usually indicates rain within three days, if not on that very day. Other signs point the same way: thus a red sky at sunset indicates rain within three days, if not before, though less certainly than a red sky at dawn.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="11">
   <p>Again, if the sun sets in a cloud in winter or spring, this generally indicates rain within three days. So too, if there are streaks of light from the south, while, if these are seen from the north, it is a less certain sign.</p>
   <p>Again, if the sun when it rises has a black mark, or if it rises out of clouds, it is a sign of rain; while, if at sunrise there are rays shooting out before the actual rising, it is a sign of rain and also of wind.</p>
   <p>Again if, as the sun sinks, a cloud forms below it and this breaks up its rays, it is a sign of stormy weather.</p>
   <p>Again, if it sets or rises with a burning heat, and there is no wind, it is a sign of rain.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="12">
   <p>Moonrise gives similar indications, at the time of full moon: they are less certain when the moon is not full.</p>
   <p>If the moon looks fiery, it indicates breezy weather for that month, if dusky, wet weather; and, whatever indications the crescent moon gives, are given when it is three days old.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="13">
   <p>Many shooting stars are a sign of rain or wind, and the wind or rain will come from that quarter from which they appear. Again, if at sunrise or sunset the sun's rays appear massed together, it is a sign of rain. Also it is a sign of rain when at sunrise the rays are coloured as in an eclipse; and also when there are clouds like a fleece of wool. The rising of bubbles in large numbers on the surface of rivers is a sign of abundant rain. And in general, when a rainbow is seen round or through a lamp, it signifies rain from the south.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="14">
   <p>Again, if the wind is from the south, the snuff of the lamp-wick indicates rain; it also indicates wind in proportion to its bulk and seize: while if the snuff is small, like <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">millet-seed</name>, and of bright colour, it indicates rain as well as wind. Again, when in winter the lamp rejects the flame but catches, as it were, here and there in spurts, it is a sign of rain; so also is it, if the rays of light leap up on the lamp, or if there are sparks.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="15">
   <p>It is a sign of rain or storm when <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">birds</name> which are not aquatic take a bath. It is a sign of rain when a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">toad</name> takes a bath, and still more so when <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">frogs</name> are vocal. So too is the appearance of the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">lizard</name> known as '<name type="animal" xml:lang="en">salamander</name>,' and still more the chirruping of the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">green frog</name> in a tree. It is a sign of rain when <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">swallows</name> hit the water of the lakes with their belly. It is a sign of storm or rain when the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">ox</name> licks his fore-hoof; if he puts his head up towards the sky and snuffs the air, it is a sign of rain.</p>
</div>

<div type="section" n="16">
   <p>It is a sign of rain when a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">crow</name> puts back its head on a rock which is washed by waves, or when it often dives or hovers over the water. It is a sign of rain if the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">raven</name>, who is accustomed to make many different sounds, repeats one of these twice quickly and makes a whirring sound and shakes its wings. So too if, during a rainy season, he utters many different sounds, or if he searches for <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">lice</name> perched in an <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">olive-tree</name>. And if, whether in fair or wet weather, he imitates, as it were, with his voice falling drops, it is a sign of rain. So too is it if <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">ravens</name> or <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">jackdaws</name> fly high and scream like <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">hawks</name>. And, if a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">raven</name> in fair weather does not utter his accustomed note and makes a whirring with his wings, it is a sign of rain.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="9">
   <p>It is a sign of rain if a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">hawk</name> perches on a tree, flies right into it and proceeds to search for lice: also, when in summer a number of birds living on an island pack together: if a moderate number left, it is a good sign for <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">goats</name> and flocks, while if the number is exceedingly large, it portends a severe drought. And in general it is a sign of rain when <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">cocks</name> and <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">hens</name> search for lice; as also when they make a noise like that of falling rain.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="10">
   <p>Again it is a sign of rain when a tame <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">duck</name> gets under the eaves and flaps its wings. Also it is a sign of rain when <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">jackdaws</name> and <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">fowls</name> flap their wings whether on a lake or on the sea — like the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">duck</name>. It is a sign of wind or rain when a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">heron</name> utters his note at early morning: if, as he flies towards the sea, he utters his cry, it is a sign of rain rather than of wind, and in general, if he makes a loud cry, it portends wind.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="11">
   <p>It is a sign of rain or storm if a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">chaffinch</name> kept in the house utters its note at dawn. It is also a sign if any pot filled with water causes sparks to fly when it is put on the fire. It is also a sign of rain when a number of <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">millepedes</name> are seen crawling up a wall. A <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">dolphin</name> diving near land and frequently reappearing indicates rain or storm.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="20">
   <p>If the lesser <placeName>Mount Hymettus</placeName> , which is called <foreign xml:lang="en">Anydros</foreign> (waterless), has cloud in its hollows, it is a sign of rain: so also is it, if the greater <placeName>Hymettus</placeName> has clouds in summer on the top and on the sides: or if <foreign xml:lang="en">waterless Hymettus</foreign> has white clouds on the top and on the sides; also if the <name type="wind">south-west wind</name> blows at the equinox.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="21">
   <p>Thunder in winter and at dawn indicates <name type="wind">wind</name> rather than rain; thunder in summer at midday or in the evening is a sign of rain. If lightning is seen from all sides, it will be a sign of rain or <name type="wind">wind</name>, and also if it occurs in the evening. Again, if when the <name type="wind">south wind</name> is blowing at early dawn, there is lightning from the same quarter, it indicates rain or <name type="wind">wind</name>. When the <name type="wind">west wind</name> is accompanied by lightning from the <name type="wind">north</name>, it indicates either storm or rain. Lightning in the evening in summer time indicates rain within three days, if not immediately. Lightning from the <name type="wind">north</name> in late summer is a sign of rain.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="22">
   <p>When <name type="placeName" xml:lang="en">Euboea</name> has a girdle about it up to the waist, there will be rain in a short space. If cloud clings about <placeName>Mount Pelion</placeName>, it is an indication of rain or wind from the quarter to which it clings. When a rainbow appears, it is an indication of rain; if many rainbows appear, it is an indication of long-continued rain. So too is it often when the sun appears suddenly out of cloud. It is a sign of rain if <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">ants</name> in a hollow place carry their eggs up from the ant-hill to the high ground, a sign of fair weather if they carry them down.</p>
   <p>If two mock-suns appear, one to the south, the other to the north, and there is at the same time a halo, these indicate that it will shortly rain. A dark halo round the sun indicates rain, especially if it occurs in the afternoon.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="23">
   <p>In the <name type="constellation" xml:lang="en">Crab</name> are two stars called the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Asses</name>, and the nebulous space between them is called the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">Manger</name>; if this appears dark, it is a sign of rain. If there is no rain at the rising of the <name type="star" xml:lang="en">Dog</name> or of <name type="star" xml:lang="en">Arcturus</name>, there will generally be rain or wind towards the equinox. Also the popular saying about <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">flies</name> is true; when they bite excessively, it is a sign of rain. If a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">chaffinch</name> utters its note at dawn, it is a sign of rain or storm, if in the afternoon, of rain.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="24">
   <p>When at night a long stretch of white cloud encompasses <placeName>Hymettus</placeName> below the peaks, there will generally be rain in a few days. If cloud settles on <name type="deity">Zeus Hellanios</name> in <placeName>Aegina</placeName>, usually rain follows. If a great deal of rain falls in winter, the spring is usually dry; if the winter has been dry, the spring is usually wet. When there is much snow in winter, a good season generally follows.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="25">
   <p>Some say that, if in the embers there is an appearance as of shining <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">hail-stones</name>, it generally prognosticates <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">hail</name>; while, if the appearance is like a number of small shining <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">millet-seeds</name>, it portends fair weather, if there is wind at the time, but, if there is no wind, rain or wind. It is better both for <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">plants</name> and for <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">animals</name> that rain should come from the north before it comes from the south; it must however be fresh and not briny to the taste. And in general a season in which a north wind prevails is better and healthier than one in which southerly winds prevail. It is a sign of a long winter when <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">sheep</name> or <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">goats</name> have a second breeding season.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="26">
   <p>The following are signs of wind and breezes. If the sun rises with a burning heat but does not shine brilliantly, it is a sign of wind. If the sun has a hollow appearance, it is a sign of wind or rain. If it blazes with a burning heat for several days, it portends long-continued drought or wind. If at dawn its rays are parted, some pointing to the north and some to the south, while the orb itself is clearly seen between, it is a sign of rain and wind.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="27">
   <p>Also black spots on the sun or moon indicate rain, red spots wind. Again, if, while a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">north wind</name> blows, the horns of the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">crescent moon</name> stand out straight, westerly winds will generally succeed, and the rest of the month will be stormy. When the upper horn of the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">crescent moon</name> is bent, northerly winds will prevail for that part of the month: when the lower horn is bent, southerly winds will prevail. If however the horns up to the fourth day point straight and have not a graceful bend inwards but round to a circle, it will generally be stormy till the middle of the month. If the moon is dusky, it indicates rain, if fiery, it indicates wind.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="28">
   <p>It is a sign of rain when <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">gulls</name> and <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">ducks</name>, whether wild or tame, plunge under water, a sign of wind when they flap their wings. Wherever the bird called <foreign xml:lang="grc">kepphos</foreign> flies during a calm, it is sign of coming wind. If <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">sparrows</name> in winter begin to be clamorous at evening, it is a sign of a coming change or of a fall of rain. A <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">heron</name> flying from the sea and screaming is a sign that a breeze is coming: so is it in general a sign of wind when he screams loudly.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="29">
   <p>A <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">dog</name> rolling on the ground is a sign of violent wind. A number of <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">cobwebs</name> in motion portends wind or storm. The ebb-tide indicates a north wind, the flowing tide a wind from the south. For, if the flowing tide sets from the north, there is a change to the south, and if an ebb-tide comes from the south, there is a change to the north. It is a sign of wind when the sea has a swell or promontories moan or there is loud noise on the beach. Now the north wind has less force as it ceases to blow, the south wind as it begins. A mock sun, in whatever quarter it appears, indicates rain or wind.</p>
</div>
<div type="chapter" n="15">
   <p>§ 30 The fifteenth day after the winter solstice is generally marked by southerly winds. If there is a northerly wind, everything gets dried up, if a southerly, there is abundant moisture.</p>
   <p>If, while a south wind is blowing, glued articles make a crackling sound, it indicates a change to a <name type="wind">south wind</name>.</p>
   <p>If the feet swell, there will be a change to a <name type="wind">south wind</name>. This also sometimes indicates a hurricane.</p>
   <p>So too does it, if a man has a shooting pain in the right foot.</p>
   <p>The behaviour of the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">hedgehog</name> is also significant: this animal makes two holes wherever he lives, one towards the north, the other towards the south: now whichever hole he blocks up, it indicates wind from that quarter, and, if he closes both, it indicates violent wind.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="31">
   <p>If a mountain <quote>...</quote>, it indicates wind from the north. If at sea during a wind there is a sudden calm, it indicates a change or an increase of wind. If promontories seem to stand high out of the sea, or a single island looks like several, it indicates a change to south wind. If the land looks black from the sea, it indicates a north wind, if white, a south wind. A halo about the moon signifies wind more certainly than a halo about the sun: but in either case, if there is a break in the halo, it indicates wind, which will come from the quarter in which the break is. If the sky is overcast in whatever quarter the sun is first seen, there will be wind from that quarter. Light clouds in summer-time indicate wind.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="32">
   <p>If lightning comes from all sides, it indicates rain, and from any quarter from which the flashes come in quick succession there will be wind. In summer from whatever quarter light and thunder come, there will be violent winds: if the flashes are brilliant and startling, the wind will come sooner and be more violent; if they are of gentler character and come at longer intervals, the wind will get up gradually. In winter and autumn however the reverse happens, for the lightning causes the wind to cease: and, the more violent the lightning and thunder are, the more will the wind be reduced. In spring I consider that the indications would not so invariably have the same meaning, — and this is also true of winter.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="17">
   <p>If, while a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">south wind</name> is blowing, there comes lightning from the north, the wind ceases. If there is lightning at dawn, the wind generally ceases on the third day: other winds than a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">south wind</name> however do not cease till the fifth seventh or ninth day, though a wind which got up in the afternoon will cease sooner. A <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">north wind</name> generally ceases in an odd, a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">south wind</name> in an even number of days. Winds get up at sunrise or moonrise. If the rising sun or moon have caused the wind to cease, presently it gets up again with more force, and winds which begin to blow in the day-time last longer and are stronger than those which begin at night.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="18">
   <p>If periodic winds have been blowing for a long time, and a windy autumn follows, the winter is windless: if however the contrary happens, the character of winter is also reversed. From whatever quarter cloud streams out from a mountain peak, wind will blow in the direction thus indicated. Clouds which cling to the back of the mountain will also produce wind from the back of it. If there is a girdle of cloud halfway up <placeName>Mount Athos</placeName>, and if mountains in general wear such a girdle, there will generally follow a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">southerly wind</name>. <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Comets</name> usually indicate wind, and, if there are many of them, drought is also indicated. After snow a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">south wind</name>, after hoar-frost a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">north wind</name> generally blows. Snuff in a lamp indicates wind or rain from the south.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="35">
   <p>The points from which the winds come are as they are given in the figure. The winds which most often come on the top of other winds while these are still blowing are the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">north wind</name> (<foreign xml:lang="grc">aparktias</foreign>),<pb n="74"/> the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">north-north-east</name> and the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">north-west</name>. When however the winds are not dispersed by one another but die down of their own accord, they change to the next winds on the figure, reckoning from left to right according to the course of the sun. When the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">south wind</name> begins to blow, it is dry, but it becomes wet before it ceases: so too does the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">south-east wind</name>. The <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">east wind</name>, coming from the quarter where the sun rises at the equinox, is wet: but it brings the rain in light showers.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="36">
   <p>The <name type="wind">north-east</name> and <name type="wind">south-west</name> are the wettest <name type="wind">winds</name>; the <name type="wind">north</name> the <name type="wind">north-north-east</name> and the <name type="wind">north-east</name> bring <name type="weather">hail</name>; <name type="weather">snow</name> comes with the <name type="wind">north-north-east</name> and <name type="wind">north</name>. The <name type="wind">south</name>, the <name type="wind">west</name>, and the <name type="wind">south-east</name> <name type="wind">winds</name> bring <name type="weather">heat</name>. Some of these have their effect on <placeName>places</placeName> which they strike as they come from the <name type="water">sea</name>, others on <placeName>places</placeName> which they visit as they come over <name type="terrain">land</name>. The <name type="wind">winds</name> which more than any others make the sky thick with <name type="cloud">cloud</name> and completely cover it are the <name type="wind">north-east</name> and the <name type="wind">south-west</name>, especially the former. While the other <name type="wind">winds</name> repel the <name type="cloud">clouds</name> from themselves, the <name type="wind">north-east</name> alone attracts them as it blows. Those <name type="wind">winds</name> which chiefly bring a clear sky are the <name type="wind">north-north-west</name> and the <name type="wind">north-west</name>, and next after them the <name type="wind">north</name>. Those which most have the character of a <name type="weather">hurricane</name> are the <name type="wind">north</name> the <name type="wind">north-north-west</name> and the <name type="wind">north-west</name>.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="37">
   <p>They acquire this character when they fall upon one another as they blow, especially in <name type="season">autumn</name>, but to some extent in <name type="season">spring</name>. Those which are accompanied by <name type="phenomenon">lightning</name> are the <name type="wind">north-north-west</name> the <name type="wind">north-west</name> the <name type="wind">north</name> and the <name type="wind">north-north-east</name>. If at <name type="water">sea</name> a quantity of <name type="plant">down</name> is seen blown along, which has come from <name type="plant">thistles</name>, it indicates that there will be a great <name type="wind">wind</name>. <name type="wind">Wind</name> may be expected from any quarter in which a number of <name type="phenomenon">shooting stars</name> are seen. If these appear in every quarter alike, it indicates many <name type="wind">winds</name>. Such then are the signs of <name type="wind">winds</name>.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="38">
   <p>The following are signs of storm. The <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">sun</name> becoming obscured as it sinks indicates storm. And, according as its orb is divided as it sets, so the succeeding days turn out; for instance, a third or a half of the orb may remain visible. If the horns of the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">moon</name> point straight up till the fourth day, and if it rounds to a circle, it will be stormy till the middle of the month. If <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">cranes</name> fly early and in flocks, it will be an early winter; if they fly late and for a long time, it will be a late winter; and, if they wheel as they fly, it indicates stormy weather.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="39">
   <p>It is a sign of storm when <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">geese</name> make more clamour than usual or fight for their food; so too is it when a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">sparrow</name> or <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">chaffinch</name> twitters at dawn. It indicates a storm when the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">goldcrest</name> goes into holes and hides itself; so also when the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">redbreast</name> does the same. It is a sign of storm when the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">crow</name> caws twice in quick succession and then a third time; also when the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">crow</name> or <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">raven</name> or <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">jackdaw</name> makes its call late. It is a sign of a great storm when a white <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">sparrow</name> or <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">swallow</name> is seen, or a white specimen of any other <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">bird</name> which is not usually white, even as the appearance of a large number of such <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">birds</name> of a dark colour signifies rain.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="40">
   <p>It is also an indication of storm when <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">birds</name> flee from the sea. A <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">chaffinch</name> uttering its note in an inhabited house is a sign of storm. All the signs which indicate rain bring stormy weather, that is to say, snow and storm, if not rain.</p>
   <p>If the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">raven</name> utters a great variety of sounds in winter, it is a sign of storm. <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Jackdaws</name> flying from the south are a sign of storm, and so are <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">cuttle-fish</name>. It is a sign of storm when a loud voice is heard in harbour, which is re-echoed many times. It is a sign of a stormy season when a number of <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">jelly-fish</name> appear in the sea. It indicates an early winter when the breeding season of <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">sheep</name> begins early.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="41">
   <p>If in autumn <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">sheep</name> or <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">oxen</name> dig holes and lie keeping their heads close to one another, it indicates a severe winter.</p>
   <p>They say that in <placeName>Pontus</placeName> when <foreign xml:lang="grc">Ἀρκτοῦρος</foreign> rises, (<name type="animal" xml:lang="en">the cattle</name>) face northwards as they graze.</p>
   <p>It is a sign of storm when <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">cattle</name> eat more than usual and lie down on their right sides. So is it when the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">ass</name> shakes his ears, or when <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">sheep</name> or <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">birds</name> fight for their food more than usual, since they are then trying to secure a store against between him: also when <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">mice</name> squeak and dance.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="42">
   <p>A <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">bitch</name> digging holes with her paws and a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">tree-frog</name> croaking alone at early dawn are signs of storm: it indicates storm when a number of the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">worms</name> called 'the earth's entrails' appear. It is a sign of storm if the fire refuses to catch, or if a lamp refuses to light: while, if much ash is formed, it is a sign of snow. If a lamp burns steadily in fine weather, it is a sign of storm: so is it if in winter-time dark snuff forms: if it is, as it were, full of numerous <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">millet-seeds</name>, there will be stormy weather; and if these in fine weather appear in a circle round the flame, it is a sign of snow.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="43">
   <p>If the '<foreign xml:lang="en">'Ass's Manger'</foreign>' [<foreign xml:lang="la">Praesepe</foreign>] shrinks in size and becomes dark, it is a sign of storm; also if there is vivid lightning which does not remain in the same quarter. If at the setting of the <foreign xml:lang="en">Pleiades</foreign> there is lightning over <placeName>Parnes</placeName>, <placeName>Brilessus</placeName> and <placeName>Hymettus</placeName> — when it appears over all three mountains, it indicates a great storm; when over the two lesser heights, a less violent storm; when over <placeName>Parnes</placeName> alone, fine weather. Again, if during a storm a long cloud stretches over <placeName>Hymettus</placeName>, it signifies that the storm will increase in force. It is a sign of storm when <placeName>Athos</placeName>, <placeName>Olympus</placeName> and mountain-peaks in general are covered with clouds. If during fine weather a cloud appears in the sky stretching a long way and torn to shreds, stormy weather will continue.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="44">
   <p>If the autumn is unusually fine, the succeeding spring is usually cold. If winter begins early, it ends early and there is a fair spring; if the reverse, spring will also be late. If the winter is wet, the spring will be dry, if the winter is dry, the spring will be fair. If the late summer is satisfactory, the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">sheep</name> will generally suffer from hunger. If the spring and summer are cold, the late summer and autumn will be stifling hot and windless.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="45">
   <p>If the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">kermes-oak</name> fruits well, there follows a long succession of storms. If a cloud stands upright on a mountain-peak, it indicates storm; whence <persName>Archilochus</persName>’s lines “Mark you, <persName>Glaucus</persName>; deep ocean is now stirred up with waves, and about the heights of the <placeName>Gyrae</placeName> there rises a cloud erect, the sign of storm.” If the clouds are of uniform colour, like a white membrane, it is a sign of storm. When, as some clouds are motionless, others move towards them while they remain at rest, it is a sign of storm.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="46">
   <p>If the sun in winter after gleaming out is again obscured, and this is repeated two or three times, it will be stormy all day. If the star <name type="deity">Hermes</name> appears in winter, it indicates cold, if in summer, heat.</p>
   <p>When in fine weather <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">bees</name> do not fly long distances, but fly about where they are, it indicates that there will be a storm. The howling of a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">wolf</name> indicates a storm within three days. When a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">wolf</name> approaches or enters cultivated ground in the season of winter, it indicates that a storm will come immediately.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="47">
   <p>It is also a sign of great storms and heavy rain when many <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">wasps</name> appear in autumn, or when white <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">birds</name> approach cultivated lands; and in general when wild creatures approach such lands, it indicates a north wind and a severe storm.</p>
   <p>If the western side of <placeName>Parnes</placeName> and the side towards <placeName>Phyle</placeName> are blocked with clouds during a north wind, it is a sign of storm.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="48">
   <p>When there is a severe heat, generally there is compensation and a severe winter follows. If there is much rain in spring, it is followed by severe heat in low-lying districts and valleys; so that one should mark how the season begins.</p>
   <p>If the autumn is exceedingly fine, generally the spring is cold: if the spring is late and cold, the summer goes on late and the autumn is usually scorching hot.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="49">
   <p>When the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">kermes-oak</name> fruits exceedingly well, it generally indicates a severe winter, and sometimes they say that this sign is followed by droughts. If one takes a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">mole</name> and puts it in a tub, the bottom of which has been covered with clay, it indicates by the sounds which it utters wind or fine weather. There is also the sign of storm which is popularly recognized everywhere, namely when <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">mice</name> fight for the possession of chaff and carry it about.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="50">
   <p><persName>The SIGNS OF FAIR WEATHER</persName> The following are signs of fair weather. If the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">sun</name> rises brilliant but without scorching heat and without showing any special sign in his orb, it indicates fair weather. The same may be said of the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">moon</name> when it is full. If in winter that part of the sky into which the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">sun</name> goes down is clear, it is a sign of fair weather, unless on the preceding days that part has not been clear, though it was clear above the horizon: in that case the prospect is uncertain. It is also a sign of fair weather, if during stormy conditions that part of the sky into which the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">sun</name> sets is clear; and also if, in winter at the time of setting, the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">sun</name> has a pale colour.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="51">
   <p>Again, it indicates fair weather if the outline of the moon of the third day is bright; also if the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Ass's Manger</name> is clear and bright. If the halo forms and disappears evenly, it is a sign of fair weather. Light clouds in winter are a sign of fine weather. It is a sign of fine weather when <placeName>Olympus Athos</placeName> and in general the mountains which give signs have their tops clear: so too is it, when clouds encompass them at the sea-level. Also when after rain the clouds have a bronze colour towards sundown: in that case there will generally be fair weather the next day.</p>
</div>

<div type="section" n="52">
   <p>When there is mist, little or no rain follows. When <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">cranes</name> take flight and do not come back, it is a sign of fair weather: for they do not do so till they see a clear sky before them as they fly. It is a sign of fair weather when during a storm an <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">owl</name> makes a low hoot, or at night during a storm it utters a low sound. If the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">sea-owl</name> utters its note during a storm, it indicates fair weather, if during fair weather, it indicates a storm. It is a sign of fair weather if a solitary <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">raven</name> makes a low croak, and, after croaking three times, repeats the sound again and again. . . .</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="53">
   <p>If the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">crow</name> caws thrice directly the dawn appears, it indicates fair weather, as also if it makes a low note in the evening during a storm.</p>
   <p>It is a sign of fair weather if a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">goldcrest</name> flies out abroad from a hole or from a hedge or from its nest.</p>
   <p>Again, if during a storm from the north there is a white gleam from that quarter, while in the south a solid mass of cloud has formed, it generally signifies a change to fair weather.</p>
   <p>Again when the <foreign xml:lang="grc">Boreas</foreign> as it begins to blow violently stirs up a number of clouds, it indicates fair weather.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="54">
   <p>When <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">sheep</name> begin to breed late, it is a sign which fulfils itself in fair weather.</p>
   <p>So is it when an <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">ox</name> lies on his left side, and also when a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">dog</name> does the same: if they lie on the right side, it indicates storm.</p>
   <p>The appearance of a number of <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">cicadas</name> indicates that the season will be unhealthy.</p>
   <p>If a lamp burns quietly during a storm, it indicates fair weather.</p>
   <p>So also if it has on the surface an appearance like shining <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">millet-seeds</name>: also if a bright line surrounds the lamp-nozzle.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="55">
   <p>The fruiting of the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">mastich</name> gives signs as to the seasons of sowing: it takes place at three several periods, which indicate respectively the time for the first the second and the third sowing: and according as one or the other of these fruiting-times turns out best and produces the most abundant fruit, so too will be the success of the corresponding time of sowing.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="56">
   <p>MISCELLANEOUS SIGNS The following signs are said to affect either the whole year or whole periods of it. If at the beginning of winter there is dull weather followed by heat, and these conditions are dispersed by wind without rain, it indicates that towards the spring there will be <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">hail</name>. Again, if after the spring equinox mists come down, it is an indication of breezes and winds by the seventh month, reckoning inclusively. Those mists which come down when the moon is in its first quarter indicate breezes for that period, those which come down when the moon is in its third quarter indicate <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">rain</name>. And the more mists come down when the moon is assuming either shape, the more certainly is the result just mentioned indicated.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="57">
   <p>Also the winds which accompany the falling of the mists are significant: if the breezes come from the east or south, <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">rain</name> is indicated; if from the west or north, breezes and cold weather. And the stars which the Egyptians call <foreign xml:lang="en">'comets'</foreign> indicate not only the conditions just mentioned but also cold weather. In the case of the rising of the stars the indication, as in the case of also of the equinoxes and solstices, is given not at the actual time but a little earlier or later.</p>
</div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>