<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title xml:lang="grc">Ὁμιλίαι εἰς τὴν Ἑξαήμερον</title>
        <title type="alt" xml:lang="fr">Homélies sur l'Hexaéméron</title>
        <title type="alt" xml:lang="en">Homilies on the Hexaemeron</title>
        <author>
          <persName>BASILIUS</persName>
          <idno type="zoomathia">tlg2040</idno>
        </author>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Encodage automatique TEI P5</resp>
          <name>zoomathia_encoder.py v3.0</name>
          <date when="2026-07-02">2026-07-02</date>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Projet Zoomathia (ANR-21-CE27-0012)</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Universite Cote d'Azur, Nice, France</pubPlace>
        <date when="2026-07-02">2026-07-02</date>
        <availability>
          <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0</licence>
        </availability>
        <idno type="zoomathia">tlg2040</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Encode automatiquement par zoomathia_encoder.py v3.0 - Projet Zoomathia</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language ident="en">anglais</language>
      </langUsage>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="zoomathia">
          <term>Zoomathia</term>
          <term>animaux</term>
          <term>tardo-antique (300 - 700 ap. J.-C.)</term>
          <term>anglais</term>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>Fichier encode automatiquement dans le cadre du projet Zoomathia (ANR).
        Encodage produit par zoomathia_encoder.py v3.0. Verification humaine recommandee.</p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>Balisage automatique des structures textuelles et des entites nommees
        pertinentes pour Zoomathia (animaux, plantes, personnes, lieux).</p>
        <correction status="unknown">
          <p>Encodage automatique - erreurs possibles, revision manuelle recommandee.</p>
        </correction>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="en">
    <body>
Voici l'encodage TEI P5 strict du texte fourni, conforme aux règles du projet Zoomathia et aux spécifications demandées :


<div type="book" n="1">
  <div type="chapter" n="9">
    <milestone unit="section" n="1.9" />
    <p><persName>Basil</persName>: Hexaemeron, Homily IX</p>
    <p>The creation of terrestrial <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">animals</name>.</p>
  </div>
</div>
Voici l'encodage TEI P5 strictement conforme aux règles du projet Zoomathia pour le texte de Basilius, *Homiliae in Hexaemeron* (2/21) :


<div type="section" n="2.21">
   <p>How did you like the fare of my morning's discourse? It seemed to me that I had the good intentions of a poor giver of a feast, who, ambitious of having the credit of keeping a good table saddens his guests by the poor supply of the more expensive dishes. In vain he lavishly covers his table with his mean fare; his ambition only shows his folly. It is for you to judge if I have shared the same fate. Yet, whatever my discourse may have been, take care lest you disregard it. No one refused to sit at the table of <persName>Elisha</persName>; and yet he only gave his friends wild vegetables. <quote><foreign xml:lang="he">2 Kings 4:39</foreign></quote></p>
   <p>I know the laws of allegory, though less by myself than from the works of others. There are those truly, who do not admit the common sense of the Scriptures, for whom water is not water, but some other nature, who see in a <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">plant</name>, in a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">fish</name>, what their fancy wishes, who change the nature of <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">reptiles</name> and of <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">wild beasts</name> to suit their allegories, like the interpreters of dreams who explain visions in sleep to make them serve their own ends. For me <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">grass</name> is <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">grass</name>; <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">plant</name>, <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">fish</name>, <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">wild beast</name>, <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">domestic animal</name>, I take all in the literal sense.</p>
   <p>For I am not ashamed of the gospel. <quote><foreign xml:lang="he">Romans 1:16</foreign></quote></p>
   <p>Those who have written about the nature of the universe have discussed at length the shape of the earth. If it be spherical or cylindrical, if it resemble a disc and is equally rounded in all parts, or if it has the forth of a winnowing basket and is hollow in the middle; all these conjectures have been suggested by cos</p>
</div>
Voici l'encodage TEI P5 strictement conforme à vos exigences pour ce passage de Basilius, *Homiliae in Hexaemeron* (3/21) :


<div type="book" n="3">
  <div type="chapter" n="21">
    <p>mographers, each one upsetting that of his predecessor. It will not lead me to give less importance to the creation of the universe, that the servant of God, <persName>Moses</persName>, is silent as to shapes; he has not said that the earth is a hundred and eighty thousand furlongs in circumference; he has not measured into what extent of air its shadow projects itself while the sun revolves around it, nor stated how this shadow, casting itself upon the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">moon</name>, produces eclipses. He has passed over in silence, as useless, all that is unimportant for us. Shall I then prefer foolish wisdom to the oracles of the Holy Spirit? Shall I not rather exalt Him who, not wishing to fill our minds with these vanities, has regulated all the economy of Scripture in view of the edification and the making perfect of our souls? It is this which those seem to me not to have understood, who, giving themselves up to the distorted meaning of allegory, have undertaken to give a majesty of their own invention to Scripture. It is to believe themselves wiser than the <name type="deity">Holy Spirit</name>, and to bring forth their own ideas under a pretext of exegesis. Let us hear Scripture as it has been written.</p>
  </div>
</div>
Voici l'encodage TEI P5 strict du texte fourni, conforme aux règles du projet Zoomathia :


<div type="book" n="2">
   <div type="section" n="4">
      <milestone unit="section" n="2.4" />
      <p>Let the earth bring forth the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">living creature</name>. Genesis 1:24</p>
      <p>Behold the word of God pervading creation, beginning even then the efficacy which is seen displayed today, and will be displayed to the end of the world!</p>
      <p>As a ball, which one pushes, if it meet a declivity, descends, carried by its form and the nature of the ground and does not stop until it has reached a level surface; so nature, once put in motion by the Divine command, traverses creation with an equal step, through birth and death, and keeps up the succession of kinds through resemblance, to the last.</p>
      <p>Nature always makes a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">horse</name> succeed to a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">horse</name>, a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">lion</name> to a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">lion</name>, an <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">eagle</name> to an <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">eagle</name>, and preserving each <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">animal</name> by these uninterrupted successions she transmits it to the end of all things.</p>
      <p><name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Animals</name> do not see their peculiarities destroyed or effaced by any length of time; their nature, as though it had been just constituted, follows the course of ages, for ever young.</p>
      <p>Let the earth bring forth the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">living creature</name>. This command has continued and earth does not cease to obey the Creator.</p>
      <p>For, if there are <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">creatures</name> which are successively produced by their predecessors, there are others that even today we see born from the earth itself.</p>
      <p>In wet weather she brings forth <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">grasshoppers</name> and an immense number of <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">insects</name> which fly in the air and have no names because they are so small; she also produces <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">mice</name> and <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">frogs</name>.</p>
      <p>In the environs of <placeName>Thebes</placeName> in <placeName>Egypt</placeName>, after abundant rain in hot weather, the country is covered with f</p>
   </div>
</div>
Voici l'encodage TEI P5 strictement conforme à vos exigences pour le texte de Basilius, *Homiliae in Hexaemeron* 5/21 :


<div type="book" n="5">
  <div type="section" n="21">
    <p>ield mice.  We see mud alone produce <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">eels</name>; they do not proceed from an egg, nor in any other manner; it is the earth alone which gives them birth.  Let the earth produce a living creature.</p>
    <p><name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Cattle</name> are terrestrial and bent towards the earth. <persName>Man</persName>, a celestial growth, rises superior to them as much by the mould of his bodily conformation as by the dignity of his soul. What is the form of <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">quadrupeds</name>? Their head is bent towards the earth and looks towards their belly, and only pursues their belly's good. Your head, O <persName>man</persName>, is turned towards heaven; your eyes look up.</p>
    <p>When therefore you degrade yourself by the passions of the flesh, slave of your belly, and your lowest parts, you approach <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">animals</name> without reason and becomest like one of them.  You are called to more noble cares; seek those things which are above where <name type="deity">Christ</name> sits. <quote>Colossians 3:1</quote> Raise your soul above the earth; draw from its natural conformation the rule of your conduct; fix your conversation in heaven. Your true country is the heavenly <placeName>Jerusalem</placeName>;  your fellow citizens and your compatriots are the first-born which are written in heaven. <quote>Hebrews 12:23</quote></p>
  </div>
</div>
<div type="section" n="6">
   <p>Let the earth bring forth the living creature. Thus when the soul of <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">brutes</name> appeared it was not concealed in the earth, but it was born by the command of God. <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Brutes</name> have one and the same soul of which the common characteristic is absence of reason. But each <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">animal</name> is distinguished by peculiar qualities. The <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">ox</name> is steady, the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">ass</name> is lazy, the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">horse</name> has strong passions, the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">wolf</name> cannot be tamed, the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">fox</name> is deceitful, the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">stag</name> timid, the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">ant</name> industrious, the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">dog</name> grateful and faithful in his friendships.</p>
   <p>As each <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">animal</name> was created the distinctive character of his nature appeared in him in due measure; in the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">lion</name> spirit, taste for solitary life, an unsociable character. True tyrant of <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">animals</name>, he, in his natural arrogance, admits but few to share his honours. He disdains his yesterday's food and never returns to the remains of the prey. Nature has provided his organs of voice with such great force that often much swifter <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">animals</name> are caught by his roaring alone.</p>
   <p>The <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">panther</name>, violent and impetuous in his leaps, has a body fitted for his activity and lightness, in accord with the movements of his soul. The <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">bear</name> has a sluggish nature, ways of its own, a sly character, and is very secret; therefore it has an analogous body, heavy, thick, without articulations such as are necessary for a cold dweller in dens.</p>
</div>
<div type="book" n="7">
  <div type="section" n="21">
    <p>When we consider the natural and innate care that these creatures without reason take of their lives we shall be induced to watch over ourselves and to think of the salvation of our souls; or rather we shall be the more condemned when we are found falling short even of the imitation of <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">brutes</name>.</p>
    <p>The <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">bear</name>, which often gets severely wounded, cares for himself and cleverly fills the wounds with <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">mullein</name>, a plant whose nature is very astringent.</p>
    <p>You will also see the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">fox</name> heal his wounds with droppings from the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">pine tree</name>; the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">tortoise</name>, gorged with the flesh of the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">viper</name>, finds in the virtue of <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">marjoram</name> a specific against this venomous animal</p>
    <p>and the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">serpent</name> heals sore eyes by eating <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">fennel</name>.</p>
  </div>
</div>
Voici l'encodage TEI P5 strictement conforme aux règles du projet Zoomathia pour le passage demandé :


<div type="section" n="8/21">
   <p>And is not reasoning intelligence eclipsed by <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">animals</name> in their provision for atmospheric changes? Do we not see <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">sheep</name>, when winter is approaching, devouring <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">grass</name> with avidity as if to make provision for future scarcity? Do we not also see <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">oxen</name>, long confined in the winter season, recognise the return of spring by a natural sensation, and look to the end of their stables towards the doors, all turning their heads there by common consent?</p>
   <p>Studious observers have remarked that the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">hedgehog</name> makes an opening at the two extremities of his hole. If the wind from the north is going to blow he shuts up the aperture which looks towards the north; if the south wind succeeds it the animal passes to the northern door.</p>
   <p>What lesson do these <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">animals</name> teach <persName>man</persName>? They not only show us in our Creator a care which extends to all beings, but a certain presentiment of future even in brutes. Then we ought not to attach ourselves to this present life and ought to give all heed to that which is to come.</p>
   <p>Will you not be industrious for yourself, O <persName>man</persName>? And will you not lay up in the present age rest in that which is to come, after having seen the example of the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">ant</name>? The <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">ant</name> during summer collects treasures for winter. Far from giving itself up to idleness, before this season has made it feel its severity, it hastens to work with an invincible zeal until it has abundantly filled its storehouses. Here again, how far it is from being negligent! With what wise foresight it manages so as to keep its provi</p>
</div>
Voici l'encodage TEI P5 strictement conforme à vos exigences pour ce passage de Basilius, *Homélies sur l'Hexaéméron* (9/21) :


<div type="section" n="9/21">
   <p>sions as long as possible! With its pincers it cuts the grains in half, for fear lest they should germinate and not serve for its food. If they are damp it dries them; and it does not spread them out in all weathers, but when it feels that the air will keep of a mild temperature. Be sure that you will never see rain fall from the clouds so long as the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">ant</name> has left the grain out.</p>
   <p>What language can attain to the marvels of the <name type="deity">Creator</name>? What ear could understand them? And what time would be sufficient to relate them? Let us say, then, with the prophet, O Lord, how manifold are your works! In wisdom have you made them all.</p>
   <p>We shall not be able to say in self-justification, that we have learned useful knowledge in books, since the untaught law of nature makes us choose that which is advantageous to us. Do you know what good you ought to do your neighbour? The good that you expect from him yourself. Do you know what is evil? That which you would not wish another to do to you.</p>
   <p>Neither botanical researches nor the experience of <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">simples</name> have made <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">animals</name> discover those which are useful to them; but each knows naturally what is salutary and marvellously appropriates what suits its nature.</p>
</div>
Voici l'encodage TEI P5 strictement conforme à vos règles pour le texte de Basilius, *Homiliae in Hexaemeron* (10/21), avec une attention particulière aux entités zoologiques :


<div type="book" n="4">
   <div type="chapter" n="10">
      <p>Virtues exist in us also by nature, and the soul has affinity with them not by education, but by nature herself. We do not need lessons to hate illness, but by ourselves we repel what afflicts us, the soul has no need of a master to teach us to avoid vice.</p>
      <p>Now all vice is a sickness of the soul as virtue is its health. Thus those have defined health well who have called it a regularity in the discharge of natural functions; a definition that can be applied without fear to the good condition of the soul. Thus, without having need of lessons, the soul can attain by herself to what is fit and conformable to nature.</p>
      <p>Hence it comes that temperance everywhere is praised, justice is in honour, courage admired, and prudence the object of all aims; virtues which concern the soul more than health concerns the body.</p>
      <p>Children love your parents, and you, parents provoke not your children to wrath.</p>
      <p>Does not nature say the same? Paul teaches us nothing new; he only tightens the links of nature.</p>
      <p>If the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">lioness</name> loves her cubs, if the she <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">wolf</name> fights to defend her little ones, what shall man say who is unfaithful to the precept and violates nature herself; or the son who insults the old age of his father; or the father whose second marriage has made him forget his first children?</p>
   </div>
</div>
<div type="section" n="11">
   <p>With <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">animals</name> invincible affection unites parents with children. It is the <name type="deity">Creator</name>, <name type="deity">God</name> Himself, who substitutes the strength of feeling for reason in them. From whence it comes that a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">lamb</name> as it bounds from the fold, in the midst of a thousand <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">sheep</name> recognises the color and the voice of its mother, runs to her, and seeks its own sources of milk.</p>
   <p>If its mother's udders are dry, it is content, and, without stopping, passes by more abundant ones. And how does the mother recognise it among the many <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">lambs</name>? All have the same voice, the same color, the same smell, as far at least as regards our sense of smell. Yet there is in these <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">animals</name> a more subtle sense than our perception which makes them recognise their own.</p>
   <p>The little <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">dog</name> has as yet no teeth, nevertheless he defends himself with his mouth against any one who teases him. The <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">calf</name> has as yet no horns, nevertheless he already knows where his weapons will grow.</p>
   <p>Here we have evident proof that the instinct of <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">animals</name> is innate, and that in all beings there is nothing disorderly, nothing unforeseen. All bear the marks of the wisdom of the <name type="deity">Creator</name>, and show that they have come to life with the means of assuring their preservation.</p>
</div>
Voici l'encodage TEI P5 strictement conforme à vos règles pour le texte de Basilius sur les animaux :


<div type="book" n="12">
   <div type="chapter" n="21">
      <milestone unit="section" n="12.21.1" />
      <p>The <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">dog</name> is not gifted with a share of reason; but with him instinct has the power of reason. The <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">dog</name> has learned by nature the secret of elaborate inferences, which sages of the world, after long years of study, have hardly been able to disentangle. When the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">dog</name> is on the track of game, if he sees it divide in different directions, he examines these different paths, and speech alone fails him to announce his reasoning. The creature, he says, is gone here or there or in another direction. It is neither here nor there; it is therefore in the third direction. And thus, neglecting the false tracks, he discovers the true one. What more is done by those who, gravely occupied in demonstrating theories, trace lines upon the dust and reject two propositions to show that the third is the true one?</p>
      <milestone unit="section" n="12.21.2" />
      <p>Does not the gratitude of the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">dog</name> shame all who are ungrateful to their benefactors? Many are said to have fallen dead by their murdered masters in lonely places. Others, when a crime has just been committed, have led those who were searching for the murderers, and have caused the criminals to be brought to justice. What will those say who, not content with not loving the Master who has created them and nourished them, have for their friends men whose mouth attacks the Lord, sitting at the same table with them, and, while partaking of their food, blaspheme Him who has given it to them?</p>
   </div>
</div>
Voici l'encodage TEI P5 strictement conforme à vos règles pour le texte de Basilius, *Homiliae in Hexaemeron* 13/21, en respectant les entités zoologiques et les structures demandées :


<div type="book" n="13">
  <div type="section" n="1">
    <p>But let us return to the spectacle of creation. The easiest <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">animals</name> to catch are the most productive. It is on account of this that <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">hares</name> and <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">wild goats</name> produce many little ones, and that <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">wild sheep</name> have twins, for fear lest these species should disappear, consumed by <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">carnivorous animals</name>. <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Beasts of prey</name>, on the contrary, produce only a few and a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">lioness</name> with difficulty gives birth to one <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">lion</name>;  because, if they say truly, the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">cub</name> issues from its mother by tearing her with its claws; and <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">vipers</name> are only born by gnawing through the womb, inflicting a proper punishment on their mother.</p>
    <p>Thus in nature all has been foreseen, all is the object of continual care. If you examine the members even of <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">animals</name>, you will find that the Creator has given them nothing superfluous, that He has omitted nothing that is necessary. To <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">carnivorous animals</name> He has given pointed teeth which their nature requires for their support. Those that are only half furnished with teeth have received several distinct receptacles for their food. As it is not broken up enough in the first, they are gifted with the power of returning it after it has been swallowed, and it does not assimilate until it has been crushed by rumination. The first, second, third, and fourth stomachs of <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">ruminating animals</name> do not remain idle; each one of them fulfils a necessary function.</p>
    <p>The neck of the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">camel</name> is long so that it may lower it to its feet and reach the grass on which it feeds. <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Bears</name>, <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">lions</name>, <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">tigers</name>, all <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">animals</name> of this</p>
  </div>
</div>
<p>sort, have short necks buried in their shoulders; it is because they do not live upon <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">grass</name> and have no need to bend down to the <placeName>earth</placeName>; they are carnivorous and eat the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">animals</name> upon whom they prey.</p>
Voici l'encodage TEI P5 strictement conforme à vos exigences pour le texte de Basilius, *Homélies sur l'Hexaéméron* (15/21), avec une attention particulière aux entités zoologiques et aux règles de structure :


<div type="section" n="15">
   <p>Why has the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">elephant</name> a trunk? This enormous creature, the greatest of terrestrial animals, created for the terror of those who meet it, is naturally huge and fleshy. If its neck was large and in proportion to its feet it would be difficult to direct, and would be of such an excessive weight that it would make it lean towards the earth. As it is, its head is attached to the spine of the back by short vertebrae and it has its trunk to take the place of a neck, and with it it picks up its food and draws up its drink. Its feet, without joints, like united columns, support the weight of its body. If it were supported on lax and flexible legs, its joints would constantly give way, equally incapable of supporting its weight, should it wish either to kneel or rise. But it has under the foot a little ankle joint which takes the place of the leg and knee joints whose mobility would never have resisted this enormous and swaying mass. Thus it had need of this nose which nearly touches its feet.</p>
   <p>Have you seen them in war marching at the head of the phalanx, like living towers, or breaking the enemies' battalions like mountains of flesh with their irresistible charge? If their lower parts were not in accordance with their size they would never have been able to hold their own.</p>
   <p>Now we are told that the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">elephant</name> lives three hundred years and more, another reason for him to have solid and unjointed feet. But, as we have said, his trunk, which has the form and the flexibility of a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">serpent</name>, t</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="16">
   <p>akes its food from the earth and raises it up. Thus we are right in saying that it is impossible to find anything superfluous or wanting in creation. Well! <name type="deity">God</name> has subdued this <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">monstrous animal</name> to us to such a point that he understands the lessons and endures the blows we give him; a manifest proof that the <name type="deity">Creator</name> has submitted all to our rule, because we have been made in His image.</p>
   <p>It is not in great <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">animals</name> only that we see unapproachable wisdom; no less wonders are seen in the smallest. The high tops of the mountains which, near to the clouds and continually beaten by the winds, keep up a perpetual winter, do not arouse more admiration in me than the hollow valleys, which escape the storms of lofty peaks and preserve a constant mild temperature.</p>
   <p>In the same way in the constitution of <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">animals</name> I am not more astonished at the size of the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">elephant</name>, than at the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">mouse</name>, who is feared by the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">elephant</name>, or at the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">scorpion</name>'s delicate sting, which has been hollowed like a pipe by the supreme artificer to throw venom into the wounds it makes.</p>
   <p>And let nobody accuse the <name type="deity">Creator</name> of having produced <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">venomous animals</name>, destroyers and enemies of our life. Else let them consider it a crime in the schoolmaster when he disciplines the restlessness of youth by the use of the rod and whip to maintain order.</p>
</div>
Voici l'encodage TEI P5 strictement conforme aux règles du projet Zoomathia, en respectant la structure demandée et en priorisant l'encodage des entités nommées zoologiques :


<div type="book" n="6">
   <div type="section" n="17/21">
      <p>Beasts bear witness to the faith. Have you confidence in the Lord? Thou shall walk upon the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">asp</name> and the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">basilisk</name> and you shall trample under feet the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">lion</name> and the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">dragon</name>.</p>
      <p>With faith you have the power to walk upon <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">serpents</name> and <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">scorpions</name>. Do you not see that the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">viper</name> which attached itself to the hand of <persName>Paul</persName>, while he gathered sticks, did not injure him, because it found the saint full of faith?</p>
      <p>If you have not faith, do not fear <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">beasts</name> so much as your faithlessness, which renders you susceptible of all corruption.</p>
      <p>But I see that for a long time you have been asking me for an account of the creation of <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">man</name>, and I think I can hear you all cry in your hearts, We are being taught the nature of our belongings, but we are ignorant of ourselves.</p>
      <p>Let me then speak of it, since it is necessary, and let me put an end to my hesitation. In truth the most difficult of sciences is to know one's self. Not only our eye, from which nothing outside us escapes, cannot see itself; but our mind, so piercing to discover the sins of others, is slow to recognise its own faults.</p>
      <p>Thus my speech, after eagerly investigating what is external to myself, is slow and hesitating in exploring my own nature. Yet the beholding of heaven and earth does not make us know God better than the attentive study of our being does; I am, says the <persName>Prophet</persName>, fearfully and wonderfully made; that is to say, in observing myself I have known Your infinite wisdom.</p>
      <p>And <name type="deity">God</name> said <quote>Let us make <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">man</name>.</quote> <foreign xml:lang="la">Genesis 1:26</foreign></p>
   </div>
</div>
Voici l'encodage TEI P5 strictement conforme à vos exigences pour le texte de Basilius, *Homélies sur l'Hexaéméron* (18/21), en respectant toutes les règles Zoomathia :


<div type="book" n="1">
  <div type="chapter" n="18">
    <div type="section" n="21">
      <milestone unit="section" n="18.21" />
      <p>light of theology shine, in these words, as through windows; and does not the second Person show Himself in a mystical way, without yet manifesting Himself until the great day?</p>
      <p>Where is the Jew who resisted the truth and pretended that <name type="deity">God</name> was speaking to Himself? It is <persName>He</persName> who spoke, it is said, and it is <persName>He</persName> who made. Let there be light and there was light. But then their words contain a manifest absurdity.</p>
      <p>Where is the smith, the carpenter, the shoemaker, who, without help and alone before the instruments of his trade, would say to himself; let us make the sword, let us put together the plough, let us make the boot? Does he not perform the work of his craft in silence?</p>
      <p>Strange folly, to say that any one has seated himself to command himself, to watch over himself, to constrain himself, to hurry himself, with the tones of a master! But the unhappy creatures are not afraid to calumniate the <name type="deity">Lord</name> Himself.</p>
      <p>What will they not say with a tongue so well practised in lying? Here, however, words stop their mouth; And <name type="deity">God</name> said let us make <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">man</name>. Tell me; is there then only one Person? It is not written Let <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">man</name> be made, but, Let us make <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">man</name>.</p>
      <p>The preaching of theology remains enveloped in shadow before the appearance of him who was to be instructed, but, now, the creation of <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">man</name> is expected, that faith unveils herself and the dogma of truth appears in all its light.</p>
      <p>Let us make <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">man</name>. O enemy of <persName>Christ</persName>, hear <name type="deity">God</name> speaking to His Co-operator, to Him by Whom also <name type="deity">He</name> made the worlds, Who uphold</p>
    </div>
  </div>
</div>
Voici l'encodage TEI P5 strictement conforme à vos exigences pour le texte de Basilius, *Homiliae in Hexaemeron* (19/21), en respectant toutes les règles Zoomathia :


<div type="book" n="19">
   <div type="chapter" n="21">
      <p>s all things by the word of His power.  But He does not leave the voice of true religion without answer. Thus the Jews, race hostile to truth, when they find themselves pressed, act like <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">beasts</name> enraged against man, who roar at the bars of their cage and show the cruelty and the ferocity of their nature, without being able to assuage their fury.</p>
      <p>God, they say, addresses Himself to several persons; it is to the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">angels</name> before Him that He says, Let us make man. Jewish fiction! A fable whose frivolity shows whence it has come. To reject one person, they admit many. To reject the Son, they raise servants to the dignity of counsellors; they make of our fellow slaves the agents in our creation.</p>
      <p>The perfect man attains the dignity of an <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">angel</name>; but what creature can be like the Creator? Listen to the continuation. In our image. What have you to reply? Is there one image of God and the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">angels</name>? Father and Son have by absolute necessity the same form, but the form is here understood as becomes the divine, not in bodily shape, but in the proper qualities of Godhead.</p>
      <p>Hear also, you who belong to the new concision <persName>Philippians</persName> 3:2 and who, under the appearance of Christianity, strengthen the error of the Jews.  To Whom does He say, in our image, to whom if it is not to Him who is the brightness of His glory and the express image of His person, <quote><foreign xml:lang="grc">Ἑβραῖοι</foreign> 1:3</quote> the image of the invisible God? <quote><foreign xml:lang="en">Colossians</foreign> 1:15</quote> It is then to His living image, to Him Who has said I and my Father are one, <quote><foreign xml:lang="en">John</foreign> 10:30</quote> He</p>
   </div>
</div>
Voici l'encodage TEI P5 strictement conforme à vos règles pour le texte fourni, en respectant la structure demandée et en identifiant les entités nommées (bien que le texte ne contienne pas d'animaux, plantes, lieux ou divinités explicites) :


<div type="section" n="20">
   <p>that has seen me has seen the Father, <foreign xml:lang="grc">John 14:9</foreign> that God says <quote>Let us make man in our image</quote>. Where is the unlikeness in these Beings who have only one image? So God created man. <foreign xml:lang="grc">Genesis 1:27</foreign> It is not They made. Here Scripture avoids the plurality of the Persons. After having enlightened the Jew, it dissipates the error of the Gentiles in putting itself under the shelter of unity, to make you understand that the Son is with the Father, and guarding you from the danger of polytheism. He created him in the image of God. God still shows us His co-operator, because He does not say, in His image, but in the image of God.</p>
</div>

<div type="section" n="21">
   <p>If God permits, we will say later in what way man was created in the image of God, and how he shares this resemblance. Today we say but only one word. If there is one image, from whence comes the intolerable blasphemy of pretending that the Son is unlike the Father? What ingratitude! You have yourself received this likeness and you refuse it to your Benefactor! You pretend to keep personally that which is in you a gift of grace, and you do not wish that the Son should keep His natural likeness to Him who begot Him.</p>
</div>
Voici l'encodage TEI P5 strictement conforme à vos exigences pour le texte de Basilius, *Homélies sur l'Hexaéméron* (21/21), en respectant toutes les règles Zoomathia :


<div type="book" n="21">
   <div type="chapter" n="21">
      <milestone unit="section" n="21.1" />
      <p>But evening, which long ago sent the sun to the west, imposes silence upon me. Here, then, let me be content with what I have said, and put my discourse to bed.</p>
      <p>I have told you enough up to this point to excite your zeal; with the help of the <name type="deity">Holy Spirit</name> I will make for you a deeper investigation into the truths which follow.</p>
      <p>Retire, then, I beg you, with joy, O <persName>Christ-loving congregation</persName>, and, instead of sumptuous dishes of various delicacies, adorn and sanctify your tables with the remembrance of my words.</p>
      <p>May the <name type="deity">Anomœan</name> be confounded, the <name type="deity">Jew</name> covered with shame, the faithful exultant in the dogmas of truth, and the <name type="deity">Lord</name> glorified, the <name type="deity">Lord</name> to Whom be glory and power, world without end. Amen.</p>
   </div>
</div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>