<TEI.2>	<teiHeader type="text">		<fileDesc>			<titleStmt>				<title>Quaestiones Naturales</title>				<author>Plutarch</author>				<editor role="editor">William W. Goodwin</editor>				<funder n="org:Google">Google Digital Humanities Awards Program</funder>			</titleStmt>			<publicationStmt>				<publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>				<pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>				<authority>Perseus Project</authority>			</publicationStmt>			<sourceDesc>				<biblStruct>					<monogr>						<title>Quaestiones Naturales</title>						<author>Plutarch</author>				<editor role="editor">William W. Goodwin</editor>						<imprint>													<publisher>Little, Brown and company</publisher>							<place>Boston</place>							<publisher>Press Of John Wilson and son</publisher>							<place>Cambridge</place>							<date>1874</date>						</imprint>						<respStmt>							<name>Translated from the Greek by several hands</name>							<resp>translation</resp>							<name>William W. Goodwin</name>							<resp>correction and revision</resp>						</respStmt>					</monogr>				</biblStruct>				<p>Keyboarding</p>			</sourceDesc>		</fileDesc>		<encodingDesc>			<refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">				<state unit="chapter"/>			</refsDecl>		</encodingDesc>		<profileDesc>			<langUsage>				<language id="english">English</language>			</langUsage>		</profileDesc>	</teiHeader>	<text>		<body>			<div1 type="chapter" n="1"> 				<p>What is the reason that sea-water nourishes not the trees?</p>
				<p>Is it not for the same reason that it nourishes not earthlyanimals? For Plato, Anaxagoras, and Democritus thinkplants are earthly animals. Nor, though sea-water be aliment to marine plants, as it is to fishes, will it thereforenourish earthly plants, since it can neither penetrate theroots, because of its grossness, nor ascend, by reason ofits weight; for this, among many other things, shows seawater to be heavy and terrene, because it more easilybears up ships and swimmers. Or is it because droughtis a great enemy to trees? For sea-water is of a dryingfaculty; upon which account salt resists putrefaction, andthe bodies of such as wash in the sea are presently dryand rough. Or is it because oil is destructive to earthlyplants, and kills things anointed with it? But sea-waterparticipates of much fatness; for it burns together with it.Wherefore, when men would quench fire, we forbid themto throw on sea-water. Or is it because sea-water is notfit to drink and bitter (as Aristotle says) through a mixtureof burnt earth?</p>
				<p>For a lye is made by the falling of ashesinto sweet water, and the dissolution ejects and corruptswhat was good and potable, as in us men fevers convertthe humors into bile. As for what woods and plants mentalk of growing in the Red Sea, they bear no fruit, butare nourished by rivers casting up much mud; thereforethey grow not at any great distance from land, but verynear to it.</p>			</div1>			<div1 type="chapter" n="2"> 				<p>Why do trees and seeds thrive better with rain than with watering?</p>				<p>Whether is it because (as Laitus thinks) showers, parting the earth by the violence of their fall, make passages,whereby the water may more easily penetrate to the root?Or cannot this be true; and did Laitus never consider thatmarsh-plants (as cat's-tail, pond-weeds, and rushes) neitherthrive nor sprout when the rains fall not in their season;but it is true, as Aristotle said, rain-water is new and fresh,that of lakes old and stale? And what if this be ratherprobable than true? For the waters of fountains andrivers are ever fresh, new always arriving; thereforeHeraclitus said well, that no man could go twice into thesame river. And yet these very waters nourish worse thanrain-water. But water from the heavens is light and aerial,and, being mixed with spirit, is the quicker passed andelevated into the plant, by reason of its tenuity. And forthis very reason it makes bubbles when mixed with theair. Or does that nourish most which is soonest alteredand overcome by the thing nourished?—for this very thingis concoction. On the contrary, inconcoction is when thealiment is too strong to be affected by the thing nourished.Now thin, simple, and insipid things are the most easilyaltered, of which number is rain-water, which is bred inthe air and wind, and falls pure and sincere. But fountain-water, being assimilated to the earth and places throughwhich it passes, is filled with many qualities which renderit less nutritive and slower in alteration to the thingnourished. Moreover, that rain-water is easily alterable isan argument; because it sooner putrefies than either springor river-water. For concoction seems to be putrefaction,as Empedocles says,— When in vine wood the water putrefies, It turns to wine, while under bark it lies.</p>				<p>Or, which may most readily be assigned for a reason, isit because rain is sweet and mild, when it is presently sentby the wind? For this reason cattle drink it most greedily,and frogs in expectation of it raise their voice, as if theywere calling for rain to sweeten the marsh and to be sauceto the water in the pools. For Aratus makes this a sign ofapproaching rain, When father frogs, to watery snakes sweet food, Do croak and sing in mud, a wretched brood.</p>			</div1>			<div1 type="chapter" n="3"> 				<p>WHY DO HERDSMEN SET SALT BEFORE CATTLE?Whether (as many think) to nourish them the more, andfatten them the better? For salt by its acrimony sharpensthe appetite, and by opening the passages brings meatmore easily to digestion. Therefore Apollonius, Herophilus's scholar, would not have lean persons, and such asdid not thrive, be fed with sweet things and gruel, butordered them to use pickles and salt things for their food,whose tenuity, serving instead of frication or sifting, mightapply the aliment through the passages of the body. Oris it for health's sake that men give sheep salt to lick, tocut off the redundance of nutriment? For when theyare over fat, they grow sick; but salt wastes and melts thefat. And this they observe so well, that they can moreeasily flay them; for the fat, which agglutinates and fastensthe skin, is made thin and weak by the acrimony. Theblood also of things that lick salt is attenuated; nordo things within the body stick together when salts aremixed with them. Moreover, consider this, whether thecattle grow more fruitful and more inclined to coition; forbitches do sooner conceive when they are fed with saltvictuals, and ships which carry salt are more pestered withmice, by reason of their frequent coition.</p>			</div1>			<div1 type="chapter" n="4"> 				<p>WHY IS THE WATER OF SHOWERS WHICH FALLS IN THUNDER AND LIGHTNING FITTER TO WATER SEEDS? AND THEY ARE THEREFORE CALLED THUNDER-SHOWERS.Is it because they contain much spirit, by reason of theirconfusion and mixture with the air? And the spirit moving the humor sends it more upwards. Or is it becauseheat fighting against cold causes thunder and lightning?Whence it is that it thunders very little in winter, but inspring and autumn very much, because of the inequalityof temper; and the heat, concocting the humor, renders itfriendly and commodious for plants. Or does it thunderand lighten most in the spring for the aforesaid cause, anddo the seeds have greater occasion for the vernal rainsbefore summer? Therefore that country which is bestwatered with rain in spring, as Sicily is, produces abundance of good fruit.</p>			</div1>			<div1 type="chapter" n="5"> 				<p>How comes it to pass, that since there be eight kinds of tastes, we find the salt in no fruit whatever?</p>				<p>Indeed, at first the olive is bitter, and the grape acid;one whereof afterward turns fat, and the other vinous.But the harshness in dates and the austere in pomegranatesturn sweet. Some pomegranates and apples have only asimple acid taste. The pungent taste is frequent in rootsand seeds.</p>				<p>Is it because a salt taste is never natural, but ariseswhen the rest are corrupt? Therefore such plants andseeds as are nourished receive no nourishment from salt;it serves indeed some instead of sauce, by preventing asurfeit of other nourishment. Or, as men take away saltness and bitingness from the sea-water by distilling, issaltness so abolished in hot things by heat? Or indeeddoes the taste (as Plato says) arise from water percolatedthrough a plant, and does even sea-water percolated loseits saltness, being terrene and of gross parts? Thereforepeople that dig near the sea happen upon wells fit to drink.Several also that draw the sea-water into waxen bucketsreceive it sweet and potable, the salt and earthy matterbeing strained out. And straining through clay renderssea-water potable, since the clay retains the earthy partsand does not let them pass through. And since things areso, it is very probable either that plants receive no saltnessextrinsically, or, if they do, they put it not forth into fruit;for things terrene and consisting of gross parts cannotpass, by reason of the straitness of the passages. Or maysaltness be reckoned a sort of bitterness? For so Homersays: Out of his mouth the bitter brine did flow, And down his body from his head did go.</p>				<p>Plato also says that both these tastes have an abstersiveand colliquative faculty; but the salt does it less, nor is itrough. And the bitter seems to differ from the salt inabundance of heat, since the salt has also a drying quality.</p>			</div1>			<div1 type="chapter" n="6"> 				<p>What is the reason that, if a man frequently pass along dewy trees, those limbs that touch the wood are seized with a leprosy?</p>				<p>Whether (as Laitus said) that by the tenuity of the dewthe moisture of the skin is fretted away? Or, as smut andmildew fall upon moistened seeds, so, when the green andtender parts on the superficies are fretted and dissolved bythe dew, is a certain noxious taint carried and imparted tothe most bloodless parts of the body, as the legs and feet,which there eats and frets the superficies? For that byNature there is a corrosive faculty in dew sufficiently appears, in that it makes fat people lean; and gross womengather it, either with wool or on their clothes, to take downtheir flesh.</p>			</div1>			<div1 type="chapter" n="7"> 				<p>Why in winter do ships sail slower in rivers, but do not so in the sea?</p>				<p>Whether, because the river-air, which is at all timesheavy and slow, being in winter more condensed by thecold, does more resist sailing? Or is it long of the waterrather than the air? For the piercing cold makes thewater heavy and thick, as one may perceive in a water-clock; for the water passes more slowly in winter than insummer. Theophrastus talks of a well about Pangaeum inThrace, how that a vessel filled with the water of it weighstwice as much in winter as it does in summer. Besides,hence it is apparent that the grossness of the water makesships sail slower, because in winter river-vessels carrygreater burthens. For the water, being made more denseand heavy, makes the more renitency; but the heat hinders the sea from being condensed or frozen.</p>			</div1>			<div1 type="chapter" n="8"> 				<p>Why, since all other liquors upon moving and stirring about grow cold, does the sea by being tossed in waves grow hot?</p>				<p>Whether that motion expels and dissipates the heat ofother liquors as a thing adscititious, and the winds do ratherexcite and increase the innate heat of the sea? Its transparentness is an argument of heat; and so is its not beingfrozen, though it is terrene and heavy.</p>			</div1>			<div1 type="chapter" n="9"> 				<p>Why in winter is the sea least salt and bitter to the taste? for they say that dionysius the hydragogue reported this.</p>				<p>Is it that the bitterness of the sea is not devoid of allsweetness, as receiving so many rivers into it; but, sincethe sun exhales the sweet and potable water thereof,arising to the top by reason of its levity, and since this isdone in summer more than in winter, when it affects thesea more weakly by reason of the debility of its heat, thatso in winter a great deal of sweetness is left, which tempers and mitigates its excessive poisonous bitterness? Andthe same thing befalls potable waters; for in summer theyare worse, the sun wasting the lightest and sweetest partof them. And a fresh sweetness returns in winter, ofwhich the sea must needs participate, since it moves, andis carried with the rivers into the sea.</p>			</div1>			<div1 type="chapter" n="10"> 				<p>Why do men pour sea-water upon wine, and say the fishermen had an oracle given them, whereby they were bid to dip bacchus into the sea? and why do they that live far from the sea cast in some zacynthian earth toasted?</p>				<p>Whether that heat is good against cold? Or that itquenches heat, by diluting the wine and destroying itsstrength? Or that the aqueous and aerial part of wine(which is therefore prone to mutation) is stayed by thethrowing in of terrene parts, whose nature it is to constipate and condense? Moreover, salts with the sea-water,attenuating and colliquating whatever is foreign and superfluous, suffer no fetidness or putrefaction to breed. Besides,the gross and terrene parts, being entangled with the heavyand sinking together, make a sediment or lees, and somake the wine fine.</p>			</div1>			<div1 type="chapter" n="11"> 				<p>Why are they sicker that sail on the sea than they that sail in fresh rivers, even in calm weather?</p>				<p>Of all the senses, smelling causes nauseousness themost, and of all the passions of the mind, fear. For mentremble and shake and bewray themselves upon apprehension of great danger. They that sail in a river aretroubled with neither of these. And the smell of sweetand potable water is familiar to all, and the voyage is without danger. On the sea an unusual smell is troublesome;and men are afraid, not knowing what the issue may be.Therefore tranquillity abroad avails not, while an estuatingand disturbed mind disorders the body.</p>			</div1>			<div1 type="chapter" n="12"> 				<p>Why does pouring oil on the sea make it clear and calm?</p>				<p>Is it for that the winds, slipping the smooth oil, haveno force, nor cause any waves? This may be probablysaid in respect of things external; but they say that diverstake oil in their mouths, and when they spout it out theyhave light at the bottom, and it makes the water transparent; so that the slipping of the winds will not hold goodhere for an argument. Therefore it is to be considered,whether the sea, which is terrene and uneven, is not compacted and made smooth by the dense oil; and so the sea,being compact in itself, leaves passes, and a pelluciditypenetrable by the sight. Or whether that the air, whichis naturally mixed with the sea, is lucid, but by beingtroubled grows unequal and shady; and so by the oil'sdensity, smoothing its inequality, the sea recovers its evenness and pellucidity.</p>			</div1>			<div1 type="chapter" n="13"> 				<p>Why do fishermen's nets root more in winter than in summer, since other things rot more in summer?</p>				<p>Is not that the cause which Theophrastus assigns,—thatheat (to wit) shuns the cold, and is constrained by it onevery side? Hence the waters are hottest in the bottomof the sea. And so it is on land; for springs are hotterin winter, and then lakes and rivers send up most vapors,because the heat is compelled to the bottom by the prevailing cold. Or it may be, nets do not rot at that timemore than at another; but being frozen and dried in thecold, since they are therefore the more easily broken bythe waves, they are liable to something like putrefactionand rottenness. And they suffer most in the cold (asstrained cords are aptest to break in such a season), because then there be most frequent storms at sea. Therefore fishermen guard their nets with certain tinctures, forfear they should break. Otherwise a net, neither tingednor daubed with any thing, might more easily deceive thefish; since line is of an air color, and is not easily discerned in the sea.</p>			</div1>			<div1 type="chapter" n="14"> 				<p>Why do the dorians pray for bad making of their hay?</p>				<p>Is it because hay rained upon is never well made? Forthe grass is cut down green and not dry, wherefore it putrefies when wet with rain water. But when before harvest it rains upon corn, this is a help to it against the hotsouth winds; which otherwise would not let the grain fillin the ear, but by their heat would hinder and destroy allcoalition, unless by watering the earth there came a moisture to cool and moisten the ear.</p>			</div1>			<div1 type="chapter" n="15"> 				<p>Why is a fat and deep soil fruitful of wheat, and a lean soil of barley?</p>				<p>Is it because a stronger grain needs more nourishment,and a weaker a light and thin one? Now barley is weakerand laxer than wheat, therefore it affords but little nourishment. And, as a farther testimony to this reason, wheat,that is ripe in three months, grows in dryer ground; because it is juiceless, and stands in need of less nourishment, and therefore is more easily brought to perfection.</p>			</div1>			<div1 type="chapter" n="16"> 				<p>Why do men say, sow wheat in clay and barley in dust?</p>				<p>Is the reason (as we said) because wheat takes up morenourishment; and barley cannot bear so much, but ischoked with it? Or does wheat, because it is hard andligneous, thrive better when it is softened and loosened ina moist soil; and barley at the first in a dry soil, becauseof its rarity? Or is the one temperament congruous andharmless to wheat, because it is hot; and the other to barley, because it is cold? Or are men afraid to sow wheatin a dry soil, because of the ants, which presently lie inwait for it; but they cannot so easily deal with barley norcarry it away, because it is a larger grain?</p>			</div1>			<div1 type="chapter" n="17"> 				<p>Why do men use the hair of horses rather than of mares for fishing-lines?</p>				<p>Is it that the males are stronger in those parts, as wellas in others, than the females? Or is it that the femalesspoil the hair of their tails by their staling?</p>			</div1>			<div1 type="chapter" n="18"> 				<p>Why is the sight of a cuttle-fish a sign of a great storm?</p>				<p>Is it because all fishes of the soft kind cannot endurecold, by reason of their nakedness and tenderness? Forthey are covered neither with shell, skin, or scale, thoughwithin they have hard and bony parts. Hence the Greekscall them soft fish. Therefore they easily perceive a stormcoming, since they are so soon affected by the cold. Whenthe polypus gets to shore and embraces the rocks, it is asign the wind is rising; but the cuttle-fish jumps up, toshun the cold and the trouble of the bottom of the sea;for, of all soft fishes, she is the tenderest and soonest hurt.</p>			</div1>			<div1 type="chapter" n="19"> 				<p>Why does the polypus change color?</p>				<p>Whether, as Theophrastus writes, because it is an animal by nature timorous; and therefore, being disturbed,it changes color with its spirit, as some men do, of whomit is said, an ill man ever changes color? But though thismay serve as a reason for changing its color, it will not forthe imitation of colors. For the polypus does so changeits color, that it is of the color of every stone it comesnigh. Hence that of Pindar, Mind the color of the marine beast, and so converse cunningly in all cities; andthat of Theognis: Put on a mind like th' polyp fish,— And learn so to dissemble,— Which of the rock whereto it sticks The color doth resemble.</p>				<p>And they say, that such as are excellent at craftiness andjuggling have this in their eye,—that they may the bettercheat them they have to deal withal,—ever to imitate thepolypus. Some think the polypus can use her skin as agarment, and can put it on or off at pleasure. But iffear occasions this change in the polypus, is not somethingelse more properly the cause? Let us consider what Empedocles says, that effluvia proceed from all things whatever. For not only animals, plants, the earth and sea, butstones, and even brass and iron, do continually send outmany effluvia. For all things corrupt and smell, becausethere runneth always something from them, and they wearcontinually; insomuch that it is thought that by theseeffluvia come all attractions and insultations, some supposing embraces, others blows, some impulses, others circuitions. But especially about the sea rocks, when they arewet and cool by the waves (as is most likely), constantlysome small particles are washed off, which do not incorporate with other bodies, but either pass by the smallerpassages, or pass through the larger. Now the flesh ofthe polypus, as one may judge by the eye, is hollow, fullof pores, and capable of effluvia. When therefore sheis afraid, as her spirit changes she changes herself, and bystraitening and contracting her body, she encloses theneighboring effluvia. And, as a good token of this argument, the polypus cannot imitate the color of every thinghe comes near, nor the chameleon of any thing that iswhite; but each of these creatures is assimilated only tothose things to whose effluvia it has pores proportionable.</p>			</div1>			<div1 type="chapter" n="20"> 				<p>What is the reason, that the tears of wild boars are sweet, and the tears of the hart salt and hurtful?</p>				<p>The reason seems to be the heat and cold of these animals. For the hart is cold, and the boar is very hot andfiery; therefore the one flies from, the other defends himselfagainst, his pursuers. Now when great store of heat comesto the eyes (as Homer says, with horrid bristles, and eyesdarting fire), tears are sweet. Some are of Empedocles'sopinion, who thought that tears proceed from the disturbance of the blood, as whey does from the churning ofmilk; since therefore boar's blood is harsh and black, andhart's blood thin and watery, it is consentaneous thatthe tears, which the one sheds when excited to anger, andthe other when dejected with fear, should be of the samenature.</p>			</div1>			<div1 type="chapter" n="21"> 				<p>Why do tame sows farrow often, some at, one time and others at another; and the wild but once a year, and all of them about the same time at the beginning of summer, whence it is said,— The wild sow farrowing, that night falls no rain?</p>				<p>Is it because of plentiful feeding, as in very truth fulnessdoth produce wantonness? For abundance of nourishment breeds abundance of seed both in animals and plants.Now wild sows live by their own toil, and that with fear;the tame have always food enough, either by nature orgiven them. Or may it not be ascribed to their rest andexercise? For the tame do rest and go not far from theirkeepers; the wild get to the mountains, and run about, bywhich means they waste the nutriment, and consume itupon the whole body. Therefore either through continualconverse, or abundance of seed, or because the femalesfeed in herds with the males, the tame sows call to mindcoition and stir up lust, as Empedocles talks of men.But in wild sows, which feed apart, desire is cold and dullfor want of love and conversation. Or is it true, whatAristotle says, that Homer called the wild boar <foreign lang="greek">xlou/nhs</foreign>, because he had but one stone? For most boars spoil theirstones (he says) by rubbing them against stumps of trees.</p>			</div1>			<div1 type="chapter" n="22"> 				<p>Why are the paws of bears the sweetest and pleasantest food?</p>				<p>Because the flesh of those parts of the body which concoct aliment the best is sweetest; and that concocts bestwhich transpires most by motion and exercise. But thebear uses the fore-feet most in going and running, and inmanaging of things, as it were with hands.</p>			</div1>			<div1 type="chapter" n="23"> 				<p>Why are the steps of wild beasts most difficultly traced in spring-time?</p>				<p>Whether the dogs, as Empedocles says,  with noses findthe steps of all wild beasts, and draw in those effluviawhich the beasts leave in the ground; but the varioussmells of plants and flowers lying over the footsteps doin spring-time obscure and confound them, and put thedogs to a loss at winding them? Therefore about Etna inSicily no man keeps any hunting dogs, because abundanceof wild marjoram flourishes and grows there the year round,and the perpetual flagrancy of the place destroys the scentof the wild beasts. There is also a tale, how Proserpine,as she was gathering flowers thereabout, was ravished byPluto; therefore people, revering that place as an asylum,do not catch any creature that feeds thereabout.</p>			</div1>			<div1 type="chapter" n="24"> 				<p>Why are the tracks of wild beasts worse scented about the full moon?</p>				<p>Whether for the foresaid cause? For the full moonsbring down the dews; and therefore Alcman calls dew thedaughter of Jove and Luna in a verse of his, Fed by the dew, bred by the Moon and Jove.</p>				<p>For dew is a weak and languid rain, and there is but littleheat in the moon; which draws water from the earth, as thesun does; but because it cannot raise it on high, it soonlets it fall.</p>			</div1>			<div1 type="chapter" n="25"> 				<p>Why does frost make hunting difficult?</p>				<p>Whether is it because the wild beasts leave off goingfar abroad by reason of the cold, and so leave but few signsof themselves? Therefore some say, beasts spare the neighboring places, that they may not be sore put to it by goingfar abroad in winter, but may always have food ready athand. Or is it because that for hunting the track alone isnot sufficient, but there must be scent also? And thingsgently dissolved and loosened by heat afford a smell, buttoo violent cold binds up the scent, and will not let itreach the sense. Therefore they say that unguents andwine smell least in winter and cold weather; for the thenconcrete air keeps the scent in, and suffers it not todisperse.</p>			</div1>			<div1 type="chapter" n="26"> 				<p>What is the reason that brutes, when they ail any thing, seek and pursue remedies, and are often cured by the use of them?</p>				<p>Dogs eat grass, to make them vomit bile. Swine seekcraw-fish, because the eating of them cures the headache.The tortoise, when he has eaten a viper, feeds on wildmarjoram. They say, when a bear has surfeited himselfand his stomach grows nauseous, he licks up ants, and bydevouring them is cured. These creatures know suchthings neither by experience nor by chance.</p>				<p>Whether, as wax draws the bee, and carcasses the vulture afar off by the scent, do craw-fish so draw swine, wildmarjoram the tortoise, and ants the bear, by smells andeffluvia accommodated to their nature, they being promptedaltogether by sense, without any assistance from reason?Or do not the temperaments of the body create appetites inanimals, while diseases create these, producing diversacrimonies, sweetnesses, and other unusual and absurd qualities, the humors being altered; as is plain in womenwith child, who eat stones and earth? Therefore skilfulphysicians take their prognostic of recovery or death fromthe appetites of the sick. For Mnesitheus the physiciansays that, in the beginning of a disease of the lungs, hethat craves onions recovers, and he that craves figs dies;because appetites follow the temperament, and the temperament follows diseases. It is therefore probable thatbeasts, if they fall not into mortal diseases, have such adisposition and temper, that by following their temper theylight on their remedies.</p>			</div1>			<div1 type="chapter" n="27"> 				<p>why does must, if the vessel stand in the cold, continue long sweet?</p>				<p>Is it because the changing of the sweet must into wineis concoction, but cold hinders concoction, because this iscaused by heat? Or, on the contrary, is the proper tasteof the grape sweet, and is it then said to be ripe, whenthe sweetness is equally diffused all over it; but does cold,not suffering the heat of the grape to exhale, and keepingit in, conserve the sweetness of the grape? And this isthe reason that, in a rainy vintage, must ferments but little;for fermentation proceeds from heat, which the cold doescheck.</p>			</div1>			<div1 type="chapter" n="28"> 				<p>Why, of all wild beasts, does not the boar bite the toil, although both wolves and foxes do this?</p>				<p>Is it because his teeth stand so far within his head, thathe cannot well come at the thread? For his lips, byreason of their thickness and largeness, meet close before.Or does he rather rely on his paws and mouth, and withthose rend the toil, and with this defend himself againstthe hunters? His chief refuge is rolling and wallowing;therefore, rather than stand gnawing the toil, he rolls oftenabout, and so clears himself, having no occasion for histeeth.</p>			</div1>			<div1 type="chapter" n="29"> 				<p>What is the reason that we admire hot waters (i. e. baths) and not cold; since it is plain that cold is as much the cause of one sort as heat is of the other?</p>				<p>It we do itbecause Nature has attributed admiration to what is rare,and she puts men upon enquiry how any thing comes topass that seldom happens. As Euripides saith, Behold the boundless Heaven on high, Bearing the earth in his moist arms,—</p>				<p>what wonders he brings out by night, and what beauty heshows forth by day! . . . The rainbow and the variedbeauty of the clouds by day, and the lights which burstforth by night . . .</p>			</div1>			<div1 type="chapter" n="30"> 				<p>Why are vines which are rank of leaves, but otherwise fruit- less, said τραγᾶν?</p>				<p>Is it because very fat goats (<foreign lang="greek">tra/goi</foreign>) are less able to procreate, nay, scarce able to use coition, by reason of theirfatness. Seed is the superfluity of the aliment which isallotted to the body: now, when either an animal or aplant is of a very strong constitution and grows fat, it is asign that all the nourishment is spent within, and thatthere is little and base excrement, or none at all.</p>			</div1>			<div1 type="chapter" n="31"> 				<p>Why does the vine irrigated with wine die, especially the very wine made from its own grapes?</p>				<p>Is it as baldness happens to great wine-bibbers, the heatof the wine evaporating the moisture? Or, as Empedocles saith, the putrefied water in the wood becomes winebeneath the bark, . . . thus, when the vine is outwardlyirrigated with wine, it is as fire to the vine, and destroysthe nutritive faculty. Or, because wine is obstructive, itgets into the roots, stops the passages, and so hindersany moisture from coming to the plant to make it growand thrive. Or, it may seem contrary to Nature that thatshould return into the vine which came out of it; for whatsover moisture comes from plants can neither nourish norbe again a part of the plant.</p>			</div1>			<div1 type="chapter" n="32"> 				<p>Why doth the palm alone of all trees bend upward when a weight is laid thereupon?</p>				<p>Is it that the fiery and spiritual power which it hath,being once provoked and (as it were) angered, puttethforth itself so much the more, and mounteth upward? Oris it because the weight, forcing the boughs suddenly,oppresseth and keepeth down the airy substance whichthey have, and driveth all of it inward; but the sameafterwards, having resumed strength again, maketh headafresh, and more eagerly withstandeth the weight? Or,lastly, is it that the softer and more tender branches, notable to sustain the violence at first, so soon as the burdenresteth quiet, by little and little lift up themselves, andmake a show as if they rose up against it?</p>			</div1>			<div1 type="chapter" n="33"> 				<p>What is the reason that pit-water is less nutritive than either that which ariseth out of springs or that which falleth down from heaven?</p>				<p>Is it because it is more cold, and withal hath less air init? Or because it containeth much salt from the earthmingled therewith?—now it is well known that salt aboveall other things causeth leanness. Or because standingstill, and not exercised with running and stirring, it gettetha certain malignant quality, which is hurtful to both plantsand animals, and is the cause that it is neither well concocted nor able to feed and nourish any thing? Hence itis that all dead waters of pools are unwholesome, for thatthey cannot digest and despatch those harmful qualitieswhich they borrow of the evil property of the air or ofthe earth.</p>			</div1>			<div1 type="chapter" n="34"> 				<p>why is the west wind held commonly to be the swiftest, according to this verse of Homer: Let us likewise bestir our feet, As fast as Western winds do fleet.</p>				<p>Is it not because this wind is wont to blow when thesky is very well cleansed, and the air is exceeding clearand without all clouds?—for the thickness and impurityof the air doth not a little impeach and interrupt thecourse of the winds. Or is it rather because the sun,striking through a cold wind with his beams, is the causethat it passeth the faster away?—for whatsoever of coldis drawn in by the force of the winds, when the sameis overcome by heat, as it were its enemy, we mustthink, is driven and set forward further and with greatercelerity.</p>			</div1>			<div1 type="chapter" n="35"> 				<p>Why cannot bees abide smoke?</p>				<p>Whether is it because the passages of their vital spiritsare exceeding strait, and, if it chance that smoke be gotteninto them and there kept in and intercepted, it is enoughto stop the poor bees' breath,—yea, and to strangle themquite? Or is not the acrimony and bitterness (think you)of the smoke in cause—for bees are delighted withsweet things, and in very truth they have no other nourishment; and therefore no marvel if they detest and abhorsmoke, as a thing for the bitterness most adverse and contrary unto them. Therefore honey-masters, when theymake a smoke for to drive away bees, are wont to burnbitter herbs, as hemlock, centaury, etc.</p>			</div1>			<div1 type="chapter" n="36"> 				<p>Why will bees sooner sting those who newly before have committed whoredom?</p>				<p>Is it not because it is a creature that wonderfully delighteth in purity, cleanliness, and elegancy, and withalhath a marvellous quick sense of smelling? Becausetherefore such unclean dealings between man and womanare wont to leave behind much filthiness and impurity,the bees both sooner find them out and also conceivethe greater hatred against them. Hereupon it is thatin Theocritus the shepherd pleasantly sendeth Venusaway unto Anchises to be well stung with bees for heradultery: Now to mount Ida, to Anchises go, Where mighty oaks and cypresses do grow; Where hives and trees with honey sweet abound, And both with humming noise of bees resound.</p>				<p>And Pindar saith: Thou little creature, who honey-combsdost frame, and with thy sting hast pricked false impureRhoecus for his lewd villanies.</p>			</div1>			<div1 type="chapter" n="37"> 				<p>Why do dogs follow after a stone that is thrown at them and bite it, letting the man alone who flung it?</p>				<p>Is it because he can comprehend nothing by imaginationnor call a thing to mind, which are gifts and virtues properto man alone; and therefore, seeing he cannot discern theparty that offered him injury, he supposeth that to be hisenemy which seemeth in his eye to threaten him, and ofit he goes about to be revenged? Or is it that he thinksthe stone, while it runs along the ground, to be some wildbeast, and according to his nature he intendeth to catch itfirst; but afterwards, when he seeth himself deceived andput besides his reckoning, he setteth upon the man? Orrather, doth he not hate the man and the stone both alike,but pursueth that only which is next unto him?</p>			</div1>			<div1 type="chapter" n="38"> 				<p>Why at a certain time of the year do all she-wolves whelp within the compass of twelve days?</p>				<p>Antipater in his History of Animals affirms, that shewolves exclude forth their young ones about the time thatmast trees shed their blossoms, for upon the taste thereoftheir wombs open; but if there be none of such bloomsto be had, then their young die within the body and nevercome to light. Moreover, he saith, those countries whichbring not forth oaks and mast are never troubled norspoiled with wolves. Some attribute all this to a talethat goes of Latona; who being with child, and findingno abiding place of rest and safety by reason of Juno forthe space of twelve days, went to Delos, and, being transmuted by Jupiter into a wolf, obtained at his hands thatall wolves for ever after might within that time be deliveredof their young.</p>			</div1>			<div1 type="chapter" n="39"> 				<p>How cometh it that water, seeming white aloft, showeth to be black in the bottom?</p>				<p>Is it because depth is the mother of darkness, so that itdoth dim and mar the sunbeams before they can descendso low as it? As for the uppermost superficies of thewater, because it is immediately affected by the sun, itmust needs receive the white brightness of the light; thewhich Empedocles verily approveth in these verses: A river in the bottom seems By shade of color black; The like is seen in caves and holes, By depth, where light they lack.</p>				<p>Or, since the bottom of the sea and of great rivers isoften full of mud, doth it by reflection of the sunbeamsrepresent the like color that the said mud hath? Or is itmore probable that the water toward the bottom is notpure and sincere, but corrupted with an earthy quality,—as continually carrying with it somewhat of that by whichit runneth and wherewith it is stirred,—and the samesettling once to the bottom causeth it to be more troubledand less transparent?</p>			</div1>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI.2>