<TEI.2>
	<teiHeader type="text">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>De Amore Prolis</title>
				<author>Plutarch</author>
				<editor role="editor">William W. Goodwin</editor>
				<funder n="org:Google">Google Digital Humanities Awards Program</funder>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
				<pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
				<authority>Perseus Project</authority>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<monogr>
						<title>De Amore Prolis</title>
						<author>Plutarch</author>
				<editor role="editor">William W. Goodwin</editor>
						<imprint>
							<publisher>Little, Brown and company</publisher>
							<place>Boston</place>
							<publisher>Press Of John Wilson and son</publisher>
							<place>Cambridge</place>
							<date>1874</date>
						</imprint>
						<respStmt>
							<name>Translated from the Greek by several hands</name>
							<resp>translation</resp>
							<name>William W. Goodwin</name>
							<resp>correction and revision</resp>
						</respStmt>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
				<p>Keyboarding</p>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
				<state unit="chapter"/>
			</refsDecl>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<langUsage>
				<language id="english">English</language>
			</langUsage>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>			<div1 type="section" n="1">				<p>APPEALS to foreign judicatures first came in requestamong the Grecians out of their distrust of one another'sjustice, they deeming it as requisite to fetch justice fromabroad, as any other necessary commodity which was notof their own growth. And is it not even so that philosophers, by reason of dissensions amongst themselves, havein the decision of some questions appealed to the natureof irrational beings, as to a strange city, and have submitted the final determination of such questions to the affections or to the dispositions of brutes, as being unbiassed and not corrupted by bribes? Or else this is the general complaint of human frailty, that while we differ about themost necessary and the greatest things, we consult horses,dogs, and birds, how we should marry, beget children, andbring them up; and, as if the evidence of Nature in ourselves were not to be trusted, we appeal to the dispositionsand affections of brute beasts, and testify against the manifold transgressions of our own lives, intimating how atthe very first and in the first things we are confounded anddisturbed. For Nature conserves the propriety in thempure, unmixed, and simple; but in men, the mixture ofascititious opinions and judgments (as oil is served by thedruggists) alters the properties, and does not preserve whatis their peculiar. Nor need we wonder if irrational animals follow Nature more than rational; for plants do itmore than animals, for they have neither imagination norpassion for what is not according to Nature, but are boundin chains, and ever go that one way that Nature leadsthem. Brutes do little regard gentleness, wit, or liberty;they have indeed the use of irrational incitements and appetites, which put them upon wandering and runningabout,—but seldom far, for they seem to lie at the anchorof Nature, who guides them in the right way (as it were)by bit and bridle. But reason, the lord and master in man,finds sometimes one turning, sometimes another; but in allits wanderings leaves no mark or footstep of Nature.</p>				</div1> 			<div1 type="section" n="2">				<p>But in brutes observe how all things are accommodated to Nature. As to marriages, they tarry not till lawsare passed against celibacy and late marriages, as Lycurgusand Solon's citizens did; they matter not the disgrace ofwanting children; nor are they ambitious of the honor ofhaving three children, as many Romans, who marry andget children, not that they may have heirs, but that theymay get estates. Again, the male accompanies with thefemale not at all times, because not pleasure but procreation is his end. Therefore in the spring time, when thefruitful breezes blow and the air is of a pregnant temper,then the female approaches the male, gentle and desirable,wantoning in the sweet smell and peculiar ornament ofher body, full of dew and pure grass; and when she perceives she has conceived, she modestly departs, and provides for her bringing forth and for the safety of what sheshall be delivered of. What brutes do cannot be sufficientlyexpressed; in all of them their affection to their young isevident by their providence, patience, and continence. Indeed we call the bee wise, and we celebrate her who deviseth the yellow honey, flattering her for glutting us withher sweetness; but the wisdom and art of other creatures,about their bringing forth and the rearing their young, wewholly neglect. For instance, first, the king-fisher, whenshe has conceived, makes her nest of the prickles of thesea-needle, weaving them one among another, in form of along oval fishing-net; then she puts it under the dashingof the waters, that being by degrees beaten upon andmilled, it may acquire a smooth surface, and become sosolid that it cannot easily be divided by either stone or iron.And what is more wonderful, the mouth of the nest is soexactly fitted to the king-fisher, that neither a greater nora less animal can enter it; and when she is in (as theysay) it will not admit the sea-water. The sea-fish called<foreign lang="greek">galeoi/</foreign> give birth to their young within themselves, let themgo abroad to feed, and then take them into their belliesagain when they go to sleep. The bear, a most fierce andugly beast, brings forth her young shapeless and withoutlimbs, but with her tongue, as with a tool, she shapes themembers; so that she seems not only to bring forth but towork out her young. And Homer's lioness,—div1 Thus in the centre of some gloomy wood, With many a step the lioness surrounds Her tawny young, beset by men and hounds; Elate her heart, and rousing all her powers, Dark o'er the fiery balls each hanging eyebrow lowers;  div1does she not, I say, look as if she were contriving how tomake a bargain with the huntsman for her whelps? Forgenerally the love of their young makes bold creaturestimorous, the slothful industrious, and the voracious parsimonious. So Homer's bird gives to her young, thoughwith herself it go hard.  She feeds them by starvingherself, and when she has taken up her food, she lays itdown again, and keeps it down with her bill, lest sheshould swallow it unawares. In like manner,div1 For tender whelps, when strangers come in sight, The barking bitch prepares herself to fight;  div1 and fear for her young turns into a second passion. Whenpartridges and their young are pursued, the old suffer theyoung to fly away before, so contriving it that the fowlermay think to catch them. Thus they hover about, runforward a little, then turn again, and so detain the fowlertill their young are safe. We daily behold hens, how theycherish their chickens, taking some of them under theirspread wings, suffering others of them to run upon theirbacks, and taking them in again, with a voice expressingkindness and joy. When themselves are concerned, they flyfrom dogs and serpents; but to defend their chickens, theywill venture beyond their strength and fight. And shall we think that Nature has bred such affectionsin these creatures, because she is solicitous for the propagation of hens, dogs, and bears, and not that she may bythese means make us ashamed? Certainly we must conclude that these creatures, following the duct of nature,are for our example, and that they much upbraid the remorselessness of humanity, of which human nature aloneis culpable, in not being capable of gratuitous love, norknowing how to be a friend without profit. Well therefore might the comedian be admired who said, For rewardonly man loves man. Epicurus thinks that after this manner children are beloved of their parents, and parents oftheir children. But if the benefit of speech were allowedto brutes, and if horses, cows, dogs, and birds were broughtupon the stage, and the song were changed, and it weresaid that neither the bitch loved her whelps for gain, northe mare her foal, nor fowls their chickens, but that theywere all beloved gratis and by impulse of nature, then bythe affection of all brutes this assertion would be approvedas just and true. And is it not a shame, that the procreation of beasts, their birth, pains in birth, and their education, should be by nature and gratis, and yet for thesethings that man should require usury, rewards, and bribes? </p>				</div1> 			<div1 type="section" n="3">				<p>This assertion, as to pure Nature, can never be true,nor ought it to be believed. For, as in wild plants, suchas wild vines, figs, and olives, Nature has implanted theprinciples of cultivated fruit, though crude and imperfect;so she has endowed beasts with a love of their young,though imperfect and not attaining to justice, nor proceeding further than utility. But in man, whom she produceda rational and political being, inclining him to justice, law,religion, building of cities, and friendship, she hath placedthe seed of those things that are generous, fair, and fruitful,—that is, the love of their children,—following the firstprinciples which entered into the very constitution of theirbodies. For terms and expressions are wanting to declarewith what industry Nature—who is skilful, unerring, andnot to be surpassed, and (as Erasistratus says) has nothingidle or frivolous—has contrived all things pertaining tothe procreation of mankind; and modesty will not permitit. The making and economy of milk sufficiently speakher providence and care. In women what abundance ofblood more than serves for necessary uses, which, throughlanguidness and want of spirit, wanders about and disturbsthe body; being at other times by Nature in monthly periodsdischarged by proper canals and passages, for the reliefand purgation of the body, and to render the womb like afield fit for the plough and seed, and desirous of it atseasons. But when the womb has caught the seed, and ithas taken root (for the navel as Democritus says, growsfirst, like an anchor to keep the foetus from fluctuating, oras a stay or footstalk to the child), then Nature stops thepassages proper for monthly purgations, and keeps thesuperfluous blood after that for nourishment and to moistenthe birth, which now begins to be formed and fashioned,and at the end of a set number of days increases so in thewomb, that it must seek another place and other sort offood. Then Nature, more diligent than any husbandman,deriving the blood to other uses, has as it were some subterraneanfountains, which receive the affluent liquors;and they receive them not negligently nor without affection,but with a gentle heat and womanish softness they concoct,mollify, and alter them; for in this manner are the breastsinternally affected and tempered. And milk is not pouredout of them by pipes in a full stream; but the breasts,terminating in flesh that is pervious by small and insensible passages, do afford store of sweet and pleasant sucking to the infant's mouth. But for all this, such and somany instruments for procreation, such preparation, sogreat industry and providence, were all to no purpose,unless Nature had inbred in the mothers a love and careof their offspring.div1 Than man more wretched naught takes breath, Not th' vilest thing that creeps on earth;  div1which infallibly holds good of infants new-born. Fornothing can be beheld so imperfect, helpless, naked, shapeless, and nasty, as man is just at his birth; to whom alonealmost Nature has denied a cleanly passage into the world;and as he is smeared with blood, and daubed with filth,more like to one killed than to one new-born, he couldnever be touched, taken in arms, kissed, or hugged by anyone to whom Nature had not given an inbred affection forhim. Therefore other animals have their dugs below theirbelly, which grow on woman above her breast, that shemay the more conveniently kiss, embrace, and cherish herinfant; because the end of bringing forth and rearing isnot necessity but love.</p>				</div1> 			<div1 type="section" n="4">				<p>For let us look back to ancient times, to those whofirst brought forth and who first saw a child born. Uponthem certainly no law enjoined any necessity of rearingtheir offspring, nor could expectation of thanks obligethem to feed their infants, as if it were for usury. Nay,rather, they were angry with their children, and long remembered the injuries they had received from them, asauthors of so many dangers and of so much pain and travailto them.div1 As when keen darts the fierce Ilithyiae send; the powers that cause the teeming matron's throes, Sad mothers of unutterable woes! These verses, some say, were not written by Homer, butby some Homeress, who either had been or was then intravail, and felt the very pangs in her bowels. Yet thelove implanted by Nature melts and sways the childbedwoman. While she is still in a sweat and trembling forpain, she is not averse to her infant; but turns it to her,smiles on it, hugs and kisses it. Though she finds no truesweetness, nor yet profit, however, she sometimes rocks itin a warm cradle, sometimes she dances it in the cool air,turning one toil into another, resting neither night nor day. For what reward or gain was all this? For as littlethen as now; for the hopes are uncertain and far off. Hethat plants a vine in the vernal equinox gathers grapesupon it in the autumnal. He that sows wheat at the setting of the Pleiades reaps it at their rising. Cows, mares,and birds bring forth young ready for use. Man'seducation is laborious, his increase slow, his virtue lies ata distance; so that most parents die before their childrenshow their virtue. Neocles never saw Themistocles's victory at Salamis, nor Miltiades the valor of Cimon at Eurymedon; Xanthippus never heard Pericles pleading; norAristo Plato philosophizing; nor did the fathers of Euripides and Sophocles know the victories their sons won,though they heard them indeed stammering and learningto talk. It is the mishap of fathers to see the revelling,drinking, and love intrigues of their children; to whichpurpose that of Evenus is memorable, div1 Terror or grief unto his father's heart A son must ever be. div1And yet men find no end of rearing of children; they especially who have no need of them. For it is ridiculousto think that rich men, when they have children born tothem, sacrifice and rejoice that they may have some tomaintain and to bury them. Or is it perhaps that theybring up children for want of heirs, because, forsooth, mencannot be found to accept of another man's estate? Sand,dust, and the feathers of all the birds in the world, are notso numerous as heirs are to other men's estates. Danauswas the father of fifty daughters; but if he had wantedissue, he might have had many more heirs. The case isfar otherwise with children; they make not acknowledgments nor curry favor nor pay their devotions, as expectingthe inheritance of due. But you may hear strangers whohang about them that have no heirs, talking like the comedian:div1 O Demos, having after judgment bathed, Drink, eat a morsel, take three oboli.  div1And what Euripides said,div1 'Tis money that procures us friends to choose, And mightiest power o'er all things that men use, div1does not universally hold true, but of such only as haveno children. To such the rich give banquets, such greatmen honor, and for such only lawyers plead gratis. Arich man who has no known heir can do great matters.Many a man who has had a great number of friends andfollowers, as soon as he has had a child, has been divestedof all his alliances and power. So that children do notaugment a man's power; but their whole power over theirparents' affection is due to Nature, and is shown no lessin men than in beasts.</p>				</div1> 			<div1 type="section" n="5">				<p>But this natural affection, like many other good qualities in men, may be choked and obscured by vices; aswhen a wild forest is sown with garden-seeds. Can wesay that man loves not himself, because some hang themselves, others break their own necks, Oedipus put out hisown eyes, and Hegesias, by his disputation, persuadedmany of his auditors to pine themselves to death?For fatal things in various shapes do walk.div1But all these things are disease and craziness of mind,transporting a man out of his own nature; and in thismen testify against themselves. For if a sow or a bitchkill the young they have brought forth, men look dejected,are disturbed, sacrifice to the Gods to avert the mischief,and do account it a miracle; because men know that Nature has implanted in all creatures the love of their young,so that they should feed them and not kill them. For asamong metals gold, though mixed with much rubbish, willappear; so Nature, even in vicious deeds and affection, declares the love to posterity. For poor people do not reartheir children, fearing that, if they should not be well educated, they would prove slavish, clownish, and destitute of allthings commendable; since they cannot endure to entailpoverty, which they look upon as the worst of all evils ordiseases, upon their posterity.</p>			</div1>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI.2>