<TEI.2>
	<teiHeader type="text">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>De Sollertia Animalium</title>
				<author>Plutarch</author>
				<editor role="editor">William W. Goodwin</editor>
				<funder n="org:Google">Google Digital Humanities Awards Program</funder>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
				<pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
				<authority>Perseus Project</authority>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<monogr>
						<title>De Sollertia Animalium</title>
						<author>Plutarch</author>
				<editor role="editor">William W. Goodwin</editor>
						<imprint>
							<publisher>Little, Brown and company</publisher>
							<place>Boston</place>
							<publisher>Press Of John Wilson and son</publisher>
							<place>Cambridge</place>
							<date>1874</date>
						</imprint>
						<respStmt>
							<name>Translated from the Greek by several hands</name>
							<resp>translation</resp>
							<name>William W. Goodwin</name>
							<resp>correction and revision</resp>
						</respStmt>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
				<p>Keyboarding</p>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
				<state unit="chapter"/>
			</refsDecl>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<langUsage>
				<language id="english">English</language>
			</langUsage>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body> 			<div1 type="section" n="1">				<p> Reason persuades us now to return with fresh cogitations and dispositions to what we left cold yesterday ofour discourse about flesh-eating. It is indeed a hard anda difficult task to undertake (as Cato once said) to disputewith men's bellies, that have no ears; since most havealready drunk that draught of custom, which is like thatof Circe, Of groans and frauds and sorcery replete. And it is no easy task to pull out the hook of flesh-eating from the jaws of such as lave gorged themselveswith luxury and are (as it were) nailed down with it. Itwould indeed be a good action, if as the Egyptians drawout the stomach of a dead body, and cut it open andexpose it to the sun, as the only cause of all its evilactions, so we could, by cutting out our gluttony andblood-shedding, purify and cleanse the remainder of ourlives. For the stomach itself is not guilty of bloodshed,but is involuntarily polluted by our intemperance. But ifthis may not be, and we are ashamed by reason of customto live unblamably, let us at least sin with discretion. Letus eat flesh; but let it be for hunger and not for wantonness. Let us kill an animal; but let us do it with sorrowand pity, and not abusing and tormenting it, as many nowadays are used to do, while some run red-hot spits throughthe bodies of swine, that by the tincture of the quenched ironthe blood may be to that degree mortified, that it maysweeten and soften the flesh in its circulation; othersjump and stamp upon the udders of sows that are readyto pig, that so they may trample into one mass, (O PiacularJupiter!) in the very pangs of delivery, blood, milk, andthe corruption of the crushed and mangled young ones,and so eat the most inflamed part of the animal; otherssew up the eyes of cranes and swans, and so shut them upin darkness to be fattened, and then souse up their fleshwith certain monstrous mixtures and pickles. </p>			</div1> 			<div1 type="section" n="2">				<p> By all which it is most manifest, that it is not fornourishment, or want, or any necessity, but for mere gluttony, wantonness, and expensiveness, that they make apleasure of villany. Just as it happens in persons whocannot satiate their intemperance upon women, and havingmade trial of every thing else and falling into vagaries, atlast attempt things not to be mentioned; even so inordinateness in feeding, when it hath once passed the boundsof nature and necessity, studies at last to diversify the lustsof its intemperate appetite by cruelty and villany. Forthe senses, when they once quit their natural measures,sympathize with each other in their distempers, and areenticed by each other to the same consent and intemperance. Thus a distempered ear first debauched music, thesoft and effeminate notes of which provoke immodesttouches and lascivious tickling. These things first taughtthe eye not to delight in Pyrrhic dances, gesticulations ofhands, or elegant pantomimes, nor in statues and finepaintings; but to reckon the slaughtering and death ofmankind and wounds and duels the most sumptuous ofshows and spectacles. Thus unlawful tables are accompanied with intemperate copulations, with unmusician-likeballs, and theatres become monstrous through shamefulsongs and rehearsals; and barbarous and brutish showsare again accompanied with an unrelenting temper andsavage cruelty towards mankind. Hence it was that thedivine Lycurgus in his Three Books of Laws gave ordersthat the doors and ridges of men's houses should be madewith a saw and an axe, and that no other instrument shouldso much as be brought to any house. Not that he didhereby intend to declare war against augers and planesand other instruments of finer work; but because he verywell knew that with such tools as these you will neverbring into your house a gilded couch, and that you willnever attempt to bring into a slender cottage either silvertables, purple carpets, or costly stones; but that a plainsupper and a homely dinner must accompany such a house,couch, table, and cup. The beginning of a vicious diet ispresently followed by all sorts of luxury and expensiveness, Ev'n as a mare is by her thirsty colt. </p>			</div1> 			<div1 type="section" n="3">				<p> And what meal is not expensive? That for which noanimal is put to death. Shall we reckon a soul to be asmall expense. I will not say perhaps of a mother, or afather, or of some friend, or child, as Empedocles did; butone participating of feeling, of seeing, of hearing, of imagination, and of intellection; which each animal hath received from Nature for the acquiring of what is agreeableto it, and the avoiding what is disagreeable. Do but consider this with yourself now, which sort of philosophersrender us most tame and civil, they who bid people to feedon their children, friends, fathers, and wives, when they aredead; or Pythagoras and Empedocles, that accustom mento be just towards even the other members of the creation.You laugh at a man that will not eat a sheep: but we(they will say again)—when we see you cutting off theparts of your dead father or mother, and sending it to yourabsent friends, and calling upon and inviting your presentfriends to eat the rest freely and heartily—shall we notsmile? Nay, peradventure we offend at this instant timewhile we touch these books, without having first cleansedour hands, eyes, feet, and ears; if it be not (by Jupiter) asufficient purgation of them to have discoursed of thesematters in potable and fresh language (as Plato speaketh),thereby washing off the brackishness of hearing. Now ifa man should set these books and discourses in oppositionto each other, he will find that the philosophy of the onesort suits with the Scythians, Sogdians, and Melanchlaenians, of whom Herodotus's relation is scarce believed;but the sentiments of Pythagoras and Empedocles were thelaws and customs of the ancient Grecians. </p>			</div1> 			<div1 type="section" n="4">				<p> Who then were the first authors of this opinion, thatwe owe no justice to dumb animals? Who first beat out accursed steel, And made the laboring ox a knife to feel. In the very same manner oppressors and tyrants begin firstto shed blood. For example, the first man that the Athenians ever put to death was one of the basest of all knaves,whom all thought deserving of death; after him they putto death a second and a third. After this, being now accustomed to blood, they patiently saw Niceratus the son ofNicias, and their own general Theramenes, and Polemarchus the philosopher suffer death. Even so, in the beginning, some wild and mischievous beast was killed and eaten,and then some little bird or fish was entrapped. And thelove of slaughter, being first experimented and exercisedin these, at last passed even to the laboring ox, and thesheep that clothes us, and to the poor cock that keepsthe house; until by little and little, unsatiableness beingstrengthened by use, men came to the slaughter of men,to bloodshed and wars. Now even if one cannot demonstrate and make out, that souls in their regenerations makea promiscuous use of all bodies, and that that which is nowrational will at another time be irrational, and that againtame which is now wild,—for that Nature changes andtransmutes every thing, With different fleshy coats new clothing all,— this thing should be sufficient to change and reclaim men,that it is a savage and intemperate habit, that it brings sickness and heaviness upon the body, and that it inclines themind the more brutishly to bloodshed and destruction, whenwe have once accustomed ourselves neither to entertain aguest nor keep a wedding nor to treat our friends withoutblood and slaughter. </p>			</div1> 			<div1 type="section" n="5">				<p> And if what is argued about the return of souls intobodies is not of force enough to beget faith, yet methinksthe very uncertainty of the thing should fill us with apprehension and fear. Suppose, for instance, one should insome night engagement run on with his drawn sword uponone that had fallen down and covered his body with hisarms, and should in the mean time hear one say, that hewas not very sure, but that he fancied and believed, thatthe party lying there was his own son, brother, father, ortent-companion; which were more advisable, think you,—to hearken to a false suggestion, and so to let go an enemyunder the notion of a friend, or to slight an authority notsufficient to beget faith, and to slay a friend instead of afoe? This you will all say would be insupportable. Dobut consider the famous Merope in the tragedy, who takingup a hatchet, and lifting it at her son's head, whom shetook for her son's murderer, speaks thus as she was readyto give the fatal blow, Villain, this pious blow shall cleave thy head; what a bustle she raises in the whole theatre while sheraises herself to give the blow, and what a fear they areall in, lest she should prevent the old man that comes tostop her hand, and should wound the youth. Now if another old man should stand by her and say, Strike, it isthy enemy, and this, Hold, it is thy son; which, thinkyou, would be the greater injustice, to omit the punishingof an enemy for the sake of one's child, or to suffer one'sself to be so transported with anger at an enemy as to killone's child? Since then neither hatred nor wrath nor anyrevenge nor fear for ourselves carries us to the slaughterof a beast, but the poor sacrifice stands with an inclinedneck, only to satisfy thy lust and pleasure, and then onephilosopher stands by and tells thee, Cut him down, it isbut an unreasonable animal, and another cries, Hold,what if there should be the soul of some kinsman or Godinclosed in him—good Gods! is there the like dangerif I refuse to eat flesh, as if I for want of faith murder mychild or some other friend? </p>			</div1> 			<div1 type="section" n="6">				<p> The Stoics' way of reasoning upon this subject of flesh-eating is no way equal nor consonant with themselves.Who is this that hath so many mouths for his belly and thekitchen? Whence comes it to pass, that they so verymuch womanize and reproach pleasure, as a thing that theywill not allow to be either good or preferable, or so muchas agreeable, and yet all on a sudden become so zealousadvocates for pleasures? It were indeed but a reasonableconsequence of their doctrine, that, since they banish perfumes and cakes from their banquets, they should be muchmore averse to blood and to flesh. But now, just as if theywould reduce their philosophy to their day-books, theylessen the expenses of their suppers in certain unnecessaryand needless matters, but the untamed and murderous partof their expense they nothing boggle at. Well! Whatthen? say they. We have nothing to do with brutebeasts. Nor have you any with perfumes, nor with foreign sauces, may some one answer; therefore expel thesefrom your banquets, if you are driving out every thingthat is both useless and needless. </p>			</div1> 			<div1 type="section" n="7">				<p> Let us therefore in the next place consider, whetherwe owe any justice to the brute beasts. Neither shall wehandle this point artificially, or like subtle sophisters, butby casting our eye into our own breasts, and conversing withourselves as men, we will weigh and examine the wholematter.</p>			</div1>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI.2>