<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng"
    type="application/xml"
    schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title xml:lang="en">Κυνηγετικά</title>
        <author>
          <persName>ARRIANUS</persName>
          
        </author>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Encodage automatique TEI P5</resp>
          <name>zoomathia_encoder.py v3.0</name>
          <date when="2026-07-11">2026-07-11</date>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Projet Zoomathia (ANR-21-CE27-0012)</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Universite Cote d'Azur, Nice, France</pubPlace>
        <date when="2026-07-11">2026-07-11</date>
        <availability>
          <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0</licence>
        </availability>
        <idno type="zoomathia"></idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Encode automatiquement par zoomathia_encoder.py v3.0 - Projet Zoomathia</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language ident="en">anglais</language>
      </langUsage>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="zoomathia">
          <term>Zoomathia</term>
          <term>animaux</term>
          <term>inconnu</term>
          <term>anglais</term>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>Fichier encode automatiquement dans le cadre du projet Zoomathia (ANR).
        Encodage produit par zoomathia_encoder.py v3.0. Verification humaine recommandee.</p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>Balisage automatique des structures textuelles et des entites nommees
        pertinentes pour Zoomathia (animaux, plantes, personnes, lieux).</p>
        <correction status="unknown">
          <p>Encodage automatique - erreurs possibles, revision manuelle recommandee.</p>
        </correction>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
<div type="book" n="1">
   <p>The <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Cynegeticus</name> was originally written by <persName>Arrian</persName>, in imitation of <persName>Xenophon</persName>’s <foreign xml:lang="la">Treatise de Venatione</foreign>, to supply the lacunæ of that work in the particular department of Coursing.</p>
   <p>The manuscript seems to have been neglected in the <placeName>Vatican library</placeName> for several years after it had been first discovered, in consequence of its bearing the name of <persName>Xenophon</persName>: for the persons who accidentally met with it, not being aware of <persName>Arrian</persName>’s assumption of that title, took no pains to examine it, under an impression that it was the edited <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Cynegeticus</name> of the elder <persName>Xenophon</persName>, and not a new and unknown treatise on a different branch of the same subject, by an author of the same assumed name, a pseudo-<persName>Xenophon</persName>.</p>
   <p>We are told by <persName>Mausacus</persName> that <persName>Rigaltius</persName> intended to have edited it with the <foreign xml:lang="la">Scriptores de Re Accipitrariâ et de Curâ Canum</foreign>, (the first edition of which he published in 1612, with a forged epistle in <foreign xml:lang="en">Castilian</foreign> and <foreign xml:lang="la">Latin</foreign> from <persName>Aquila Symmachus</persName> and <persName>Theodotion</persName> to a <persName>Ptolemy</persName>, King of <placeName>Egypt</placeName>,) but the 52 printers refused their consent, unless he added a <foreign xml:lang="la">Latin</foreign> translation; a desideratum which was afterwards supplied by <persName>Holstein</persName> in the first edition. <persName>Henry Stephens</persName>, however, had previously perused the unpublished treatise, and given to the world, in his <foreign xml:lang="la">Schediasmata</foreign>, some observations on different passages.</p>
   <p><persName>Holstein</persName>, the first editor, was a celebrated scholar of his day, and is commemorated in the <foreign xml:lang="la">Sept. Illustr. Vir. Poemata</foreign> as—</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="2/56">
   <p>His edition issued from the Paris press of <persName>Sebastian</persName> and <persName>Gabriel Cramoisy</persName> in the year 1644. The <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Greek</name> text, and version attached to it, were amended by <persName>Blancard</persName> in his <placeName>Amsterdam</placeName> edition of 1683; which contains also the minor works of <persName>Arrian</persName>, and the pertinent <foreign xml:lang="la">schediasmata</foreign> of <persName>Henry Stephens</persName> above mentioned. My library affords no editions but the above two, and the accurate reprint of <persName>Schneider</persName> by the <placeName>University of Oxford</placeName> in 1817. The last is certainly the best edition of the <foreign xml:lang="la">Cynegeticus</foreign> of <persName>Arrian</persName> which I have seen. The <placeName>Clarendon</placeName> press also published in the same volume the <foreign xml:lang="la">Cynegeticus</foreign> of the elder <persName>Xenophon</persName>, and his <foreign xml:lang="la">Opuscula Politica</foreign>; the same collection of the minor works as <persName>Zeune</persName> comprehended in one volume, printed at <placeName>Leipsic</placeName>, 1778.</p>
</div>
<div type="book" n="3">
  <p>M. Gail is reported to have published a French translation of the work, with critical notes and dissertations, at <placeName>Paris</placeName>, in 1801: but, notwithstanding repeated applications to the Parisian booksellers, I have not been able to procure a copy.</p>
  <p>Equally unsuccessful have been my endeavours to obtain from the same source <persName>Defermat</persName>’s version, published by <persName>Hortemels</persName> of <placeName>Paris</placeName>, in 1690.</p>
  <p>The latter, however, in consequence of the literary character given of its author by <persName>Belin de Ballu</persName>, in his prolegomena to <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Oppian</name>, I do not much regret.</p>
  <p>It accompanied 53 a French version of the two last books of the <foreign xml:lang="la">Cynegetics</foreign> of the <placeName>Cilician</placeName> poet, which are stated to abound in errors of translation, and to be performed in a tedious and barbarous style by <persName>Defermat</persName>, eminent as a mathematician, but of moderate attainment in Greek literature.</p>
  <p>The present version was completed before I was aware of any prior attempt to translate the <foreign xml:lang="la">Cynegeticus</foreign> into English: the first notice of which, in the partial labours of Mr. <persName>Blane</persName>, was derived from <persName>Schneider</persName>’s annotations.</p>
  <p>I do not believe any other to exist in the English language, with the exception of such fragments of the treatise as may have been occasionally made to speak English, on the emergency of a periodical publication needing an article on <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Coursing</name>; or a literary sportsman wishing to enliven his communications by a reference to the manual, and quoting it in his vernacular tongue.</p>
</div>
<div type="book" n="1">
   <p>Mr. Blane’s attempt did not extend apparently to the whole treatise. It is in parts inaccurately executed, and omits numerous sentences, where he professes to translate; and whole chapters in sequence, where we can see no reason for omission.</p>
   <p>The fourth, and ten following chapters to the fourteenth inclusive, and the twenty-third and twelve following chapters to the thirty-fifth inclusive, are entirely omitted by this capricious translator.</p>
   <p>Since, then, in a work consisting of only thirty-five chapters, he has, without assigning any cause, passed over twenty-four unnoticed, nearly all of them important to practical <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">coursers</name>, some evincing the kindly feelings of their author, (as for instance, the one containing the affectionate history of his beloved dog <persName>Hormē</persName>,) and others most honourable to his humanity, and confirmative of the purity of his religious faith, operative in a heathen breast, (as the two closing chapters, showing, amidst much fabulous allusion, his unreserved acknowledgment of human dependence on divine aid, and the certainty of evil and misfortune being consequent on irreligion and moral transgression,)</p>
   <p>I hope a complete translation of this ancient <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">courser</name>’s enchiridion will not be considered an useless undertaking.</p>
   <p><persName>BIOGRAPHICAL NOTICE OF ARRIAN</persName>.</p>
</div>
<div type="chapter" n="5">
   <p>Mr. Addison has remarked, that <quote>“a reader seldom peruses a book with pleasure till he knows whether the writer of it be a black or a fair man, of a mild or a choleric disposition, married, or a bachelor, with other particulars of the like nature, that conduce very much to the right understanding of an author.”</quote> If, however, the satisfaction of perusing the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Cynegeticus</name> of <persName>Arrian</persName> be dependent on a previous acquaintance with these personal particulars of their author, I fear the modern reader will regret the insufficiency of the following biographical notice. Scanty as it is, it contains all the information I have been able to collect relative to the younger <persName>Xenophon</persName>.⁠ <pb n="27"/></p>
</div>
<div type="book" n="6">
  <div type="chapter" n="56">
    <p>Flavius <persName>Arrianus</persName>⁠ <ref target="#note28">[28]</ref> was a citizen both of <placeName>Athens</placeName> and <placeName>Rome</placeName>, of Grecian extraction, and born probably in the reign of <persName>Domitian</persName>, at <placeName>Nicomedia</placeName>, a celebrated city of <placeName>Bithynia</placeName>; where, according to <persName>Photius</persName> on the authority of our author’s “<title>Bithynica</title>,” <ref target="#note55">55</ref> a lost work on the subject of his native country, he was priest of <name type="deity">Ceres</name> and <name type="deity">Proserpine</name>, to whom the city of <placeName>Nicomedia</placeName> was sacred.</p>
    <p>His fondness for polite literature, and celebrity for philosophical knowledge, acquired him the honour of the twofold citizenship. <foreign xml:lang="la">Arriani Bithynica et Parthica</foreign> apud <persName>Photii</persName> <foreign xml:lang="la">Eclogas</foreign>. But, though a friend and disciple of <persName>Epictetus</persName>, and the first recorder of his Stoical <foreign xml:lang="la">Apophthegms</foreign>—<foreign xml:lang="grc">φιλόσοφος μὲν ἐπιστήμην, εἷς τῶν ὁμιλητῶν Ἐπικτήτου</foreign>, he appears, like the elder <persName>Xenophon</persName>, to have been much engaged in military affairs; and as Roman prefect of <placeName>Cappadocia</placeName>, in the reign of <persName>Hadrian</persName>, to have taken an active part in the war against the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Alani</name> and <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Massagetæ</name>, a people bred to eternal warfare—</p>
    <p>It is related by <persName>Dion Cassius</persName>, and the epitomizer <persName>Xiphilin</persName>, that the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Scythian</name> barbarians under <persName>Pharasmanes</persName> having committed great havock and spoil in <placeName>Media</placeName>, (A.D. 136.) had begun to threaten <placeName>Armenia</placeName> and <placeName>Cappadocia</placeName>; <quote><persName>Dion. Cassii Hist. Roman.</persName> L. lxix.</quote> but finding <persName>Flavius Arrianus</persName>, the prefect of the latter province, better prepared for their reception than they had anticipated, they were induced, partly by the bribes of <persName>Vologæsus</persName>, and partly through fear of the governor, to retire from the territory under his jurisdiction.</p>
  </div>
</div>
<div type="book" n="7">
  <div type="section" n="56">
    <p>Suidas, on the authority of <persName>Heliconius</persName>, states that <persName>Arrian</persName> was advanced to the senatorial and consular dignities, and that he was denominated “the second <name type="person">Xenophon</name>” from the sweetness of his literary style.</p>
    <p>And <persName>Photius</persName> also, in his “<foreign xml:lang="la">Eclogæ</foreign>,” speaking of our author’s “<foreign xml:lang="la">Parthica</foreign>” observes, <quote><foreign xml:lang="grc">ἐπωνόμαζον αὐτὸν Ξενοφῶντα νέον· διὰ δὲ τὸ παιδείας ἐπίσημον, ἄλλας τε πολιτικὰς ἀρχὰς ἐπιστεύθη, καὶ εἰς τὸ τῶν ὑπάτων ἀνέβη τέλος</foreign></quote>; and again he adds, <quote><foreign xml:lang="grc">δῆλον δὲ ὡς οὐδὲ ῥητορικῆς σοφίας τε καὶ δυνάμεως ἀπελείπετο</foreign></quote>.</p>
    <p>Like his namesake, as I have remarked, he united the character of a man of letters with that of a warrior, dedicating a great portion of his time to philosophical and historical research.</p>
    <p>But it is not my intention to enlarge on his literary character in general, nor to enter in detail into the merits of his several compositions.</p>
    <p>His principal historical work, “<foreign xml:lang="en">The Anabasis of Alexander</foreign>,” though composed, says <persName>Dr. Robertson</persName>, “long after <placeName>Greece</placeName> had lost its liberty, and in an age when genius and taste were on the decline, is not unworthy the purest times of <placeName>Attic</placeName> literature.”</p>
    <p>And his “<foreign xml:lang="en">Indian history</foreign>” is one of the most curious treatises transmitted to us from antiquity.”</p>
    <p>The latter may be considered an episode to the former. It is partly historical and partly geographical, and will be found to contain a fund of entertainment.</p>
  </div>
</div>
<div type="book" n="8">
  <div type="section" n="56">
    <p>On the model of the Socratic <persName>Xenophon</persName>, he committed to writing the dictates of <persName>Epictetus</persName>, during the philosopher’s lifetime, and published them as his dissertations:—</p>
    <p>[29] subsequently compiling his <foreign xml:lang="la">Enchiridion</foreign> or manual—a brief compendium of all the principles of his master, and acknowledged to be one of the most valuable and beautiful pieces of morality extant.</p>
    <p>His <foreign xml:lang="la">Periplus</foreign> of the <placeName>Euxine</placeName>, in the form of a letter from its author to the <persName>Emperor</persName>, contains an accurate topographical survey of the coast of that sea,</p>
  </div>
</div>
<div type="book" n="9">
  <div type="section" n="56">
    <p>from the commencement of his voyage at <placeName>Trapezus</placeName>, within his own prefecture of <placeName>Cappadocia</placeName>, to its completion at <placeName>Byzantium</placeName>; and was written probably while he held his office of command in the province, a short time before the breaking out of the 57 war against the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Alani</name>.</p>
    <p>Many learned men, as <persName>Ramusius</persName>, <persName>Ortelius</persName>, and others, have doubted whether he wrote the <foreign xml:lang="la">Periplus</foreign> of the <foreign xml:lang="en">Erythrean Sea</foreign>, which sometimes passes under his name; indeed the late Dean of Westminster says positively “it is not the work of <persName>Arrian</persName> of <placeName>Nicomedia</placeName>:” but his claim to the <foreign xml:lang="la">Circumnavigation</foreign> of the <foreign xml:lang="la">Euxine</foreign> has never been disputed.</p>
    <p>It was compiled expressly for the <persName>Emperor</persName>; who, according to <persName>Spartian</persName> and <persName>Dion Cassius</persName>, was particularly attached to geographical research, and had visited in person a large portion of his extensive <foreign xml:lang="la">Eutropii L. viii.</foreign> dominions—“<quote>orbem Romanorum circumivit.</quote>”</p>
    <p>The elder <persName>Xenophon</persName> is spoken of, sub initio, by our scientific geographer, in the same relative terms, as in the <foreign xml:lang="la">Cynegeticus</foreign>, <foreign xml:lang="grc">ὡς λέγει ὁ Ξενοφῶν ἐκεῖνος</foreign>, and it is fair to infer that the <foreign xml:lang="la">Periplus</foreign> and <foreign xml:lang="la">Cynegeticus</foreign> are the works of the same individual.</p>
  </div>
</div>
<div type="book" n="10">
   <div type="section" n="56">
      <p>In his <name type="work" xml:lang="en">Tactics</name>, written, as he states himself, in the 20th year of the reign of <persName>Hadrian</persName>, there is a brief account of former writers on this subject, and a description of the order and arrangement of an army in general: but in the <quote><name type="work" xml:lang="en">Acies contra Alanos</name></quote>, a short and imperfect fragment annexed thereto, the particular instructions,<foreign xml:lang="la">[30]</foreign> which were delivered by him as general, for the march of the Roman army against the northern barbarians, are minutely given.</p>
      <p>Fragments of other historical works, supposed to have been written by him, are preserved by the learned and indefatigable patriarch of <placeName>Constantinople</placeName>—<quote><name type="work" xml:lang="en">The History of Events subsequent to Alexander’s Death</name>, in 10 books</quote>, <quote><name type="work" xml:lang="en">The Parthica</name>, in 17 books</quote>, and <quote><name type="work" xml:lang="en">Bithynica</name>, in 8 books</quote>. Under the review of the first of which works, the Byzantine has left us his opinion<foreign xml:lang="la">58</foreign> of <persName>Arrian</persName> as an historiographer, and of the style of his compositions: <foreign xml:lang="grc">ἀνὴρ οὐδενὸς τῶν ἄριστα συνταξαμένων ἱστορίας δεύτερος</foreign>, κ. τ. λ.</p>
   </div>
</div>
<div type="book" n="11">
  <p>Of the Libellus de Venatione, the treatise on <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Coursing</name>, I have already made mention; and shall merely add, what is in some degree pertinent to the subject, that there seems to have been a strong similarity of taste between <persName>Hadrian</persName> and our author.</p>
  <p>The Emperor, like his prefect, was not only intimately conversant with <foreign xml:lang="la">Eutropii L. viii.</foreign> Greek and Latin literature, “<quote>facundissimus Latino sermone, Græco eruditissimus</quote>,” but also passionately fond of the chase.</p>
  <p>While living in his native town of <placeName>Italica</placeName> in <placeName>Spain</placeName>, <persName>Spartian</persName> tells us, he bore the title of <foreign xml:lang="la">Græculus</foreign>, and was, at the same time, “<quote>venandi usque ad reprehensionem studiosus—equos et <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">canes</name> sic amavit, ut eis sepulchra constitueret</quote>.”</p>
  <p>To such a height did he carry this regard, that, according to <persName>Xiphilin</persName>, he graced a monument to the memory of his beloved hunter <persName>Borysthenes</persName>, with an inscription written by his own pen:</p>
  <p>For all which unbounded affection for the brute creation, the reader may remember, <foreign xml:lang="la">De Remediis U. F. L. i . D. xxxii.</foreign> he incurs the severity of <persName>Petrarch</persName>’s satire in the dialogue “<quote>de Venatu et Aucupio</quote>.”</p>
</div>
<div type="book" n="12">
  <div type="section" n="56">
    <p>Whether the similarity of <persName>Arrian</persName>’s rural diversions to those of <persName>Hadrian</persName> in early life, co-operated with other causes to his elevation by so capricious and eccentric a patron, must ever remain doubtful. He is not mentioned by name in the biography of <persName>Hadrian</persName> by <persName>Spartian</persName>: where it is stated, in general terms only, of this singular Emperor, that he was on terms of familiar intimacy with <persName>Epictetus</persName>, <persName>Heliodorus</persName>, and all grammarians, rhetoricians, &amp;c. Of his acquaintance with the eminent men of his capital there can be no doubt, and his roving disposition</p>
    <p>59 must have introduced such to his notice in the colonies and more distant parts of the empire. One, therefore, who had been following the same pursuits with himself from his youth upwards, a sportsman, a military tactician, and a joint friend of <persName>Epictetus</persName>, was not likely to escape him. Besides, we are assured that he was, on all occasions, sociable in his field amusements, <quote>“venationem semper cum amicis participavit;”</quote> and therefore we may suppose that the literary founder of <placeName>Adrianotheræ</placeName> would gladly avail himself of the earliest opportunity of adding to his personal friends and sporting associates the most accomplished writer and courser of his day. We know how much the pleasure of intercourse is enhanced by identity of pursuit; and how strong the hold which innocent amusements, shared with congenial friends, have on our affections!</p>
  </div>
</div>
<div type="chapter" n="1">
   <p>As to the period of his life at which <persName>Arrian</persName> may be supposed to have written the <foreign xml:lang="la">Cynegeticus</foreign>, the inference to be drawn from the meagre paragraph of autobiography in the first chapter, wherein he states his fitness to supply the deficiencies of the elder <persName>Xenophon</persName>’s work, <quote>De Venat. c. i.</quote> from having been <foreign xml:lang="grc">ἀμφὶ ταὐτὰ ἀπὸ νέου ἐσπουδακὼς, κυνηγέσια καὶ στρατηγίαν καὶ σοφίαν</foreign>, although it establishes the fact of his early predilection for field sports, yet it rather militates against the idea of the <foreign xml:lang="la">Cynegeticus</foreign> having been written at a very early period of the author’s life.</p>
   <p>However, be this as it may, his patronage of “ the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">long dogs</name> ” continued at the time of his writing this libellus; and his beloved <foreign xml:lang="grc">Εἰς ἐκεῖνον</foreign> <foreign xml:lang="grc">Ὁρμὴ, ὠκυτάτη, καὶ σοφωτάτη, καὶ ἱεροτάτη</foreign>, was then in his possession, living seemingly in the closest intimacy with his attached and philosophic master, and sharing with <persName>Megillus</persName> his society at home and abroad, the well-earned recompense in declining years of the excellence he had manifested in the vigour of his youthful days on the coursing plain; where, in <persName>Arrian</persName>’s own words of eulogy, <foreign xml:lang="grc">τέτταρσιν ἤδη ποτὲ λαγωοῖς ἐφ’ ἡλικίας ἀντήρκησεν.</foreign></p>
</div>
<div type="book" n="1">
   <p>Antiquity is almost silent relative to the personal history of the younger <persName>Xenophon</persName>;⁠ <pb n="32"/> and as an autobiographer, he seems to have been desirous that nothing should be known of himself or family; but rather that his personal history should be darkened under the doubtful celebrity of anonymous authorship, or merged in the somewhat arrogant assumption of a fictitious and equivocal title.</p>
   <p>In the conclusion of the 12th chapter of the 1st book of his History of <foreign xml:lang="la">Alexander</foreign>’s <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Anabasis</name>, he says that the number and magnitude of the exploits of the son of <persName>Philip</persName>, were his inducement to record them, not deeming himself altogether unworthy to transmit them to posterity.</p>
   <p><persName>Arrian</persName>. <foreign xml:lang="la">de Exped. Alexand.</foreign> L. i. c. xii. <quote>Vide Raphelii annotat. in loc.</quote> “But who I am,” he continues, “that thus characterise myself, and what my name, (though far from obscure,) it concerns the reader but little to know. Neither would an account of my family, my city, nor such offices as I have there borne, be of any use to him. Be it sufficient for him to know, that an ardent love of literature, in which I have constantly indulged myself from youth, has been with me instead of family connexion, and civic and magisterial honours. Wherefore I may perhaps be little less worthy of a place among the most celebrated authors of <foreign xml:lang="grc">Γραικός</foreign>, than <persName>Alexander</persName> among her most illustrious heroes.”</p>
</div>
<div type="book" n="15">
   <div type="chapter" n="56">
      <p>After the brief sketch which I have given of the writings of the younger <persName>Xenophon</persName>, it must strike every one that he was influenced in the choice of his subjects as an author, by a recollection of what had engaged the literary attention of his celebrated namesake; and that while writing under the same personal appellative, he probably proposed to imitate the matter and style of composition of his <quote>Phot. Eclog. Arrian. Parthica.</quote> prototype—<foreign xml:lang="grc">ἰσχνὸς τὴν φράσιν, καὶ μιμητὴς ὡς ἀληθῶς Ξενοφῶντος.</foreign></p>
      <p>Under this view of his works we have the dissertations of <persName>Epictetus</persName> from the pen of his most renowned follower, the <placeName>Bithynian</placeName> <persName>Xenophon</persName>, and the <name type="work">Memorabilia</name> of <persName>Socrates</persName> from that of the son of <persName>Gryllus</persName>, the most eminent disciple of the <name type="deity">Socratic</name> school: the <name type="work">Anabasis</name> of <persName>Alexander</persName> for that of <persName>Cyrus</persName>, with the same distribution of the work into seven books, and the same title. The <name type="work">Hellenica</name> of <persName>Xenophon</persName> gave birth to the <name type="work">Parthica</name> and <name type="work">Bithynica</name> of <persName>Arrian</persName>: and in imitation of the <name type="work">Essay on Hunting</name>, our <persName>pseudo-Xenophon</persName> has left us his <name type="work">Observations on Coursing</name>.</p>
   </div>
</div>
<div type="section" n="16">
   <p>Upon their general similarity of character in active life I have already remarked, and shall only observe farther, that, as far as we can judge from the scanty personal anecdotes which have survived of the younger, for comparison with those of the elder philosopher, this similarity appears to have extended to the frame and composition of their minds. Many of the same excellencies, and respectable weaknesses of character, co-existed in both; the same patient and unerring virtue—the same kind and generous feeling—the same credulous and enthusiastic regard to celestial admonitions—<foreign xml:lang="grc">πειθομένους τεράεσσι θεῶν</foreign>—with a proportionate degree of the purest heathen piety.</p>
</div>
<div type="chapter" n="17">
   <p>If it be stigmatised with the title of superstitious credulity in the priest of <persName>Ceres</persName>, that he supposed himself led by divine inspiration to write the history of a man, <quote>De Expedit. Alexandri L. vii. c. xxx. <foreign xml:lang="grc">οὐδενὶ ἄλλῳ ἀνθρώπων ἐοικὼς</foreign></quote>, I would plead his enthusiastic admiration of his hero in palliation of the fond supposition, qualified as it is, with equal good sense and piety, in the concluding sentences of the <name type="book">Anabasis</name>; where he states that as so extraordinary a person as <persName>Alexander</persName> could not have risen up in the world without divine interference—<foreign xml:lang="grc">οὐδ’ ἔξω τοῦ θείου</foreign>; so, with admiration of his good qualities, and reprobation of his bad ones, with a strict regard to truth, and public utility, he professes himself his historian, writing, as he verily believes, under the same divine influence that first gave being to the subject of his memoir.</p>
   <p>Surely such a belief in heavenly interference, exciting its professor to what is just and honourable, and deterring him from every breach of propriety, as an historian of truth, must be applauded by every fair and impartial judge of human character; and more particularly so, when in the person of a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Stoic</name>, unenlightened by any philosophy but that of <persName>Epictetus</persName>, it could have no other foundation than innate rectitude of mind.</p>
</div>
<div type="chapter" n="18">
   <p>Under the conviction that Arrian’s expectation of posthumous fame has been realized in general, and that my brethren of the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">leash</name> will award him particular honour as the first writer of a Courser’s Manual, I conclude this brief sketch of his life and literary labours; which might have been more full, if his biography by <persName>Dion Cassius</persName> had come down to us.</p>
   <p>As the compiler of the Stoical philosophy of “the <foreign xml:lang="la">Phrygian Slave</foreign>,” the historian of the son of <persName>Philip</persName>,<pb n="33"/> the hydrographer of the <placeName>Euxine</placeName>, a military tactician, a warrior-prefect, and a classic <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">courser</name>, he has left works behind him which will endure as long as literature itself;—he has done all in his power to benefit and instruct mankind in various departments of human learning;—has contributed his mite to the advancement of rational science and healthful recreation, and proved himself worthy of the immortality he so fondly anticipated.</p>
   <p><quote><foreign xml:lang="grc">Οὐ γάρ τοι οὐδ’ ἴσος ὁ ἀγὼν λαγωῷ καὶ κυνί· ἀλλ’ ὁ μὲν, ὅποι βούλεται, θεῖ, ἡ δὲ ἄλλῳ ἐφομαρτεῖ· καὶ ὁ μὲν ἐξελίξας τὸν δρόμον καὶ διαῤῥίψας τὴν κύνα ἴεται τοῦ πρόσω, ἡ δὲ, εἰ διαῤῥιφθείη, πλάζεται· καὶ ἀνάγκη φθάσαντα αὖ μεταθεῖν καὶ ἀναλαβεῖν, ὅσον ἐξηνέχθη τοῦ δρόμου.</foreign> — <persName>Arrian</persName>. <foreign xml:lang="la">de Venat.</foreign> c. xvii.</quote></p>
   <div type="section" n="1">
      <p>Preface. The advantages that accrue to mankind from hunting, and the regard of the <name type="deity">Gods</name> for those instructed in it by <persName>Chiron</persName>,<pb n="34"/> and their honourable distinction throughout <placeName>Greece</placeName>, have been related by <persName>Xenophon</persName>, the son of <persName>Gryllus</persName>.</p>
   </div>
</div>
<div type="section" n="19">
   <p>He has pointed out the similitude between <foreign xml:lang="grc">Κυνηγετικά</foreign> and Military science;⁠ <note n="35">[35]</note> and the age, constitution, and frame of mind,⁠ <note n="36">[36]</note> that essentially qualify for entering on the chase;—has given a description of purse-nets, hayes, and road-nets,⁠ <note n="37">[37]</note> such as are necessary to be prepared—the mode of fixing snares for <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">animals</name> that may be entrapped⁠ <note n="38">[38]</note> —the natural history of <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">hares</name>, their food, haunts, forms, and the method of searching for them—what <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">dogs</name> are clever at scenting, and what faulty—and how, by their shape and work, each may be ascertained. Some few remarks are also left by him on the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">boar</name>-hunt, the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">stag</name>, <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">bear</name>, and <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">lion</name> chases—how these <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">animals</name> may be taken by cunning and stratagem.</p>
   <p>The omissions of his work (which do not appear to me to have arisen from negligence, but from ignorance of the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Celtic</name> breed of <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">dogs</name>,⁠ <note n="39">[39]</note> and the <placeName>Scythian</placeName> and <placeName>African</placeName> <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">horses</name>,) I shall <pb n="69"/> endeavour to fill up: being his namesake and fellow-citizen,⁠ <note n="40">[40]</note> of similar pursuits with himself, as a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">sportsman</name>, a <persName>general</persName>, and a <persName>philosopher</persName>—writing under the same feeling that actuated him, when he thought fit to amend the imperfections of <persName>Simon</persName>’s work on horsemanship;⁠ <note n="41">[41]</note> not out of rivalry with its author, but from a conviction that his labours would be useful to mankind.</p>
</div>
<div type="chapter" n="2">
   <p>In my opinion no proof is required that <persName>Xenophon</persName> was ignorant of the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Celtic</name> breed of <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">dogs</name>, beyond this: <quote>[42] Proofs of <persName>Xenophon</persName>’s ignorance of <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Celtic</name> <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Dogs</name>.</quote></p>
   <p>that the nations inhabiting that district of <placeName>Europe</placeName> were unknown, <quote>[43] 70 except the parts of <placeName>Italy</placeName> occupied by the <name type="deity">Greeks</name>,</quote> and those with whom they had commercial intercourse by sea. And <quote>[44] and those with whom they had commercial intercourse by sea.</quote> And <quote>[45] 71</quote> that he was unacquainted with any other breed of <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">dogs</name>, resembling the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Celtic</name> in point of swiftness, is evident from these words:—</p>
   <p>“whatever <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">hares</name>,” he says, “are caught by <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">dogs</name>, become their prey, contrary to the natural shape of the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">animal</name>, or accidentally.”</p>
   <p>Now, if he had been acquainted with the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Celtic</name> breed, I think he would have made the very same remark on the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">dogs</name>; “whatever <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">hares</name> the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">dogs</name> do not catch at speed, they fail of catching in contradiction of their shape, or from some accidental circumstance.” For assuredly when <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">greyhounds</name> are in good condition, and of high courage, no <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">hare</name> can escape them; unless the country present some obstacles, either a covert to conceal her, or a hollow deep pit to break off the course, or a ditch to favour her escape while out of sight of the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">dogs</name>.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="21">
   <p>To this ignorance, in my opinion, is to be attributed the length of his instructions on driving the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">hare</name> into nets,⁠ <quote>[46]</quote> and if she pass them,⁠ <quote>[47]</quote> pursuing and recovering her by scent, till she be taken, at last, completely tired out. But he has no where said either that fleet <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">dogs</name> altogether supersede the necessity of a <persName>sportsman</persName> having nets,⁠ <quote>[48]</quote> or of his hunting by scent after the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">hare</name> has escaped them. Indeed he has described only the mode of hunting which is practised by the <placeName>Carians</placeName> and <placeName>Cretans</placeName>.⁠ <quote>[49]</quote></p>
   <p>But such of the <placeName>Celts</placeName> as hunt for the beauty of the sport, and not as a means of livelihood, never make use of nets. And yet they have a variety of <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">dog</name> not less clever at hunting on scent than the <placeName>Carian</placeName> and <placeName>Cretan</placeName>,⁠ <quote>[50]</quote> but in shape sorry brutes.⁠ <quote>[51]</quote> In pursuit these give tongue with a clanging howl like the yelping <placeName>Carians</placeName>, but are more eager, when they catch the scent.⁠ <quote>[52]</quote> Sometimes, indeed, they gladden so outrageously, even on a stale trail, that I have rated them for their excessive barking,—alike Their Qualities. on every scent, whether it be of the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">hare</name> going to form, or at speed.⁠ <quote>[53]</quote> In pursuing and recovering her, when 74 started, they are not inferior to the <placeName>Carians</placeName> or <placeName>Cretans</placeName>, save in the one point of speed.</p>
   <p>It is good sport, if they kill but a single <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">hare</name> in the winter season, so much resting-time do they give her in the chase; unless, indeed, by being frightened out of her wits at the tumultuous uproar of the pack, she become an easy prey.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="22">
   <p>These dogs are called <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Segusians</name>,⁠ <pb n="54"/> deriving their name from a Celtic people, amongst whom, I suppose, they were first bred, and held in repute. But⁠ <pb n="55"/> all that can be said about them has been anticipated by the elder <persName>Xenophon</persName>. For they manifest nothing different from others in their mode of finding, or hunting their game;—having no peculiarity, unless one were inclined to speak of their shape, Shape, &amp;c. which I scarce think worth while, except merely to say, that they are shaggy and ugly; and such as are most high-bred are most unsightly. So that the comparison of them to mendicants on the highways is popular with the Celts. For their voice is dolorous and pitiful; and they do not bark on scent of their game, as if eager and savage, but as if plaintively whining after it.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="23">
   <p>About these, then, I do not think any thing memorable can be written. But the swift-footed <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Celtic hounds</name> are called in the <foreign xml:lang="la">Celtic</foreign> tongue <foreign xml:lang="la">Vertragi</foreign>. <foreign xml:lang="grc">οὐέρτραγοι</foreign>;⁠ <quote>[56]</quote> —not deriving their name from any particular nation, like the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Cretan</name>, <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Carian</name>, or <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Spartan</name> <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">dogs</name>: <quote>[57]</quote> but, as some of the <placeName>Cretans</placeName> are named <foreign xml:lang="grc">διάπονοι</foreign>⁠ <quote>[58]</quote> from working hard, <foreign xml:lang="grc">ἰταμαὶ</foreign> from their keenness, and mongrels from their being compounded of both; so these <placeName>Celts</placeName> are named from their swiftness.</p>
   <p>Their Beauty. In figure, the most high-bred are a prodigy of beauty;⁠ <quote>[59]</quote> —their eyes, their hair, their colour, and bodily shape throughout. Such brilliancy of gloss is there about the spottiness of the parti-coloured, and in those of uniform colour such glistening over the sameness of tint, as to afford a most delightful spectacle to an amateur of coursing.</p>
</div>
<div type="chapter" n="IV">
   <p>I will specify the indications of speed and good breeding in <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">greyhounds</name>,⁠ <quote>[60]</quote> Marks of Speed and good Blood. and by attention to what points ill-bred and slow ones may be distinguished from them.</p>
   <quote>[61]</quote>
</div>
<div type="chapter" n="24">
   <p>In the first place, let them be lengthy from head to tail; <note n="62">76</note> for in every variety of <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">dog</name>, you will find, on reflection, no one point so indicative of speed and good breeding as length; and on the other hand, no such mark of slowness and degeneracy as shortness. So that I have even seen <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">dogs</name> with numerous other faults, that have been, on account of their length, both swift and high-couraged.</p>
   <p>And farther, the larger <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">dogs</name>, <note n="63">when in other respects equal</note>, show higher breeding than small ones on the very score of size. But those large <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">dogs</name> are bad, whose limbs are unknit, and destitute of symmetry; <note n="64">being indeed, when so formed, worse than small <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">dogs</name>, with an equal share of other faults attached to them</note>.</p>
   <p>Your <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">greyhounds</name> should have light and well-articulated heads; <note n="65">whether hooked <note n="66">or flat nosed</note> is not of much consequence</note>: <note n="67">77</note> nor does it greatly matter whether the parts beneath the forehead be protuberant with muscle. They are alone bad which are heavy-headed, having thick nostrils, with a blunt instead of a pointed termination.</p>
   <p>Such then are well-headed hounds. Their eyes should be large, up-raised, clear, strikingly bright. The best look fiery, and flash like lightning, resembling those of <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">leopards</name>, <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">lions</name>, or <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">lynxes</name>. <note n="68">78</note> Next to these are black eyes, provided they are wide-open and grim-looking; and last of all, grey: <note n="69">nor are these to be considered bad, nor indicative of bad <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">dogs</name>, provided they are clear, and have a savage look</note>.</p>
</div>
<div type="chapter" n="5">
   <p>For I have myself bred up a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">hound</name> whose eyes are the greyest of the grey; a swift, hard-working, courageous, sound-footed <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">dog</name>, and, in his prime, a match, at any time, for four <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">hares</name>. He is, moreover, (for while I am writing, he is yet alive), most gentle, and kindly-affectioned; and never before had any <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">dog</name> such regard for myself, and friend and fellow-sportsman, <persName>Megillus</persName>.</p>
   <p>For when not actually engaged in coursing, he is never away from one or other of us. But while I am at home he remains within, by my side, accompanies me on going abroad, follows me to the gymnasium, and, while I am taking exercise, sits down by me. On my return he runs before me, often looking back to see whether I had turned any where out of the road; and as soon as he catches sight of me, showing symptoms of joy, and again trotting on before me.</p>
   <p>If I am going out on any government business, he remains with my friend, and does exactly the same towards him. He is the constant companion of whichever may be sick; and if he has not seen either of us for only a short time, he jumps up repeatedly by way of salutation, and barks with joy, as a greeting to us.</p>
   <p>At meals he pats us first with one foot and then with the other, to put us in mind that he is to have his share of food. He has also many tones of speech —more than I ever knew in any other <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">dog</name>—pointing out, in his own language, whatever he wants.</p>
</div>
<div type="chapter" n="26">
   <p>Having been beaten, when a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">puppy</name>, with a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">whip</name>, if any one, even at this day, does but mention a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">whip</name>, he will come up to the speaker cowering and begging,⁠ <pb n="80"/> applying his mouth to the man’s as if to kiss him, and jumping up, will hang on his neck, and not let him go until he has appeased his angry threats.</p>
   <p>Now really I do not think that I should be ashamed to write even the name of this <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">dog</name>; that it may be left to posterity, that <persName>Xenophon</persName> the <placeName>Athenian</placeName> had a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">greyhound</name> called <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Hormē</name>, of the greatest speed and intelligence,⁠ <pb n="82"/> and altogether supremely excellent.⁠ <pb n="83"/></p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="27">
   <p>Let the ears of your <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">greyhounds</name> be large and soft,⁠ <pb n="84"/> so as to appear, from their size and softness, as if broken. Such are best: but it is no bad indication if they appear erect, provided they are not small and stiff.⁠ <pb n="85"/></p>
   <p>The neck should be long, round, and flexible;⁠ so that if you forcibly draw the dogs backwards by their collars, it may seem to be broken, from its flexibility and softness. Broad chests are better than narrow. Let them have shoulders standing wide-apart,⁠ not tied together, but as loose, and free from each other, as possible—legs round, straight, and well-jointed—sides strong—loins broad, firm, not fleshy, but sinewy—upper flanks loose and supple⁠ —hips wide asunder—lower flanks hollow—tails fine, long, rough with hair, supple, flexible, and more hairy towards the tip—haunches sweeping, and firm to the touch:⁠ with regard to their legs, if the hind ones are longer than the fore, the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">greyhound</name> will run best up hill; if the fore legs are longest, down hill; but if both are equal, he will run best on a flat.⁠ Since, however, it is more difficult to beat a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">hare</name> on an acclivity, because she runs best up hill, those are deemed the better class of dogs, whose hind legs are longer than their fore ones.⁠ Round and strong feet are decidedly best.⁠ <pb n="92"/></p>
</div>
<div type="chapter" n="6">
   <p>The colour of <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">greyhounds</name> is not of any importance; nor does it matter if they are perfectly black, red, or white; nor is a simple, uniform colour to be suspected as ferine. The colours, such as they are, should be bright and pure; and the hair, whether the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">dog</name> be of the rough or smooth sort, should be fine, close, and soft.</p>
   <p>The best <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">dogs</name> are such as are large and well put together, and resemble <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">bitches</name> in point of suppleness; and the best <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">bitches</name> are such as resemble <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">dogs</name> in spirit, and muscularity of body.</p>
   <p>Now if any one pays attention to these hints, as to the shape of <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">greyhounds</name>, they will fully supply him, in my opinion, with the indications of good blood for his kennel, and the opposite of the reverse.</p>
</div>
<div type="chapter" n="7">
   <p>Nor will the temper of <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">greyhounds</name> afford fewer indications of good and bad blood to a careful observer.</p>
   <p>Such <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">hounds</name>, in the first place, as are crabbed to all persons alike, are not of a generous breed. But if you find any cross to strangers, and good-tempered to their feeder, it is rather a favourable sign than otherwise.</p>
   <p>I once knew a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">greyhound</name>, who was dull and sullen at home, and took no pleasure in any of the persons about him; but, when led out hunting, was beyond measure delighted, and showed, by smiling and fawning at every body that came near him, that he was vexed at staying at home. This may be held a good sign.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="29">
   <p>The best <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">dogs</name>, however, are those of most attachment to man, and to whom no human countenance is strange.⁠ <pb n="98"/></p>
   <p>Such, on the other hand, as are afraid of people, and astounded at noise,⁠ <pb n="99"/> obstreperous, and often excited without cause, are senseless brutes of no pluck. Like men that are timid and frightened out of their wits, such <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">dogs</name> as these can never be deemed of generous blood.</p>
   <p>From obedience in the field. Those, too, are bad, which, when let loose from couples in a field, do not come back at the call of their keeper, but gallop away.⁠ <pb n="100"/></p>
   <p>If you call them in mildly, they pay no attention to you;—if threateningly, they keep aloof from fear.</p>
   <p>For when a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">greyhound</name> has had his gallop, and has run about, he ought to come back to his keeper, even without a call,⁠ <pb n="90"/></p>
   <p>—showing that he is under command at will; but, if the keeper does not choose to take him up, let him again bound away, and again return. Such <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">dogs</name> are well broken in as, at the voice of their keeper, crouch before him;⁠ <pb n="91"/></p>
   <p>not from fear, but regard and respect for their feeder, cowering like the worshippers⁠ <pb n="91"/> of the <name type="deity">Great King</name>.⁠ <pb n="91"/></p>
   <p>It is no good sign for a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">hound</name> to stand still, when let out of couples on an open plain, unless he happen to be advanced in age,⁠ <pb n="91"/> for it shows sluggishness.</p>
</div>
<div type="chapter" n="VIII">
   <p>The most high-bred <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">greyhounds</name> have a prominent brow, and look proud.⁠ <pb n="106"/></p>
   <p>Their tread is light, quick-stepping, on their toes; and they walk sideways,⁠ <pb n="107"/> extending their necks like horses curvetting.⁠ <pb n="108"/></p>
   <p>Some <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">greyhounds</name> eat voraciously, others with delicacy.⁠ <pb n="109"/></p>
   <p>The latter from their mode of feeding. mode of feeding indicates a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">dog</name> of better blood than the former.⁠ <pb n="110"/></p>
   <p>Good <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">dogs</name> are not bad feeders, but fond of bread or gruel.⁠ <pb n="111"/></p>
   <p>This kind of farinaceous food is most strengthening to them, and there is no fear of their gorging themselves too much with it. I prefer, however, their liking food quite dry;⁠ <pb n="112"/></p>
   <p>and yet, if it be moistened with water, and they still relish it, it is no evil.</p>
   <p>When a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">dog</name> is sick, administer the broth of fat meat to him, or having roasted a bullock’s liver over some hot coals, and rubbed it abroad, sprinkle it like flour into the broth.⁠ <pb n="113"/></p>
   <p>This is good also for puppies to strengthen their limbs, when they are first weaned from milk.⁠ <pb n="114"/></p>
   <p>But milk is the best food for the support of puppies till the ninth month, and even longer; and is serviceable to the sick and delicate, both as drink and aliment. Fasting too is beneficial to a sick <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">dog</name>.⁠ <pb n="115"/></p>
</div>
<div type="chapter" n="9">
   <p>There is nothing like a soft and warm bed for <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">greyhounds</name>; but it is best for them to sleep with Management of the <foreign xml:lang="la">Kennel</foreign>. men:—as they become thereby affectionately attached—pleased with the Bedding. contact of the human body, and as fond of their bedfellow as of their feeder.⁠ <pb n="116"/></p>
   <p>If any ailing affect the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">dog</name>, the man will perceive it, and will relieve him in the night, when thirsty, or urged by any call of nature. He will also know how the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">dog</name> has rested. For if <pb n="95"/> he has passed a sleepless night,⁠ <pb n="117"/> or groaned frequently in his sleep,⁠ <pb n="118"/> or thrown up any of his food,⁠ <pb n="119"/> it will not be safe to take him out coursing. All these things the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">dog</name>’s bedfellow will be acquainted with.</p>
   <p>Nothing can be worse than for <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">dogs</name> to sleep with each other; and more especially so, if they touch one another in bed. For as all cutaneous irritation is removed by a man sleeping with them, so, when they sleep together, they generate every sort of foulness of skin by warmth and close contact, and are generally full of mange.⁠ <pb n="96"/></p>
   <p>To which cause must be referred the very offensive and pungent stench on entering a <foreign xml:lang="la">kennel</foreign> where many <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">hounds</name> are confined together.</p>
</div>
<div type="chapter" n="10">
   <p>Rubbing the whole body Rubbing down. is of great service to the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">greyhound</name>;⁠ <pb n="121"/> no less than to the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">horse</name>.⁠ <pb n="122"/> For it is conducive to the firmness and strength of his limbs—renders his hair soft, and skin shining,⁠ <pb n="123"/> and cleanses it from all foulness.</p>
</div>
<div type="chapter" n="11">
   <p>The back and loins you should rub with your right hand, placing your left under the belly; lest the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">dog</name>, being forcibly pressed down upon his knees, should suffer injury. The sides should be rubbed with both hands at once, and the haunches quite down to the feet, and the shoulders in the same way. When the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">dog</name> seems to have had enough of it, lay hold of his tail, and lift him up by it; and then having drawn it through your hand, let him go. As soon as he is at liberty, he will shake himself, and show that he is pleased with the operation.</p>
   <p>It is a point of equal importance with any other, that <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">greyhounds</name> be Kennelling confined during the day; otherwise they will unavoidably become intractable, and, whenever fastened with a collar, will be impatient under the restraint, and whine, and gnaw the straps, so as even to require chains like malefactors. Besides, a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">hound</name> that is at liberty must needs eat every thing that falls in his way; and, from running about during the day-time, lose the acme of his speed. But, though generally at rest, they should still have their appointed times for walking out.</p>
</div>
<div type="chapter" n="12">
   <p>Four times a day, at least, take your <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">dogs</name> out of kennel to a level and open field, Exercising. and there loose them from couples, to empty themselves, gallop, and run about.<pb n="126"/></p>
   <p>But if they have quite ceased coursing, let it be done more frequently. Slip them in pairs, a brace at a time, so that by contending and playing with each other, they may enjoy their pleasure, and take their exercise together. But on no account let many loose at once, as they sometimes do great mischief by falling on each other.<pb n="100"/></p>
   <p>Never slip a strong and full-grown <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">dog</name> with a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">puppy</name>; for the old <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">dog</name> is an overpowering and distressing antagonist for the youngster, easily overtaking him in pursuit, and as readily running away from him, and leaving him behind; whereby the pup must of course be cowed and dispirited, having in either case the worst of the contest. And farther, such as are spiteful towards each other, never give these their liberty at one and the same time, lest they injure one another. For there are <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">dogs</name>, as well as men, with mutual antipathies, and others again with mutual attachments.</p>
   <p>Those of the same sex are particularly inimical to each other, <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">dogs</name> to <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">dogs</name>, and <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">bitches</name> to <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">bitches</name>; and this generally from spiteful jealousy. These matters are not to be made light of.</p>
</div>
<div type="chapter" n="13">
   <p>In the winter season feed your <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">dogs</name> only once a day,⁠ <pb n="129"/> a little before evening; Feeding in winter and summer.</p>
   <p>for the days are short, and the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">greyhounds</name> are to be so managed, that if you need their services for coursing till a late hour, they may be able to bear the necessary fasting.</p>
   <p>But in summer it is right to give them a little <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">bread</name> in addition,⁠ <pb n="130"/> that they may not be exhausted by the length of the day; and if thirsty, they will drink with less detriment after having eaten.</p>
   <p>To thrust down a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">dog</name>’s throat a piece of salted suet is also found beneficial.⁠ <pb n="131"/></p>
   <p>But if <foreign xml:lang="la">102</foreign> the weather be very hot, I would have you take an <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">egg</name> in your hand, open your <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">dog</name>’s mouth, and push it down, that he may swallow it at one gulp.</p>
   <p>This will be nourishment enough for him, will cherish his wind, and quench his thirst.⁠ <pb n="132"/></p>
</div>
<div type="chapter" n="14">
   <p>Seasons of Coursing. You may go out coursing frequently in spring and autumn,<pb n="133"/> these seasons being attended with the least risk to your <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">dogs</name>—but rarely in summer,<pb n="134"/> lying by, generally,<pb n="135"/> when the heat is oppressive.</p>
   <p>For <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">greyhounds</name> are impatient of heat, and often, when pursuing a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">hare</name> with all their might, have been suffocated from a stoppage of their wind.<pb n="136"/></p>
   <p>To guard against which, a courser should carry <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">eggs</name> with him, and administer them entire, if his <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">hound</name>’s breathing be exceedingly distressed. For there is no better refrigerative, nothing that appeases difficulty of breathing so much. It is not unattended with danger for a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">dog</name>, under these circumstances of distress, to drink immoderately.</p>
   <p>For the reasons given, then, be cautious of coursing in hot weather. Never go out in winter when the cold is severe, and, on no account, when the ground is frozen hard. For <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">dogs</name><pb n="104"/> bruise themselves in frost,<pb n="137"/> lose their nails,<pb n="138"/> lacerate the soles of their feet, and if very high-couraged, break even the bones of their toes against the frozen ground from running with excessive eagerness. Whereas the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">hare</name> is light, with woolly and soft feet,<pb n="139"/> and trips along without injury in frost.</p>
</div>
<div type="chapter" n="15">
   <p>Whoever courses with <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">greyhounds</name> should neither slip them near the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">hare</name>, nor more than a brace at a time; for though the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">hare</name> be remarkably swift-footed, and have often beaten many <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">dogs</name>, yet being just started from her form, she cannot but be fluttered at heart, and terrified at the hallooing, and the hounds pressing close upon her:—and in this way, many a noble <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">hare</name> has often ignobly perished without an effort, showing no diversion worth mentioning.</p>
   <p>Let the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">hare</name>, therefore, creep away from her form as if unperceived, and recover her presence of mind. And then, if she be a racer, she will prick up her ears, and bound away from her seat with long strides; and the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">greyhounds</name>, having capered about as if they were dancing, will stretch out at full speed after her. And at this time is the spectacle worthy indeed of the pains that must necessarily be bestowed on these <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">dogs</name>.</p>
</div>
<div type="chapter" n="16">
   <p>Those are the strongest <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">hares</name> which have their forms in open and exposed places; for, from boldness, they do not conceal themselves, but seem to me to challenge the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">dogs</name>. When coursed, they do not fly to the woods or groves, however near, for immediate liberation from danger, but stretch away to the open country; and during the contest, if they are pursued by slow <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">hounds</name>, they moderate their own speed according as they are pressed; but if their pursuers are fast, they run with all their might.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="37">
   <p>Often when they have turned aside to the champaign country, if they perceive a fleet <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">dog</name> following so close as to overshadow them, they throw him off by frequent ricks and turns, and again make for the woods, or wherever they know of a place of refuge; and this should be deemed a proof that the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">dog</name> has beaten the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">hare</name>.</p>
   <p>For <foreign xml:lang="en">coursers</foreign>, such at least as are true sportsmen, do not take their <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">dogs</name> out for the sake of catching a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">hare</name>, but for the contest and sport of coursing;⁠ <pb n="149"/> 109 and are glad if the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">hare</name> meet with an escape: if she fly to any thin brake for concealment, though they may see her trembling and in the utmost distress, they will call off their <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">dogs</name>,⁠ <pb n="150"/> and more particularly so, when they have run well.⁠ <pb n="151"/></p>
   <p>Often, indeed, when following a course on horseback, have I come up to the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">hare</name> as soon as caught, and myself saved her alive: and then, having taken away my <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">dog</name>, and fastened him up, allowed her to escape.⁠ <pb n="152"/></p>
   <p>And if I have arrived too late to save her, I have struck my head with sorrow, that the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">dogs</name> had killed so good an antagonist.⁠ <pb n="153"/></p>
</div>
<div type="chapter" n="17">
   <p>On this point alone I cannot agree with my namesake. I allow indeed that a man may forget every other object of which he is enamoured, when he sees a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">hare</name> found, and pursued at speed;⁠ <pb n="154"/> but to see her taken is, I own, neither a pleasant nor striking spectacle; but disagreeable rather, and not at all likely to make us forgetful of other objects of attachment.⁠ <pb n="155"/></p>
   <p>And yet we must not blame <persName>Xenophon</persName>, considering he was ignorant of <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">greyhounds</name>, if even the capture of a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">hare</name> appeared to him a grand sight.</p>
   <p>I am aware, (even if my instructions were opposed to it), how strong the inducement is to halloo, when following a course, and that even a dumb man might break forth, as is related of the son of <persName><foreign xml:lang="la">Crœsus</foreign></persName>.⁠ <pb n="156"/></p>
   <p>Chap. XVII. Cheering <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">greyhounds</name>. It is proper sometimes to speak to the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">greyhounds</name>; for they are pleased at hearing their master’s voice,⁠ <pb n="112"/> and have the consciousness of his presence, and of their brilliant running not escaping his notice, as an encouragement and reward for their exertions.</p>
</div>
<div type="chapter" n="39">
   <p>There is no objection to your cheering your <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">hound</name> as often as you like in his first course; but in his second or third, when it is probable that he is fagged, I think it wrong to cheer him very often by name, lest from his ardour, and desire of pleasing his master, he exert himself beyond his strength, and suffer some inward rupture; an accident which has been fatal to many a high-bred <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">greyhound</name>.</p>
   <p>But he should be allowed to slacken his running as he chooses. For the contest is by no means equal between the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">hare</name> and <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">greyhound</name>: <foreign xml:lang="la">[158]</foreign> the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">hare</name> runs 113 where she likes, and the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">dog</name> pursues; she shifts her course, <foreign xml:lang="la">[159]</foreign> throws him off, and darts forward; and if thrown out, the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">dog</name> is wide of the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">hare</name>, and must again stretch away after her a-head, and recover what he has lost of the course by overshooting himself. <foreign xml:lang="la">[160]</foreign></p>
   <p>Moreover, the natural difficulties of the country are more in favour of the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">hare</name>, than the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">dog</name>—such as rough and stony <foreign xml:lang="la">115</foreign> grounds, <foreign xml:lang="la">[161]</foreign> steeps and inequalities of surface—both because she is light, and because her feet, from their woolliness, are not liable to be lacerated by the roughness of the ground; <foreign xml:lang="la">[162]</foreign> and <foreign xml:lang="la">116</foreign> the running for her life, too, takes away all sense of difficulties.</p>
</div>
<div type="chapter" n="18">
   <p>When the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">greyhound</name> has caught the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">hare</name>, or been otherwise victorious in the course, <pb n="163"/> you should dismount from your <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">horse</name>, pat him with your hand and praise him, kissing his head, and stroking his ears, and speaking to him by name—“Well done, <persName>Cirras</persName>!”—“Well done, <persName>Bonnas</persName>!”—“Bravo, my <persName>Hormé</persName>!”—calling each <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">hound</name> by his name; for, like men of generous spirit, they love to be praised: <pb n="164"/> and the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">dog</name>, if not quite tired out, will come up with joy to caress you. At this time, it is a good sign for him to roll himself on the ground, as we see <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">horses</name> do; <pb n="165"/> for it shows that he is not done up with the course, and, at the same time, rolling refreshes him.</p>
</div>
<div type="chapter" n="19">
   <p><pb n="169"/> Celtic mode of coursing with hare-finders. The more opulent <placeName>Celts</placeName>, who live in luxury, course in the following manner. They send out <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">hare</name>-finders <pb n="170"/> early in the morning to look over such places as are likely to afford <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">hares</name> in form; and a messenger brings word if they have found any, and what number. They then go out themselves, and having started the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">hare</name>, slip the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">dogs</name> after her, and follow on <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">horseback</name>.</p>
</div>
<div type="chapter" n="20">
   <p>Without <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">hare</name>-finders. But others, who have no <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">hare</name>-finders, go out on horseback, collecting a large party of fellow-sportsmen together; and coming to likely lying-ground, when a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">hare</name> is started, they slip their <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">dogs</name>. While others again, who are more of workmen at the sport, sally forth on foot;⁠ <pb n="174"/> and if any one accompanies them on horseback, it is his duty to keep up with the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">dogs</name>.</p>
   <p>They beat the ground in regular array, with an extended front, proceeding in a straight line to the completion of a certain extent of country; and then, wheeling about in a body, return in the same way by the side of their former track, omitting as far as possible none of the likely lying.⁠ <pb n="175"/></p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="42">
   <p>But it is necessary, if many <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">dogs</name> are taken into the field, that they should not be left at random, and without arrangement. For when the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">hare</name> is started from her form, not a man would refrain from slipping his <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">hound</name> after her: one from eagerness to see his own <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">dog</name> run, and another from being startled and beside himself at the hallooing; and the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">hare</name> would be caught, in consequence of the crowd and confusion of the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">dogs</name>, without a struggle, and the whole value of the 119 spectacle destroyed.</p>
   <p><persName>Steward</persName>. On which account a <persName>steward</persName> should be appointed over the sport, [176] should match the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">dogs</name>, and give orders to the field:—if the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">hare</name> start on this side, you and you are to slip, and nobody else; but if on that side, you and you : and let strict attention be paid to the orders given. [177]</p>
</div>
<div type="chapter" n="21">
   <p>Coursing with sagacious and swift <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">hounds</name> together. The <persName>Celts</persName> sometimes course with a mixture of sagacious and swift-footed <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">hounds</name>; and while the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">dogs</name> of scent are trying, they stand apart with the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">greyhounds</name>, leading them in their hands where it is most probable the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">hare</name> will direct her course, that they may slip them at her when she breaks cover. And here the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">greyhounds</name> answer the same purpose as <quote>Xenophon’s nets</quote>. But the courses in this way are irregular and confused, and the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">hare</name>, however good, is generally so terrified at the barking of the finders, that, unless she get far enough a-head to be able to recover herself, she is easily caught, being frightened out of her wits. Whoever, therefore, is a good slipper, should not let go his <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">dog</name> while the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">hare</name> is at all bewildered, (unless he would destroy the sport,) but should allow her to make her first turns, and then slip.</p>
</div>
<div type="chapter" n="22">
   <p>Ware <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Leveret</name>. Let it be deemed unlawful to slip to a young <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">hare</name>; but rather, in obedience to my namesake, spare such for the <name type="deity">Goddess</name>. If possible, indeed, you should endeavour to call off the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">dogs</name> on scent; though they are with difficulty checked, being intractable from hunger, and so keen at devouring whatever prey they take, that you can scarce drive them away, even by beating them with sticks.</p>
</div>
<div type="chapter" n="23">
   <p>Stag-coursing. You should course the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">stag</name>, or any game of equal size in the same way, slipping high-couraged hounds;⁠ <pb n="184"/> for the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">animal</name> is large, runs a long while, and is by no means safe to contend with;⁠ <pb n="185"/> indeed there is no little danger of a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">greyhound</name> being destroyed by a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">stag</name>.⁠ <pb n="186"/></p>
   <p>But where the plains are adapted for riding, as in <placeName>Mysia</placeName>, <placeName>Dacia</placeName>, <placeName>Scythia</placeName>, and <placeName>Illyricum</placeName>,⁠ <pb n="125"/> they are in the habit of coursing <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">deer</name> with <foreign xml:lang="la">Scythian</foreign> and <foreign xml:lang="la">Illyrian</foreign> horses; which, though slow at first in pursuit, and utterly despicable, as far as appearance goes, by the side of those of <placeName>Thessaly</placeName>, <placeName>Sicily</placeName>, or <placeName>Peloponnesus</placeName>, hold out to the last under the most severe work.⁠ <pb n="126"/></p>
   <p>On such occasions you will see the huge, swift, proud-looking horse flagging, and this lean and scrubby little animal at first passing him, then leaving him behind, and at last even driving the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">stag</name> away from him. He holds on indeed until the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">stag</name> gives out and stops, gasping with distress;⁠ when you may, if you choose, spear him at close quarters as if enfettered,⁠ or throw a noose over his neck, and lead him away alive.</p>
</div>
<div type="chapter" n="24">
   <p>African Coursing of <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Wild Asses</name>.</p>
   <p>In Africa there is a mode of coursing on <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Libyan horses</name>,<pb n="192"/>
   called <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Nomades</name>, on which the sportsmen, mounted, catch not only <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">red deer</name> and <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">roe deer</name>,<pb n="193"/>
   (for these are taken with little effort, and the horses are not esteemed good in consequence,<pb n="194"/>
   ) but also <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">127 wild asses</name>,<pb n="195"/>
   which excel in speed, and power of holding out for the greatest length of course.</p>
   <p>For when the <persName>Greeks</persName> marched with <persName>Cyrus</persName>, the son of <persName>Darius</persName>, against the great king,<pb n="196"/>
   (in which expedition <persName>Xenophon</persName> was engaged, who relates the circumstance,<pb n="197"/>
   ) while they were passing over the plains of <placeName>Arabia</placeName>,<pb n="198"/>
   there appeared herds of <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">wild asses</name>, but not one could be caught by any single horseman, and therefore the <persName>Greeks</persName> pursued them with relays of horsemen at stated distances; and after the asses had held out for a long while against several, they sunk at last from fatigue. Thus even <persName>Cyrus</persName> himself, the son of the great king, and the brother of the great king, had not horses good enough<pb n="128"/>
   for this chase; and yet the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Libyan</name> boys, some at eight years of age, and others not much older, mounted on their naked steeds,<pb n="129"/>
   and guiding them with a switch, as the <persName>Greeks</persName> employ the rein, press these <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">wild asses</name> so closely in pursuit, that at last they throw a noose around their necks and lead them away quite subdued.<pb n="200"/>
   </p>
</div>
<div type="chapter" n="XXV">
   <p>Such are the methods of coursing adopted by those who have fleet <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">hounds</name> and <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">horses</name>: they neither ensnare the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">animals</name> with toils, nets, or springes; <pb n="201"/> nor employ, in short, any other tricks or wily inventions, but contend with them in a straight-forward trial of speed. <pb n="202"/></p>
   <p>And to me, the two spectacles appear nowise akin: the former being like thievish depredation; the latter, like a battle fought out with main strength: the one class of sportsmen resembling pirates in their clandestine attack, while the other are as openly victorious as were the <persName>Athenians</persName> over the <persName>Medes</persName> in the naval engagement at <placeName>Artemisium</placeName>, <pb n="130"/> or at <placeName>Salamis</placeName> and <placeName>Psyttalia</placeName>, or again at <placeName>Cyprus</placeName>.</p>
   <p>Age and mode of entering bitch-puppies. As to the age at which <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">greyhounds</name> should begin coursing, <pb n="203"/> you may take a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">bitch</name> out after the eleventh month; <pb n="204"/> or, if she <pb n="131"/> be well set, and not loose-limbed, you may let go a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">hare</name> from your hand before her, in an open field, a month earlier than this, starting the pup close to the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">hare</name>, that she may enjoy the sight of her game, and, by seeing it quite close, may work with eagerness. <pb n="205"/></p>
   <p>But presently slip another good <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">dog</name> to the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">hare</name>, that the puppy may not suffer by too long a course, nor flag from over-fatigue; and the second <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">dog</name> turning the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">hare</name> with ease again and again, will drive her into the puppy’s mouth, when the latter should be allowed to tear her with her teeth till she has killed her. <pb n="206"/> <pb n="207"/></p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="47">
   <p>As soon as the season arrives for taking out your <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">puppies</name>, let them be first walked over such roads as are rough;⁠ <pb n="208"/> for this exercise is conducive to forming and strengthening their feet. Then station the man who leads them upon a conspicuous and elevated spot, and be sure that he does not slip a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">puppy</name> when the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">hare</name> has got much a-head, and is out of sight; (notwithstanding the elder <persName>Xenophon</persName> advises it in regard to <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">dogs</name> that are to be practised at running on scent;⁠ <pb n="209"/> ) for if you slip a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">greyhound</name> <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">puppy</name> out of sight of her game, she runs wide, and jumps about, and is beside herself and bewildered. And after she is full-grown, if a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">hare</name> happen to escape her, she is never at rest, neither returning to her keeper, nor obeying his call, but, from eagerness for a course, continuing to run about wildly, like a mad <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">dog</name>, after nothing.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="48">
   <p>Let the man, then, that holds the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">puppy</name> stand on such a spot as I have stated, <pb n="211"/> concealed from view at the point where it is most probable the tired <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">hare</name> will come in the course of her <foreign xml:lang="la">134</foreign> turns; and when he sees her quite weary, let him slip the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">puppy</name> close to her, neither before, nor directly opposite to her; for the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">bitch</name> rushing right upon her will overshoot herself, and the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">hare</name>, with a wrench, easily skimming by, will of course leave the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">bitch</name> far behind; the latter with difficulty turning herself, as <foreign xml:lang="en">gallies</foreign> sailing briskly a-head cannot readily tack, unless the rowing be much slackened before they are brought about.</p>
   <p>Let the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">hare</name>, therefore, just pass by, and then let him slip obliquely after her. Some one should follow up quickly, as soon as the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">hare</name> is caught, before the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">dogs</name> are gorged with her blood. Not that the flesh of a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">hare</name> is to be accounted of much worth by a person who courses for the beauty of the sport; <pb n="212"/> but it is a bad thing to teach a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">greyhound</name> to eat a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">hare</name>. <foreign xml:lang="la">135</foreign> Many a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">dog</name>, too, has been Ware dead. destroyed by gorging himself while out of breath, after a long course, and has died of suffocation.</p>
</div>
<div type="chapter" n="26">
   <p>Age of entering <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">dog-puppies</name>. <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Dog-puppies</name> must not be taken out coursing until they are two years old, <pb n="215"/> for their limbs become set at a much later period than those of <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">bitches</name>. Besides it is attended with no little danger to take them out earlier, many a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">greyhound</name> having been prematurely destroyed by a severe course before he was full-grown, and especially those of the greatest spirit and highest breeding; for, in consequence of their spirit, they run to the very utmost of their power.</p>
   <p>The other practical points, already insisted on in reference to <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">bitches</name>, are equally to be attended to in regard to the other sex. <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Dogs</name> Age of sexual intercourse. are to be kept from copulation within the age stated; for the seed being not yet matured in them, is generally weak and evanid, <quote><foreign xml:lang="grc">καθάπερ ἡ τῶν παίδων</foreign></quote> <pb n="216"/> The puppies themselves 136 too are so utterly ruined by it that you can never afterwards, do what you will, remedy the error. The proper and seasonable time for sexual intercourse is from the completion of the third year. <pb n="217"/></p>
</div>
<div type="chapter" n="27">
   <p>Time of sexual intercourse. And it should be thus managed:—watch the opportunity of 138 the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">bitch</name> being clear of vaginal blood; for if she receive the seed before, it generally is not retained, but is washed out 139 by the blood, <quote><foreign xml:lang="grc">καθάπερ ταῖς γυναιξί</foreign></quote> <pb n="218"/> and you must here pay her particular attention, as it is only for a short interval of time 140 that she preserves her heat after the vaginal blood has stopped.</p>
</div>
<div type="chapter" n="28">
   <p>A <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">bitch</name>’s age may be considered good for the purpose from the second to the seventh year.⁠ <pb n="219"/></p>
   <p>Mode of sexual intercourse. It is best for the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">dog</name> and <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">bitch</name> to be shut up by themselves, and to be out of sight while together.⁠ <pb n="220"/></p>
   <p>For open and public copulations, if we may believe sportsmen, are not prolific;⁠ <pb n="221"/></p>
   <p>but such as are effected by <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">dogs</name> in private are reported to succeed.⁠ <pb n="141"/></p>
   <p><name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Bitches</name>, after being warded, may be led out, as walking about is conducive to their strength;⁠ <pb n="222"/></p>
   <p>but they must not be slipped again to a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">hare</name>, for fear of being destroyed by overstraining or excessive fatigue. The <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">dog</name> likewise should not be let loose after a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">hare</name> until he is recovered from his exhaustion, and invigorated by an interval of at least sixty days’ rest. After which there will be no obstacle to his being coursed.⁠ <pb n="142"/></p>
</div>
<div type="chapter" n="29">
   <p>Breeding season. The most favourable season for breeding is the spring of the year,⁠ <pb n="225"/></p>
   <p>as the temperature is mediate between hot and cold. <pb n="143"/></p>
   <p>Winter is not propitious for rearing <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">puppies</name>, more especially on account of the want of milk:⁠ <pb n="226"/></p>
   <p>and summer is distressing to the dams for suckling. Autumn is worse than spring for this reason, that the winter arrests the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">whelps</name> before they are thoroughly formed.⁠ <pb n="227"/></p>
</div>
<div type="chapter" n="30">
  <p>Management after whelping. If you wish a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">brood-bitch</name> to recover her previous speed, <pb n="228"/> you must not let her suckle her <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">whelps</name>, except merely to lighten any excess of milk,—and then put them to other <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">bitches</name>, selecting such as are well-bred: for the milk of degenerate <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">curs</name> is not congenial to high-bred <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">puppies</name>. <pb n="229"/></p>
  <p>If, however, the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">dam</name> herself appear no longer serviceable for coursing, it is best to leave the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">whelps</name> with their own mother, and not to put them under a foster-parent. For the growth is stinted by a stranger’s nursing, (as the other <persName>Xenophon</persName> declares,) but the mother’s milk and breath are cherishing to her <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">puppies</name>.</p>
</div>
<div type="chapter" n="31">
  <p>Food of weaned <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">puppies</name>. When <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">puppies</name> can run about, <persName>Xenophon</persName> properly recommends that they be fed with milk; for the filling them with heavy food distorts their legs, and occasions diseases in their bodies. And as to giving <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">dogs</name> short names of easy pronunciation, <pb n="149"/> in this we should also attend to him; <persName>Xenophon</persName>’s instructions approved. for the names which he has enumerated, (in part the invention of others, and some of his own creation), are cleverly composed.<pb n="150"/></p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="52">
   <p>But if you do not as yet wish your <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">bitches</name> to breed up any puppies, you must take the greatest possible care of them while under distress in consequence.⁠ <pb n="234"/></p>
   <p>For when they have ceased to give suck, their teats become turgid and full of milk, and the parts beneath the belly distended. At which time, it is not safe to loose them after a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">hare</name>,—for their flanks may be burst asunder: nor should you let them play with another <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">dog</name>, as, by contending and striving with him beyond their strength, they may be placed in equal danger.</p>
   <p>It is best to wait till their teats are become flaccid. And you will have a proof that it is safe to take them out, when the hair falls off abundantly, as you stroke it with your hand. They are then, I think, free from the distress they laboured under on account of their milk, and are ready for coursing.⁠ <pb n="235"/></p>
</div>
<div type="chapter" n="32">
   <p>Estimate of Sexes. The <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">greyhound</name> <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">bitch</name> is fleeter than the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">dog</name>,<pb n="236"/> but the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">dog</name> has more bottom than the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">bitch</name>;<pb n="152"/> and, because he can run through the whole year, is a much more valuable acquisition: and as good <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">bitches</name> abound, but it is no easy thing to meet with a thorough-good <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">dog</name>, the latter is on this account more precious: and again, it is fortunate if <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">bitches</name> preserve their speed to the fifth year,<pb n="238"/> whereas <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">dogs</name> retain theirs even to the tenth.<pb n="239"/></p>
   <p>For all which reasons, in my opinion, a really good, high-bred <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">dog</name> is a great treasure<pb n="240"/>—one that falls not to the lot of a <foreign xml:lang="en">courser</foreign> without the favour of some <name type="deity">god</name>.<pb n="241"/> For such a blessing, then, he should sacrifice to <name type="deity">Diana Venatrix</name>.<pb n="242"/> He<pb n="155"/> should sacrifice, too, whenever successful in his sport, dedicate<pb n="156"/> the first-fruits of his spoils to the <name type="deity">goddess</name>,<pb n="243"/> and purify his <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">dogs</name> and sportsmen,<pb n="244"/> as regulated by the established rites of the country.</p>
</div>
<div type="chapter" n="33">
   <p>Celtic hunting rites. Some of the <persName>Celts</persName> have a custom of annually sacrificing to <name type="deity">Diana</name>;<pb n="245"/> while others institute a treasury for the <name type="deity">goddess</name>,<pb n="246"/>—into<pb n="157"/> which they pay two oboli for every <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">hare</name> that is caught,<pb n="247"/>—a drachma for a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">fox</name>,<pb n="248"/> (because he is a crafty <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">animal</name>, and destroys <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">hares</name>,)—and four drachmæ for a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">roe-deer</name>,<pb n="249"/> in consideration of his size, and greater value as game.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="54">
   <p>When the year comes round, on the return of the nativity of <name type="deity">Diana</name>, <pb n="250"/><quote>the treasury is opened, and a victim purchased out of the money collected;</quote> either a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">sheep</name>, or <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">kid</name>, or <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">heifer</name>, <pb n="159"/> according to the amount of the sum: and then, after having sacrificed, and presented the first-offerings of their victims to the Goddess of the chase, <pb n="253"/> according to their respective rites, they give themselves up, with their <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">hounds</name>, to indulgence and recreation, <pb n="254"/> —crowning the latter on this day with garlands, <pb n="160"/> as an indication of the festival being celebrated on their account.</p>
</div>
<div type="chapter" n="34">
   <p>Injunctions to the observance of religious rites. This Celtic custom I follow with my fellow-sportsmen, <pb n="257"/>&amp; declare no human undertaking to have a prosperous issue <quote>without the interposition of the Gods</quote>.</p>
   <p>For that Mariners, <pb n="163"/> who regard their safety, supplicate the Gods at embarkation; <pb n="164"/> and, after dangers escaped, offer up sacrifices of gratitude to the sea-deities, <name type="deity">Neptune</name>, <name type="deity">Amphitrite</name>, and the <name type="deity">Nereids</name>.</p>
   <p>Cultivators of the soil do the same to <name type="deity">Ceres</name>, her daughter, and <name type="deity">Bacchus</name>; <pb n="165"/> Artificers, to <name type="deity">Minerva</name> and <name type="deity">Vulcan</name>; <pb n="166"/></p>
   <p>Professors of instruction, <pb n="167"/> to the <name type="deity">Muses</name>, <name type="deity">Apollo Musagetes</name>, <name type="deity">Mnemosyne</name>, <pb n="168"/> and <name type="deity">Mercury</name>; <pb n="169"/></p>
   <p>Lovers, to <name type="deity">Venus</name>, <name type="deity">Cupid</name>, <name type="deity">Suada</name>, <pb n="170"/> and the <name type="deity">Graces</name>.</p>
   <p>And, upon the same principle, Sportsmen should not be neglectful of <name type="deity">Diana Venatrix</name>, <pb n="171"/> nor <name type="deity">Apollo</name>, nor <name type="deity">Pan</name>, nor the <name type="deity">Nymphs</name>, nor <name type="deity">Mercury</name>, the conductor and president of the highways, nor any other mountain gods <pb n="172"/> that there may be: otherwise their pursuits must turn out abortive, their <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">dogs</name> injured, their <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">horses</name> lamed, <pb n="173"/> and themselves disappointed.</p>
</div>
<div type="chapter" n="35">
   <p>Enforced by examples from Homer. And of this, Homer gives evidence in his poem. <pb n="280"/> Teucer, he says, the best bowman of the Greeks, in the archery-contest hit the cord only, and cut it asunder, because he had offered no vow to <name type="deity">Apollo</name>; but that <persName>Merion</persName>, who was no archer at all, by having invoked <name type="deity">Apollo</name>, struck the bird when on the wing.</p>
   <p>Again, the posterity of those, who fought against <placeName>Thebes</placeName> with <persName>Polynices</persName>, captured the city, whereas their fathers, not at all inferior to them in valour, had perished before it, because they were disobedient to the signs vouchsafed to them by the Gods.</p>
   <p>And lastly, <persName>Hector</persName>, inattentive to <persName>Polydamas</persName> when he objected to an attack on the Grecian fleet, (because the Trojans would not return from it with honour to themselves, as he inferred from a serpent dropped by an <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">eagle</name>), was soon afterwards taught otherwise by experience, that no good comes of being refractory towards the Deity.</p>
   <p>Following these examples, it is right in field-sports, as in every thing else, to begin with adoration of the Gods; and, after having obtained success, to offer thanksgiving-sacrifices and libations, with auspicious words, and crowns, and hymns, and to dedicate the first-fruits of the captured game, as the conqueror does of the spoils of war.</p>
</div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>