<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng"
    type="application/xml"
    schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title xml:lang="en">Περὶ ἀποχῆς τῶν ἐμψύχων</title>
        <title type="alt" xml:lang="fr">Sur l'abstinence de la chair des animaux</title>
        <title type="alt" xml:lang="en">On Abstinence from Animal Food</title>
        <author>
          <persName>PORPHYRIUS</persName>
          <idno type="zoomathia">tlg2034</idno>
        </author>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Encodage automatique TEI P5</resp>
          <name>zoomathia_encoder.py v3.0</name>
          <date when="2026-06-30">2026-06-30</date>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Projet Zoomathia (ANR-21-CE27-0012)</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Universite Cote d'Azur, Nice, France</pubPlace>
        <date when="2026-06-30">2026-06-30</date>
        <availability>
          <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0</licence>
        </availability>
        <idno type="zoomathia">tlg2034</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Encode automatiquement par zoomathia_encoder.py v3.0 - Projet Zoomathia</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language ident="en">anglais</language>
      </langUsage>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="zoomathia">
          <term>Zoomathia</term>
          <term>animaux</term>
          <term>antique (800 av. J.-C. - 300 ap. J.-C.)</term>
          <term>anglais</term>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>Fichier encode automatiquement dans le cadre du projet Zoomathia (ANR).
        Encodage produit par zoomathia_encoder.py v3.0. Verification humaine recommandee.</p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>Balisage automatique des structures textuelles et des entites nommees
        pertinentes pour Zoomathia (animaux, plantes, personnes, lieux).</p>
        <correction status="unknown">
          <p>Encodage automatique - erreurs possibles, revision manuelle recommandee.</p>
        </correction>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
<div type="book" n="3">
   <head>BOOK THREE</head>
   <p>In the two preceding books, O <persName>Firmus Castricius</persName>, we have demonstrated that animal food does not contribute either to temperance and frugality, or to the piety which especially gives completion to the theoretic life, but is rather hostile to it.</p>
   <p>Since, however, the most beautiful part of justice consists in piety to the <name type="deity">Gods</name>, and this is principally acquired through abstinence, there is no occasion to fear that we shall violate justice towards men, while we preserve piety towards the <name type="deity">Gods</name>.</p>
   <p><persName>Socrates</persName> therefore says, in opposition to those who contend that pleasure is the supreme good, that though all <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">swine</name> and <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">goats</name> should accord in this opinion, yet he should never be persuaded that our felicity was placed in the enjoyment of corporeal delight, as long as intellect has dominion over all things.</p>
   <p>And we also say, that though all <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">wolves</name> and <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">vultures</name> should praise the eating of flesh, we should not admit that they spoke justly, as long as man is by nature innoxious, and ought to abstain from procuring pleasure for himself by injuring others.</p>
   <p>We shall pass on, therefore, to the discussion of justice; and since our opponents say that this ought only to be extended to those of similar species, and on this account deny that irrational animals can be injured by men, let us exhibit the true, and at the same time Pythagoric opinion, and demonstrate that every soul which participates of sense and memory is rational.</p>
   <p>For this being demonstrated, we may extend, as our opponents will also admit, justice to every <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">animal</name>. But we shall epitomize what has been said by the ancients on this subject.</p>
</div>
<div type="chapter" n="2">
<p>Since, however, with respect to reason, one kind, according to the doctrine of the <persName>Stoics</persName>, is internal, but the other external <note place="foot">1</note>, and again, one kind being right, but the other erroneous, it is requisite to explain of which of these two, <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">animals</name>, according to them, are deprived.</p>
   <p>Are they therefore deprived of right reason alone? or are they entirely destitute both of internal and externally proceeding reason?</p>
   <p>They appear, indeed, to ascribe to <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">brutes</name> an entire privation of reason, and not a privation of right reason alone.</p>
   <p>For if they merely denied that <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">brutes</name> possess right reason, <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">animals</name> would not be irrational, but rational beings, in the same manner as nearly all <persName>men</persName> are according to them.</p>
   <p>For, according to their opinion, one or two wise men may be found in whom alone right reason prevails, but all the rest of <persName>mankind</persName> are depraved; though some of these make a certain proficiency, but others are profoundly depraved, and yet, at the same time, all of them are similarly rational.</p>
   <p>Through the influence, therefore, of self-love, they say, that all other <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">animals</name> are irrational; wishing to indicate by irrationality, an entire privation of reason.</p>
   <p>If, however, it be requisite to speak the truth, not only reason may plainly be perceived in all <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">animals</name>, but in many of them it is so great as to approximate to perfection.</p>
</div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>