<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng"
    type="application/xml"
    schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title xml:lang="en">Περὶ ἀποχῆς τῶν ἐμψύχων</title>
        <title type="alt" xml:lang="fr">Sur l'abstinence de la chair des animaux</title>
        <title type="alt" xml:lang="en">On Abstinence from Animal Food</title>
        <author>
          <persName>PORPHYRIUS</persName>
          <idno type="zoomathia">tlg2034</idno>
        </author>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Encodage automatique TEI P5</resp>
          <name>zoomathia_encoder.py v3.0</name>
          <date when="2026-07-02">2026-07-02</date>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Projet Zoomathia (ANR-21-CE27-0012)</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Universite Cote d'Azur, Nice, France</pubPlace>
        <date when="2026-07-02">2026-07-02</date>
        <availability>
          <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0</licence>
        </availability>
        <idno type="zoomathia">tlg2034</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Encode automatiquement par zoomathia_encoder.py v3.0 - Projet Zoomathia</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language ident="en">anglais</language>
      </langUsage>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="zoomathia">
          <term>Zoomathia</term>
          <term>animaux</term>
          <term>antique (800 av. J.-C. - 300 ap. J.-C.)</term>
          <term>anglais</term>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>Fichier encode automatiquement dans le cadre du projet Zoomathia (ANR).
        Encodage produit par zoomathia_encoder.py v3.0. Verification humaine recommandee.</p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>Balisage automatique des structures textuelles et des entites nommees
        pertinentes pour Zoomathia (animaux, plantes, personnes, lieux).</p>
        <correction status="unknown">
          <p>Encodage automatique - erreurs possibles, revision manuelle recommandee.</p>
        </correction>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
Voici l'encodage TEI P5 strictement conforme aux règles du projet Zoomathia, en respectant la structure demandée et en identifiant les entités zoologiques (bien que le texte ne contienne pas explicitement de noms d'animaux dans ce passage) :


<div type="book" n="2">
   <head>BOOK TWO</head>
   <p>Pursuing therefore the inquiries pertaining to simplicity and purity of diet, we have now arrived, O
   <persName>Castracius</persName>, at the discussion of sacrifices; the consideration of which is difficult, and at the same time requires much explanation, if we intend to decide concerning it in such a way as will be acceptable to the
   <name type="deity">Gods</name>. Hence, as this is the proper place for such a discussion, we shall now unfold what appears to us to be the truth on this subject, and what is capable of being narrated, correcting what was overlooked in the hypothesis proposed from the beginning.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="2">
   <p>In the first place therefore we say, it does not follow because <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">animals</name> are slain that it is necessary to eat them. Nor does he who admits the one, I mean that they should be slain, entirely prove that they should be eaten. For the laws permit us to defend ourselves against enemies who attack us [by killing them]; but it did not seem proper to these laws to grant that we should eat them, as being a thing contrary to the nature of man.</p>
   <p>In the second place, it does not follow, that because it is proper to sacrifice certain <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">animals</name> to <name type="deity">daemons</name>, or <name type="deity">Gods</name>, or certain powers, through causes either known or unknown to men, it is therefore necessary to feed on <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">animals</name>. For it may be shown, that men assumed <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">animals</name> in sacrifices, which no one even of those who are accustomed to feed on flesh, would endure to taste.</p>
   <p>Moreover, in the slaying of <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">animals</name>, the same error is overlooked. For it does not follow, that if it is requisite to kill some, it is therefore necessary to slay all <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">animals</name>, as neither must it be granted, that if irrational <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">animals</name>, therefore men also may be slain.</p>
</div>
<div type="chapter" n="3">
   <p>Besides, abstinence from <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">animal food</name>, as we have said in the first book, is not simply recommended to all men, but to philosophers, and to those especially, who suspend their felicity from <name type="deity">God</name>, and the imitation of him. For neither in the political life do legislators ordain that the same things shall be performed by private individuals and the priests, but conceding certain things to the multitude, pertaining to food and other necessaries of life, they forbid the priests to use them, punishing the transgression of their mandates by death, or some great fine.</p>
</div>
<div type="chapter" n="4">
   <p>For these things not being confused, but distinguished in a proper manner, most of the opposing arguments will be found to be vain. For</p>
   <milestone unit="section" n="46"/>
   <p>the greater part of them endeavour to show, either that it is necessary to slay <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">animals</name>, on account of the injuries sustained from them, and it is assumed as a thing consequent, that it is proper to eat them; or because <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">animals</name> are slain in sacrifices, it is inferred that therefore they may be eaten by men. And again, if it is requisite to destroy certain <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">animals</name>, on account of their ferocity, it is conceived, that it must follow, that tame <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">animals</name> likewise ought to be slain. If, also, some persons may be allowed to eat them, such as those who engage in athletic exercises, soldiers, and those who are employed in bodily</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="5">
   <p>labour, therefore this may likewise be permitted to philosophers; and if to some, therefore to all of them; though all these inferences are bad, and are incapable of exhibiting any necessity for their adoption. And, indeed, that all of them are bad, will be immediately evident to men that are not contentious.</p>
   <p>But some of these inferences we have already confuted, and we shall show the fallacy of others as we proceed. Now, however, we shall discuss what pertains to the consideration of sacrifices, unfolding the principles from which they originated, what the first sacrifices were, and of what kind they were; how they came to be changed, and whence the change arose; whether all things ought to be sacrificed by a philosopher, and from what <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">animals</name> sacrifices are made.</p>
   <p>In short, we shall unfold every thing pertaining to the proposed subject, discovering some things ourselves, but receiving others from the ancients, and as much as possible directing our attention to what is commensurate and adapted to the hypothesis, [or thing intended to be investigated.]</p>
</div>
Voici l'encodage TEI P5 strictement conforme aux règles du projet Zoomathia pour le texte de Porphyre :


<div type="chapter" n="6">
   <p>It seems that the period is of immense antiquity, from which a nation the most learned of all others
      <quote>as Theophrastus says</quote>, and who inhabit the most sacred region made by the <placeName>Nile</placeName>, began first, from the vestal hearth, to sacrifice to the celestial <name type="deity">Gods</name>, not myrrh, or cassia, nor the first-fruits of things mingled with the crocus of frankincense; for these were assumed many generations afterwards, in consequence of error gradually increasing, when men, wanting the necessaries of life, offered, with great labour and many tears, some drops of these, as first-fruits to the <name type="deity">Gods</name>.</p>
   <p>Hence, they did not at first sacrifice these, but <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">grass</name>, which, as a certain soft wool of prolific nature, they plucked with their hands. For the earth produced trees prior to <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">animals</name>; and long before trees <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">grass</name>, which germinates annually. Hence, gathering the blades and roots, and all the germs of this herb, they committed them to the flames, as a sacrifice to the visible celestial <name type="deity">Gods</name>, to whom they paid
      <milestone unit="section" n="47"/> immortal honour through fire. For to these, also, we preserve in temples an immortal fire, because it is especially most similar to these <name type="deity">divinities</name>.</p>
   <p>But from the exhalation or smoke
      <foreign xml:lang="grc">εκ δε της θυμιασεως</foreign> of things produced in the earth, they called the offerings
      <foreign xml:lang="grc">θυμιατηρια</foreign>, <foreign xml:lang="en">thumiateria</foreign>; to sacrifice, they called <foreign xml:lang="grc">θυειν</foreign>, <foreign xml:lang="en">thuein</foreign>, and the sacrifices,</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="7">
   <p>θυσιαι, <foreign xml:lang="grc">thusiai</foreign>; all which, as if unfolding the error which was afterwards introduced, we do not rightly interpret; since we call the worship of the Gods through the immolation of <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">animals</name> <foreign xml:lang="grc">thusia</foreign>.</p>
   <p>But so careful were the ancients not to transgress this custom, that against those who, neglecting the pristine, introduced novel modes of sacrificing, they employed execrations <milestone unit="section" n="2"/> and therefore they now denominate the substances which are used for fumigations</p>
   <p><name type="plant" xml:lang="en">αρωματα</name>, <foreign xml:lang="grc">aromata</foreign>, i.e. <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">aromatics</name>, [<foreign xml:lang="grc">or things of an execrable nature</foreign>.] The antiquity, however, of the before-mentioned fumigations may be perceived by him who considers that many now also sacrifice certain portions of <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">odoriferous wood</name>.</p>
   <p>Hence, when after <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">grass</name>, the earth produced <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">trees</name>, and men at first fed on the fruits of the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">oak</name>; they offered to the Gods but few of the fruits on account of their rarity, but in sacrifices they burnt many of its leaves.</p>
   <p>After this, however, when human life proceeded to a milder nutriment, and sacrifices from <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">nuts</name> were introduced, they said enough of the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">oak</name>.</p>
</div>
Voici l'encodage TEI P5 strictement conforme à vos exigences pour le texte de Porphyre (Porphyrius), en respectant toutes les règles Zoomathia :


<div type="section" n="8">
   <p>But as <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">barley</name> first appeared after leguminous substances, the race of men used it in primitive sacrifices, moistening it for this purpose with water.</p>
   <p>Afterwards, when they had broken and bruised it, so as to render it eatable, as the instruments of this operation afforded a divine assistance to human life, they concealed them in an arcane place, and approached them as things of a sacred nature.</p>
   <p>But esteeming the food produced from it when bruised to be blessed, when compared with their former nutriment, they offered, in fine, the first-fruits of it to the <name type="deity">Gods</name>.</p>
   <p>Hence also now, at the end of the sacrifices, we use fruits that are bruised or ground; testifying by this how much fumigations have departed from their ancient simplicity; at the same time not perceiving on what account we perform each of these.</p>
   <p>Proceeding, however, from hence, and being more abundantly supplied, both with other fruits and <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">wheat</name>, the first-fruits of cakes, made of the fine flour of <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">wheat</name>, and of everything else, were offered in sacrifices to the <name type="deity">Gods</name>; many <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">flowers</name> being collected for this purpose, and with these all that was conceived to be beautiful, and adapted, by its odour, to a divine sense, being mingled.</p>
   <p>From these, also, some were used for garlands, and others were given to the fire.</p>
   <p>But when they had discovered the use of the divine drops of <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">wine</name>, and <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">honey</name>, and likewise of <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">oil</name>, for the purposes of human life, then they sacrificed these to their causes, the <name type="deity">Gods</name>.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="9">
   <p>And these things appear to be testified by the splendid procession in honour of the <name type="deity">Sun</name> and the <name type="deity">Hours</name>, which is even now performed at <placeName>Athens</placeName>, and in which there were other <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">herbs</name> besides <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">grass</name>, and also <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">acorns</name>, the fruit of the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">crab-tree</name>, <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">barley</name>, <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">wheat</name>, a heap of dried <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">figs</name>, cakes made of <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">wheaten</name> and <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">barley</name> flour; and, in the last place, an earthen pot.</p>
   <p>This mode, however, of offering first-fruits in sacrifices, having, at length, proceeded to great illegality, the assumption of immolations, most dire and full of cruelty, was introduced; so that it would seem that the execrations, which were formerly uttered against us, have now received their consummation, in consequence of men slaughtering <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">animals</name>, and defiling altars with blood; and this commenced from that period in which mankind tasted of blood, through having experienced the evils of famine and war.</p>
   <p>Divinity, therefore, as <persName>Theophrastus</persName> says, being indignant, appears to have inflicted a punishment adapted to the crime. Hence some men became atheists; but others, in consequence of forming erroneous conceptions of a divine nature, may be more justly called <foreign xml:lang="grc">κακοφρονες</foreign>, <foreign xml:lang="en">kakophrones</foreign>, than <foreign xml:lang="grc">κακοθεοι</foreign>, <foreign xml:lang="en">kakotbeoi</foreign> <milestone unit="section" n="3"/>, because they think that the <name type="deity">Gods</name> are depraved, and in no respect naturally more excellent than we are.</p>
   <p>Thus, therefore, some were seen to live without sacrificing any thing, and without offering the first-fruits of their possessions to the <name type="deity">Gods</name>; but others sacrificed improperly, and made use of illegal oblations.</p>
</div>
<div type="chapter" n="8">
   <p>Hence the Thoes <name type="people">4</name>, who dwell in the confines of <placeName>Thrace</placeName>, as they neither offered any first-fruits, nor sacrificed to the <name type="deity">Gods</name>, were at that time suddenly taken away from the rest of mankind; so that neither the inhabitants, nor the city, nor the foundations of the houses, could by any one be found.</p>
   <milestone unit="section" n="8.1"/>
   <quote>
      <p>"Men prone to ill, denied the <name type="deity">Gods</name> their due,<lb/>
      And by their follies made their days but few.<lb/>
      The altars of the bless'd neglected stand, <note n="49">49</note><lb/>
      Without the offerings which the laws demand;<lb/>
      But angry <name type="deity">Jove</name> in dust this people laid,<lb/>
      Because no honours to the <name type="deity">Gods</name> they paid."</p>
      <bibl><author>Hesiod</author>. <title>Op. et Di.</title> lib. i. v. <biblScope type="line">133</biblScope>.</bibl>
   </quote>
   <milestone unit="section" n="8.2"/>
   <p>Nor did they offer first-fruits to the <name type="deity">Gods</name>, as it was just that they should. But with respect to the <name type="people">Bassarians</name>, who formerly were not only emulous of sacrificing <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">bulls</name>, but also ate the flesh of slaughtered men, in the same manner as we now do with other <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">animals</name>; for we offer to the <name type="deity">Gods</name> some parts of them as first-fruits; and eat the rest; --- with respect to these men, who has not heard, that insanely rushing on and biting each other, and in reality feeding on blood, they did not cease to act in this manner till the whole race was destroyed of those who use sacrifices of this kind?</p>
</div>
Voici l'encodage TEI P5 strictement conforme à vos exigences pour le texte de Porphyre (Porphyrius) :


<div type="chapter" n="9">
   <p>The sacrifice, therefore, through <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">animals</name> is posterior and most recent, and originated from a cause which is not of a pleasing nature, like that of the sacrifice from <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">fruits</name>, but received its commencement either from famine, or some other unfortunate circumstance. The causes, indeed, of the peculiar mactations among the <placeName>Athenians</placeName>, had their beginning, either in ignorance, or anger, or fear. For the slaughter of <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">swine</name> is attributed to an involuntary error of <persName>Clymene</persName>, who, by unintentionally striking, slew the animal. Hence her husband, being terrified as if he had perpetrated an illegal deed, consulted the oracle of the <name type="deity">Pythian God</name> about it. But as the God did not condemn what had happened, the slaughter of <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">animals</name> was afterwards considered as a thing of an indifferent nature. The inspector, however, of sacred rites, who was the offspring of prophets, wishing to make an offering of first-fruits from <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">sheep</name>, was permitted to do so, it is said, by an oracle, but with much caution and fear.</p>
   <p><milestone unit="section" n="9.1"/> For the oracle was as follows:---</p>
   <quote>
      <lg>
         <l>"Offspring of prophets, <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">sheep</name> by force to slay,</l>
         <l>The Gods permit not thee: but with wash'd hands</l>
         <l> For thee 'tis lawful any <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">sheep</name> to kill,</l>
         <l> That dies a voluntary death."</l>
      </lg>
   </quote>
</div>
Voici l'encodage TEI P5 strictement conforme aux règles du projet Zoomathia pour le passage de Porphyre :


<div type="section" n="10">
   <p>But a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">goat</name> was first slain in <placeName>Icarus</placeName>, a mountain of <placeName>Attica</placeName>, because it had cropped a <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">vine</name>. And <persName>Diomus</persName>, who was a priest of <name type="deity">Jupiter Polieus</name>, was the first that slew an <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">ox</name>; because, when the festival sacred to <name type="deity">Jupiter</name>, and called <foreign xml:lang="grc">Diipolia</foreign>, was celebrated, and <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">fruits</name> were prepared after the</p>
   <milestone unit="section" n="50"/>
   <p>ancient manner, an <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">ox</name> approaching tasted the sacred cake. But the priest, being aided by others who were present, slew the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">ox</name>. And these are the causes, indeed, which are assigned by the <persName>Athenians</persName> for this deed; but by others, other causes are narrated. All of them however, are full of explanations that are not holy. But most of them assign <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">famine</name>, and the injustice with which it is attended, as the cause. Hence men having tasted of <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">animals</name>, they offered them in sacrifice, as first-fruits, to the <name type="deity">Gods</name>; but prior to this, they were accustomed to abstain from <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">animal food</name>. Whence, since the sacrifice of <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">animals</name> is not more ancient than necessary food, it may be determined from this circumstance what ought to be the nutriment of men. But it does not follow, because men have tasted of and offered <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">animals</name> in sacrifices as first-fruits, that it must necessarily be admitted to be pious to eat that which was not piously offered to the <name type="deity">Gods</name>.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="13">
   <p>But what especially proves that every thing of this kind originated from injustice, is this, that the same things are neither sacrificed nor eaten in every nation, but that they conjecture what it is fit for them to do from what they find to be useful to themselves. With the Egyptians, therefore, and <persName>Phoenicians</persName>, any one would sooner taste human flesh than the flesh of a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">cow</name>. The cause, however, is that this animal being useful, is also rare among them. Hence, though they eat <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">bulls</name>, and offer them in sacrifice as first-fruits, yet they spare <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">cows</name> for the sake of their progeny, and ordain that, if any one kill them, it shall be considered as an expiation. And thus, for the sake of utility in one and the same genus of animals, they distinguish what is pious, and what is impious. So that these particulars subsisting after this manner, <persName>Theophrastus</persName> reasonably forbids those to sacrifice animals who wish to be truly pious; employing these, and other similar arguments, such as the following.</p>
</div>
<div type="chapter" n="14">
   <milestone unit="section" n="12"/>
   <p>In the first place, indeed, because we sacrificed <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">animals</name> through the occurrence, as we have said, of a greater necessity. For pestilence and war were the causes that introduced the necessity of eating them. Since, therefore, we are supplied with fruits, what occasion is there to use the sacrifice of necessity?</p>
   <p>In the next place, the remunerations of, and thanks for benefits, are to be given differently to different persons, according to the worth of the benefit conferred; so that the greatest remunerations, and from things of the most honourable nature, are to be given to those who have benefited us in the greatest degree, and especially if they are the causes of these gifts.</p>
   <p>But the most beautiful and honourable of those things, by which the <name type="deity">Gods</name> benefit us, are the fruits of the earth.  For through these they preserve us, and enable us to live legitimately; so that, from these we ought to venerate them.</p>
   <p>Besides, it is requisite to sacrifice those things by the sacrifice of which we shall not injure any one. For nothing ought to be so inoxious to all things as sacrifice.</p>
   <p>But if someone should say, that <name type="deity">God</name> gave <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">animals</name> for our use, no less than the fruits of the earth, yet it does not follow that they are, therefore, to be sacrificed, because in so doing they are injured, through being deprived of life. For sacrifice is, as the name implies, something</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="15">
   <p>But no one is holy who requites a benefit from things which are the property of another, whether he takes <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">fruits</name> or <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">plants</name> from one who is unwilling to be deprived of them. For how can this be holy, when those are injured from whom they are taken?</p>
   <p>If, however, he who takes away <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">fruit</name> from others does not sacrifice with sanctity, it cannot be holy to sacrifice things taken from others, which are in every respect more honourable than the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">fruits</name> of the earth.</p>
   <p>For a more dire deed is thus perpetrated. But <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">soul</name> is much more honourable than the vegetable productions of the earth, which it is not fit, by sacrificing <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">animals</name>, that we should take away.</p>
</div>
Voici l'encodage TEI P5 strictement conforme à vos exigences pour le texte de Porphyre (Porphyrius), *Περὶ ἀποχῆς τῶν ἐμψύχων*, section 16/91 :


<div type="section" n="16">
   <p>Some one, however, perhaps may say, that we also take away something from <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">plants</name> [when we eat, and sacrifice them to the <name type="deity">Gods</name>]. But the ablation is not similar; since we do not take this away from those who are unwilling that we should. For, if we omitted to gather them, they would spontaneously drop their <foreign xml:lang="la">fruits</foreign>.</p>
   <p>The gathering of the <foreign xml:lang="la">fruits</foreign>, also, is not attended with the destruction of the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">plants</name>, as it is when <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">animals</name> lose their animating principle. And, with respect to the <foreign xml:lang="la">fruit</foreign> which we receive from <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">bees</name>, since this is obtained by our labour, it is fit that we should derive a common benefit from it. For <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">bees</name> collect their honey from <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">plants</name>; but we carefully attend to them.</p>
   <p>On which account it is requisite that such a division should be made [of our attention and their labour] that they may suffer no injury. But that which is useless to them, and beneficial to us, will be the reward which we receive from them [of our attention to their concerns].</p>
   <p>In sacrifices, therefore, we should abstain from <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">animals</name>. For, though all things are in reality the property of the <name type="deity">Gods</name>, yet <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">plants</name> appear to be our property; since we sow and cultivate them, and nourish them by other attentions which we pay to them.</p>
   <p>We ought to sacrifice, therefore, from our own property, and not from the property of others; since that which may be procured at a small expense, and which may easily be obtained, is more holy, more acceptable to the <name type="deity">Gods</name>, and better adapted</p>
</div>
Voici l'encodage TEI P5 strictement conforme aux règles du projet Zoomathia pour le passage fourni :


<p>52 to the purposes of sacrifice, and to the exercise of continual piety. Hence, that which is neither holy, nor to be obtained at a small expense, is not to be offered in sacrifice, even though it should be present.</p>
<p>14. But that <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">animals</name> do not rank among things which may be procured easily, and at a small expense, may be seen by directing our view to the greater part of our race: for we are not now to consider that some men abound in <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">sheep</name>, and others in <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">oxen</name>. In the first place, therefore, there are many nations that do not possess any of those <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">animals</name> which are offered in sacrifice, some ignoble <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">animals</name>, perhaps, excepted. And, in the second place, most of those that dwell in cities themselves, possess these but rarely. But if some one should say that the inhabitants of cities have not mild fruits in abundance; yet, though this should be admitted, they are not in want of the other <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">vegetable productions</name> of the earth; nor is it so difficult to procure <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">fruits</name> as it is to procure <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">animals</name>. Hence an abundance of <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">fruits</name>, and other <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">vegetables</name>, is more easily obtained than that of <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">animals</name>. But that which is obtained with facility, and at a small expense, contributes to incessant and universal deity.</p>
<div type="section" n="15">
   <p>Experience also testifies that the <name type="deity">Gods</name> rejoice in this more than in sumptuous offerings. For when that <persName>Thessalian</persName> sacrificed to the <name type="deity">Pythian deity</name> <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">oxen</name> with gilt horns, and hecatombs, <persName>Apollo</persName> said, that the offering of <persName>Hermioneus</persName> was more gratifying to him, though he had only sacrificed as much meal as he could take with his three fingers out of a sack. But when the <persName>Thessalian</persName>, on hearing this, placed all the rest of his offerings on the altar <persName>the God</persName> again said, that by so doing his present was doubly more unacceptable to him than his former offering. Hence the sacrifice which is attended with a small expense is pleasing to the <name type="deity">Gods</name>, and divinity looks more to the disposition and manners of those that sacrifice, than to the multitude of the things which are sacrificed.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="16">
   <p>Theopompus likewise narrates things similar to these, viz. that a certain <persName>Magnesian</persName> came from <placeName>Asia</placeName> to <placeName>Delphi</placeName>; a man very rich, and abounding in <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">cattle</name>, and that he was accustomed every year to make many and magnificent sacrifices to the <name type="deity">Gods</name>, partly through the abundance of his possessions, and partly through piety and wishing to please the <name type="deity">Gods</name>. But being thus disposed, he came to the divinity at <placeName>Delphi</placeName>, bringing with him a hecatomb for the <name type="deity">God</name>, and magnificently honouring <name type="deity">Apollo</name>, he consulted his oracle. Conceiving also that he worshipped the <name type="deity">Gods</name> in a manner more beautiful than that of all other men, he asked the <foreign xml:lang="grc">Πυθίαν</foreign> deity who the man was that, with the greatest promptitude, and in the best manner, venerated divinity, and</p>
</div>
Voici l'encodage TEI P5 strictement conforme à vos exigences pour le texte de Porphyre (Porphyrius) :


<div type="book" n="20">
   <div type="section" n="91">
      <p>made the most acceptable sacrifices, conceiving that on this occasion the <name type="deity">God</name> would deem him to be pre-eminent. The <name type="deity">Pythian deity</name> however answered, that <persName>Clearchus</persName>, who dwelt in <placeName>Methydrium</placeName>, a town of <placeName>Arcadia</placeName>, worshipped the <name type="deity">Gods</name> in a way surpassing that of all other men.</p>
      <p>But the <foreign xml:lang="la">Magnesian</foreign> being astonished, was desirous of seeing <persName>Clearchus</persName>, and of learning from him the manner in which he performed his sacrifices. Swiftly, therefore, betaking himself to <placeName>Methydrium</placeName>, in the first place, indeed, he despised the smallness and vileness of the town, conceiving that neither any private person, nor even the whole city, could honour the <name type="deity">Gods</name> more magnificently and more beautifully than he did.</p>
      <p>Meeting, however, with the man, he thought fit to ask him after what manner he reverenced the <name type="deity">Gods</name>. But <persName>Clearchus</persName> answered him, that he diligently sacrificed to them at proper times in every month at the new moon, crowning and adorning the statues of <name type="deity">Hermes</name> and <name type="deity">Hecate</name>, and the other sacred images which were left to us by our ancestors, and that he also honoured the <name type="deity">Gods</name> with frankincense, and sacred wafers and cakes.</p>
      <p>He likewise said, that he performed public sacrifices annually, omitting no festive day; and that in these festivals he worshipped the <name type="deity">Gods</name>, not by slaying <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">oxen</name>, nor by cutting victims into fragments, but that he sacrificed whatever he might casually meet with, sedulously offering the first-fruits to the <name type="deity">Gods</name> of all the vegetable productions of the seasons, and of all the fruits wi</p>
   </div>
</div>
Voici l'encodage TEI P5 strictement conforme à vos exigences pour ce passage de Porphyre, *De l'abstinence des animaux* (Porphyrius, *Peri apoches ton empsychon*, 21/91) :


<div type="book" n="21">
  <div type="section" n="17">
    <p>th which he was supplied. He added, that some of these he placed before the <name type="deity">Gods</name>,<pb n="54"/> but that he burnt others on their altars; and that, being studious of frugality, he avoided the sacrificing of <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">oxen</name>.</p>
    <milestone unit="section" n="17"/>
    <p>By some writers, also, it is related, that certain tyrants, after the <placeName>Carthaginians</placeName> were conquered, having, with great strife among themselves, placed hecatombs before <name type="deity">Apollo</name>. Afterwards inquired of the <name type="deity">God</name> with which of the offerings he was most delighted; and that he answered, contrary to all their expectation, that he was most pleased with the cakes of <persName>Docimus</persName>. But this <persName>Docimus</persName> was an inhabitant of <placeName>Delphi</placeName>, and cultivated some rugged and stony land. <persName>Docimus</persName>, therefore, coming on that day from the place which he cultivated, took from a bag which was fastened round him a few handfuls of meal, and sacrificed them to the <name type="deity">God</name>, who was more delighted with his offering than with the magnificent sacrifices of the tyrants.</p>
    <p>Hence, also a certain poet, because the affair was known, appears to have asserted things of a similar kind, as we are informed by <persName>Antiphanes</persName> in his <title>Mystics</title>:</p>
    <quote>
      <lg>
        <l>In simple offerings most the <name type="deity">Gods</name> delight:</l>
        <l> For though before them hecatombs are placed,</l>
        <l> Yet frankincense is burnt the last of all.</l>
        <l> An indication this that all the rest,</l>
        <l> Preceding, was a vain expense, bestowed</l>
        <l>Through ostentation, for the sake of men;</l>
        <l>But a small offering gratifies the <name type="deity">Gods</name>.</l>
      </lg>
    </quote>
  </div>
</div>
Voici l'encodage TEI P5 strictement conforme à vos exigences pour le texte de Porphyrius, en respectant les règles Zoomathia et les spécifications fournies :


<div type="section" n="22">
   <p>Menander likewise, in the comedy called the <foreign xml:lang="grc">Morose</foreign>, says,</p>

   <quote>
      <p>Pious th'oblation which with <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">frankincense</name> And <foreign xml:lang="la">Popanum</foreign> is made; for in the fire Both these, when placed, divinity accepts.</p>
   </quote>

   <milestone unit="section" n="18"/>

   <p>On this account also, <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">earthen</name>, <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">wooden</name>, and <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">wicker</name> vessels were formerly used, and especially in public sacrifices, the ancients being persuaded that divinity is delighted with things of this kind. Whence, even now, the most ancient vessels, and which are made of <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">wood</name>, are thought to be more divine, both on account of the matter and the simplicity of the art by which they were fashioned. It is said, therefore, that <persName>Aeschylus</persName>, on his brother's asking him to write a Paean in honour of <name type="deity">Apollo</name>, replied, that the best Paean was written by <persName>Tynnichus</persName>; and that if his composition were to be compared with that of Tynnichus, the same thing would take place as if new were compared with ancient statues. For the latter, though they are simple in their formation, are conceived to be divine; but the former, though they are most accurately elaborated, produce indeed admiration, but are not believed to possess so much of a divine nature. Hence <persName>Hesiod</persName>, praising the law of ancient sacrifices, very properly says,</p>

   <quote>
      <p>Your country's rites in sacrifice observe: [In pious works] the ancient law is best.</p>
   </quote>
</div>
<div type="section" n="19">
   <p>But those who have written concerning sacred operations and sacrifices, admonish us to be accurate in preserving what pertains to the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">popana</name>, because these are more acceptable to the <name type="deity">Gods</name> than the sacrifice which is performed through the mactation of <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">animals</name>.</p>
   <quote>
      <p><persName>Sophocles</persName> also, in describing a sacrifice which is pleasing to divinity, says in his <foreign xml:lang="en">Polyidus</foreign>:</p>
      <lg>
         <l>The skins of <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">sheep</name> in sacrifice were used,</l>
         <l>Libations too of <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">wine</name>, <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">grapes</name> well preserved,</l>
         <l>And <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">fruits</name> collected in a heap of every kind;</l>
         <l>The <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">olive</name>'s <foreign xml:lang="en">pinguid</foreign> juice, and waxen work</l>
         <l>Most variegated, of the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">yellow bee</name>.</l>
      </lg>
   </quote>
</div>
Voici l'encodage TEI P5 strictement conforme aux règles Zoomathia pour le texte de Porphyre, en respectant la structure demandée et en mettant l'accent sur les entités zoologiques (bien que le texte n'en contienne pas explicitement dans cet extrait) :


<div type="chapter" n="24">
   <p>Formerly, also, there were venerable monuments in <placeName>Delos</placeName> of those who came from the <persName>Hyperboreans</persName>, bearing handfuls [of fruits]. It is necessary, therefore, that, being purified in our manners, we should make oblations, offering to the <name type="deity">Gods</name> those sacrifices which are pleasing to them, and not such as are attended with great expense.</p>
   <p>Now, however, if a man's body is not pure and invested with a splendid garment, he does not think it is qualified for the sanctity of sacrifice. But when he has rendered his body splendid, together with his garment, though his soul at the same time is not, purified from vice, yet he betakes himself to sacrifice, and thinks that it is a thing of no consequence; as if divinity did not especially rejoice in that which is most divine in our nature, when it is in a pure condition, as being allied to his essence.</p>
   <p>In <placeName>Epidaurus</placeName>, therefore, there was the following inscription on the doors of the temple:</p>
   <quote>
      <p>Into an odorous temple, he who goes<br/>
      Should pure and holy be; but to be wise<br/>
      In what to sanctity pertains, is to be pure.</p>
   </quote>
</div>
Voici l'encodage TEI P5 strictement conforme aux règles du projet Zoomathia, en respectant la structure demandée et en encodant toutes les entités nommées zoologiques ou autres :


<div type="section" n="20">
   <p>But that <name type="deity">God</name> is not delighted with the amplitude of sacrifices, but with any casual offering, is evident from this, that of our daily food, whatever it may be that is placed before us, we all of us make an offering to the <name type="deity">Gods</name>, before we have tasted it ourselves; this offering being small indeed, but the greatest testimony of honour to divinity.</p>
   <p>Moreover, <persName>Theophrastus</persName> shows, by enumerating many of the rites of different countries, that the sacrifices of the ancients were from <name type="plant">fruits</name>, and he narrates what pertains to libations in the following manner: "Ancient sacrifices were for the most part performed with sobriety. But those sacrifices are sober in which the libations are made with <name type="plant">water</name>. Afterwards, however, libations were made with <name type="plant">honey</name>. For we first received this liquid <name type="plant">fruit</name> prepared for us by the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">bees</name>. In the third place, libations were made with <name type="plant">oil</name>; and in the fourth and last place with <name type="plant">wine</name>."</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="21">
   <p>These things, however, are testified not only by the pillars which are preserved in <placeName>Cyrbe</placeName> 10, and which contain, as it were, certain true descriptions of the <placeName>Cretan</placeName> sacred rites of the <name type="deity">Corybantes</name>; but also by <persName>Empedocles</persName>, who, in discussing what pertains to sacrifices and theogony, or the generation of the <name type="deity">Gods</name>, says:</p>
   <quote>
      <p>With them nor <name type="deity">Mars</name> nor tumult dire was found,</p>
      <p>Nor <name type="deity">Saturn</name>, <name type="deity">Neptune</name>, or the sovereign <name type="deity">Jove</name>,</p>
      <p>But <name type="deity">Venus</name> [<foreign xml:lang="en">beauty's</foreign>] queen.</p>
   </quote>
   <p>And <name type="deity">Venus</name> is friendship.  Afterwards he adds,</p>
</div>
Voici l'encodage TEI P5 strictement conforme aux règles Zoomathia pour le texte de Porphyre :


<div type="section" n="26">
   <p>With painted <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">animals</name>, and statues once
   Of sacred form, with unguents sweet of smell,
   The fume of <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">frankincense</name> and genuine <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">myrrh</name>,
   And with libations poured upon the ground
   Of yellow <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">honey</name>, <persName>Venus</persName> was propitious made.</p>

   <p>Which ancient custom is still even now preserved by some persons as a certain vestige of the truth.  And in the last place, <persName>Empedocles</persName> says,</p>

   <quote>
      <p>Nor then were altars wet with blood of <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">bulls</name>
      Irrationally slain.</p>
   </quote>
</div>
<div type="chapter" n="22">
   <p>For, as it appears to me, when friendship and a proper sense of the duties pertaining to kindred natures, was possessed by all men, no one slaughtered any living being, in consequence of thinking that other
      <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">animals</name> were allied to him. But when strife, and tumult, every kind of contention, and the principle of war, invaded mankind, then, for the first time, no one in reality spared any one of his kindred natures. The following particulars, likewise, ought to be considered:</p>
   <p>For, as though there is an affinity between us and noxious men, who, as it were, by a certain impetus of their own nature and depravity, are incited to injure anyone they may happen to meet, yet we think it requisite that all of them should be punished and destroyed; thus also, with respect to those irrational
      <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">animals</name> that are naturally malefic and unjust, and who are impelled to injure those that approach them, it is perhaps fit that they should be destroyed.</p>
   <p>But with respect to other
      <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">animals</name> who do not at all act unjustly, and are not naturally impelled to injure us, it is certainly unjust to destroy and murder them, no otherwise than it would be to slay men who are not iniquitous. And this seems to evince that the justice between us and other
      <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">animals</name> does not arise from some of them being naturally noxious and malefic, but others not, as is also the case with respect to men.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="23">
   <p>Are therefore those <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">animals</name> to be sacrificed to the <name type="deity">Gods</name> which are thought to be deserving of death? But how can this be possible, if they are naturally depraved? For it is no more proper to sacrifice such as these, than it would be to sacrifice mutilated <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">animals</name>. For thus, indeed, we shall offer the first-fruits of things of an evil nature, but we shall not sacrifice for the sake of honouring the <name type="deity">Gods</name>. Hence, if <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">animals</name> are to be sacrificed to the <name type="deity">Gods</name>, we should sacrifice those that are perfectly innoxious. It is however acknowledged, that those <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">animals</name> are not to be destroyed who do not at all injure us, so that neither are they to be sacrificed to the <name type="deity">Gods</name>. If, therefore, neither these, nor those that are noxious, are to be sacrificed, is it not evident that we should abstain from them more than from any thing else, and that we should not sacrifice any one of them, though it is fit that some of them should be destroyed?</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="24">
   <p>To which may be added, that we should sacrifice to the <name type="deity">Gods</name> for the sake of three things, viz. either for the sake of honouring them, or of testifying our gratitude, or through our want of good. For, as we offer first-fruits to good men, thus also we think it is necessary that we should offer them to the <name type="deity">Gods</name>. But we honour the <name type="deity">Gods</name>, either exploring the means of averting evils, and obtaining good, or when we have been previously benefited, or in order that we may obtain some present advantage and assistance, or merely for the purpose of venerating the goodness of their nature. So that if the first-fruits of <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">animals</name> are to be</p>
</div>
<div type="chapter" n="30">
  <p>offered to the <name type="deity">Gods</name>, some of them for the sake of this are to be sacrificed. For whatever we sacrifice, we sacrifice for the sake of some one of the above mentioned particulars. Is it therefore to be thought that <name type="deity">God</name> is honoured by us, when we are directly seen to act unjustly through the first-fruits which we offer to him? Or will he not rather think that he is dishonoured by such a sacrifice, in which, by immolating <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">animals</name> that have not at all injured us, we acknowledge that we have acted unjustly.</p>
  <p>So that no one of other <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">animals</name> is to be sacrificed for the sake of honouring divinity. Nor yet are they to be sacrificed for the purpose of testifying our gratitude to the <name type="deity">Gods</name>. For he who makes a just retribution for the benefits he has received, ought not to make it by doing an injury to certain other <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">animals</name>.</p>
  <p>For he will no more appear to make a retribution than he who, plundering his neighbour of his property, should bestow it on another person for the sake of honour. Neither are <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">animals</name> to be sacrificed for the sake of obtaining a certain good of which we are in want.</p>
  <p>For he who endeavours to be benefited by acting unjustly, is to be suspected as one who would not be grateful even when he is benefited. So that <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">animals</name> are not to be sacrificed to the <name type="deity">Gods</name> through the expectation of deriving advantage from the sacrifice.</p>
  <p>For he who does this, may perhaps elude men, but it is impossible that he can elude <name type="deity">divinity</name>. If, therefore, we ought to sacrifice for the sake of a cer</p>
</div>
<p>tain thing, but this is not to be done for the sake of any of the before mentioned particulars, it is evident that <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">animals</name> ought not to be sacrificed.</p>
Voici l'encodage TEI P5 strictement conforme à vos exigences pour le texte de Porphyre, avec une attention particulière aux entités nommées zoologiques et aux règles de structure :


<div type="section" n="25">
   <p>For, by endeavouring to obliterate the truth of these things through the pleasures which we derive from sacrifices, we deceive ourselves, but cannot deceive <name type="deity">divinity</name>.</p>
   <p>Of those <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">animals</name>, therefore, which are of an ignoble nature, which do not impart to our life any superior utility, and which do not afford us any pleasure, we do not sacrifice any one to the <name type="deity">Gods</name>.</p>
   <p>For who ever sacrificed <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">serpents</name>, <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">scorpions</name>, and <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">apes</name>, or any one of such like <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">animals</name>?</p>
   <p>But we do not abstain from any one of those <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">animals</name> which afford a certain utility to our life, or which have something in them that contributes to our enjoyments; since we, in reality, cut their throats, and excoriate them, under the patronage of <name type="deity">divinity</name> 11.</p>
   <p>For we sacrifice to the <name type="deity">Gods</name> <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">oxen</name> and <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">sheep</name>, and besides these, <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">stags</name> and <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">birds</name>, and fat <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">hogs</name>, though they do not at all participate of purity, but afford us delight.</p>
   <p>And of these <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">animals</name>, indeed, some, by co-operating with our labours, afford assistance to our life, but others supply us with</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="33">
   <p>food, or administer to our other wants. But those which effect neither of these, yet, through the enjoyment which is derived from them, are slain by men in sacrifices similarly with those who afford us utility.</p>
   <p>We do not, however, sacrifice <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">asses</name> or <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">elephants</name>, or any other of those <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">animals</name> that co-operate with us in our labours, but are not subservient to our pleasure; though, sacrificing being excepted, we do not abstain from such like <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">animals</name>, but we cut their throats on account of the delight with which the deglutition of them is attended; and of those which are fit to be sacrificed, we do not sacrifice such as are acceptable to the <name type="deity">Gods</name>, but such as in a greater degree gratify the desires of <persName>men</persName>; thus testifying against ourselves, that we persist in sacrificing to the <name type="deity">Gods</name>, for the sake of our own pleasure, and not for the sake of gratifying the <name type="deity">Gods</name>.</p>
</div>
Voici l'encodage TEI P5 strictement conforme à vos règles pour le passage de Porphyre (Porphyrius), *Περὶ ἀποχῆς τῶν ἐμψύχων* (De l'abstinence des êtres animés), section 34/91 :


<div type="chapter" n="34">
   <p>But of the <persName>Syrians</persName>, the <persName>Jews</persName> indeed, through the sacrifice which they first made, even now, <quote>says <persName>Theophrastus</persName></quote>, sacrifice <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">animals</name>, and if we were persuaded by them to sacrifice in the same way that they do, we should abstain from the deed. For they do not feast on the flesh of the sacrificed <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">animals</name>, but having thrown the whole of the victims into the fire, and poured much <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">honey</name> and <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">wine</name> on them during the night, they swiftly consume the sacrifice, in order that the all-seeing <name type="deity">sun</name> may not become a spectator of it. And they do this, fasting during all the intermediate days, and through the whole of this time, as belonging to the class of philosophers, and also discourse with each other about the divinity</p>
   <milestone unit="section" n="12"/>
   <p>But in the night, they apply themselves to the theory of the <foreign xml:lang="la">stars</foreign>, surveying them, and through prayers invoking <name type="deity">God</name>. For these make offerings both of other <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">animals</name> and themselves, doing this from necessity, and not from their own will. The truth of this, however, may be learnt by any one who directs his attention to the <persName>Egyptians</persName>, the most learned of all men; who are so far from slaying other <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">animals</name>, that they make the images of these to be imitations of the <name type="deity">Gods</name>; so adapted and allied do they conceive these to be both to <name type="deity">Gods</name> and men.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="35">
   <p>For at first, indeed, sacrifices of fruits were made to the <name type="deity">Gods</name>; but, in the course of time, men becoming negligent of sanctity, in consequence of fruits being scarce, and through the want of legitimate nutriment, being impelled to eat each other, then supplicating divinity with many prayers, they first began to make oblations of themselves to</p>
</div>
Voici l'encodage TEI P5 strictement conforme aux règles du projet Zoomathia pour le passage de Porphyre :


<div type="chapter" n="36">
  <milestone unit="section" n="36.1"/>
  <p>the Gods, not only consecrating to the <name type="deity">divinities</name> whatever among their possessions was most beautiful, but, proceeding beyond this, they sacrificed those of their own species.</p>
  <p>Hence, even to the present time, not only in <placeName>Arcadia</placeName>, in the <placeName>Lupercal</placeName> festivals, and in <placeName>Carthage</placeName>, men are sacrificed in common to <name type="deity">Saturn</name>, but periodically, also, for the sake of remembering the legal institute, they sprinkle the altars of those of the same tribe with blood, although the rites of their sacrifices exclude, by the voice of the crier, him from engaging in them who is accused of human slaughter.</p>
  <milestone unit="section" n="36.2"/>
  <p>Proceeding therefore from hence, they made the bodies of other <name type="animal">animals</name> supply the place of their own in sacrifices, and again, through a satiety of legitimate nutriment, becoming oblivious of piety, they were induced by voracity to leave nothing untasted, nothing un-devoured.</p>
  <p>And this is what now happens to all men with respect to the aliment from fruits. For when, by the assumption of them, they have alleviated their necessary indigence, then searching for a superfluity of satiety, they labour to procure many things for food which are placed beyond the limits of temperance.</p>
  <milestone unit="section" n="36.3"/>
  <p>Hence, as if they had made no ignoble sacrifices to the <name type="deity">Gods</name>, they proceeded also to taste the <name type="animal">animals</name> which they immolated; and from this, as a principle of the deed, the eating of <name type="animal">animals</name> became an addition to men to the nutriment derived from fruits.</p>
  <p>As, therefore, antiquity offered the first produce of fruits to the <name type="deity">Gods</name>,</p>
</div>
Voici l'encodage TEI P5 strictement conforme aux règles Zoomathia pour le passage fourni :


<p>and gladly, after their pious sacrifice, tasted what they offered, thus also, when they sacrificed the firstlings of <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">animals</name> to the <name type="deity">divinities</name>, they thought that the same thing ought to be done by them, though ancient piety did not ordain these particulars after this manner, but venerated each of the <name type="deity">Gods</name> from <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">fruits</name>. For with such oblations, both nature, and every sense of the human soul, are delighted.</p>

<p>No altar then was wet with blood of <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">bulls</name>
Irrationally slain; but this was thought
To be of every impious deed the worst,
Limbs to devour of <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">brutes</name> deprived of life.</p>
<div type="chapter" n="28">
   <p>The truth of this may also be perceived from the altar which is even now preserved about <placeName>Delos</placeName>, which, because no <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">animal</name> is brought to, or is sacrificed upon it, is called the altar of the pious. So that the inhabitants not only abstain from sacrificing <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">animals</name>, but they likewise conceive, that those who established, are similarly pious with those who use the altar.</p>
   <p>Hence, the <persName>Pythagoreans</persName> having adopted this mode of sacrifice, abstained from <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">animal</name> food through the whole of life. But when they distributed to the <name type="deity">Gods</name> a certain <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">animal</name> instead of themselves, they merely tasted of it, living in reality without touching other <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">animals</name>.</p>
   <p>We, however, do not act after this manner; but being filled with <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">animal</name> diet, we have arrived at this manifold illegality in our life by slaughtering <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">animals</name>, and using them for food.</p>
   <p>For neither is it proper that the altars of the <name type="deity">Gods</name> should be defiled with murder, nor that food of this kind should be touched by men, as neither is it fit that men should eat one another; but the precept which is still preserved at <placeName>Athens</placeName>, should be obeyed through the whole of life.</p>
</div>
Voici l'encodage TEI P5 strictement conforme à vos règles pour le texte de Porphyre sur les animaux :


<div type="section" n="29">
   <p>For formerly, as we have before observed, when men sacrificed to the <name type="deity">Gods</name> fruits and not <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">animals</name>, and did not assume the latter for food, it is said, that a common sacrifice being celebrated at <placeName>Athens</placeName>, one <persName>Diomus</persName>, or <persName>Sopater</persName>, who was not a native, but cultivated some land in <placeName>Attica</placeName>, seizing a sharp axe which was near to him, and being excessively indignant, struck with it an <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">ox</name>, who, coming from his labour, approached to a table, on which were openly placed cakes and other offerings which were to be burnt as a sacrifice to the <name type="deity">Gods</name>, and ate some, but trampled on the rest of the offerings.</p>
   <p>The <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">ox</name>, therefore, being killed, <persName>Diomus</persName>, whose anger was now appeased, at the same time perceived what kind of deed he had perpetrated. And the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">ox</name>, indeed, he buried. But embracing a voluntary banishment, as if he had been accused of impiety, he fled to <placeName>Crete</placeName>.</p>
   <p>A great dryness, however, taking place in the <placeName>Attic</placeName> land from vehement heat, and a dreadful sterility of fruit, and the <name type="deity">Pythian deity</name> being in consequence of it consulted by the general consent, the <name type="deity">God</name> answered, that the <placeName>Cretan</placeName> exile must expiate the crime; and that, if the murderer was punished, and the statue of the slain <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">ox</name> was erected in the place in which it fell, this would be beneficial both to those who had and those who had not tasted its flesh.</p>
   <p>An inquiry therefore being made into the affair, and <persName>Sopater</persName>, together with the deed, having been discovered, he, thinking that he should be liberated from the difficulty in which</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="40">
   <p>he was now involved, through the accusation of impiety, if the same thing was done by all men in common, said to those who came to him, that it was necessary an <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">ox</name> should be slain by the city. But, on their being dubious who should strike the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">ox</name>, he said that he would undertake to do it, if they would make him a citizen, and would be partakers with him of the slaughter. This, therefore, being granted, they returned to the city, and ordered the deed to be accomplished in such a way as it is performed by them at present, [and which was as follows:]</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="30">
   <p>They selected virgins who were drawers of water; but these brought water for the purpose of sharpening an axe and a knife. And these being sharpened, one person gave the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">ox</name>, another struck with it the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">ox</name>,
      <milestone unit="section" n="62"/> and a third person cut the throat of the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">ox</name>. But after this, having excoriated the animal, all that were present ate of its flesh. These things therefore being performed, they sewed up the hide of the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">ox</name>, and having stuffed it with straw, raised it upright in the same form which it had when alive, and yoked it to a plough, as if it was about to work with it. Instituting also a judicial process, respecting the slaughter of the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">ox</name>, they cited all those who were partakers of the deed, to defend their conduct. But as the drawers of water accused those who sharpened the axe and the knife, as more culpable than themselves, and those who sharpened these instruments accused him who gave the axe, and he accused him who cut the throat of the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">ox</name>, and this last person accused the</p>
</div>
<p>knife,---hence, as the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">knife</name> could not speak, they condemned it as the cause of the slaughter.</p>
<p>From that time also, even till now, during the festival sacred to <name type="deity">Jupiter</name>, in the <placeName>Acropolis</placeName>, at <placeName>Athens</placeName>, the sacrifice of an <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">ox</name> is performed after the same manner.</p>
<p>For, placing cakes on a brazen table, they drive <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">oxen</name> round it, and the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">ox</name> that tastes of the cakes that are distributed on the table, is slain.</p>
<p>The race likewise of those who perform this, still remains.</p>
<p>And all those, indeed, who derive their origin from <persName>Sopater</persName> are called <foreign xml:lang="en">boutupoi</foreign> [i.e. slayers of <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">oxen</name>]; but those who are descended from him that drove the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">ox</name> round the table, are called <foreign xml:lang="en">kentriadai</foreign>, [or stimulators.] And those who originate from him that cut the throat of the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">ox</name>, are denominated <foreign xml:lang="en">daitroi</foreign>, [or dividers,] on account of the banquet which takes place from the distribution of flesh.</p>
<p>But when they have filled the hide, and the judicial process is ended, they throw the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">knife</name> into the sea.</p>
Voici l'encodage TEI P5 strictement conforme à vos règles pour le texte de Porphyre (Porphyrius), *Περὶ ἀποχῆς τῶν ἐμψύχων* (De l'abstinence des animaux), section 43/91 :


<div type="section" n="43">
   <p>Hence, neither did the ancients conceive it to be holy to slay <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">animals</name> that co-operated with us in works beneficial to our life, and we should avoid doing this even now. And as formerly it was not pious for men to injure these <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">animals</name>, so now it should be considered as unholy to slay them for the sake of food.</p>
   <p>If, however, this is to be done from motives of religious reference of the <name type="deity">Gods</name>, yet every passion or affection which is essentially produced from bodies is to be rejected, in order that we may not procure food from improper substances, and thus have an incentive to violence as the intimate associate of our life.</p>
   <p>For by such a rejection we shall, at least, all of us derive great benefit in what pertains to be our mutual security, if we do not in anything else. For those whose sense is averse to the destruction of <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">animals</name> of a species different from their own, will evidently abstain from injuring those of their own kind.</p>
   <p>Hence it would perhaps have been best, if men in after-times had immediately abstained from slaughtering these <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">animals</name>; but since no one is free from error, it remains for posterity to take away by purifications the crime of their ancestors, respecting nutriment.</p>
   <p>This, however, will be effected, if, placing before our eyes, the dire nature of such conduct, we exclaim with <persName>Empedocles</persName>:</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="44">
   <p>Ah me, while yet exempt from such a crime,</p>
   <p>Why was I not destroyed by cruel <name type="time">Time</name>,</p>
   <p>Before these lips began the guilty deed,</p>
   <p>On the dire nutriment of <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">flesh</name> to feed?</p>
   <milestone unit="section" n="44"/>
   <p>For in those only the appropriate sense sympathetically grieves for errors that have been committed, who endeavour to find a remedy for the evils with which they are afflicted; so that every one, by offering pure and holy sacrifices to the <name type="deity">divinity</name>, may through sanctity obtain the greatest benefits from the <name type="deity">Gods</name>.</p>
</div>
Voici l'encodage TEI P5 strictement conforme à vos exigences pour le texte de Porphyre (Porphyrius), extrait de *Περὶ ἀποχῆς τῶν ἐμψύχων* (De l'abstinence des animaux) :


<div type="chapter" n="32">
   <p>But the benefit derived from fruits is the first and the greatest of all others, and which, as soon as they are matured, should alone be offered to the <name type="deity">Gods</name>, and to <name type="earth">Earth</name>, by whom they are produced. For she is the common <foreign xml:lang="la">Vesta</foreign> of <name type="deity">Gods</name> and men; and it is requisite that all of us, reclining on her surface, as on the bosom of our mother and nurse, should celebrate her divinity, and love her with a parental affection, as the source of our existence.</p>
   <p>For thus, when we exchange this life for another, we shall again be thought worthy of a residence in the heavens, and of associating with all the celestial <name type="deity">Gods</name>, whom, now beholding <milestone unit="section" n="13"/>, we ought to venerate with those fruits of which they are the causes, sacrificing indeed to them from all these, when they have arrived at maturity, but not conceiving all of us to be sufficiently worthy to sacrifice to the <name type="deity">Gods</name>.</p>
   <p>For as all things are not to be sacrificed to the <name type="deity">Gods</name>, so neither perhaps are the <name type="deity">Gods</name> gratified by the sacrifice of everyone. This, therefore, is the substance of the arguments adduced by <persName>Theophrastus</persName>, to show that <name type="animal">animals</name> ought not to be sacrificed; exclusive of the interspersed fabulous narrations, and a few things which we have added to what he has said.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="33">
   <p>I, however, shall not attempt to dissolve the legal institutes which the several nations have established. For it is not my design at present to speak about a polity.</p>
   <p>But as the laws by which we are governed permit us to venerate <name type="deity">divinity</name> by things of the most simple, and of an inanimate nature, hence, selecting that which is the least costly, let us sacrifice according to the law of the city, and endeavour to offer an appropriate sacrifice, approaching with consummate purity to the <name type="deity">Gods</name>.</p>
   <p>In short, if the oblation of first-fruits is of any value, and is an acknowledgment of thanks for the benefits which we receive, it will be most irrational to abstain ourselves from <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">animals</name>, and yet offer the first-fruits of these to the <name type="deity">Gods</name>.</p>
   <p>For neither are the <name type="deity">Gods</name> worse than we are, so as to be in want of those things of which we are not indigent, nor is it holy to offer the first-fruits of that nutriment from which we ourselves abstain.</p>
   <p>For we find it is usual with men, that, when they refrain from <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">animal food</name>, they do not make oblations of <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">animals</name>; but that they offer to the <name type="deity">Gods</name> the first-fruits of what they themselves eat.</p>
   <p>Hence also it is now fit, that he who abstains from <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">animals</name> should offer the first-fruits of things which he touches [for the purpose of food].</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="34">
   <p>Let us therefore also sacrifice, but let us sacrifice in such a manner as is fit, offering different sacrifices to different powers;<note n="14">to the God indeed who is above all things, as a certain wise man said</note>, neither sacrificing with incense, nor consecrating any thing sensible. For there is nothing material, which is not immediately impure to an immaterial nature. Hence, neither is vocal language, nor internal speech, adapted to the highest God, when it is defiled by any passion of the soul; but we should venerate him in profound silence with a pure soul, and with pure conceptions about him. It is necessary, therefore, that being conjoined with and assimilated to him, we should offer to him, as a sacred sacrifice, the elevation of our intellect, which offering will be both a hymn and our salvation. In an impassive contemplation, therefore, of this divinity by the soul, the sacrifice to him is effected in perfection;</p>
</div>
Voici l'encodage TEI P5 strictement conforme à vos règles pour le texte de Porphyre (Porphyrius), en respectant la structure demandée et en identifiant les entités nommées Zoomathia :


<div type="section" n="48">
   <milestone unit="section" n="48"/>
   <p>but to his progeny, the intelligible Gods, hymns, orally enunciated, are to be offered. For to each of the divinities, a sacrifice is to be made of the first-fruits of the things which <name type="deity">he</name> bestows, and through which <name type="deity">he</name> nourishes and preserves us. As therefore, the husbandman offers handfuls of the fruits and berries which the season first produces; thus also we should offer to the <name type="deity">divinities</name> the first-fruits of our conceptions of their transcendent excellence, giving them thanks for the contemplation which <name type="deity">they</name> impart to us, and for truly nourishing us through the vision of themselves, which <name type="deity">they</name> afford us, associating with, appearing to, and shining upon us, for our salvation.</p>

   <p>35. Now, however, many of those who apply themselves to philosophy are unwilling to do this; and, pursuing renown rather than honouring divinity, they are busily employed about statues, neither considering whether they are to be reverenced or not, nor endeavouring to learn from those who are divinely wise, to what extent, and to what degree, it is requisite to proceed in this affair. We, however, shall by no means contend with these, nor are we very desirous of being well instructed in a thing of this kind; but imitating holy and ancient men, we offer to the <name type="deity">Gods</name>, more than anything else, the first-fruits of contemplation, which <name type="deity">they</name> have imparted to us, and by the use of which we become partakers of true salvation.</p>
</div>
Voici l'encodage TEI P5 strictement conforme à vos exigences pour le texte de Porphyre, en respectant toutes les règles et priorités Zoomathia :


<div type="section" n="36">
   <p>The Pythagoreans, therefore, diligently applying themselves to the study of numbers and lines, sacrificed for the most part from these to the Gods, denominating, indeed, a certain number <name type="deity">Minerva</name>, but another <name type="deity">Diana</name>, and another <name type="deity">Apollo</name>: and again, they called one number justice, but another temperance <milestone unit="section" n="15"/>.</p>
   <p>In diagrams also they adopted a similar mode. And thus, by offerings of this kind, they rendered the Gods propitious to them, so as to obtain of them the object of their wishes, by the things which they dedicated to, and the names by which they invoked them.</p>
   <p>They likewise frequently employed their aid in divination, and if they were in want of a certain thing for the purpose of some investigation. In order, therefore to affect this, they made use of the Gods within the heavens, both the erratic and non-erratic, of all of whom it is requisite to consider the <name type="deity">sun</name> as the leader; but to rank the <name type="deity">moon</name> in the second place; and we should conjoin with these <name type="deity">fire</name>, in the third place, from its</p>
</div>
Voici l'encodage TEI P5 strictement conforme à vos règles pour le passage de Porphyre (Porphyrius) :


<div type="section" n="66">
   <p>alliance to them, as the theologist <persName>16</persName> says. He also says that no <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">animal</name> is to be sacrificed; but that first-fruits are to be offered from meal and honey, and the <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">vegetable</name> productions of the earth. He adds, that fire is not to be enkindled on a hearth defiled with gore; and asserts other things of the like kind.</p>
   <p>For what occasion is there to transcribe all he says? For he who is studious of piety knows, indeed, that to the <name type="deity">Gods</name> no <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">animal</name> is to be sacrificed, but that a sacrifice of this kind pertains to <foreign xml:lang="en">daemons</foreign>, and other powers, whether they are beneficent, or depraved<note n="1">1</note>. He likewise knows who those are that ought to sacrifice to these, and to what extent they ought to proceed in the sacrifices which they make.</p>
   <p>Other things, however, will be passed over by me in silence. But what some <persName>Platonists</persName> have divulged, I shall lay before the reader, in order that the things proposed to be discussed, may become manifest to the intelligent.</p>
   <p>What they have unfolded, therefore, is as follows:</p>
</div>
Voici l'encodage TEI P5 strictement conforme à vos règles pour le texte de Porphyre (Porphyrius), en respectant la structure demandée et en priorisant l'identification des entités nommées Zoomathia :


<div type="book" n="51">
  <milestone unit="section" n="37"/>
  <p>The first <name type="deity">God</name> being incorporeal, immoveable, and impartible, and neither subsisting in any thing, nor restrained in his energies, is not, as has been before observed, in want of any thing external to himself, as neither is the soul of the world; but this latter, containing in itself the principle of that which is triply divisible, and being naturally self-motive, is adapted to be moved in a beautiful and orderly manner, and also to move the body of the world, according to the most excellent reasons [i.e. productive principles or powers]. It is, however, connected with and comprehends <name type="animal">body</name>, though it is itself incorporeal, and liberated from the participation of any passion.</p>

  <p>To the remaining <name type="deity">Gods</name>, therefore, to the <placeName>world</placeName>, to the inerratic and erratic <name type="animal">stars</name>, who are visible <name type="deity">Gods</name>, consisting of soul and <name type="animal">body</name>, thanks are to be returned after the above-mentioned manner, through sacrifices from inanimate natures. The multitude, therefore, of those invisible beings remains for us, whom <persName>Plato</persName> indiscriminately calls</p>

  <p><name type="animal">daemons</name> <foreign xml:lang="la">17</foreign>; but of these, some being denominated by <persName>men</persName>, obtain from them honours, and other religious observances, similar to those which are paid to the <name type="deity">Gods</name>; but others, who for the most part are not explicitly denominated, receive an occult religious reverence and appellation from certain persons in <placeName>villages</placeName> and certain <placeName>cities</placeName>; and the remaining multitude is called in common by the</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="52">
   <p>name of <name type="deity">daemons</name>. The general persuasion, however, respecting all these invisible beings, is this, that if they become angry through being neglected, and deprived of the religious reverence which is due to them, they are noxious to those by whom they are thus neglected, and that they again become beneficent, if they are appeased by prayers, supplications, and sacrifices, and other similar rites.</p>
</div>
Voici l'encodage TEI P5 strictement conforme à vos exigences pour le texte de Porphyre (Porphyrius) :


<div type="chapter" n="38">
   <p>But the confused notion which is formed of these beings, and which has proceeded to great crimination, necessarily requires that the nature of them should be distinguished according to reason. For perhaps it will be said, that it is requisite to show whence the error concerning them originated among men. The distinction, therefore, must be made after the following manner. Such souls as are the progeny of the whole soul of the universe, and who govern the great parts of the region under the moon, these, being incumbent on a pneumatic substance or spirit, and ruling over it conformably to reason, are to be considered as good daemons, who are diligently employed in causing every thing to be beneficial to the subjects of their government, whether they preside over certain <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">animals</name>, or fruits, which are arranged under their inspective care, or over things which subsist for the sake of these, such as showers of rain, moderate winds, serene weather, and other things which co-operate with these, such as the good temperament of the seasons of the year. They are also our leaders in the attainment of music, and the whole of erudition, and likewise of medicine and gymnastic, and of every thing else similar to these. For it is impossible that these daemons should impart utility, and yet become, in the very same things, the causes of what is detrimental. Among these two, those transporters, as <persName>Plato</persName> calls them, <quote>[in his Banquet]</quote> are to be enumerated, who announce the affairs of men to th</p>
</div>
<div type="chapter" n="54">
   <p>e Gods, and the will of the Gods to men; carrying our prayers, indeed, to the Gods as judges, but oracularly unfolding to us the exhortations and admonitions of the Gods. But such souls as do not rule over the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">pneumatic</name> substance with which they are connected, but for the most part are vanquished by it; these are vehemently agitated and borne along [in a disorderly manner,] when the irascible motions and the desires of the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">pneumatic</name> substance, received an impetus. These souls, therefore, are indeed <name type="deity">daemons</name>, but are deservedly called malefic <name type="deity">daemons</name>.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="39">
   <p>All these being, likewise, and those who possess a contrary power, are invisible, and perfectly imperceptible by human senses; for they are not surrounded with a solid body, nor are all of them of one form, but they are fashioned in numerous figures.
   The forms, however, which</p>
</div>
Voici l'encodage TEI P5 strictement conforme à vos exigences pour le texte de Porphyre, avec une attention particulière aux entités nommées Zoomathia et à la structure demandée :


<div type="book" n="56">
  <p>characterize their pneumatic substance, at one time become apparent, but at another are invisible. Sometimes also those that are malefic, change their forms; but the pneumatic substance, so far as it is corporeal, is passive and corruptible: and though, because it is thus bound by the souls [that are incumbent on it,] the form of it remains for a long time, yet it is not eternal.</p>
  <p>For it is probable that something continually flows from it, and also that it is nourished. The pneumatic substance, therefore, of good <name type="deity">daemons</name>, possesses symmetry, in the same manner as the bodies of the visible <name type="deity">Gods</name>; but the spirit of malefic <name type="deity">dsemons</name> is deprived of symmetry, and in consequence of its abounding in passivity, they are distributed about the terrestrial region.</p>
  <p>Hence, there is no evil which they do not attempt to effect; for, in short, being violent and fraudulent in their manners, and being also deprived of the guardian care of more excellent <name type="deity">dsemons</name>, they make, for the most part, vehement and sudden attacks; sometimes endeavouring to conceal their incursions, but at other times assaulting openly.</p>
  <p>Hence the molestations which are produced by them are rapid; but the remedies and corrections which proceed from more excellent <name type="deity">dsemons</name>, appear to be more slowly effected: for every thing which is good being tractable and equable, proceeds in an orderly manner, and does not pass beyond what is fit.</p>
  <p>By forming this opinion, therefore, you will never fall into that most absurd notion, that</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="57">
   <p>evil may be expected from the good, or good from the evil. For this notion is not truly attended with absurdity, but the multitude, receiving through it the most erroneous conceptions of the <name type="deity">Gods</name>, disseminate them among the rest of mankind.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="40">
   <p>It must be admitted, therefore, that one of the greatest injuries occasioned by malefic <name type="deity">dsemons</name> is this, that though they are the causes of the calamities which take place upon the earth, such as pestilence, sterility, earthquakes, excessive dryness, and the like, yet they endeavour to persuade us, that they are the causes of things the most contrary to these, viz. of fertility, [<quote>salubrity, and elementary peace.</quote>] Hence, they exonerate themselves from blame, and, in the first place, endeavour to avoid being detected as the sources of injury; and, in the next place, they convert us to supplications and sacrifices to the beneficent <name type="deity">Gods</name>, as if they were angry. But they effect these, and things of a similar nature, in consequence of wishing to turn us from right conceptions of the <name type="deity">Gods</name>, and convert us to themselves; for they are delighted with all such as act thus incongruously and discordantly, and, as it were, assuming the persons of other <name type="deity">Gods</name>, they enjoy the effects of our imprudence and folly; conciliating to themselves the good opinion of the vulgar, by inflaming the minds of men with the love of riches, power, and pleasure,</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="59">
   <p>and fulling them with the desire of vain glory, from which sedition, and war, and other things allied to these, are produced. But that which is the most dire of all things, they proceed still farther, and persuade men that similar things are effected by the <name type="deity">greatest Gods</name>, and do not stop till they even subject the most excellent of the <name type="deity">divinities</name> to these calumnies, through whom they say every thing is in perfect confusion. And not only the vulgar are affected in this manner, but not a few also of those who are conversant with <foreign xml:lang="grc">φιλοσοφία</foreign>.</p>
   <p>The cause of this, however, extends equally to philosophers, and the vulgar; for of philosophers, those who do not depart from the prevailing notions, fall into the same error with the multitude; and again, the multitude, on hearing assertions from celebrated men conformable to their own opinions, are in a greater degree corroborated in conceiving things of this kind of the <name type="deity">Gods</name>.</p>
</div>
Voici l'encodage TEI P5 strictement conforme à vos exigences pour le texte de Porphyre (Porphyrius), en respectant toutes les règles et priorités :


<div type="section" n="41">
   <p>For poetry also inflames the opinions of men, by employing a diction adapted to produce astonishment and enchantment, and not only allures the ears, but is also capable of procuring belief in things that are most impossible. At the same time, however, it is requisite to be firmly persuaded, that what is good can never injure, or what is evil can never be beneficial; for, as <persName>Plato</persName> says, it is not the province of heat to refrigerate, but of that which is contrary to heat; and, in like manner, neither is it the province of that which is just to injure. But divinity is naturally the most just of all things; since otherwise he would not be divinity. Hence this power and portion of good is not to be abscinded from beneficent <name type="deity">daemons</name>; for the power which is naturally adapted, and wishes to injure, is contrary to the power which is beneficent: but contraries can never subsist about the same thing. As malefic <name type="animal">daemons</name>, therefore, injure the mortal race in many respects, and sometimes in things of the greatest consequence, good <name type="animal">daemons</name> not only never cease to act conformably to their office, but also, as much as possible, presignify to us the dangers which are impendent from malefic <name type="animal">daemons</name>, unfolding these through dreams, through a divinely inspired soul, and through many other things; so that he who is capable of explaining what is signified, may know and avoid all the perils with which he is threatened. For they indicate [future events] to all men, but every one cannot understand</p>
</div>
Voici l'encodage TEI P5 strictement conforme aux règles et au texte fourni :


<div type="section" n="42">
   <p>what they indicate nor is every one able to read what is written by them; but he alone is able to do this, who has learnt their letters. All enchantment, however, [<quote>[or witchcraft,]</quote>] is effected through <name type="deity">daemons</name> of a contrary nature; for those who perpetrate evil through enchantments, especially venerate these malefic beings, and the power that presides over them.</p>
   <milestone unit="section" n="70"/>
   <p>For they are full of every kind of imagination, and are sufficiently qualified to deceive, through effects of a prodigious nature; and through these, unhappy men procure philtres, and amatory allurements. For all intemperance, and hope of possessing wealth and renown, and especially deception, exist through these, since falsehood is allied to these malevolent beings; for they wish to he considered as <name type="deity">Gods</name>, and the power which presides over them is ambitious to appear to be the greatest <name type="deity">God</name>. These are they that rejoice in libations, and the savour of sacrifices, through which their pneumatic vehicle is fattened; for this vehicle lives through vapours and exhalations, and the life of it is various through various exhalations. It is likewise corroborated by the savour of blood and flesh.</p>
</div>
Voici l'encodage TEI P5 strictement conforme à vos exigences pour le texte de Porphyre, en respectant toutes les règles et priorités :


<div type="section" n="43">
   <p>On this account, a wise and temperate man will be religiously afraid to use sacrifices of this kind, through which he will attract to himself such-like <name type="deity">daemons</name>; but he will endeavour in all possible ways to purify his soul. For these malefic beings do not attack a pure soul, because it is dissimilar to them; but if it is necessary to cities to render them propitious, this is nothing to us. For by these riches, and things external and corporeal, are thought to be good, and their contraries evil; but the smallest attention is paid by them to the good of the soul.</p>
   <p>We however, to the utmost of our ability, endeavour not to be in want of those things which they impart; but all our endeavour is to become similar to <name type="deity">God</name>, and to the [divine] powers with which he is surrounded both from what pertains to the soul, and from externals; and this is effected through an entire liberation from the dominion of the passions, an evolved perception of truly existing beings, and a vital tendency towards them.</p>
   <p>On the other hand, we strive to become dissimilar to depraved men and evil <name type="deity">daemons</name>, and, in short, to every being that rejoices in a mortal and material nature. So that, conformably to what is said by <persName>Theophrastus</persName>, we also shall sacrifice from those things which <name type="deity">theologists</name> permit us to use for this purpose; as well knowing, that by how much the more we neglect to exempt ourselves from the passions of the soul, by so much the more we connect ourselves with a depraved power, and render it</p>
</div>
<p>necessary that he should become propitious to us. For, as theologists say, it is necessary for those who are
bound <milestone unit="section" n="18"/> to things <foreign xml:lang="grc">|71</foreign>
external, and have not yet vanquished their passions, should avert the anger of this [<name type="deity">power</name>]; since, if they do not, there will be no end to their labours.</p>
<div type="section" n="44">
   <p>Thus far what pertains to sacrifices has been elucidated. As we said, however, at first, as it is not entirely necessary, if <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">animals</name> are to be sacrificed, that they are also to be eaten, we shall now show that it is necessary we should not eat them, though it may be sometimes necessary that they should be sacrificed.</p>
   <p>For all theologists agree in this that in sacrifices, which are made for the purpose of averting some evil, the immolated <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">animals</name> are not to be tasted, but are to be used as expiations.</p>
   <p>For, say they, no one should go into the <placeName>city</placeName>, nor into his own <placeName>house</placeName>, till he has first purified his garments, and his body, in rivers, or some fountain.</p>
   <p>So that they order those whom they permit to sacrifice, to abstain from the victims, and to purify themselves before they sacrifice by fasting, and especially by abstaining from <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">animals</name>.</p>
   <p>They add, that purity is the guardian of piety; and is, as it were, a symbol or divine seal, which secures its possessor from the attacks and allurements of evil <name type="deity">daemons</name>.</p>
   <p>For such a one, being contrarily disposed to, and more divine in his operations than those by whom he is attacked, because he is more pure both in his body and in the passions of his soul, remains uninjured, in consequence of being surrounded with purity as with a bulwark.</p>
</div>
Voici l'encodage TEI P5 du texte selon les règles strictes du projet Zoomathia :


<div type="section" n="45">
   <p>Hence a defence of this kind has appeared to be necessary even to <name type="deity">enchanters</name>; though it is not efficacious with them on all occasions. For they invoke evil <name type="deity">daemons</name> for lascivious purposes. So that purity does not belong to <name type="deity">enchanters</name>, but to divine men, and such as are divinely wise; since it everywhere becomes a guard to those that use it, and conciliates them with a divine nature.</p>
   <p>I wish, therefore, that <name type="deity">enchanters</name> would make use of purity continually, for then they would not employ themselves in incantations, because, through this, they would be: deprived of the enjoyment of those things, for the sake of which they act impiously.</p>
   <p>Whence becoming full of passions, and abstaining for a short time from impure food, they are notwithstanding replete with impurity, and suffer the punishment of their illegal conduct towards the whole of things, partly from those whom they irritate, and partly from <name type="deity">Justice</name>, who perceives all mortal deeds and conceptions.</p>
   <p>Both inward,</p>
</div>
<div type="chapter" n="46">
   <milestone unit="section" n="46"/>
   <p>For, indeed, it must not be admitted as necessary in temples, which are consecrated by men to the <name type="deity">Gods</name>, that those who enter into them should have their feet pure, and their shoes free from every stain, but that in the temple of the father [of all], which is this world, it is not proper to preserve our ultimate and cutaneous vestment pure, and to dwell in this temple with an undefiled garment.</p>
   <p>For if the danger consisted only in the defilement of the body, it might, perhaps, be lawful to neglect it. But now, since every sensible body is attended with an efflux of material <foreign xml:lang="grc">δαίμονες</foreign>, hence, together with the impurity produced from flesh and blood, the power which is friendly to, and familiar with, this impurity, is at the same time present through similitude and alliance.</p>
</div>
Voici l'encodage TEI P5 strictement conforme à vos exigences pour le texte de Porphyre (Porphyrius) :


<div type="chapter" n="47">
   <p>Hence theologists have rightly paid attention to abstinence. And these things were indicated to us by a certain
      <persName>Egyptian</persName> 19, who also assigned a most natural cause of them, which was verified by experience. For, since a depraved and irrational soul, when it leaves the body, is still compelled to adhere to it, since the souls also of those men who die by violence, are detained about the body; this circumstance should prevent a man from forcibly expelling his soul from the body. The violent slaughter, therefore, of <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">animals</name>, compels souls to be delighted with the bodies which they have left, but the soul is by no means prevented from being there, where it is attracted by a kindred nature; whence many souls are seen to lament, and some remain about the bodies that are</p>
</div>
Voici l'encodage TEI P5 strictement conforme à vos exigences pour le texte de Porphyre (Porphyrius), *Peri apoches tōn empsuchōn* (De l'abstinence des animaux), section 68/91 :


<div type="section" n="68">
   <p>unburied; which souls are improperly used by enchanters, as subservient to their designs, being compelled by them to occupy the body, or a part of the body, which they have left. Since, therefore, these things were well known to theologists, and they also perceived the nature of a depraved soul, and its alliance to the bodies from which it was divulsed, and the pleasure which it received from a union with them, they very properly avoided <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">animal</name> food, in order that they might not be disturbed by alien souls, violently separated from the body and impure, and which are attracted to things of a kindred nature, and likewise that they might not be impeded by the presence of evil <name type="deity">daemons</name>, in approaching alone [or without being burdened with things of a foreign nature] to the highest <name type="deity">God</name> 20.</p>
   <milestone unit="section" n="48"/>
   <p>For that the nature of a kindred body is attractive of soul, experience abundedly taught these theologists. Hence those who wish to receive into themselves the souls of prophetic <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">animals</name>, swallow the most principal parts of them, such as the hearts of <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">crows</name>, or of <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">moles</name>, or of <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">hawks</name>. For thus they have soul present with, and predicting to them like a <name type="deity">God</name>, and entering into them together with the intromission of the body.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="49">
   <p>Very properly, therefore, will the <persName>philosopher</persName>, and who is also the priest of the <name type="deity">God</name> that is above all things, abstain from all <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">animal</name> food, in consequence of earnestly endeavouring to approach through himself alone to the alone <name type="deity">God</name></p>
   <milestone unit="section" n="21"/>
   <p>without being disturbed by any attendants. Such a one likewise is cautious, as being well acquainted with the necessities of <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">nature</name>. For he who is truly a <persName>philosopher</persName>, is skilled in, and an observer of many things, understands the works of <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">nature</name>, is sagacious, temperate and modest, and is in every respect the saviour of</p>
   <pb n="74"/>
   <p>himself. And as he who is the priest of a certain particular <name type="deity">God</name>, is skilled in placing the statues of that <name type="deity">divinity</name>, and in his orgies, mysteries and the like, thus also he who is the priest of the highest <name type="deity">God</name>, is skilled in the manner in which his statue ought to be fashioned, and in purifications, and other things, through which he is conjoined to this <name type="deity">divinity</name>.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="50">
   <p>But if in the sacred rites which are here, those that are priests and diviners order both themselves and others to abstain from
      <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">sepulchres</name>, from impious men, from menstrual purgations, and from venereal congress, and likewise from base and mournful spectacles, and from those auditions which excite the passions, (because frequently, through those that are present being impure, something appears which disturbs the diviner; on which account it is said, that to sacrifice inopportunely, is attended with greater detriment than gain);
   </p>
   <p>--- if this, therefore, is the case, will he, who is the priest of the father of all things, suffer himself to become the sepulchre of dead bodies? And will such a one, being full of defilement, endeavour to associate with the transcendent God?</p>
   <p>It is sufficient, indeed, that in fruits we assume parts of death, for the support of our present life. This, however, is not yet the place for such a discussion. We must, therefore, still farther investigate what pertains to sacrifices.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="51">
   <p>For some one may say that we shall subvert a great part of divination, viz. that which is effected through an inspection of the viscera, if we abstain from destroying <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">animals</name>. He, therefore, who makes this objection, should also destroy <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">men</name>: for it is said that future events are more apparent in the viscera of <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">men</name> than in those of <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">brutes</name>; and many of the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Barbarians</name> exercise the art of divination through the entrails of <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">men</name>. As, however, it would be an indication of great injustice, and inexhaustible avidity, to destroy those of our own species for the sake of divination, thus also it is unjust for the sake of this to slay an irrational <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">animal</name>. But it does not belong to the present discussion to investigate whether <name type="deity">God</name>, or <foreign xml:lang="grc">δαίμονες</foreign>, or <foreign xml:lang="grc">ψυχή</foreign> liberated from the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">animal</name> [with which it had been connected], exhibit signs of future events to those who explore such signs, through the indications which the viscera afford.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="52">
   <p>Nevertheless, we permit those whose life is rolled about externals, having once acted impiously towards themselves, to be borne along to that which they tend; but we rightly say, that the man who we designate as a <persName>philosopher</persName>, and who is separated from externals, will not</p>
   <milestone unit="section" n="75"/>
   <p>be disturbed by <name type="deity">daemons</name>, nor be in want of <name type="animal">diviners</name>, nor of the viscera of <name type="animal">animals</name>. For he earnestly endeavours to be separated from those things for the sake of which divinations are effected. For he does not betake himself to nuptials, in order that he may molest the diviner about wedlock, or merchandise, or inquiries about a servant, or an increase of property, or any other object of vulgar pursuit. For the subjects of his investigation are not clearly indicated by any diviner or viscera of <name type="animal">animals</name>. But he, as we have said, approaching through himself to the [<foreign xml:lang="grc">τὸν θεὸν</foreign>] <name type="deity">God</name>, who is established in the true inward parts of himself, receives from thence the precepts of eternal life, tending thither by a conflux of the whole of himself, and instead of a diviner praying that he may become a confabulator of the mighty <name type="deity">Jupiter</name>.</p>
</div>
Voici l'encodage TEI P5 strictement conforme à vos exigences pour le texte de Porphyre (Porphyrius), en respectant toutes les règles et priorités Zoomathia :


<div type="section" n="53">
   <p>For if such a one is impelled by some necessary circumstance, there are good <name type="deity">daemons</name>, who, to the man living after this manner, and who is a domestic of divinity, will indicate and prevent, through dreams and symbols, and omens, what may come to pass, and what is necessarily to be avoided.</p>
   <p>For it is only requisite to depart from evil, and to know what is most honourable in the whole of things, and every thing which in the universe is good, friendly, and familiar. But vice, and an ignorance of divine concerns, are dire, through which a man is led to despise and defame things of which he has no knowledge; since nature does not proclaim these particulars with a voice which can be heard by the ears, but being herself intellectual <milestone unit="note" n="22"/>, she initiates through intellect those who venerate her.</p>
   <p>And even though some one should admit the art of divination for the sake of predicting what is future, yet it does not from thence necessarily follow that the flesh of <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">animals</name> is to be eaten; as neither does it follow, that because it is proper to sacrifice to <name type="deity">Gods</name> or <name type="deity">daemons</name>, food from <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">animals</name> is therefore to be introduced.</p>
   <p>For, not only the history which is related by <persName>Theophrastus</persName>, but also many other narrations inform us, that in ancient times <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">men</name> were sacrificed, yet it must not be inferred that on this account <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">men</name> are to be eaten.</p>
   <milestone unit="section" n="76"/>
</div>
Voici l'encodage TEI P5 strictement conforme à vos exigences pour le texte de Porphyre, en respectant toutes les règles et priorités Zoomathia :


<div type="section" n="54">
   <p>And that we do not carelessly assert these things, but that what we have said is abundantly confirmed by history, the following narrations sufficiently testify.</p>
   <p>For in <placeName>Rhodes</placeName>, on the sixth day of June, a man was sacrificed to <name type="deity">Saturn</name>; which custom having prevailed for a long time, was afterwards changed [into a more human mode of sacrificing].</p>
   <p>For one of those men who, by the public decision, had been sentenced to death, was kept in prison till the <foreign xml:lang="la">Saturnalia</foreign> commenced; but as soon as this festival began, they brought the man out of the gates of the city, opposite to the temple of <persName>Aristobulus</persName>, and giving him wine to drink, they cut his throat.</p>
   <p>But in the island which is now called <placeName>Salamis</placeName>, but was formerly denominated <placeName>Coronis</placeName>, in the month according to the <name type="people">Cyprians</name> <foreign xml:lang="la">Aphrodisius</foreign>, a man was sacrificed to <name type="deity">Agraule</name>, the daughter of <persName>Cecrops</persName>, and the nymph <name type="deity">Agraulis</name>.</p>
   <p>And this custom continued till the time of <persName>Diomed</persName>. Afterwards it was changed, so that a man was sacrificed to <persName>Diomed</persName>.</p>
   <p>The temples of <name type="deity">Minerva</name>, of <name type="deity">Agraule</name>, and <persName>Diomed</persName>, were contained in one and the same enclosure.</p>
   <p>The man who was also about to be slain, was first led by young men thrice round the altar, afterwards the priest pierced him with a lance in the stomach, and thus being thrown on the pyre, he was entirely consumed.</p>
</div>
Voici l'encodage TEI P5 strictement conforme aux règles Zoomathia pour le texte fourni :


<div type="section" n="55">
   <p>This sacred institute was, however, abolished by <persName>Diphilus</persName>, the king of <placeName>Cyprus</placeName>, who flourished about the time of <persName>Seleucus</persName>, the theologist. But <persName>Daemon</persName> substituted an <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">ox</name> for a man; thus causing the latter sacrifice to be of equal worth with the former.</p>
   <p><persName>Amosis</persName> also abolished the law of sacrificing men in the Egyptian city <placeName>Heliopolis</placeName>; the truth of which is testified by <persName>Manetho</persName> in his treatise on Antiquity and Piety. But the sacrifice was made to <name type="deity">Juno</name>, and an investigation took place, as if they were endeavouring to find pure <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">calves</name>, and such as were marked by the impression of a seal. Three men also were sacrificed on the day appointed for this purpose, in the place of whom <persName>Amosis</persName> ordered them to substitute three waxen images.</p>
   <p>In <placeName>Chios</placeName> likewise, they sacrificed a man to <name type="deity">Omadius Bacchus</name> <milestone unit="section" n="23"/>, the man being for this purpose torn in pieces; and the same custom, as <persName>Eulpis Carystius</persName> says, was adopted in <placeName>Tenedos</placeName>. To which may be added, that the <persName>Lacedaemonians</persName>, as <persName>Apollodorus</persName> says, sacrificed a man to <name type="deity">Mars</name>.</p>
</div>
Voici l'encodage TEI P5 strictement conforme à vos règles pour le texte de Porphyre, en respectant les entités nommées Zoomathia et la structure demandée :


<pb n="56"/>
<p>Moreover the <name type="people">Phoenicians</name>, in great calamities, either of war, or excessive dryness, or pestilence, sacrificed some one of their dearest friends, who was selected by votes for this purpose. The <name type="people">Phoenician</name> history also is replete with instances of men being sacrificed, which history was written by <persName>Sanchoniatho</persName> in the <foreign xml:lang="grc">Φοινικιστὶ</foreign> tongue, and was interpreted into <foreign xml:lang="grc">Ἑλληνιστὶ</foreign> in eight books, by <persName>Philo Byblius</persName>. But <persName>Ister</persName>, in his collection of the <name type="place">Cretan</name> sacrifices, says that the <name type="people">Curetes</name> formerly sacrificed children to <name type="deity">Saturn</name>. And <persName>Pallas</persName>, who is the best of those who have collected what pertains to the mysteries of <name type="deity">Mithras</name>, says, that under the Emperor <persName>Adrian</persName> the sacrificing of men was nearly totally abolished. For, prior to his time, in <placeName>Laodicea</placeName>, which is in <name type="place">Syria</name>, they anciently sacrificed a virgin to <name type="deity">Minerva</name>, but now they sacrifice a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">stag</name>. The <name type="people">Carthaginians</name> too, who dwell in <name type="place">Libya</name>, formerly sacrificed men; but this custom was abolished by <persName>Iphicrates</persName>. And the <name type="people">Dumatii</name>, a people of <name type="place">Arabia</name>, annually sacrificed a boy, whom they buried under the altar, which was used by them as a statue. But <persName>Phylarchus</persName> narrates, that it was the general custom of all the <name type="people">Greeks</name>, before they went to war, to immolate men. I omit to mention the <name type="people">Thracians</name> and <name type="people">Scythians</name>, and also the <name type="people">Athenians</name>, who slew the daughter of <persName>Erechtheus</persName> and <persName>Praxithea</persName>. And even at present, who is ignorant that in the great city of <placeName>Rome</placeName>, in the festival of <name type="deity">Jupiter Latialis</name>, they cut the throat of a man? Human flesh, however, is not on th</p>
<p>is account to be eaten; though, through a certain necessity, a man should be sacrificed. For, when a famine takes place during a siege some of the besieged feed on each other, yet at the same time those who do so are deemed execrable and the deed is thought to be impious.</p>
Voici l'encodage TEI P5 strictement conforme à vos exigences, en respectant toutes les règles et en priorisant les entités nommées Zoomathia :


<div type="section" n="57">
   <p>After the first war, likewise, waged by the Romans against the Carthaginians, in order to obtain Sicily, when the mercenary soldiers of the Phoenicians revolted, and, together with them, those of Africa deserted,</p>
   <p>Hamilcar, who was surnamed <persName>Barkas</persName>, in attacking the Romans, was reduced to such a scarcity of food, that at first his men ate those that fell in battle; but afterwards, these failing, they ate their captives; in the third place, their servants; and in the last place, they attacked each other, and devoured their fellow-soldiers, who were led to be slaughtered for this purpose by lot.</p>
   <p>But <persName>Hamilcar</persName>, taking those men that were in his power, caused his <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">elephants</name> to trample on such of the soldiers as had acted in this manner, conceiving that it was not holy to suffer them to be any longer mingled with other men; and neither did he admit that</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="79">
   <p>men should be eaten because certain persons had dared to do this; nor <persName>his son Hannibal</persName>, who, when he was leading his army into <placeName>Italy</placeName>, was advised by a certain person to accustom his troops to feed on <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">human flesh</name>, in order that they might never be in want of food.</p>
   <p>It does not follow, therefore, that because famine and war have been the causes of eating other <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">animals</name>, it is also requisite to feed on them for the sake of pleasure; as neither must we admit, that on this account <persName>men</persName> are to be eaten.</p>
   <p>Nor does it follow, that because <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">animals</name> are sacrificed to certain powers, it is also requisite to eat them. For neither do those who sacrifice <persName>men</persName>, on this account, feed on <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">human flesh</name>.</p>
   <p>Through what has been said, therefore, it is demonstrated, that it does not entirely follow that <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">animals</name> are to be eaten because they are sacrificed.</p>
</div>
Voici l'encodage TEI P5 strictement conforme à vos règles pour le texte de Porphyre (Porphyrius), *Peri apoches tōn empsuchōn* (De l'abstinence des animaux), section 80/91 :


<div type="chapter" n="80">
   <p>But that those who had learnt what the nature is of the powers in the universe, offered sacrifices through blood, not to Gods, but to daemons, is confirmed by theologists themselves. For they also assert, that of daemons, some are <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">malefic</name>, but others beneficent, who will not molest us, if we offer to them the first-fruits of those things alone which we eat, and by which we nourish either the soul or the body.</p>
   <p>After, therefore, we have added a few observations more, in order to show that the unperverted conceptions of the multitude accord with a right opinion respecting the <name type="deity">Gods</name>, we shall conclude this book. Those poets, therefore, who are wise, though but in a small degree, say,</p>

   <quote>
      <lg>
         <l>What man so credulous and void of mind,</l>
         <l>What man so ignorant, as to think the <name type="deity">Gods</name></l>
         <l>In fiery bile and fleshless bones rejoice,</l>
         <l>For hungry <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">dogs</name> a nutriment not fit;</l>
         <l>Or that such offerers they will e'er reward?</l>
      </lg>
   </quote>

   <p>But another poet says,</p>

   <quote>
      <lg>
         <l>My offerings to the <name type="deity">Gods</name> from cakes alone</l>
         <l>And frankincense shall be; for not to friends</l>
         <l>But deities my sacrifice I make.</l>
      </lg>
   </quote>
</div>
Voici l'encodage TEI P5 strictement conforme à vos règles pour le texte de Porphyre (Porphyrius) :


<div type="section" n="59">
   <p>Apollo also, when he orders men to sacrifice according to paternal institutes, appears to refer every thing to ancient custom. But the ancient custom of sacrificing was, as we have before shown, with cakes and fruits.</p>
   <p>Hence also, sacrifices were called
      <foreign xml:lang="grc">θυσιαι</foreign> thusiai, and
      <foreign xml:lang="grc">θυηλαι</foreign> thuelai, and
      <foreign xml:lang="grc">θυμελαι</foreign> thumelai, and
      <foreign xml:lang="grc">αυτο το θυειν</foreign>
      <foreign xml:lang="grc">auto to thuein</foreign>, i.e. the act of sacrificing, signified the same thing as
      <foreign xml:lang="grc">του θυμιαν</foreign>
      <foreign xml:lang="grc">ton thumian</foreign>, i.e. to offer incense, and which is now called by us,
      <foreign xml:lang="grc">επιθυειν</foreign> <foreign xml:lang="grc">epithuein</foreign>, i.e. to
      <quote>sacrifice something more</quote>. For what we now call
      <foreign xml:lang="grc">θυειν</foreign> <foreign xml:lang="grc">thuein</foreign>, i.e. to sacrifice, the ancients denominated
      <foreign xml:lang="grc">ερδειν</foreign> <foreign xml:lang="grc">erdein</foreign>, i.e. to perform or make.</p>
   <milestone unit="section" n="79"/>
   <p>They perfect hecatombs of
      <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">bulls</name>, or
      <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">goats</name>,
      <quote>Made to Apollo.</quote>
   </p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="60">
   <p>But those who introduced costliness into sacrifices, were ignorant that, in conjunction with this, they also introduced a swarm of evils, viz., superstition, luxury, an opinion that a divine nature may be corrupted by gifts, and that a compensation may be made by sacrifices for injustice. Or whence do some make an oblation of three <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">animals</name> with gilded horns, but others of hecatombs? And whence did <persName>Olympias</persName>, the mother of <persName>Alexander [the Great]</persName> sacrifice a thousand of each species of <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">animals</name>, unless sumptuousness had at length proceeded to superstition?</p>
   <p>But when the young man was informed that the <name type="deity">Gods</name> rejoiced in magnificent sacrifices, and, as they say, in solemn banquets of <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">oxen</name> and other <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">animals</name>, how, though he was willing to act wisely, was it possible that he could? How also, when he conceived that these sacrifices were acceptable to the <name type="deity">Gods</name>, was it possible he should not fancy that he was permitted to act unjustly, when he might exonerate himself from erroneous conduct through sacrifices?</p>
   <p>But if he had been persuaded that the <name type="deity">Gods</name> have no need of these things, and that they look to the manners of those who approach to them, and conceive that a right opinion of them, and of things themselves, is the greatest sacrifice, how is it possible that he should not have been temperate, holy, and just?</p>
</div>
<div type="chapter" n="61">
   <p>To the Gods, indeed, the most excellent offering is a pure intellect and an impassive soul, and also a moderate oblation of our own property and of other things, and this not negligently, but with the greatest alacrity. For the honours which we pay to the <name type="deity">Gods</name> should be accompanied by the same promptitude as that with which we give the first seat to worthy men, and with which we rise to salute them, and not by the promptitude with which we pay a tribute. For man must not use such language as the following to <name type="deity">God</name>:</p>

   <quote>
      <p>If, O <persName>Philinus</persName>, you recall to mind,<lb/>
      And love me for, the benefits which I<lb/>
      On you conferr'd, 'tis well, since for the sake<lb/>
      Of these alone my bounty was bestow'd.</p>
   </quote>
</div>
<p>For divinity is not satisfied with such assertions as these. <milestone unit="section" n="80"/></p>
<div type="section" n="85">
   <p>Plato says <quote>in his <foreign xml:lang="grc">Laws</foreign></quote>, that it pertains to a good man to sacrifice, and to be always conversant with the <name type="deity">Gods</name> by prayers, votive offerings, sacrifices, and every kind of religious worship; but that to the bad man, much labour about the <name type="deity">Gods</name> is inefficacious and vain. For the good man knows what ought to be sacrificed, and from what it is requisite to abstain; what things are to be offered to divinity; and of what the first-fruits are to be sacrificed; but the bad man exhibiting honours to the <name type="deity">Gods</name> from his own disposition and his own pursuits, acts in so doing more impiously than piously. Hence Plato thought, that a philosopher ought not to be conversant with men of depraved habits; for this is neither pleasing to the <name type="deity">Gods</name>, nor useful to men; but the philosopher should endeavour to change such men to a better condition, and if he cannot effect this, he should be careful that he does not himself become changed into their depravity. He adds, that having entered into the right path, he should proceed in it, neither fearing danger from the multitude nor any other blasphemy which may happen to take place. For it would be a thing of a dire nature, that the <persName>Syrians</persName> indeed will not taste <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">fish</name>, nor the <persName>Hebrews</persName> <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">swine</name> nor most of the <persName>Phoenicians</persName> and <persName>Egyptians</persName> <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">cows</name>; and though many kings have endeavoured to change these customs, yet those that adopt them would rather suffer death, than a transgression of the law [which forbids them to eat these <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">animals</name>]; and yet that we should choose</p>
</div>
Voici l'encodage TEI P5 strictement conforme à vos exigences pour le texte de Porphyre, avec une attention particulière aux entités nommées Zoomathia et à la structure demandée :


<div type="section" n="86">
   <p>to transgress the laws of nature and divine precepts through the fear of men, or of a certain denunciation of evil from them. For the divine choir of <name type="deity">Gods</name>, and <persName>divine men</persName>, may justly be greatly indignant with us, if it perceives us directing our attention to the opinions of depraved men, and idly looking to the terror with which they are attended, though we daily meditate how we may become [philosophically] dead to other things in the present life.</p>

   <milestone unit="section" n="86"/>

   <p>[Footnotes moved to the end and numbered]</p>

   <p>1. <quote>* i.e. The <name type="placeName">Egyptians</name></quote></p>

   <p>2. <quote>* In the original <foreign xml:lang="grc">αρασαμενους</foreign>, which is derived from the verb
<foreign xml:lang="grc">αραομαι</foreign>,
imprecor, maledico; and from hence, according to <persName>Porphyry</persName>, came the word <foreign xml:lang="grc">αραματα</foreign>.</quote></p>

   <p>3. <quote>* i.e.   May be rather called malevolent than unhappy.</quote></p>

   <p>4. <quote>+ <persName>Fabricius</persName> is of opinion that these  <name type="placeName">Thoes</name> are the same with the <name type="placeName">Acrothoitae</name>, mentioned by <persName>Simplicius</persName> in his Comment. in <persName>Epictet</persName>. from <persName>Theophrastus</persName>.</quote></p>

   <p>5. <quote>* In the original, <foreign xml:lang="grc">η γαρ θησια, οσια τις εστιν κατα τουνομα</foreign>.</quote></p>

   <p>6. <quote>* In the original, <foreign xml:lang="grc">και τα μεν παρατιθεναι</foreign>, which <persName>Felicianus</persName> very erroneously renders, "alius sequidem mihi ad vescendum sumo;" but <persName>Valentinus</persName> rightly , "et horum aliqua coram illis
apponere."</quote></p>

   <p>7. <quote>* A round, broad, and thin cake, which was offered in sacrifice to the <name type="deity">Gods</name>.</quote></p>

   <p>8. <quote>+ <persName>Tynnichus</persName>, the <name type="placeName">Chalcidensian</name>, is mentioned by <persName>Plato</persName> in his <persName>Io</persName>.</quote></p>

   <p>9. <quote>* Vid. <persName>Hesiod</persName>. Fragm. v. 169.</quote></p>

   <p>10. <quote>* A city of <name type="placeName">Crete</name>.</quote></p>

   <p>11. <quote>* i.e.   Under the pretext of being patronized by <name type="deity">divinity</name> in so doing.</quote></p>
</div>
Voici l'encodage TEI P5 du texte de Porphyre selon les règles strictes du projet Zoomathia :


<div type="section" n="12">
   <p>* Porphyry, in what he here says of the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Jews</name>, alludes to that sect of them called
   <persName>Essenes</persName>; concerning whom, see the 4th book of this work.</p>
</div>

<div type="section" n="13">
   <p>* In the original, <foreign xml:lang="grc">ους νυν ορωντας τιμαν τουτους</foreign>, κ.τ.λ., instead of which, Reisk proposes to read,
   <foreign xml:lang="grc">ους νυν ουχ ορωντας τιμαν δει ̔̃ϝελ χρἦ τουτοις</foreign>, κ.τ.λ. But the insertion of
   <foreign xml:lang="grc">ουχ</foreign> is most absurd: for the celestial are called the visible <name type="deity">Gods</name>. Thus <persName>Plato</persName>, in the <foreign xml:lang="grc">Timaeus</foreign>, in the speech of the <name type="deity">Demiurgus</name> to the junior or mundane <name type="deity">Gods</name>, who consist of the celestial and sublunary deities, calls the celestial <name type="deity">Gods</name> those that visibly revolve, and the sublunary, those that become apparent when they please:
   <quote>
      <foreign xml:lang="grc">Επει ουν παντες οσοι τε περιπολουσι φανερως, και οσοι φαινονται καθ̕ οσον αν εθελωσι θεοι, γενεσιν εσχον</foreign>, κ.τ.λ.
   </quote>
   conformably, therefore, to the above translation, I read, <foreign xml:lang="grc">ους νυν ορωντας τιμαν δει τουτοις</foreign>, κ.τ.λ. To which may be added, that our author, in paragraph 37, expressly calls the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">stars</name> visible <name type="deity">Gods</name>.</p>
</div>

<div type="section" n="14">
   <p>* In the original, <foreign xml:lang="grc">θυσομον τοινυν κα ημεις· αλλα θυσομεν, ως προσηκει, διαφορους τας θυσιας, ως αν διαφοροις δυναμεσι πρασαγοντες</foreign>. This <persName>Valentinus</persName> erroneously translates as follows: "Sacrificabimus igitur
   etiam et nos, sed prout decet, victimas scilicet eximias potestatibus eximiis adducentes." For
   <foreign xml:lang="grc">διαφορους</foreign> and
   <foreign xml:lang="grc">διαφοροις</foreign>, in this passage, evidently mean different, and not excellent.</p>
</div>
Voici l'encodage TEI P5 strictement conforme aux règles du projet Zoomathia pour le texte de Porphyre :


<pb n="88"/>
<div type="section" n="15">
  <p>* Concerning the appellations which the Pythagoreans gave to <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">numbers</name>, see my Theoretic Arithmetic, in which also the occult meaning of these appellations is unfolded.</p>
</div>

<div type="section" n="16">
  <p>* <quote>"Plotinus ni fallor, aut Plato, sed ille potius"</quote>, says Reisk; but everyone who is at all conversant with Platonic writers, will immediately see that by the theologist, Porphyry means <persName>Orpheus</persName>.</p>
</div>

<div type="section" n="17">
  <p>+ For a more theological account of <name type="deity">daemons</name>, I refer the reader to my translation of the before-mentioned admirable treatise of <persName>Iamblichus</persName> On the Mysteries.</p>
</div>

<div type="section" n="18">
  <p>* In the original, <foreign xml:lang="grc">ως γαρ φασιν οι θεολογοι τοις δεομενοις υπο των εκτος και μηδεπω κρατουσιν των παθων</foreign>, κ.τ.λ. But for
  <foreign xml:lang="grc">δεομενοις</foreign>, it is necessary to read
  <foreign xml:lang="grc">δεδεμενοις</foreign>; and it is evident that both the Latin translators of the work found
  <foreign xml:lang="grc">δεδεμενοις</foreign>
  in their manuscripts. For <persName>Felicianus</persName> has "qui devincti externus rebus sunt," and <persName>Valentinus</persName>, "qui
  rebus externis illigantur." <persName>Reisk</persName>, however, has taken no notice of this error on the printed text.</p>
</div>
Voici l'encodage TEI P5 strictement conforme à vos règles pour le texte de Porphyre, en respectant la structure demandée et les balises spécifiques pour les entités nommées Zoomathia :


<pb n="89"/>
<div type="section" n="19">
  <p>Reisk, with his usual stupidity, where merely verbal emendations are not concerned, says that this Egyptian is <persName>Plotinus</persName>, whose country was <placeName>Lycopolis</placeName>, in <placeName>Egypt</placeName>. But what instance can be adduced, in all antiquity, of the disciple of a philosopher speaking of his preceptor in this indefinite manner? Is it not much more probable that this Egyptian is the priest mentioned by <persName>Porphyry</persName> in his Life of <persName>Plotinus</persName>, who, at the request of a certain friend of <persName>Plotinus</persName>, (which friend was, perhaps, <persName>Porphyry</persName> himself,) exhibited to <persName>Plotinus</persName>, in the temple of <name type="deity">Isis</name>, at <placeName>Rome</placeName>, the familiar daemon, or, in modern language, the guardian angel of that philosopher?</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="20">
  <p>Conformably to this, the <persName>Pythagorean</persName> <persName>Demophilus</persName> beautifully observes,</p>
  <quote>
    <foreign xml:lang="grc">Γυμνος αποσταλεις σοφος, γυμνιτευων καλεσει τον πεμψαντα· μονου γαρ του μη τοις αλλοτριοις πεφορτισμενου επικοος ο θεος.</foreign>
    <cit>
      <quote xml:lang="en">i.e. "The wise man being sent hither naked, should naked invoke him by whom he was sent. For he alone is heard by divinity, who is not burdened with things of a foreign nature."</quote>
    </cit>
  </quote>
</div>
Voici l'encodage TEI P5 strictement conforme aux règles du projet Zoomathia pour le texte de Porphyre, en respectant la structure demandée et les balises d'entités nommées :


<div type="chapter" n="90">
   <milestone unit="section" n="21"/>
   <p>This expression of "approaching alone to the alone God," Porphyry derived from his master, the great <persName>Plotinus</persName>, who divinely concludes his <foreign xml:lang="grc">Enneads</foreign> as follows:</p>
   <p><quote>και ουτω θεων και ανθρωπων θειων και ευδαιμονων βιος, απαλλαγη των αλλων των τῃδε, ανηδονος των τῃδε, φυγη μονου προς μονον</quote> — i.e. "This, therefore, is the life of the <name type="deity">Gods</name>, and of divine and happy men, a liberation from all terrene concerns, a life unaccompanied by human pleasures, and a flight of the alone to the alone.</p>
</div>
<div type="chapter" n="91">
   <milestone unit="section" n="22"/>
   <p><name type="animal">Nature</name>, considered as the last of the causes which fabricate this corporeal and sensible world, "bounds (says <persName>Proclus</persName> in <foreign xml:lang="la">Tim.</foreign>) the progressions of incorporeal essences, and is full of forms and powers, through which she governs mundane affairs. And she is a <name type="deity">Goddess</name>, indeed, considered as deified; but not according to the primary signification of the word. By her summit likewise she comprehends the heavens, but through these rules over the fluctuating empire of generation; and she every where weaves together partial <name type="animal">natures</name> in admirable conjunction with wholes." See more on this subject in my translation of that work.</p>
</div>
Voici l'encodage TEI P5 strictement conforme à vos exigences pour le texte de Porphyre, avec une structure minimale et une attention particulière aux entités nommées Zoomathia :


<div type="section" n="23">
  <p>
    <milestone unit="section" n="23"/>
    <foreign xml:lang="la">* </foreign>This epithet is used in two of the Orphic hymns, viz. in Hymn
    <name type="deity" xml:lang="en">LI</name>. 7., and Hymn
    <name type="deity" xml:lang="en">XXIX</name>. 5. But the following appears to be the reason why
    <name type="deity" xml:lang="en">Bacchus</name> is so called.
    <name type="deity" xml:lang="en">Bacchus</name> is the intellect, and
    <persName>Ippa</persName> the soul of the world, according to the Orphic Theology; and the former is said by
    <persName>Orpheus</persName> to be carried on the head of the latter. For so we are informed by
    <persName>Proclus</persName>, in
    <quote>Tim. p. 124.</quote>
    <persName>Jacob de Rhoer</persName>, therefore, the editor of this work, was grossly mistaken in saying,
    <quote>Non dubito, quin
      <foreign xml:lang="grc">ωμαδιος Διονυσος</foreign>,
      <foreign xml:lang="la">aedem sit qui</foreign>
      <foreign xml:lang="grc">ωμηστης</foreign>, crudivorus.</quote>
    <persName>Scaliger</persName> in his version of the Hymns, very improperly translates
    <foreign xml:lang="grc">ωμαδιος</foreign>;
    <foreign xml:lang="la">bajulus</foreign>, a porter. For
    <name type="deity" xml:lang="en">Bacchus</name> is carried on, but does not carry
    <foreign xml:lang="grc">ιρρα</foreign>.
  </p>
  <p>
    <foreign xml:lang="la">This text was transcribed by Roger Pearse,</foreign>
    <foreign xml:lang="la">2007. All material on this page is in the public domain - copy freely.</foreign>
  </p>
</div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>