<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng"
    type="application/xml"
    schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title xml:lang="en">Cynegetica</title>
        <author>
          <persName>NEMESIANUS, MARCUS AURELIUS OLYMPUS</persName>
          
        </author>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Encodage automatique TEI P5</resp>
          <name>zoomathia_encoder.py v3.0</name>
          <date when="2026-07-16">2026-07-16</date>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Projet Zoomathia (ANR-21-CE27-0012)</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Universite Cote d'Azur, Nice, France</pubPlace>
        <date when="2026-07-16">2026-07-16</date>
        <availability>
          <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0</licence>
        </availability>
        <idno type="zoomathia"></idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Encode automatiquement par zoomathia_encoder.py v3.0 - Projet Zoomathia</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language ident="en">anglais</language>
      </langUsage>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="zoomathia">
          <term>Zoomathia</term>
          <term>animaux</term>
          <term>inconnu</term>
          <term>anglais</term>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>Fichier encode automatiquement dans le cadre du projet Zoomathia (ANR).
        Encodage produit par zoomathia_encoder.py v3.0. Verification humaine recommandee.</p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>Balisage automatique des structures textuelles et des entites nommees
        pertinentes pour Zoomathia (animaux, plantes, personnes, lieux).</p>
        <correction status="unknown">
          <p>Encodage automatique - erreurs possibles, revision manuelle recommandee.</p>
        </correction>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
<head>Cynegetica</head>
<lg type="strophe">
<l n="1">For ere now who has not sung of <persName>Niobe</persName> saddened by death upon death of her children?</l>
<l n="2">Who does not know of <persName>Semele</persName> and of the fire that was at once bridal and doom for her — as the outcome of her rival's⁠</l>
<l n="3">craft?</l>
<l n="4">Who fails to record the cradling renewed for mighty <name type="deity" xml:lang="en">Bacchus</name> — how the Almighty Sire deigned to restore his mother's months and fulfilled the time of regular pregnancy.⁠</l>
<l n="5">Poets there are whose taste is to tell the hackneyed tales of <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Bacchic</name> wands dripping with unholy blood,⁠</l>
<l n="6">or <persName>Dirce</persName>'s bonds,⁠</l>
<l n="7">and the terms imposed for the wooing at <placeName>Pisa</placeName>,⁠</l>
<l n="8">and <persName>Danaus</persName>' bloody behest, and the merciless brides who, fresh from plighted troth, changed sweet joys to funeral torches.⁠</l>
<l n="9">No poet fails to tell of <persName>Biblis</persName>' criminal passion;⁠</l>
<l n="10">we know of <persName>Myrrha</persName>'s p489 impious amour, of her father defiled with cruel crimes, and how, traversing in her flight the fields of <placeName>Araby</placeName>, she passed into the greenwood life of the leafy trees.⁠</l>
<l n="11">There are some who relate the fierce hissing of <persName>Cadmus</persName> turned into a scaly <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">serpent</name>, and Maiden <persName>Io</persName>'s gaoler starred with eyes,⁠</l>
<l n="12">or who fain for ever to recount the labours of <persName>Hercules</persName>, or <persName>Tereus</persName>' wonderment that after your banquet, <persName>Philomela</persName>,⁠</l>
<l n="13">he could raise wings as yet untried; there are others whose theme is <persName>Phaethon</persName>'s ill-starred attempt upon the heights of the universe in the <name type="deity" xml:lang="en">Sun</name>'s chariot, and whose song is of flames quenched in the thunderbolt launched forth, and of the river <placeName>Padus</placeName> reeking, of <persName>Cycnus</persName> and the plumage of his old age, of the (poplar-)</l>
</lg>
<div>
   <lg type="strophe">
      <l n="13">trees for ever weeping by reason of a brother's death.</l>
      <l n="14"><persName>Bards</persName> ere now have told of the misfortunes of the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Tantalids</name>, the blood-besprinkled tables, the <name type="deity">Titan Sun</name> hiding his face at the sight of <placeName>Mycenae</placeName> and the dread vicissitudes of a race.</l>
      <l n="15">We do not sing of gifts imbued with the accursed poison of the angry <persName>Colchian dame</persName></l>
      <l n="16">and of the burning of fair <persName>Glauce</persName>; not of <persName>Nisus</persName>' lock;</l>
      <l n="17">not of cruel <persName>Circe</persName>'s <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">cups</name>;</l>
      <l n="18">nor yet of the sister</l>
      <l n="19">whose conscience contrived a (brother's) burial by night: in all this ere now a band of mighty <persName>bards</persName> has forestalled us, and all the fabling of an ancient age is commonplace.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg type="strophe">
      <l n="20">We search the glades, the green tracts, the open plains, swiftly coursing here and there o'er all the fields, eager to catch varied quarries with docile <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">hound</name>.</l>
      <l n="21">We enjoy transfixing the nervous <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">hare</name>, the unresisting <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">doe</name>, the daring <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">wolf</name> or capturing the crafty <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">fox</name>;</l>
      <l n="22">our heart's desire is to rove along the river-side shades, hunting the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">ichneumon</name> on the quiet banks among the crops of <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">bulrushes</name>,</l>
      <l n="23">with the long weapon to pierce in front the threatening <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">polecat</name> on a tree-trunk and bring home the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">hedgehog</name></l>
      <l n="24">entwined in the convolution of its prickly body: for such a task it is our resolve to set sail, while our little <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">barque</name>, wont to coast by the neighbouring shore and run across safe bays with the oar, now first spreads its canvas to southern winds, and, leaving the trusty havens, dares to try the <placeName>Adriatic</placeName> storms.</l>
      <l n="25">Hereafter I will gird myself with fitter lyre to r</l>
   </lg>
</div>
<lg type="strophe">
  <l n="20">Record your triumphs, you gallant sons of deified <persName>Carus</persName>,</l>
  <l n="21">and will sing of our sea-board beneath the twin boundaries of our world,</l>
  <l n="21">and of the subjugation, by the brothers' divine power, of nations that drink from <placeName>Rhine</placeName> or <placeName>Tigris</placeName> or from the distant source of <placeName>Arar</placeName> or look upon the wells of <placeName>Nile</placeName> at their birth;</l>
  <l n="22">nor let me fail to tell what campaigns you first ended, <persName>Carinus</persName>, beneath the Northern Bear</l>
  <l n="23">with victorious hand, well-nigh outstripping even your divine father, and how your brother</l>
  <l n="24">seized on <placeName>Persia</placeName>'s very heart and the time-honoured citadels of <placeName>Babylon</placeName>, in vengeance for outrages done to the high dignity of the realms of <name type="deity">Romulus</name>' race.</l>
  <l n="24">I shall record also the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Parthians</name>' feeble flight, their unopened quivers, unbent bows and unavailing arrows.</l>
  <l n="25">Such strains shall my <name type="deity">Muses</name> consecrate to you both, as soon as it is my fortune to see your blest faces, kindly divinities of this earth.</l>
  <l n="25">Already my feelings, intolerant of slow time and disdain­ful of delay, anticipate the joys of my aspiration, and I fancy I already discern the majestic mien of the brothers, and therewith <placeName>Rome</placeName>, the illustrious senate, the generals trusted for warfare, and the marching lines of many soldiers, their brave souls stirred with devotion.</l>
  <l n="25">The golden standards gleam radiant afar with their purple drapery, and a light breeze waves the folds of the ferocious <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">dragons</name>.</l>
  <l n="25">Only do thou, <name type="deity">Diana</name>, <name type="deity">Latona</name>'s great glory, who dost roam the peaceful glade and woodland, come quickly, ass</l>
</lg>
<lg type="strophe">
  <l n="1">ume thy wonted guise, bow in hand, and hang the coloured quiver from thy shoulder;</l>
  <l n="2">golden be the weapons, thine arrows; and let thy gleaming feet be fitted with purple buskins;</l>
  <l n="3">let thy cloak be richly tricked with <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">golden</name> thread,</l>
  <l n="4">and a belt with jewelled fastenings tighten the wrinkled tunic-folds : restrain thine entwined tresses with a band.</l>
  <l n="5">In thy train let genial <name type="deity">Naiads</name> come and <name type="deity">Dryads</name> ripening in fresh youth</l>
  <l n="6">and <name type="deity">Nymphs</name> who give the streams their water, and let the apt pupil <name type="deity">Echo</name> repeat</l>
  <l n="7">the accents of thine <name type="deity">Oreads</name>.</l>
  <l n="8">Goddess, arise, lead thy poet through the untrodden boscage:</l>
  <l n="9">thee we follow; do thou disclose the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">wild beasts</name>' homes and lairs.</l>
  <l n="10">Come hither then with me, whosoever, smitten with the love of the chase,</l>
  <l n="11">dost condemn lawsuits and panic-stricken turmoil, or dost shun the din in cities</l>
  <l n="12">and the clash of war, or pursuest no spoils on the greedy surge of the deep.</l>
  <l n="13">At the outset your diligent care of your <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">dogs</name></l>
  <l n="14">must start from the beginning of the year, when <name type="deity">Janus</name>, author of the march of time,</l>
  <l n="15">opens for each twelve months the never-ceasing round.</l>
  <l n="16">At that season you must choose a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">bitch</name> obedient to speed forward,</l>
  <l n="17">obedient to come to heel, native to either the <placeName>Spartan</placeName> or the <placeName>Molossian</placeName></l>
  <l n="18">country-side , and of good pedigree.</l>
  <l n="19">She must stand high on straight legs; with a comely slope let her carry,</l>
  <l n="20">under a broad breast, where the ribs end, a width of keel that gradually again contracts</l>
  <l n="21">in a lean belly: she must be big enough with strong loins, spread at th</l>
</lg>
<lg type="strophe">
  <l n="1">e hips, and with the silkiest of ears floating in air as she runs.</l>
  <l n="2">Give her a male to match, everywhere similarly well-sized,</l>
  <l n="3">while strength holds sway, while bodily youth is in its joyous flower</l>
  <l n="4">and blood abounds in the veins of early life.</l>
  <l n="5">For burdensome diseases creep on and sluggish age,</l>
  <l n="6">and they will produce unhealthy offspring without steadfast strength.</l>
  <l n="7">But for breeding a difference of age in the parents is more suitable:</l>
  <l n="8">you should release the male, keen for mating, when he has already completed forty months:</l>
  <l n="9">and let the female be two full years old.</l>
  <l n="10">Such is the best arrangement in their coupling.</l>
  <l n="11">Presently when <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Phoebe</name> has completed the round of two full moons</l>
  <l n="12">since the birth-giving womb fertilised by the male began to swell,</l>
  <l n="13">the pregnancy in its due time reveals the fruitful offspring,</l>
  <l n="14">and straightway you see all round an abundant noisy litter.</l>
  <l n="15">Yet, however desirous of <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">dogs</name>, you must make up you mind</l>
  <l n="16">to put no value on the first set born;</l>
  <l n="17">and of the next set you must not rear all the young ones.</l>
  <l n="18">For if you decide to feed a crowd of <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">whelps</name>,</l>
  <l n="19">you will find them thin with leanness and beggared of strength,</l>
  <l n="20">and, by their long tussle to be first to suck, harassing a mother</l>
  <l n="21">weakened with teat outworn.</l>
  <l n="22">But if this is your anxiety, to keep the better sort from being killed or thrown out of the house,</l>
  <l n="23">if it is your intention to test the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">puppies</name> before even their steps</l>
  <l n="24">are steady or their eyes have felt</l>
  <l n="25">and seen the light-bearing sunbeam, then grasp what experience</l>
</lg>
<pb n="499"/>
<p>has handed on, and assent fearlessly to well-tried words. You will be able to examine the strength of a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">puppy</name> by its weight and by the heaviness of each body know in advance which will be light in running.⁠ 33 Furthermore, you should get a series of flames made in a wide circuit with the smoke of the fire to mark a convenient round space, so that you may stand unharmed in the middle of the circle: to this all the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">puppies</name>, to this the whole crowd as yet unseparated must be brought: the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">mother</name> will provide the test of her progeny, saving the valuable young ones by her selection and from their alarming peril. For when she sees her offspring shut in by flames, at once with a leap she clears the blazing boundaries of the fire-zone, snatches the first in her jaws and carries it to the kennel; next another, next another in turn: so does the intelligent <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">mother</name> distinguish her nobler progeny by her love of merit. These then along with their <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">mother</name>, now that it is clear spring, you are to feed on soft whey (for everywhere the season that abounds in milk has come, and sheepfolds are white with brimming milk-pails): at times, too, add to their food bread with milk,⁠ 34 so that they may be able to fill their young marrows with power­ful juices and even at that time give promise of vigorous strength. But after the burning <name type="deity">Sun-God</name> has reached the glowing height of heaven, entering on his slow paths and on the sign of the lingering <foreign xml:lang="la">Crab</foreign>,⁠ 35 then it will be useful to lessen their regu</p>
<lg type="strophe">
  <l n="36">lar fattening food and retain the more delicate nourishment,</l>
  <l n="37">so that the weight of heavy bulk may not overstrain their limbs;</l>
  <l n="38">for that is when they have the connecting joints of the body slack,</l>
  <l n="39">and plant on the ground unstable feet and swimming legs:</l>
  <l n="40">then too their mouths are furnished with snowy <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">teeth</name>.</l>
</lg>
<lg type="strophe">
  <l n="41">But you should not keep them shut up,</l>
  <l n="42">nor impatiently put chains on their neck,</l>
  <l n="43">and from want of foresight hurt their future running powers.</l>
  <l n="44">For often young <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">dogs</name>, when kept separate,</l>
  <l n="45">will take to worrying the timber-fittings,</l>
  <l n="46">or to gnawing the doors till they are torn,</l>
  <l n="47">and in the attempt they twist their tender limbs</l>
  <l n="48">or blunt their young <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">teeth</name> by chewing at the wood</l>
  <l n="49">or drive their tender nails into the tough doorposts.</l>
</lg>
<lg type="strophe">
  <l n="50">Later, when time, revolving eight months from their birth,</l>
  <l n="51">now lets them stand on steady legs</l>
  <l n="52">and sees the whelps everywhere with limbs unharmed,</l>
  <l n="53">then it will be suitable again to mix the gifts of <name type="deity">Ceres</name> with their whey</l>
  <l n="54">and have them given strengthening food from the produce of the fields.</l>
  <l n="55">Only then must they be trained to have their free necks in leash,</l>
  <l n="56">to run in harmony or be kept in chain.</l>
</lg>
<lg type="strophe">
  <l n="57">When <name type="deity">Phoebe</name> has now renewed twenty monthly risings,</l>
  <l n="58">start to bring out the young <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">dogs</name> on a course</l>
  <l n="59">not over-long but within the space of a small valley or enclosed fallow.</l>
  <l n="60">Out of your hand let slip for them a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">hare</name>,</l>
  <l n="61">not of equal strength nor their match in speed of running,</l>
  <l n="62">but slow in moving its limbs,</l>
  <l n="63">so that they may at once capture an easy prey.</l>
  <l n="64">Not once only mus</l>
</lg>
<lg type="strophe">
  <l n="1">t you grant the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">whelps</name> these limited runs, but until they are trained to outstrip strong <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">hares</name>,</l>
  <l n="2">exercise them long in the task of the chase, forcing them to learn and love the praise due to deserving merit.</l>
  <l n="3">Likewise they must recognise the urgent words of a well-known voice, whether calling them in or telling them to run full-speed.</l>
  <l n="4">Besides, when they have been taught to seize the vanquished prey, they must be content to kill, not mangle, what they have caught.</l>
  <l n="5">By such methods see that you recruit your swift <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">dogs</name> every season,</l>
  <l n="6"><pb n="503"/>and again direct your anxious thoughts towards the young ones.</l>
  <l n="7">For they have melancholy ailments, and the filthy <foreign xml:lang="la">mange</foreign> often comes on their veins,</l>
  <l n="8">and the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">dogs</name> cause widespread mortality without distinction:</l>
  <l n="9">you must yourself expend anxious efforts on them and every year fill up your pack by supplying progeny.</l>
  <l n="10">Besides, the right thing is to blend tart draughts of <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">wine</name> with <name type="deity">Minerva</name>'s <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">olive-fruit</name>,</l>
  <l n="11">and it will do good to anoint the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">whelps</name> and the mother <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">dogs</name>,</l>
  <l n="12">expose them to the warm sun, and expel worms from their ears with the glittering knife.</l>
  <l n="13"><name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Dogs</name> also get <foreign xml:lang="la">rabies</foreign>, a deadly peril.</l>
  <l n="14">Whether it emanates from taint in a heavenly body when the <name type="deity">Sun-God</name> shoots but languid rays from a saddened sky,</l>
  <l n="15">raising a pallid face in a world dismayed;</l>
  <l n="16">or whether, rather, in striking the glowing back of the fire-tressed <foreign xml:lang="la">Lion</foreign>,⁠</l>
  <l n="17">he drives deep into our friendly <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">dogs</name> his feverish heats,</l>
  <l n="18">whether earth breathes forth contagion from its bosom, or harmful air is the cause</l>
</lg>
<pb n="505"/>
<lg type="strophe">
  <l n="1">of the evil, or whether, when cool water runs short, the torrid germs of fire grow strong throughout the veins —</l>
  <l n="2">whatever it is, it stirs the inmost marrow beneath the heart, and with black venomous foam darts forth into ferocious snarls,</l>
  <l n="3">compelling the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">dog</name> to imprint its bites in madness.</l>
  <l n="4">Learn, therefore, the curative potions and the treatment that brings health.</l>
  <l n="5">In such cases you will take the fetid drug got from the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">beaver</name> and work it well,</l>
  <l n="6">forcing it to grow viscous with the friction of a flint: to this should be added powder from pounded or chopped <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">ivory</name>,</l>
  <l n="7">and by a long process of blending you will got both to harden together: next put in gradually the liquid flow of <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">milk</name> besides,</l>
  <l n="8">to enable you to pour through an inserted horn doses which do not stick in the throat, and so banish the melancholy <name type="deity">Furies</name>,</l>
  <l n="9">and settle the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">dogs</name>' minds once more to friendliness.</l>
</lg>
<lg type="strophe">
  <l n="10">But it is not only <persName>Spartan</persName> whelps or only <persName>Molossian</persName> which you must rear:</l>
  <l n="11">sundered <placeName>Britain</placeName> sends us a swift sort, adapted to hunting-tasks in our world.</l>
  <l n="12">You should not disdain the pedigree of the <persName>Pannonian</persName> breed, nor those whose progeny springs from <persName>Spanish</persName> blood.</l>
  <l n="13">Moreover, keen whelps are produced within the confines of dry <placeName>Libya</placeName>, and their service you must not despise.</l>
  <l n="14">Besides, <persName>Tuscan</persName> <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">dogs</name> often give a satisfaction not foreign to us.</l>
  <l n="15">Even allowing that their shape is covered with shaggy hair and that they have limbs unlike quick-footed whelps,</l>
  <l n="16">still they will give you an agreeable return in game; for t</l>
</lg>
<div type="poem">
  <head>Cynegetica</head>
  <lg type="strophe">
    <l n="40">hey recognise the tracks on the meadow, though full of scents,</l>
    <l n="41">and actually point to where a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">hare</name> lies hid.</l>
    <l n="42">Their mettle and their habits as well, and their discerning sense of smell</l>
    <l n="43">I shall record presently;</l>
  </lg>
  <lg type="strophe">
    <l n="44">for the moment the whole equipment of the chase</l>
    <l n="45">has to be explained, and I must deal with the attention due to <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">horses</name>.</l>
  </lg>
  <lg type="strophe">
    <l n="46">So then let <placeName>Greece</placeName> send us choice horny-hoofed <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">coursers</name>,</l>
    <l n="47">and let a high-mettled breed recall the traits of the <placeName>Cappadocians</placeName>,</l>
    <l n="48">and let the whole stud be soundly equipped and surpass the victorious racing-palms of their ancestors.</l>
  </lg>
  <lg type="strophe">
    <l n="49">Theirs is surface wide enough on their smooth back,</l>
    <l n="50">an enormous extent of side, and neat belly for their huge size,</l>
    <l n="51">a forehead uplifted, quick ears, high pride of comely head,</l>
    <l n="52">and eyes sparkling with restless gleam;</l>
  </lg>
  <lg type="strophe">
    <l n="53">an ample neck falls back on powerful shoulders;</l>
    <l n="54">moist breath steams from hot nostrils, and, while the foot does not maintain its duty to stand still,</l>
    <l n="55">the hoof repeatedly strikes the earth and the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">horse</name>'s spirited mettle tires its limbs.</l>
  </lg>
  <lg type="strophe">
    <l n="56">Moreover, beyond the soaring peaks of <placeName>Calpe</placeName></l>
    <l n="57">lies a vast country, productive far and wide of fine <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">coursers</name>.</l>
  </lg>
  <lg type="strophe">
    <l n="58">For they have the strength to make long runs across the prairies,</l>
    <l n="59">and their beauty is no less than that in a <placeName>Grecian</placeName> body;</l>
    <l n="60">panting they roll forth terrifying snorts, a flood of breath;</l>
    <l n="61">they shoot out spirited glances;</l>
    <l n="62">all a‑quiver they raise whinnyings and fight against the bridle,</l>
    <l n="63">never giving their ears smooth rest nor their legs repose.</l>
    <l n="64">Besides, you may</l>
  </lg>
</div>
<div>
  <lg type="strophe">
    <l n="1">select the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">courser</name> sent by <placeName>Mauretania</placeName> (if he be a stout descendant of good stock),</l>
    <l n="2">or the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">horse</name> which the dusky <persName>Mazax</persName> tribesman⁠</l>
    <l n="3">has reared in <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">desert</name> fields and taught to undergo ceaseless toil.</l>
    <l n="4">No need to repine at their ugly head and ill-shapen belly,</l>
    <l n="5">or at their lack of bridles, or because both breeds have the temper of freedom,</l>
    <l n="6">or because the neck lashes the sloping shoulders with its mane.</l>
    <l n="7">For he is an easy <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">horse</name> to guide, plies obediently under the control of a limber switch:</l>
    <l n="8">its strokes are the orders for speed, its strokes are <foreign xml:lang="la">p509</foreign> as <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">bridles</name> too.</l>
    <l n="9">Nay, once launched across the spacious levels of the <placeName>plain</placeName>,</l>
    <l n="10">with blood stirred, the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">steeds</name> win fresh strength in the race,</l>
    <l n="11">leaving by degrees their eager comrades behind.</l>
    <l n="12">Even so, on the outburst of the <name type="deity">winds</name> across the blue waters of <name type="deity">Nereus</name>,</l>
    <l n="13">when <persName>Thracian Boreas</persName> has uprisen o'er his cavern</l>
    <l n="14">and with shrill howling dismayed the dreary waves,</l>
    <l n="15">all the blasts on the troubled deep give way to him:</l>
    <l n="16">himself⁠</l>
    <l n="17"><name type="deity">aglow</name> mid foaming din, above the billows he o'ertops them</l>
    <l n="18">in mastery manifest upon the <name type="placeName">sea</name>:</l>
    <l n="19">the whole band of the <name type="deity">Nereids</name> is mazed in wonderment as he passes</l>
    <l n="20">over their watery domains.</l>
    <l n="21">These <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">horses</name> are slow to attain confidence in prolonged running;</l>
    <l n="22">also, theirs is youthful vigour even in age that has served its time.</l>
    <l n="23">For no quality which has bloomed full at its due period suffers collapse in spirit ere physical powers fail.</l>
    <l n="24">In the fresh <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">spring</name>-time, then, feed the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">coursers</name> on soft mash, and, lancing a vein, watch old-sta</l>
  </lg>
</div>
<lg type="strophe">
  <l n="1">nding ailments flow out with the ooze of the tainted blood.</l>
  <l n="2">Soon strength returns joyously to their gallant hearts, moulding the sleek</l>
  <l n="3">limbs with strength diffused: soon a better blood runs warm in their veins,</l>
  <l n="4">and they wish for long stretches of road, and to make the broad plain vanish</l>
  <l n="5">in their career.</l>
</lg>
<lg type="strophe">
  <l n="6">Next, when summer has hardened the ripening stalks and, scorching the</l>
  <l n="7">juicy blades, has dried all the moisture for harvest and joined corn-ears</l>
  <l n="8">º to stems, then be sure to furnish barley and light chaff: moreover, there</l>
  <l n="9">must be care to winnow the produce free from dust, and to run the hands</l>
  <l n="10">p511 over the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">horses</name> ' muscles, so that</l>
  <l n="11">the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">courser</name> may enjoy being patted and relax</l>
  <l n="12">his body in pleasure and quickly pass the nourishing juices throughout his</l>
  <l n="13">frame.</l>
</lg>
<lg type="strophe">
  <l n="14">This must be the task of the servants and brave young attendants.</l>
  <l n="15">Besides they too must learn always to weave with knots far enough apart</l>
  <l n="16">the hollow nets fit for the chase, and the toils set on tracks, and the nets</l>
  <l n="17">which run in a long stretch; they must learn to preserve the right size for</l>
  <l n="18">the openings between the knots and for the binding cord.</l>
</lg>
<lg type="strophe">
  <l n="19">Moreover, the line which can enclose great glades and by reason of terror</l>
  <l n="20">shut in winged game as prey must carry here and there, entwined on it,</l>
  <l n="21">feathers of different <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">birds</name>.</l>
  <l n="22">For the colours, like lightning-flashes , frighten <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">bears</name>,</l>
  <l n="23">big <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">boars</name>, timid <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">stags</name>,</l>
  <l n="24"><name type="animal" xml:lang="en">foxes</name> and fierce <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">wolves</name>, and</l>
  <l n="25">bar them from surmounting the boundary of the cord.</l>
</lg>
<lg type="strophe">
  <l n="26">These then you will always be careful to furnish</l>
</lg>
<pb n="513"/>
<lg type="strophe">
  <l n="47">ify with various hues, mixing other colours with the whites, and thus stretching all along the line one terror after another.</l>
  <l n="48">In feathers you draw a thousand means of fight from the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">vulture</name>, from Africa, fertile mother of great-sized birds,</l>
  <l n="49">from <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">cranes</name> and aged <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">swans</name> and the white <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">goose</name>, from fowl that haunt rivers and thick marshes and dip webbed feet in standing pools.</l>
  <l n="50">Of these</l>
  <l n="51">you will rather take birds with red plumage by nature's gift; for among the former you will find endless flocks of birds with bright-hued wings, their colours reddening with pleasant orange tint and gleaming everywhere in flecks upon the back.</l>
</lg>
<lg type="strophe">
  <l n="52">With such arrangements made towards the season of rainy winter, begin to send your swift <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">dogs</name> across the meadows;</l>
  <l n="53">begin to urge your <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">horses</name> over the broad fields.</l>
  <l n="54">Let us go hunting while the morning is young, while the soft meads retain the tracks imprinted by the wild beasts of the night.</l>
</lg>
<pb n="4"/>
<p>After <persName>Semele</persName> perished amidst the flames of her lover <persName>Jupiter</persName>'s visitation, the god kept her unborn child, <name type="deity">Bacchus</name>, in his thigh until his birth was due: cf. <quote><persName>Nem.</persName> Ecl. III .21‑24</quote> . ❦</p>
<pb n="5"/>
<p>i.e. of <persName>Pentheus</persName>, King of <placeName>Thebes</placeName>, torn to pieces by his mother and other <name type="deity">Bacchanalian</name> devotees. ❦</p>
<pb n="6"/>
<p><persName>Dirce</persName> was tied to a savage <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">bull</name> by <persName>Amphion</persName> and <persName>Zethus</persName> out of revenge for her part in the maltreatment of their mother, <persName>Antiope</persName>: cf. <quote><placeName>Aetna</placeName>, 577</quote> . ❦</p>
<pb n="7"/>
<p>To escape prophesied death at the hands of a son-in‑law, <persName>Oenomaus</persName>, King of <placeName>Elis</placeName> and <placeName>Pisa</placeName>, proclaimed that he would give his daughter, <persName>Hippodamia</persName>, in marriage only to the suitor who should win a chariot-race against his supernatural steeds. ❦</p>
<pb n="8"/>
<p>The fifty <name type="deity">Danaides</name>, with the exception of <persName>Hypermestra</persName>, carried out the command of their father, <persName>Danaus</persName>, to kill their bridegrooms on their marriage-night . ❦</p>
<pb n="9"/>
<p>i.e. for her brother <persName>Caunus</persName>. ❦</p>
<pb n="10"/>
<p><persName>Myrrha</persName> (or <foreign xml:lang="la">Zmyrna</foreign>), daughter of King <persName>Cinyras</persName>, was metamorphosed into a fragrant tree. ❦</p>
<pb n="11"/>
<p><persName>Juno</persName>, jealous of <persName>Jupiter</persName>'s love for <persName>Io</persName>, consigned her to the guardian ­ship of <persName>Argus</persName> of the hundred eyes, afterwards transformed into a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">peacock</name>. ❦</p>
<pb n="12"/>
<p><persName>Procne</persName> and <persName>Philomela</persName> punished <persName>Tereus</persName> for his unfaithfulness by serving to him as food <persName>Itys</persName>, his son by <persName>Procne</persName>. When <persName>Procne</persName> was changed into a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">swallow</name> and <persName>Philomela</persName> into a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">nightingale</name>, <persName>Tereus</persName> became a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">hoopoe</name> to pursue them: cf. <quote><placeName>Aetna</placeName>, 589</quote> . ❦</p>
<pb n="13"/>
<p>The fiery ruin which overtook <persName>Phaëthon</persName> in the <name type="deity">Sun-God</name>'s chariot was lamented by <persName>Cycnus</persName>, who was changed into a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">swan</name>, and by his sisters, the <persName>Heliades</persName>, who were changed into <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">poplars</name>.</p>

<pb n="14"/>
<p><persName>Blood-guilt</persName> was transmitted through <persName>Pelops</persName>, son of <persName>Tantalus</persName>, and through his sons <persName>Atreus</persName> and <persName>Thyestes</persName> to <persName>Agamemnon</persName> and his son <persName>Orestes</persName>. <persName>Atreus</persName>, King of <placeName>Mycene</placeName>, avenged himself for the seduction of his wife on his brother by slaying his two sons and setting their flesh before their father. From this "banquet of <persName>Thyestes</persName>" the <name type="deity">Sun</name> hid his face in horror: cf. <quote><title>Aetna</title>, 20</quote>.</p>

<pb n="15"/>
<p>The sorceress <persName>Medea</persName> from <placeName>Colchis</placeName>, infuriated by <persName>Jason</persName>'s desertion of her for <persName>Glauce</persName>, sent to her bridal gifts which consumed her with fire.</p>

<pb n="16"/>
<p>On the purple lock of <persName>Nisus</persName>, King of <placeName>Megara</placeName>, the safety of his kingdom depended. His betrayal by his daughter is told in <title>Ciris</title> (<title>Appendix Virgiliana</title>) <quote><title>VERGIL:CIRIS</title></quote>.</p>

<pb n="17"/>
<p><persName>Circe</persName>'s potions and spells transformed men into beasts.</p>

<pb n="18"/>
<p><persName>Antigone</persName> buried her brother <persName>Polynices</persName> in defiance of the edict of <persName>Creon</persName>.</p>

<pb n="19"/>
<p><foreign xml:lang="la">eres</foreign> (= <foreign xml:lang="la">ericius</foreign>, <foreign xml:lang="la">ericinus</foreign> or <foreign xml:lang="la">erinaceus</foreign>) corresponds to the Greek <foreign xml:lang="grc">ἐχῖνος</foreign>.</p>
<pb n="20"/>
<p>This passage dates the <title level="m" type="work">Cynegetica</title> . For the Emperor <persName>Carus</persName> and his sons, <persName>Carinus</persName> and <persName>Numerianus</persName>, see <quote>Gibbon, <title level="m" type="work">Decline and Fall</title></quote> , ch. xii. They succeeded their father on his death in A.D. 283. In 284 <persName>Carinus</persName> celebrated elaborate games at <placeName>Rome</placeName> in the name of himself and <persName>Numerian</persName>; but the brothers never saw each other after their father died. <persName>Numerian</persName>'s death in 284 during his return journey with his army from <placeName>Persia</placeName> prevented him from enjoying the triumph decreed to the young emperors at <placeName>Rome</placeName>. <quote>Thayer's Note: The main primary source for the life and reign of <persName>Carus</persName> is his biography in the <title level="m" type="work">Historia Augusta</title>: <persName>Carus</persName>, <persName>Carinus</persName> and <persName>Numerian</persName> .</quote></p>

<pb n="21"/>
<p><lg type="strophe">
<l n="21">Fines are the limits set by <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Ocean</name> on East and West. ❦</l>
</lg></p>

<pb n="22"/>
<p><lg type="strophe">
<l n="22">The war maintained against the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Sarmatians</name> by <persName>Carus</persName> after <persName>Probus</persName>' death was left to <persName>Carinus</persName> to finish, when <persName>Carus</persName> had to face the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Persian</name> menace in the East. In his Gallic campaign also, <persName>Carinus</persName> showed some degree of soldierly ability. ❦</l>
</lg></p>

<pb n="23"/>
<p><lg type="strophe">
<l n="23"><persName>Numerian</persName> is here flatteringly associated with the exploits of <persName>Carus</persName>, who after subduing <placeName>Mesopotamia</placeName> carried his victorious arms to <placeName>Ctesiphon</placeName>. <persName>Numerian</persName>'s subsequent retreat surprised the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Persians</name>. ❦</l>
</lg></p>

<pb n="24"/>
<p><lg type="strophe">
<l n="24">The reference is to violations of the Eastern frontiers of the Empire. <foreign xml:lang="la">Cacumina regni</foreign> is taken, with Wernsdorf, to mean <foreign xml:lang="la">fastigium et maiestatem imperii Romani</foreign> . ❦</l>
</lg></p>

<pb n="25"/>
<p><lg type="strophe">
<l n="25">They were military emblems from <persName>Trajan</persName>'s time. ❦</l>
</lg></p>
<pb n="91"/>
<pb n="92"/>
<pb n="93"/>
<p>26 Lines 91‑93 are discussed in a special excursus by Wernsdorf. With <foreign xml:lang="la">lusa</foreign> cf. of the <persName>Georgics</persName>’+<foreign xml:lang="la">Lat2+LatSearch</foreign>+<foreign xml:lang="la">inlusasque</foreign> (note spelling)')" onMouseOut="nd();"><quote><persName>Virg.</persName> <title type="work">G.</title> II .464</quote>, <foreign xml:lang="la">illusasque auro vestes</foreign>, "garments fancifully embroidered with gold." ❦</p>
<p>27 i.e. the surroundings should reverberate to the voices of the attendant mountain-<name type="deity">nymphs</name>. ❦</p>
<p>28 On <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">dogs</name> generally see note on <persName>Grattius</persName>, <title type="work">Cyneg.</title> 151. ❦</p>
<p>29 Cf. <persName>Grattius</persName>, <title type="work">Cyneg.</title> 181, 197, 211‑212. ❦</p>
<p>30 On the mating of <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">dogs</name> cf. <persName>Grattius</persName>, <title type="work">Cyneg.</title>, esp. 263‑284. ❦</p>
<p>31 <name type="deity">Soles</name> stands here for <foreign xml:lang="la">annos</foreign>, i.e. annual revolutions of the <name type="deity">sun</name> according to the ancient cosmology. ❦</p>
<p>32 Wernsdorf, following <persName>Barth</persName>, explains <foreign xml:lang="la">passa</foreign> as meaning <foreign xml:lang="la">aperta</foreign> (from <foreign xml:lang="la">pandere</foreign>, not from <foreign xml:lang="la">pati</foreign>). ❦</p>
<p>33 138‑139: the parallel in <persName>Grattius</persName>, <title type="work">Cyn.</title> 298‑299, is one of the points suggesting that <persName>Nemesianus</persName> had read <persName>Grattius</persName>. ❦</p>
<p>34 Cf. <persName>Grattius</persName>, <title type="work">Cyn.</title> 307, <foreign xml:lang="la">lacte novam pubem facilique tuebere maza</foreign>. For the use of the <name type="deity">goddess</name>' name by metonymy for bread cf. <persName>Gratt.</persName> <title type="work">Cyn.</title> 398: also <title type="work">Aetna</title>, 10. ❦</p>
<p>35 In the long days of midsummer the <name type="deity">sun</name> might be fancied to cross the sky more slowly. <persName>Morantis</persName> refers to the almost imperceptible lengthening and shortening of the days before and after the solstice. ❦</p>
<p>36 i.e. the <foreign xml:lang="la">molle serum</foreign> of l. 152. ❦</p>
<p>37 The reference is to the heat of the <name type="deity">sun</name> on entering the sign of <name type="deity">Leo</name>. ❦</p>
<pb n="195"/>
<p>38 For British <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">dogs</name> see <persName>Grattius</persName>, 174 sqq. and note there : <foreign xml:lang="la">divisa Britannia</foreign> is an allusion to <quote><persName>Virg.</persName> <foreign xml:lang="la">Ecl.</foreign> I .66</quote>, <foreign xml:lang="la">penitus toto divisos orbe Britannos</foreign> . ❦</p>
<p>39 <persName>Burman</persName> gives the choice between <foreign xml:lang="la">summa</foreign> and <foreign xml:lang="la">minima</foreign> as equivalents to <foreign xml:lang="la">extrema</foreign> . <foreign xml:lang="la">Non . . . externa</foreign> seems to fit better the only Italian <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">dogs</name> in the passage. ❦</p>
<p>40 This shows the incomplete state in which <persName>Nemesianus</persName> has been transmitted; for these subjects are not treated in his extant work. ❦</p>
<p>41 The <foreign xml:lang="la">supellex venandi</foreign> corresponds to <persName>Grattius</persName>' <foreign xml:lang="la">arma</foreign> , i.e. nets, traps, hunting-spears , caps and so forth. ❦</p>
<p>42 One of the fabled <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Pillars of Hercules</name>, in <placeName>Hispania Baetica</placeName>, now the <placeName>Rock of Gibraltar</placeName>. <persName>Nemesianus</persName>, writing from the standpoint of an African, thinks of all <placeName>Spain</placeName> ( <foreign xml:lang="la">gens ampla</foreign> ) as beyond <placeName>Calpe</placeName>. ❦</p>
<p>43 The commendation of Spanish <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">horses</name> is supported by of the <persName>Epigrams</persName> of <persName>Martial</persName> <quote><persName>Martial</persName> I . XLIX .21‑25</quote> : cf. of the <persName>Epigrams</persName> of <persName>Martial</persName> <quote><persName>Martial</persName> XIV . CXCIX</quote> . But, according to 11, <persName>Cyneg.</persName> I .284‑286 , the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Iberian horses</name> , although fleet ( <foreign xml:lang="grc">θοοί</foreign> ), were found wanting in staying power ( <foreign xml:lang="grc">δρόμον ἐν παύροισιν ἐλεγχόμενοι σταδίοισιν</foreign> ) . ❦</p>
<p>44 Belonging to the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Numidian</name> tribe of <persName>Mazaces</persName> in <placeName>Africa</placeName>. ❦</p>
<p>45 <name type="deity">Boreas</name>. ❦</p>
<p>46 Cf. <persName>Grattius</persName>, <foreign xml:lang="la">Cyenegeticon</foreign> , 75‑78 (the <foreign xml:lang="la">" formido "</foreign> ). ❦</p>
<p>47 e.g. the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">ostrich</name>. ❦</p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>