<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title xml:lang="en">De Aucupio</title>
        <author>
          <persName>NEMESIANUS, MARCUS AURELIUS OLYMPUS</persName>
          
        </author>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Encodage automatique TEI P5</resp>
          <name>zoomathia_encoder.py v3.0</name>
          <date when="2026-07-16">2026-07-16</date>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Projet Zoomathia (ANR-21-CE27-0012)</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Universite Cote d'Azur, Nice, France</pubPlace>
        <date when="2026-07-16">2026-07-16</date>
        <availability>
          <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0</licence>
        </availability>
        <idno type="zoomathia"/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Encode automatiquement par zoomathia_encoder.py v3.0 - Projet Zoomathia</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language ident="en">anglais</language>
      </langUsage>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="zoomathia">
          <term>Zoomathia</term>
          <term>animaux</term>
          <term>inconnu</term>
          <term>anglais</term>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>Fichier encode automatiquement dans le cadre du projet Zoomathia (ANR).
        Encodage produit par zoomathia_encoder.py v3.0. Verification humaine recommandee.</p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>Balisage automatique des structures textuelles et des entites nommees
        pertinentes pour Zoomathia (animaux, plantes, personnes, lieux).</p>
        <correction status="unknown">
          <p>Encodage automatique - erreurs possibles, revision manuelle recommandee.</p>
        </correction>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
<div type="book" n="1">
   <p>Gybertus <persName>Longolius</persName> (<placeName>de Longueil</placeName>, 1507‑1543), in a <title>Dialogus de avibus</title> printed at <placeName>Cologne</placeName> in 1544, is the authority for ascribing the two following fragments to <persName>Nemesianus</persName>.</p>
   <p>He records that they were surreptitiously copied by a young friend of his, <persName>Hieronymus Boragineus</persName> of <placeName>Lübeck</placeName>, from a poem <title>De Aucupio</title> by <persName>Nemesianus</persName> "in bibliotheca porcorum (sic) Salvatoris Bononiensis."</p>
   <p>This account is not <foreign xml:lang="la">p514</foreign> free from suspicion, any more than certain points in the Latinity and prosody of the lines.</p>
   <p><foreign xml:lang="la">Contemplaverit</foreign> in l. 3 may be an archaistic return to the active form of the verb as used in early Latin; but the metrical quantity of <foreign xml:lang="la">notae</foreign> which <persName>Longolius</persName> read in l. 13 and of <foreign xml:lang="la">gulae</foreign> in the last line of all is unclassical, and the frequent elision of a long vowel (ll. 5, 6, 14 and 27) is noticeable.</p>
   <p><persName>Teuffel</persName> considers the lines a late production, though they are usually printed along with the <title>Cynegetica</title>.</p>
   <p><persName>E. Baehrens</persName>' text, <title>P. L. M.</title> III pp203‑204. <persName>J. P. Postgate</persName>'s text, <title>C. P. L.</title> II p572. (<foreign xml:lang="la">p513</foreign>)</p>
   <div type="section" n="1">
      <p>I . . . and the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">tetrax</name> ,⁠ <note n="1"> which they have now begun to call <foreign xml:lang="la">tarax</foreign> at <placeName>Rome</placeName>.</note> It is far the silliest of birds; for although it has perched and was watched the snare laid for it, yet reckless of self it darts upon its own hurt.</p>
      <p>You, however, on finding the circles of the noose drawn tight, must hasten up and carry off your prey with its whirring wings.</p>
      <p>For it is quick to shake off the treacherous bonds of the neck when caught, deriding⁠ <note n="2"> with hoarse cry the hunter's <foreign xml:lang="la">p515</foreign> design and now in freedom delighting</note></p>
   </div>
</div>
<div type="section" n="2">
   <p>in the joy of peace. Near <placeName>Peltinum</placeName>⁠ a by the foot of the <placeName>Apennine</placeName> range it builds its nest where the sun presents himself to the outspread lands: at the neck it is very like ashes in colour, and its spotted back is marked with dark flecks in the fashion of a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">partridge</name>.</p>
   <p>The guardian of the <placeName>Tarpeian</placeName> citadel⁠ <pb n="3"/> is no larger in study, nor the bird that taught you, <persName>Palamedes</persName>, wing-like letters.⁠ <pb n="4"/></p>
   <p>Often have I seen a slave swaying beneath the unfair weight of a huge dish of such dainties,⁠ <pb n="5"/></p>
   <p>as he carries the collation which a <persName>consul</persName> or a new <persName>praetor</persName> has furnished for the circus at a fête.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="3">
   <p>When the woodland everywhere is despoiled of its green honours, make straight for the deep forest, mounted on the snow-white housing of your steed. The <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">snipe</name> is an easy and agreeable prey. You will find it no larger in body than <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Venus'</name> <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">doves</name>. It feeds close to the edge of embankments, by the wash of the water, hunting tiny worms, its favourite fare.</p>
   <p>But its pursuit thereof is rather with keen-scented nose than with the eyes, in which its sense is rather dull, too big for the body though they be. With the point of the beak driven into the ground it drags out the little worms which needs must follow, therewith rewarding an appetite cheap to satisfy.⁠ <pb n="6"/></p>
   <p>The <name type="deity">Loeb</name> Editor's Notes: <quote>1 a black grouse. The bird is identified with the urogallus by Longolius. Pliny's form is tetras</quote>. Thayer's Note: <quote>"Pliny's form" is a mystery. Our translators provide no citation; and I find no tetras (or tetrax or tarax</quote></p>
</div>
<p>in any form anywhere in <persName>Pliny</persName>, either the most likely <persName>Elder</persName> or the marginally possible <persName>Younger</persName>; nor for that matter in <persName>Lewis  Short</persName>.</p>
<p><name type="animal" xml:lang="en">geese</name> of the <placeName>Capitol</placeName> saved it from surprise by the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Gauls</name>, in 390 B.C., <persName>Livy</persName>, V . XLVII .</p>
<p><persName>Palamedes</persName> was said to have invented some of the Greek letters ( <foreign xml:lang="grc">Υ</foreign> , <foreign xml:lang="grc">Θ</foreign> , <foreign xml:lang="grc">Ξ</foreign> , <foreign xml:lang="grc">Φ</foreign> , <foreign xml:lang="grc">Χ</foreign> ) by observing the flight of <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">cranes</name>: cf. <persName>Martial</persName>, of the Epigrams of <persName>Martial</persName> IX . XIII .7 , of the Epigrams of <persName>Martial</persName> XIII . LXXV ; <persName>Ausonius</persName>, Idyll. XII ( Technopaegnion de literis monosyllabis ) 25 <persName>Ausonius</persName>:TECHNOPAEGNION; <persName>Plin.</persName> N. H. VII .192 .</p>
<p>For the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">mazonomus</name> ( <foreign xml:lang="grc">μαζονόμος</foreign> ) see <persName>Hor.</persName> Sat. II . VIII .86 .</p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
