<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng"
    type="application/xml"
    schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title xml:lang="en">De sacrificiis</title>
        <author>
          <persName>LUCIANUS SAMOSATENSIS</persName>
          
        </author>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Encodage automatique TEI P5</resp>
          <name>zoomathia_encoder.py v3.0</name>
          <date when="2026-07-12">2026-07-12</date>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Projet Zoomathia (ANR-21-CE27-0012)</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Universite Cote d'Azur, Nice, France</pubPlace>
        <date when="2026-07-12">2026-07-12</date>
        <availability>
          <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0</licence>
        </availability>
        <idno type="zoomathia"></idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Encode automatiquement par zoomathia_encoder.py v3.0 - Projet Zoomathia</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language ident="en">anglais</language>
      </langUsage>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="zoomathia">
          <term>Zoomathia</term>
          <term>animaux</term>
          <term>inconnu</term>
          <term>anglais</term>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>Fichier encode automatiquement dans le cadre du projet Zoomathia (ANR).
        Encodage produit par zoomathia_encoder.py v3.0. Verification humaine recommandee.</p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>Balisage automatique des structures textuelles et des entites nommees
        pertinentes pour Zoomathia (animaux, plantes, personnes, lieux).</p>
        <correction status="unknown">
          <p>Encodage automatique - erreurs possibles, revision manuelle recommandee.</p>
        </correction>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
<head>OF SACRIFICE</head>
<p>Methinks that <persName>man</persName> must lie sore stricken under the hand of sorrow, who has not a smile left for the folly of his superstitious brethren, when he sees them at work on <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">sacrifice</name> and festival and worship of the <name type="deity">gods</name>, hears the subject of their prayers, and marks the nature of their creed. Nor, I fancy, will a smile</p>
<div type="poem">
  <head>De sacrificiis</head>
  <lg type="strophe">
    <l n="1">be all. He will first have a question to ask himself :</l>
    <l n="2">Is he to call them devout worshippers or very outcasts,</l>
    <l n="3">who think so meanly of <name type="deity">God</name> as to suppose that he</l>
    <l n="4">can require anything at the hand of man, can take pleasure in their</l>
    <l n="5">flattery, or be wounded by their neglect ?</l>
  </lg>
  <lg type="strophe">
    <l n="6">Thus the afflictions of the <placeName>Calydonians</placeName>,</l>
    <l n="7">that long tale of misery and violence, ending with the death of</l>
    <l n="8"><persName>Meleager</persName> — all is attributed to the resentment of</l>
    <l n="9"><name type="deity">Artemis</name>, at <persName>Oeneus</persName>'s neglect</l>
    <l n="10">in not inviting her to a feast. She must have taken the disappointment</l>
    <l n="11">very much to heart. I fancy I see her, poor <name type="deity">Goddess</name>,</l>
    <l n="12">left all alone in Heaven, after the rest have set out for</l>
    <l n="13"><placeName>Calydon</placeName>, brooding darkly over the fine spread</l>
    <l n="14">at which she will not be present.</l>
  </lg>
  <lg type="strophe">
    <l n="15">Those <placeName>Ethiopians</placeName>, too ;</l>
    <l n="16">privileged, thrice-happy mortals ! <name type="deity">Zeus</name>, one supposes, is</l>
    <l n="17">not unmindful of the handsome manner in which they entertained</l>
    <l n="18">him and all his family for twelve days running.</l>
  </lg>
  <lg type="strophe">
    <l n="19">With the <name type="deity">Gods</name>, clearly, nothing goes for nothing.</l>
    <l n="20">Each blessing has its price. Health is to be had, say, for a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">calf</name> ;</l>
    <l n="21">wealth, for a couple of yoke of <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">oxen</name> ;</l>
    <l n="22">a kingdom, for a hecatomb. A safe conduct from</l>
    <l n="23"><placeName>Troy</placeName> to <placeName>Pylos</placeName> has fetched as much as nine <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">bulls</name>,</l>
    <l n="24">and a passage from <placeName>Aulis</placeName> to <placeName>Troy</placeName> has been quoted at a</l>
    <l n="25">princess. For six</l>
  </lg>
</div>
<pb n="8"/>
<p>yoke of <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">oxen</name> and a robe, <persName>Athene</persName> sold <persName>Hecuba</persName> a reprieve for <placeName>Troy</placeName>; and it is to be presumed that a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">cock</name>, a garland, a handful of frankincense, will each buy something.</p>
<p><persName>Chryses</persName>, that experienced divine and eminent theologian, <l n="3">seems to have realized this principle.</l> Returning from his fruitless visit to <persName>Agamemnon</persName>, he approaches <name type="deity">Apollo</name> with the air of a creditor, and demands repayment of his loan. His attitude is one of remonstrance, almost <quote>Good <name type="deity">Apollo</name>,</quote> he cries, <quote>here have I been garlanding your temple, where never garland hung before, and burning unlimited thigh-pieces of <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">bulls</name> and <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">goats</name> upon your altars: yet when I suffer wrong, you take no heed; you count my benefactions as nothing worth.</quote> The God is quite put out of countenance: he seizes his bow,</p>
<pb n="f"/>
<p>settles down in the harbour and smites the Achaeans with shafts of pestilence, them and their <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">mules</name> and their <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">dogs</name>.</p>
<div type="poem">
   <head>De sacrificiis</head>
   <lg type="strophe">
      <l n="1">And now that I have mentioned Apollo, I cannot refrain</l>
      <l n="2">from an allusion to certain other passages in his life, which are</l>
      <l n="3">recorded by the sages.</l>
      <l n="4">With his unfortunate love affairs —</l>
      <l n="5">the sad end of <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Hyacinth</name>, and the cruelty of <name type="deity">Daphne</name> — we</l>
      <l n="6">are not concerned.</l>
      <l n="7">But when that vote of censure was passed on</l>
      <l n="8">him for the slaughter of the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Cyclopes</name>, he</l>
      <l n="9">was dismissed from Heaven, and condemned to share the</l>
      <l n="10">fortunes of men upon earth.</l>
      <l n="11">It was then that he served <persName>Admetus</persName> in <placeName>Thessaly</placeName>,</l>
      <l n="12">and <persName>Laomedon</persName> in <placeName>Phrygia</placeName> ; and in the</l>
      <l n="13">latter service he was not alone.</l>
      <l n="14">He and <persName>Posidon</persName> together, since better might not be,</l>
      <l n="15">made bricks and built the walls of <placeName>Troy</placeName> ; and did not even</l>
      <l n="16">get their full wages ; — the <persName>Phrygian</persName>, it is said, remained their</l>
      <l n="17">debtor for no less a sum than five-and-twenty shillings Trojan,</l>
   </lg>
</div>
<lg type="strophe">
  <l n="5">and <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">goat</name>.</l>
  <l n="1">8</l>
  <l n="5">Of Sacrifice</l>
</lg>
<lg type="strophe">
  <l n="1"><name type="animal" xml:lang="en">eagle</name> ;  a  very  <persName>Proteus</persName>  for  versatility.</l>
  <l n="2">Once,  and  only  once,  he  conceived  within  his  own  brain,  and  gave  birth  to  <name type="deity">Athene</name>,</l>
  <l n="3">For  <name type="deity">Dionysus</name>,  they  say,  he  tore  from  the  womb  of  <persName>Semcle</persName></l>
  <l n="4">before  the  fire  had  yet  consumed  her,  and  hid  the  child  within</l>
  <l n="5">his  thigh,  till  the  time  of  travail  was  come.</l>
</lg>
<pb n="6"/>
<p>Similarly,  we  find <persName>Hera</persName> conceiving without external assist-
ance,  and  giving  birth  to <persName>Hephaestus</persName> ;  no  child  of fortune  he,
but  a  base  mechanic,  living  all  his  life  at  the  forge,  soot-begrimed
as  any  stoker.  He  is  not  even  sound  of  limb ;  he  has  been
lame  ever  since <persName>Zeus</persName> threw  him  down  from  Heaven.  Fortunately for  us  the <placeName>Lemnians</placeName>
broke  his  fall,  or  there  would
have  been  an  end  of  him,  as  surely  as  there  was  of <persName>Astyanax</persName>
when  he  was  flung  from  the  battlements.  But  <persName>Hephaestus</persName>  is
nothing  to  <persName>Prometheus</persName>.  Who  knows  not  the  sorrows  of  that
officious  philanthropist  ?  How  he  too  fell  a  victim  to  the  wrath
of  <persName>Zeus</persName>,  and  was  carried  into <placeName>Scythia</placeName>,  and  nailed  up  on <placeName>Caucasus</placeName>,
with  an <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">eagle</name> to  keep  him  company  and  make  daily  havoc  of
his  liver  ?  However,  there  was  a  reckoning  settled,  at  any  rate.</p>
<p>But <persName>Rhea</persName>,  now  !  We  cannot,  I  think,  pass  over  her
conduct  unnoticed.  It  is  surely  most  discreditable ; — a  lady
of  her  venerable  years,  the  mother  of  such  a  family,  still  feeling
the  pangs  of  love  and  jealousy,  and  carrying  her  beloved <persName>Attis</persName>
about  with  her  in  the <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">lion</name>-drawn  car, — and  he  so  ill  qualified
to  play  the  lover's  part  !  After  that,  we  can  but  wink,  if  we
find <persName>Aphrodite</persName> making  a  slip,  or <persName>Selene</persName> time  after  time  pulling</p>
<lg type="strophe">
  <l n="8">up  in  mid^career  to  pay  a  visit  to  <persName>Endymion</persName>.</l>
</lg>
<lg type="strophe">
  <l n="8">But  enough  of  scandal.  Borne  on  the  wings  of  poesy,  let  us</l>
  <l n="9">take  flight  for  <name type="deity">Heaven</name>  itself,  as  <persName>Homer</persName>  and  <persName>Hesiod</persName>  have  done</l>
  <l n="10">before  us,  and  see  how  all  is  disposed  up  there.  The  vault  is</l>
  <l n="11">of  brass  on  the  under  side,  as  we  know  from  <persName>Homer</persName>.  But</l>
  <l n="12">climb  over  the  edge,  and  take  a  peep  up.  You  are  now  actually</l>
  <l n="13">in  <name type="deity">Heaven</name>.  Observe  the  increase  of  light ;  here  is  a  purer  <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Sun</name>,</l>
  <l n="14">and  brighter  <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">stars</name> ;  daylight  is</l>
  <l n="15">everywhere,  and  the  floor  is  of</l>
</lg>
<lg type="strophe">
  <l>gold.  We  arrive  first  at  the  abode  of  the  <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Seasons</name>  ;  they  are</l>
  <l>the  portresses  of  <name type="deity">Heaven</name>.  Then  we  have  <persName>Iris</persName>  and  <persName>Hermes</persName>,  the</l>
  <l>servants  and  messengers  of  <persName>Zeus</persName> ;  and  next <persName>Hephaestus</persName>'s  smithy,</l>
  <l>which  is  stocked  with  all  manner  of  cunning  contrivances.  Last</l>
  <l>come  the  dwellings  of  the  <name type="deity">Gods</name>,  and  the  palace  of  <persName>Zeus</persName>.  All</l>
  <l>are  the  work  of  <persName>Hephaestus</persName> ;  and  noble  work  it  is.</l>
</lg>
<lg type="strophe">
  <l>Q  Hard  by  the  throne  of  <persName>Zeus</persName></l>
  <l>(I  suppose  we  must  adapt  our  language  to  our  altitude)</l>
  <l>sit  all  the  <name type="deity">gods</name>.</l>
  <l>Their  eyes  are  turned  downwards  ;  intently  they  search  every</l>
  <l>corner  of  the  earth  ;  is  there  nowhere  a  fire  to  be  seen,  or  the</l>
  <l>steam  of  burnt-offerings</l>
  <l>...  in  eddying  clouds  upborne ?</l>
</lg>
<div type="poem">
   <head type="main">De sacrificiis</head>
   <lg type="strophe">
      <l n="1">If  a  sacrifice  is  going  forward,  all  mouths  are  open  to  feast  upon</l>
      <l n="2">the  smoke  ;  like  <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">flies</name>  they  settle  on  the  altar  to  drink  up  the</l>
      <l n="3">trickling  streams  of  blood.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg type="strophe">
      <l n="4">If  they  are  dining  at  home,  <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">nectar</name></l>
      <l n="5">and  <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">ambrosia</name>  is  the  bill  of  fare.</l>
      <l n="6">In  ancient  days,  <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">mortals</name>  have</l>
      <l n="7">eaten  and  drunk  at  their  table.  Such  were  <persName>Ixion</persName>  and  <persName>Tantalus</persName>  ;</l>
      <l n="8">but  they  forgot  their  manners,  and  talked  too  much.</l>
      <l n="9">They</l>
      <l n="10">are  paying  the  penalty  for  it  to  this  day  ;  and  since  then  <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">mortals</name></l>
      <l n="11">have  been  excluded  from  <name type="deity">Heaven</name>.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg type="strophe">
      <l n="12">The  life  of  the  <name type="deity" xml:lang="en">Gods</name>  being  such  as  I  have  described,  our</l>
      <l n="13">religious  ordinances  are  in  admirable  harmony  with  the  divine</l>
      <l n="14">requirements.</l>
      <l n="15">Our  first  care  has  been  to  supply  each  <name type="deity">God</name>  with</l>
      <l n="16">his  sacred  grove,  his  holy  hill,  and  his  own  peculiar  <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">bird</name>  or  <name type="plant" xml:lang="en">plant</name>.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg type="strophe">
      <l n="17">The  next  step  was  to  assign  them  their  various  sacred  cities.</l>
      <l n="18"><persName>Apollo</persName>  has  the  freedom  of  <placeName>Delphi</placeName>  and  <placeName>Delos</placeName>,  <persName>Athene</persName>  that  of</l>
      <l n="19"><placeName>Athens</placeName>  (there  is  no  disputing  her  nationality)  ;  <persName>Hera</persName>  is  an</l>
      <l n="20"><placeName>Argive</placeName>,  <persName>Rhea</persName>  a  <placeName>Mygdonian</placeName>,  <persName>Aphrodite</persName>  a  <placeName>Paphian</placeName>.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg type="strophe">
      <l n="21">As  for  <persName>Zeus</persName>,  he  is  a  <placeName>Cretan</placeName>  born  and  bred — and  buried,  as  any  native</l>
      <l n="22">of  that  island  will  show  you.  It  was  a  mistake  of  ours  to  suppose  that  <persName>Zeus</persName>  was  dispensing</l>
      <l n="23">the  thunder  and  the  rain  and  the  rest  of  it ; — he  has  been  lying  snugly  underground  in  <placeName>Crete</placeName>  all</l>
      <l n="24">this  time.</l>
   </lg>
</div>
<div type="poem">
   <head>De sacrificiis</head>
   <lg type="strophe">
      <l n="1">As it would never have done to leave the <name type="deity">Gods</name> without a</l>
      <l n="2">hearth and home, temples were now erected, and the services</l>
      <l n="3">of <persName>Phidias</persName>, <persName>Polyclitus</persName>, and <persName>Praxiteles</persName> were called in to create</l>
      <l n="4">images in their likeness. Chance glimpses of their originals</l>
      <l n="5">(but where obtained I know not) enabled these artists to do</l>
      <l n="6">justice to the beard of <name type="deity">Zeus</name>, the perpetual</l>
      <l n="7">youth of <name type="deity">Apollo</name>,</l>
      <l n="8">the down on <name type="deity">Hermes</name>'s cheek, <name type="deity">Posidon</name>'s sea-green hair, and</l>
      <l n="9"><name type="deity">Athene</name>'s flashing eyes ;</l>
      <l n="10">with the result that on entering the temple of <name type="deity">Zeus</name></l>
      <l n="11">men believe that they see before them, not</l>
      <l n="12">Indian ivory, nor gold from a <placeName>Thracian</placeName> mine, but the veritable</l>
      <l n="13">son of <name type="deity">Cronus</name> and <persName>Rhea</persName>, translated to earth by the hand of</l>
      <l n="14"><persName>Phidias</persName>, with instructions to keep watch over the deserted</l>
      <l n="15">plains of <placeName>Pisa</placeName>, and content with his lot, if, once in four years, a</l>
      <l n="16">spectator of the games can snatch a moment to pay him sacrifice.</l>
   </lg>
</div>
<div type="poem">
  <head>De sacrificiis</head>
  <lg type="strophe">
    <l n="12">And now the altars stand ready; proclamation has been</l>
    <l n="13">made, and lustration duly performed. The victims are</l>
    <l n="14">accordingly brought forward — an <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">ox</name> from the plough, a</l>
    <l n="15"><name type="animal" xml:lang="en">ram</name> or a <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">goat</name>,</l>
    <l n="16">according as the worshipper is a farmer, a shepherd, or a</l>
    <l n="17">goatherd; sometimes it is only frankincense or a honey cake;</l>
    <l n="18">nay, a poor man may conciliate the <name type="deity">God</name> by merely kissing his</l>
    <l n="19">hand.</l>
  </lg>
  <lg type="strophe">
    <l n="20">But it is with the priests that we are concerned. They first</l>
    <l n="21">make sure that the victim is without blemish, and worthy of the</l>
    <l n="22">sacrificial knife; then they crown him with garlands and lead</l>
    <l n="23">him to the altar, where he is slaughtered before the <name type="deity">God</name>'s</l>
    <l n="24">eyes, to the broken accompaniment of his own sanctimonious</l>
    <l n="25">bellowings, most musical, most melancholy. The delight of the</l>
    <l n="26"><name type="deity">Gods</name> at such a spectacle, who can doubt?</l>
  </lg>
  <lg type="strophe">
    <l n="13">According to the proclamation, no man shall approach the</l>
    <l n="14">holy ground with unclean hands. Yet there stands the priest</l>
    <l n="15">himself, wallowing in gore; handling his knife like a very</l>
    <l n="16"><foreign xml:lang="en">Cyclops</foreign>, drawing out entrails and heart, sprinkling the altar</l>
  </lg>
</div>
<pb n="14"/>
<p>with  blood, — in  short,  omitting  no  detail  of  his  holy  office.  </p>
<p>Finally,  he  kindles  fire,  and  sets  the  victim  bodily  thereon,  <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">sheep</name>  or  <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">goat</name>,  unfleeced,  unflayed.  A  godly  steam,  and  fit  for  godly  nostrils,  rises  heavenwards,  and  drifts  to  each  quarter  of  the  sky.  The  <placeName>Scythian</placeName>,  by  the  way,  will  have  nothing  to  do  with  paltry  <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">cattle</name>  :  he  offers  <foreign xml:lang="la">vien</foreign>  to  <name type="deity">Artemis</name>  ;  and  the  offering  is  appreciated.  </p>
<p>But  all  this,  and  all  that  <placeName>Assyria</placeName>,  <placeName>Phrygia</placeName>,  and  <placeName>Lydia</placeName>  can  show,  amounts  to  nothing  much.  If  you  would  see  the  <name type="deity">Gods</name>  in  their  glory,  fit  denizens  of  <placeName>Heaven</placeName>,  you  must  go  to  <placeName>Egypt</placeName>.  </p>
<p>There  you  will  find  that  <name type="deity">Zeus</name>  has  sprouted  <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">ram</name>'s  horns,  our  old  friend  <persName>Hermes</persName>  has  the  muzzle  of  a  <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">dog</name>,  and  <persName>Pan</persName>  is  perfect  <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">goat</name>  ;  <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">ibis</name>,  <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">crocodile</name>,  <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">ape</name>,  — each  is  a  <name type="deity">God</name>  in  disguise.  </p>
<p>And  wouldst  thou  know  the  truth  that   lurks  herein  ?  </p>
<p>If  so,  you  will  find  no  lack  of  <persName>sages</persName>  and  <persName>scribes</persName>  and  <persName>shaven priests</persName>  to  inform  you  (after  expulsion  of  the  ■<foreign xml:lang="la">profanum vulgus</foreign>)  how,  when  the  <name type="deity">Giants</name>  and  their  other  enemies  rose  against  them,  the  <name type="deity">Gods</name>  fled  to  <placeName>Egypt</placeName>  to  hide  themselves,  and  there  took  the  form  of  <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">goat</name>  and  <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">ram</name>,  of  <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">bird</name>  and  <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">reptile</name>,  which  forms  they  preserve  to  this  day.  Of  all  this  they  have  documentary  evidence,  dating  from  thousands  of  years  back,  stored  up  in  their  temples.
</p>
<div type="poem">
  <head>De sacrificiis</head>
  <lg type="strophe">
    <l n="15">Their sacrifices differ from others only in this respect, that they</l>
    <l n="16">go into mourning for the victim, slaying him first, and beating</l>
    <l n="17">their breasts for grief afterwards, and (in some parts) burying</l>
    <l n="18">him as soon as he is killed.</l>
    <l n="19">When their great god <name type="deity">Apis</name> dies,</l>
    <l n="20">off comes every man's hair, however much he values himself on</l>
    <l n="21">it; though he had the purple lock of <persName>Nisus</persName>, it would make no</l>
    <l n="22">difference: he must show a sad crown on the occasion, if he</l>
    <l n="23">die for it.</l>
    <l n="24">It is as the result of an election that each succeeding <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">Apis</name> leaves</l>
    <l n="25">his pasture for the temple; his superior beauty</l>
    <l n="26">and majestic bearing prove that he is something more than <name type="animal" xml:lang="en">bull</name>.</l>
  </lg>
  <p>On such absurdities as these, such vulgar credulity, remonipo of Sacrifice</p>
  <p>strance would be thrown away; a <persName>Hcraclltus</persName> would best meet</p>
  <p>the case, or a <persName>Democritus</persName>; for the ignorance</p>
  <p>of these men is as laughable as their folly is deplorable. F.</p>
  <head>SALE OF CREEDS*</head>
  <lg type="strophe">
    <l n="1">Zeus.     Hermes.     Several Dealers.     Creeds</l>
    <l n="2">Zeus.  Now get those benches straight there, and make the</l>
    <l n="3">place fit to be seen.  Bring up the lots, one of you, and put</l>
    <l n="4">them in line.  Give them a rub up first, though; we must have</l>
    <l n="5">them looking their best, to attract bidders.  Hermes, you can</l>
    <l n="6">declare the sale-room open, and a welcome to all comers. — For</l>
  </lg>
</div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>